<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-04-16T19:08:42-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">InterSTEM</title><entry><title type="html">The genius of Bitcoin, a revolutionary currency</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/08/the-genius-of-bitcoin-a-revolutionary-currency.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The genius of Bitcoin, a revolutionary currency" /><published>2021-04-08T17:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-08T17:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/08/the-genius-of-bitcoin-a-revolutionary-currency</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/08/the-genius-of-bitcoin-a-revolutionary-currency.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The genius of Bitcoin, a revolutionary currency&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rachel Huang. 04/09/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/btcOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The high stakes involved with Bitcoin have only made its value soar higher than ever before. &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/four-factors-driving-the-price-of-bitcoin-87244&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(The Conversation)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Launched in 2009 from the anonymous Satoshi Nakamoto’s whitepaper, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/b/bitcoin.asp&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bitcoin&lt;/a&gt; (BTC) was created to be an electronic payment system “based on cryptographic proof instead of trust.” Bitcoin is now the world’s largest cryptocurrency (digital currency) with an astonishing value of over $55,000 for a single coin and is also the first application of blockchain technology, an innovative creation that allows it to be distributed, traded and stored. A blockchain is essentially a collection of “blocks,” files that record all of the transactions that occur, making them transparent and visible to all of the computers that run Bitcoin’s code and store its blockchain. The creation of Bitcoin has united thousands of people around the world over a common goal: obtaining bitcoin and turning a profit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are currently 12,000 computers connected to Bitcoin’s blockchain; these computers are called nodes, while the owners of the computers are called miners - the miners control Bitcoin’s release into circulation via a process called Bitcoin mining and are rewarded with coins adding blocks to the blockchain. Bitcoin mining requires the solving of complex computational puzzles in order to discover a new block, and expensive mining rigs (elaborate mining processors and hardware) increase a miner’s ability to earn more rewards. Mining rigs are available for purchase in the form of computer chips like Application-Specific Integrated Circuits (ASIC) and Graphic Processing Units (GPUs). All of these Bitcoin transactions are verified by cryptographic proof, making the system very secure. For example, a person with malicious intent would need to operate 51% of the total computing power that makes up Bitcoin to cheat the system. With miners acting as Bitcoin’s decentralized authority, miners are motivated to add to the growing blockchain because of the prospect of reward, and the blockchain benefits by growing and developing even more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While David Zeiler, cryptocurrency expert for Money Morning, describes Bitcoin as “the best-known crypto and a secure, decentralized currency that has become a store of value like gold,” there may be more exaggeration than truth in his statement. The long-term security that Zeiler describes only refers to Bitcoin’s official certification and verifiability, not Bitcoin’s prices. Cryptocurrency is a highly speculative investment, with the potential for intense price swings, or as described in the words of CEO of Digital Currency Group Barry Silbert, “It is pretty much the highest-risk, highest-return investment that you can possibly make.” As a safeguard against these risks, it is highly recommended that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/advisor/investing/what-is-cryptocurrency/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;investors&lt;/a&gt; trade on official cryptocurrency exchanges, such as Coin base and Bitfinex. Potential investors and traders are enticed by Bitcoin’s high exchange rate, lower transaction fees and instant payments that are a result of its “peer-to-peer” technology that grants instant rewards. In addition, Bitcoin can also be exchanged for traditional currencies and act as an alternative to national fiat money and traditional commodities like gold. The overall success of Bitcoin has triggered the release of a slew of other cryptocurrencies, amounting to over 5,000 different types released into circulation, collectively referred to as altcoins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As another facet of its multipurpose nature, Bitcoin can also be used to buy things! Bitcoin can be split into smaller units to make transactions easier - the common unit of Bitcoin used in everyday transactions is called the Satoshi, which is 100 millionths of a Bitcoin, currently worth approximately 0.02 cents. In response to the growing Bitcoin community, many retailers have begun to accept bitcoin with the proper hardware terminal and/or wallet address through QR codes and touch screen apps. Keys are the main form of hardware terminal through which Bitcoin can be transferred: there are public and private keys, both of which are long strings of numbers and letters linked through the mathematical encryption algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/btcTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;An example of Bitcoin’s private and public keys.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://coinsource.net/private-keys-public-keys-addresses-and-wallets/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Coinsource)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A &lt;a href=&quot;https://coinsource.net/private-keys-public-keys-addresses-and-wallets/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;public&lt;/a&gt; key’s address is published to the world and others may send bitcoins to it as necessary. On the other hand, private keys are a guarded secret and only used to authorize personal bitcoin transmissions. Keys increase Bitcoin’s liquidity by making Bitcoins less like stocks and more like cash because the private keys needed to authorize spending can be printed out and stored physically. Stores may also accept Bitcoin wallets, a physical or digital device that facilitates the trading of bitcoin and allows users to track ownership of coins with a software program that interacts with the blockchain, allowing users to exchange the currency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin’s appeal has been greatly increasing in recent years, especially because Bitcoin quickly approaches its approvable max of 21 million bitcoin. With a current count of about 18,614,806 in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/tech/what-happens-bitcoin-after-21-million-mined/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;circulation&lt;/a&gt;, there are only about 3 million Bitcoins left to be mined. This makes it seem like Bitcoin will run out soon, sending miners and investors into a frenzy. However, this is not the case because rewards are halved for every 210,000 blocks added to Bitcoin’s blockchain; the current reward for each block discovery has become a meager 6.25 bitcoins (of course, if you take into account the value of a single Bitcoin, then the overall value of the reward is greater than ever). If you think about how a store of 3 million Bitcoins gets depleted by withdrawals of 6.25 bitcoins, you will understand how, in reality, Bitcoin will actually “run out” in around 2140.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin continues to be the leader and definer of the cryptocurrency value cycle; the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/investor/2021/02/12/bitcoin-price-prediction-2021-where-is-the-top/?sh=31480e9c3ed0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;prices&lt;/a&gt; of bitcoin and Ethereum (another cryptocurrency) are currently riding a FOMO-driven high, going almost vertical. The direction and stability of these high prices are very unpredictable, or, in the words of Clem Chambers, “a week is now a long time in crypto” due to its extreme volatility. Investors can monitor transaction fees as a sign of Bitcoin’s upcoming value - transaction fees are now exorbitant; when transaction fees start to fall it will be a signal that the FOMO is falling, and the prices will drop. For now though, the fees continue to rapidly increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/btcThree.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Google Trends shows interest in bitcoin, Ethereum, DeFi (decentralized finance) and stocks.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/investor/2021/02/12/bitcoin-price-prediction-2021-where-is-the-top/?sh=31480e9c3ed0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Forbes)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As a child of the 21st century, Bitcoin is, and will no doubt continue to be at the forefront of the digital currency revolution. Versatile and secure, investable and ever-expanding, Satoshi Nakamoto’s application of blockchain technology has blossomed into proportions that must have been unimaginable before its creation. Microsoft, Home Depot, Burger King, Starbucks: all of these major retailers have started the movement of accepting Bitcoin and other forms of cryptocurrency as a form of payment. Who knows? One day, Bitcoin may become the new dollar bill - as liquid as cash, and accepted anywhere and everywhere. Only time will tell how the wonders of Bitcoin and its siblings will transform the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://coingeek.com/bitcoin-sv-rallies-as-world-record-638mb-block-is-mined/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Coingeek)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Nadwa Atwi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Rachel Huang</name></author><summary type="html">The genius of Bitcoin, a revolutionary currency Rachel Huang. 04/09/2021 The high stakes involved with Bitcoin have only made its value soar higher than ever before. (The Conversation) Launched in 2009 from the anonymous Satoshi Nakamoto’s whitepaper, Bitcoin (BTC) was created to be an electronic payment system “based on cryptographic proof instead of trust.” Bitcoin is now the world’s largest cryptocurrency (digital currency) with an astonishing value of over $55,000 for a single coin and is also the first application of blockchain technology, an innovative creation that allows it to be distributed, traded and stored. A blockchain is essentially a collection of “blocks,” files that record all of the transactions that occur, making them transparent and visible to all of the computers that run Bitcoin’s code and store its blockchain. The creation of Bitcoin has united thousands of people around the world over a common goal: obtaining bitcoin and turning a profit.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/btcCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/btcCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">CRISPR-Cas9: The award-winning genetic scissors</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/08/crispr-cas9-the-award-winning-genetic-scissors.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CRISPR-Cas9: The award-winning genetic scissors" /><published>2021-04-08T17:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-08T17:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/08/crispr-cas9-the-award-winning-genetic-scissors</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/08/crispr-cas9-the-award-winning-genetic-scissors.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;CRISPR-Cas9: The award-winning genetic scissors
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nadwa Atwi. 04/09/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/geneticOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Emmanuelle Charpentier (left) and Jennifer Doudna (right) win the 2020 Nobel Prize in Chemistry for CRISPR gene-editing. &lt;a href=&quot;https://scroll.in/article/975260/what-is-crispr-explaining-the-gene-editing-technology-that-won-the-2020-chemistry-nobel-prize&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Scroll)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Researcher Emmanuelle Charpentier and biochemist Jennifer Doudna were initially studying the immune system of a Streptococcus bacterium in hopes of developing a new antibiotic, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/chemistry/2020/popular-information/#:~:text=Emmanuelle%20Charpentier%20and%20Jennifer%20Doudna,microorganisms%20with%20extremely%20high%20precision.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Nobel Prize&lt;/a&gt;. But akin to other remarkable discoveries, this one didn’t exactly go as planned. Instead, the pair discovered a molecular tool called CRISPR which can be used to make defined cuts in genetic material, presenting an endless array of possibilities for the future of gene-editing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeats, also known as CRISPR, are DNA sequences that are naturally found in bacteria. These repeats are actually a collection of mug shots captured by CRISPR associated proteins (Cas). The mug shots are DNA pieces that Cas cut from invaders that attack the bacteria. The snipped DNA fragment is then stored between the palindromic CRISPR sequences to maintain a genetic memory for halting future infections from the same invader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until recently, “CRISPR-Cas9” —often called CRISPR for short— has only been known as genetic information that some bacteria use as part of their defense mechanism against viruses. Now, as a gene-editing tool, CRISPR-Cas9 has reformed biomedical research and may soon enable medical breakthroughs in a way few biological innovations have before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/geneticTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The diagram shows the mechanism of action of CRISPR. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yourgenome.org/facts/what-is-crispr-cas9&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(YourGenome)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Editing genes with CRISPR-Cas9 occurs by cutting DNA at a particular site and then letting the natural DNA repair processes take over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CRISPR relies on just two components: the molecular scissors (Cas9) and the guide RNA (gRNA), which works as a GPS, guiding Cas9 to the appropriate site. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.synthego.com/guide/how-to-use-crispr/sgrna#:~:text=In%20this%20document%2C%20we%20have,into%20a%20single%20RNA%20molecule.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Synthego&lt;/a&gt;, gRNA itself consists of two parts. These include the CRISPR RNA (crRNA), which is a sequence complementary to the target DNA, and a tracrRNA, which serves as a binding scaffold for the Cas protein. The crRNA part of the gRNA is the customizable one and can be modified into virtually any sequence, which allows specificity in every CRISPR experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guide RNA shepherds Cas9 to the precise spot on DNA where a cut has been called for by pairing up with the region of the DNA it has targeted. Cas9 then locks onto the double-stranded DNA and unzips it, allowing it to snip the DNA at the requested spot. This results in a break in both strands of the DNA molecule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cell, sensing a problem, repairs the break. Cells usually repair a break in their DNA by gluing the loose ends back together using DNA ligase. This repair mechanism is not an orderly process, as it typically involves the loss or addition of some nucleotides at the cut site. That often results in a mistake that disables a gene, which may not sound convenient— but sometimes it is. This is why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists cut DNA with CRISPR-Cas9 to induce changes, also known as mutations. They can understand what a protein’s actual role is by comparing cells with the mutation to ones without the mutation. A new mutation may also help them understand genetic diseases. Additionally, CRISPR-Cas9 can be useful in human cells by disabling certain genes, like ones that play a role in inherited diseases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the RNA biologist &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencenewsforstudents.org/article/explainer-how-crispr-works&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gene Yeo&lt;/a&gt;, Cas9 was originally equivalent to a Swiss army knife that has only one function: cutting. But securing proteins to those jaded blades has turned them into a multifunctional tool. CRISPR-Cas9 can now be used in new ways, such as changing a single nitrogenous base or adding a fluorescent protein to tag a spot in the DNA that scientists want to track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Applications&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CRISPR’s potential applications include correcting genetic defects, treating and preventing the spread of diseases and improving crops. Many common diseases, including heart conditions, Alzheimer’s and diabetes, are partly caused by genes; people who inherit the mutated variants of certain genes are more susceptible to the disease. For many of these conditions, the genetic component is complicated because more than one gene is involved. So for now, scientists are looking to treat diseases that are the result of a single mutated gene that is easy to target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some blood disorders, like sickle-cell anemia, fit the bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sickle-cell anemia is an inherited red blood cell disorder in which the round red blood cells become deformed and resemble sickles or crescent moons. This deformation makes the cells prone to sticking in blood vessels and blocking blood flow to the surrounding tissues. Sickle-cell anemia is the result of a mutation in the hemoglobin gene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/geneticThree.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The diagram shows the difference between normal red blood cells and the mutated ones.&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aboutkidshealth.ca/article?contentid=652&amp;amp;language=english&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(About Kids Health)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
About &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2020/06/23/877543610/a-year-in-1st-patient-to-get-gene-editing-for-sickle-cell-disease-is-thriving&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;two years ago&lt;/a&gt;, a woman called Victoria Gray became the first person to receive an experimental CRISPR treatment for sickle-cell anemia. Her doctors collected blood-producing stem cells from her bone marrow and edited the gene involved in hemoglobin formation found in the DNA they carry. Then they transfused them back. Gray has not needed the regular blood transfusions or hospitalizations her condition previously demanded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yourgenome.org/facts/what-is-crispr-cas9&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Your Genome&lt;/a&gt;, CRISPR-Cas9 currently stands out as the fastest, cheapest and most reliable gene-editing tool. It is important to mention, though, that it is still unlikely for CRISPR-Cas9 to be used routinely in humans anytime soon. Using this tool along with other gene-editing technologies in somatic cells is well-accepted. In contrast, changes made in germ line cells will be passed on from one generation to another, which has significant ethical implications. The most prominent one is the inability to obtain informed consent, as patients affected by gene edits to germ line cells are embryos and future generations. That aside, CRISPR has shown very promising results in the medical field, and it’s clear that this tool holds great potential for curing diseases we’ve at some point labeled “untreatable.” So for now, we’re just going to have to wait and see what the future holds for such a versatile —and controversial— tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drugtargetreview.com/news/74139/nobel-prize-in-chemistry-awarded-to-scientists-who-discovered-crispr-cas9/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Drug Target Review)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Nadwa Atwi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Nadwa Atwi</name></author><summary type="html">CRISPR-Cas9: The award-winning genetic scissors Nadwa Atwi. 04/09/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/geneticCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/geneticCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Bird-safe glass is the only way forward</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/02/bird-safe-glass-is-the-only-way-foward.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bird-safe glass is the only way forward" /><published>2021-04-02T17:00:03-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-02T17:00:03-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/02/bird-safe-glass-is-the-only-way-foward</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/02/bird-safe-glass-is-the-only-way-foward.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Bird-safe glass is the only way forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emily Richter. 04/03/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/birdglassCover.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This Public Health Office in Palma de Mallorca, Spain is both stunning and bird-safe.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://abcbirds.org/glass-collisions/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Boris Pena / American Bird Conservatory)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Birds do not understand windows. Though humans know there is a pane of glass, birds see a reflection of their surroundings or an inviting habitat, like an empty room. As a result, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://abcbirds.org/glass-collisions/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;American Bird Conservatory&lt;/a&gt; (ABC) reports that about one billion birds die every year due to glass collisions, making them a leading cause of avian death. For most animals, humanity’s worst threat comes in the form of habitat loss. For birds, the very buildings people inhabit can be deadly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Birds light up the skies with their beautiful feathers and enhance the sounds of the city and country alike with their beautiful songs. Birds also play important roles in maintaining the balance of the ecosystems humans depend on. Some birds, like hummingbirds, act as pollinators, fostering life in the form of plants. Others, like vultures, scavenge the remains of life, returning necessary nutrients to the soil. Still others, like orioles, spread the seeds of plants far and wide, ensuring the continued success of the natural world. Nature needs birds to function properly. Since humanity depends on the world’s ecosystems for everything from food to oxygen, humans need birds. Anything that hurts birds eventually hurts people as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new technology promises hope for the feathered friends of the sky. Bird-safe incorporates materials birds can see into the design of the glass in order to prevent birds from flying into it. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.audubon.org/news/what-does-bird-safe-glass-even-mean&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Audubon Society&lt;/a&gt; reports that bird-safe glass is a blanket term, applying to both specially-designed glass and retrofitted glass. Bird-safe glass can be colored, like the glass at the Public Health Office in Palma de Mallorca, Spain (shown above), or it can be virtually transparent, utilizing small dots or lines as a way to alert birds of its presence. The process of retrofitting glass to make it safe for birds often involves adding lines or dots to the surface of the glass. Bird-safe glass and retrofitting buildings can be costly, but in the long run, it can also be beneficial. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://abcbirds.org/glass-collisions/architecture-planning/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ABC&lt;/a&gt; reports the Jacob K. Javits Convention Center near Times Square in Manhattan used to be notorious for the number of bird collisions it caused. However, when bird-safe glass was installed, both bird collisions and heat loss declined. The building went from being an ecological issue to being a model for bird safety and energy efficiency. Bird-safe glass does not only benefit birds; it can benefit its owners as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Codes and ordinances that require new edifices to be built with bird-safe glass are beginning to become common in the United States. New York City, which sees the most yearly bird deaths due to glass collisions, &lt;a href=&quot;https://council.nyc.gov/press/2019/12/10/1847/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;passed a law in 2020&lt;/a&gt; mandating that all new structures meet certain standards of bird safety. A majority of these standards involve glass design. The grassroots organization &lt;a href=&quot;https://birdfriendlychicago.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bird Friendly Chicago&lt;/a&gt; worked for years to introduce bird-safe glass laws to the third most populous city in the United States. They found success in 2019, when a bird-safe glass ordinance was introduced to the Chicago City Council, and again in 2020 when the city council updated Chicago’s Sustainable Development Policy to include information regarding bird-safe glass and its importance. In August of 2020, the city council of Madison, Wisconsin &lt;a href=&quot;https://abcbirds.org/article/madison-bird-friendly-building-ordinance-passed/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;passed an ordinance&lt;/a&gt; requiring bird-safe glass on all new large construction projects. The efforts of committed advocates and the support of the ABC lead to a new rule promising safer skies for Wisconsin’s faster-growing city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, an organization in Madison &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ibmadison.com/city-sued-over-bird-safe-glass-requirement/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;has taken the city to court&lt;/a&gt;, saying that the new ordinance is unconstitutional. Building codes are updated often, and many new construction ordinances are introduced every year, so the chance of the law being nullified is low. However, the general public’s poor understanding of the importance and benefits of bird-safe glass still remains a threat to protective legislation. Many people who are against laws requiring the specialized glass point at the price, which is often elevated, as reasoning for their opinion. However, like in the case of the Jacob K. Javits Convention Center, bird-safe glass often leads to lower heating and cooling bills. And either way, the loss of bird life comes with a much higher price tag, both in economic and ecological terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only do birds collide with the windows of large buildings, but they also collide with the windows of ordinary houses. In most areas, glass retrofitting services are not available for homeowners. Luckily, there is a simple solution. Putting stickers, curtains, sheets, or posters can help birds avoid flying into the glass. Protecting birds from glass can provide practical benefits as well! Stickers and posters can be great decorations for a living space, and putting fabric in windows often helps keep a room cooler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many organizations of all sizes are fighting for a safer future for birds. Local organizations all over the world have had success encouraging the passing of legislation that mandates bird-safe glass in certain construction projects. National organizations like the ABC and Audubon support these grassroots movements and push for federal legislation. By passing laws that make buildings safer for birds with the help of organizations like these, humanity can move forward in a responsible and more sustainable manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://abcbirds.org/blog/truth-about-birds-and-glass-collisions&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Arenal Observatory Lodge / American Bird Conservatory)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Emily Richter&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Emily Richter</name></author><summary type="html">Bird-safe glass is the only way forward Emily Richter. 04/03/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/birdglassOne.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/birdglassOne.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Auroras: Northern Lights</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/02/auroras-northern-lights.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Auroras: Northern Lights" /><published>2021-04-02T17:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-02T17:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/02/auroras-northern-lights</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/02/auroras-northern-lights.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Auroras: Northern Lights&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Bui. 04/03/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/auroraOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Above is an image of the aurora in Iceland.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://newatlas.com/photography/2020-northern-lights-photographer-of-the-year/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Agnieszka Mrowka)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Chances are, you’ve watched “The Polar Express”. If so, do you remember the bright colorful ribbons in the dark sky? In case you’re not familiar with “The Polar Express”, have you ever seen a picture of a prismatic ribbon across a night sky, specifically in areas where it’s cold? Well, those lights are called auroras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auroras, or polar lights, are a natural phenomenon characterized by a display of colored light in the sky. This event is caused by a process involving solar wind. Solar wind is the outward expansion of plasma from the sun. The plasma is heated to the extent that the sun’s gravity cannot hold it in anymore. This solar wind then travels the Earth and enters its magnetic field before reaching the ionosphere, the layer of the atmosphere that contains the highest concentration of ions and free electrons. The energy that is released as a result of this collision creates the spectral wonder around the Northern and Southern poles: an aurora. Because auroras can only be visible at the Northern and Southern poles, they are unique and seeing them is often a once-in-a-lifetime experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auroras have many different names, other than polar lights. In the Northern pole, they can be called northern lights, and in the Southern pole, they are often called southern lights. The scientific name of auroras is aurora borealis. Aurora comes from the Latin word for “dawn,” as well as the goddess of dawn in Roman mythology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What causes the colors and patterns of auroras? There are various types of ions and atoms that collide with the atmosphere, resulting in a variety of patterns. The forms resulted from this variety can include ripples, “pulsating globs” and steady glows. The altitude affects the colors of the auroras, known as the aurora’s spectrum. This is because the particles from outer space collide with different gasses at different heights, resulting in different colors. Blue, violet and red colors are produced below 60 miles, and bright green between 60 and 150 miles. Above 150 miles, ruby red colors are seen. There is an infinite variety of shapes, colors, brightness and rays an aurora can form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The magic of auroras is only visible at specific times. Auroras are always there, but they’re not as visible at certain times. In some places, such as Abisko, auroras are visible for almost 24 hours a day during winter. In other places, it’s rarer. Of course, auroras are only limited to viewing in the Northern and Southern poles. Darkness is vital for auroras to be visible, and they can be seen from late August to early April when the sky satisfies this condition. There are also aurora forecasts for people enthusiastic about seeing the spectacle for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the beauty of auroras comes with a price. Auroras can actually be potentially &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=http://www.suntrek.org/sun-earth-connection/the-aurora/aurorae-effect-us.shtml&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1617439859423000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw2_KP9t2Wj0Shn3r--3H6oG&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;dangerous&lt;/a&gt; to the atmosphere. To make a point clear, they have absolutely no negative impact on humans watching from below whatsoever, but the technology and buildings at a higher elevation can be affected by the electrically charged particles that auroras cause. Auroras disturb the atmosphere that they reside in. They can also disrupt communication from radios, signals and so on. The magnetic energy released by solar wind can blow out electricity. When auroras are active, the Earth’s atmosphere expands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auroras are beautiful and amazing, despite their negative factors. It’s quite an interesting phenomenon with interesting facts! Although they exist in the sky, sometimes they can come relatively close to the surface of the earth. Did you know that the closest the northern lights have ever come to Earth is 80 kilometers above the surface? To give a little visual aid, 80 kilometers is roughly 50 miles, whereas the atmosphere is 6,214 miles up. Did you know that the International Space Station (ISS) is at the same altitude as the auroras, so they can see the auroras from the side? Multiple planets have auroras, including Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus and Neptune. Southern lights aren’t nearly as popular as northern lights, although they’re nearly the same, because the areas that feature southern lights don’t have much landmass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, auroras are colorful illusions that are created when the sun’s rays hit the Earth’s ionosphere. They come in a variety of shapes and sizes and can be viewed in the Northern and Southern poles. There are different names for auroras, whether it’s specified by the pole it’s in, or its scientific name. In a way, they can have a negative impact on the atmosphere. Now that you know a little more about auroras, maybe one day, you’ll be among the group of people who love them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://cdn.discover-the-world.com/app/uploads/2018/08/norway-northern-tromso-surrounds-with-aurora-istk.jpg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(CDN)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Peter Bui&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Peter Bui</name></author><summary type="html">Auroras: Northern Lights Peter Bui. 04/03/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/auroraCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/auroraCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Trees are a little like humans</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/02/trees-are-a-little-like-humans.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trees are a little like humans" /><published>2021-04-02T17:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-02T17:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/02/trees-are-a-little-like-humans</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/02/trees-are-a-little-like-humans.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Trees are a little like humans&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Bui. 04/03/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/treesOne.png&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gettyimages.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Getty Images)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Whether we go outside or just look through the window, chances are we see trees. Trees take in carbon dioxide and release oxygen around the world, giving us clean air. But are trees just there, existing? Research shows that trees have (some) feelings of their own and have quite a few human characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thought of trees having human characteristics is quite surprising and for good reason. Trees have feelings? That’s crazy! But human characteristics aren’t the limit to what trees can do. In fact, research shows that trees can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newscientist.com/article/mg21528791-800-plant-senses-sight/#:~:text=The%20obvious%20answer%20is%20that,ultraviolet%20parts%20of%20the%20spectrum.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;see&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smithsonianmag.com/science-nature/the-whispering-trees-180968084/#:~:text=They%20don%27t%20have%20nervous,signals%20like%20wounded%20human%20tissue.%E2%80%9D&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;feel&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.livescience.com/plants-squeal-when-stressed.html#:~:text=In%20times%20of%20intense%20stress,research%2C%20which%20was%20posted%20Dec.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;scream&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://english.mathrubhumi.com/news/columns/faunaforum/trees-do-cry--1.244317#:~:text=02%20AM%20IST-,Do%20trees%20cry%3F,to%20hear%2C%20it%20goes%20unheard.&amp;amp;text=Inside%20tree%20trunks%20are%20bundles,the%20highest%20leaves%20and%20branches.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;cry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the basics. Trees are grown plants, with parts including a trunk, branches, leaves and roots. They, like us, require water and basic needs. A tree takes in water, sunlight and carbon dioxide through a process known as photosynthesis. This process produces glucose, or sugar, which the tree uses for energy, and oxygen as a byproduct (humans then breathe in oxygen and exhale carbon dioxide for the tree to use, continuing the cycle).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trees play a big role in our everyday lives at the cost of their own lives (which could span for hundreds or even thousands of years if left undisturbed) because they are used to create paper, furniture, lumber and so much more. However, they prove more useful while they live by cleaning our air and supplying us with many other benefits such as cleaning the environment. Some trees even produce fruit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But do trees have feelings? Trees lack a nervous system, so they can’t experience emotions that we feel, like happiness or excitement. Even though trees lack a brain, the fact that electric signals can be fired from within the trees hints at consciousness. Botanist author &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pri.org/stories/2014-01-09/new-research-plant-intelligence-may-forever-change-how-you-think-about-plants#:~:text=Pollan%20says%20plants%20have%20all,he%20says%2C%20to%20avoid%20obstacles.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Michael Pollan&lt;/a&gt; explains that they may have a system that produces neurotransmitters, like serotonin, that the human brain also produces. In addition to this, it has been proved that trees do feel a few emotions. Although they don’t experience feelings while being chopped down, they do not like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The emotional range of a tree is somewhat limited, but that doesn’t mean it doesn’t exist. For instance, they can sense and react to cold, heat, drought, touch and external trouble. When a plant feels that it is too cold, it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lyndontreecare.com/educate/2017/1/28/how-do-trees-survive-winter#:~:text=This%20dormancy%20is%20what%20allows,with%20the%20loss%20of%20leaves.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;initiates responses&lt;/a&gt; that can help to protect the tree from harm. Trees use their bark to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bioinspiration.net/post/bark-of-trees#:~:text=Bark%20of%20trees%20have%20a,between%206%20and%2010%20microns.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;reflect light and disperse heat&lt;/a&gt;. To protect themselves from heat, they use their leaves to shade themselves, as well as use &lt;a href=&quot;https://spatialexperiments.wordpress.com/2016/02/08/coping-with-the-heat-trees/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;conductive and insulative cooling&lt;/a&gt;. They sense drought when they do not have enough water to meet their needs, the equivalent of us being thirsty. In this case, they save water and slow down evaporation. In general, plants can feel touch, but it is debated if being touched is beneficial or harmful for the plant. Some studies even show that touch results in stunted growth of the plant. Trees can even sense insects and internally mix chemicals to create compounds that act as repellants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most human responses that trees can feel are rather sad. This includes trees &lt;a href=&quot;https://english.mathrubhumi.com/news/columns/faunaforum/trees-do-cry--1.244317#:~:text=02%20AM%20IST-,Do%20trees%20cry%3F,to%20hear%2C%20it%20goes%20unheard.&amp;amp;text=Inside%20tree%20trunks%20are%20bundles,the%20highest%20leaves%20and%20branches.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;crying&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.livescience.com/plants-squeal-when-stressed.html%23:~:text%3DIn%2520times%2520of%2520intense%2520stress,research%252C%2520which%2520was%2520posted%2520Dec.&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1617439122668000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw1wb0Gj7etCY8AZW2sBMSLQ&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;screaming&lt;/a&gt; (when they are cut down). The “tears of trees” can have a double meaning: the liquid tears of a tree or the wailing of the tree. The liquid is produced through a process known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.topperlearning.com/answer/why-negative-root-pressure-develops-due-to-excessive-transpiration/d04llzhh%23:~:text%3DRoot%2520pressure%2520is%2520the%2520positive,of%2520nutrients%2520from%2520the%2520soil.%26text%3DThis%2520creates%2520a%2520negative%2520pressure,the%2520roots%252C%2520through%2520the%2520stem.&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1617439274558000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw2bD6a3IfP__AuR0iquYh-N&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;positive root pressure&lt;/a&gt;, where the roots take up water to the limbs of the trees in warm weather so that the buds can break. The wailing of the tree is what occurs when the tree is thirsty. When trees lack water, they suffer and make a noise. The noise, however, is ultrasonic, meaning that it is too high-pitched for the human ear to possibly pick up. Trees will also produce ultrasonic noises between 20 and 100 kilohertz when they’re in pain or when they’re scared, such as when they are being cut down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trees, of course, do not have eyes, ears, a mouth or any other means to communicate. But trees can actually &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newscientist.com/article/mg21528791-800-plant-senses-sight/#:~:text=The%20obvious%20answer%20is%20that,ultraviolet%20parts%20of%20the%20spectrum.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;see&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://now.northropgrumman.com/can-plants-hear-the-science-of-sound-sensing-flora/#:~:text=Shhhhhh.,More%20importantly%2C%20they%20can%20react.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;hear&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cannagardening.com/how_plants_communicate#:~:text=Plants%20taste%20and%20smell%20as,far%20away%20other%20plants%20are.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;taste&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smithsonianmag.com/science-nature/the-whispering-trees-180968084/#:~:text=To%20communicate%20through%20the%20network,are%20just%20beginning%20to%20decipher.&amp;amp;text=Trees%20also%20communicate%20through%20the,pheromones%20and%20other%20scent%20signals.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;communicate&lt;/a&gt;. The sight of a plant may exist because they grow towards areas with light, meaning that they can sense the light with their leaves. Plants can also hear to the degree that they can even respond to human voices. Trees use their roots to absorb nutrients and to taste. They also have a wide arsenal of ways to communicate with one another, including sending chemical, hormonal and slow-pulsing electrical signals and communicating through the air using scent. Trees even have senses that we lack, such as being able to sense &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pri.org/stories/2014-01-09/new-research-plant-intelligence-may-forever-change-how-you-think-about-plants&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gravitational changes, the presence of water or even a block in their roots&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a way, the needs of a tree are similar to that of a human. Trees need water, food and air. In contrast to humans needing water to use their bodies and excrete waste, trees need water to make their food. As stated, trees use water, sunlight and carbon dioxide to create oxygen and glucose using the equation 6CO2 + 6H2O → C6H12O6 + 6O2 where 6 carbon dioxide molecules and 6 water molecules along with sunlight produce glucose (C6H12O6) and 6 oxygen atoms as a waste product. Unlike us, the tree basically inhales carbon dioxide and exhales oxygen, while we inhale oxygen and exhale carbon dioxide. Trees drink water through a natural straw known as their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/science/xylem&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;xylem&lt;/a&gt;, which brings water to their utmost branches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anatomy of a tree is similar to human anatomy as well. The arms of a human can be like the branches of a tree. Trees have tree sap that transports nutrients and water through the tree, very much like how blood transports nutrients and water to our entire body. The bronchi in our lungs are also similar to the roots of trees. The leaves of a tree, aside from producing glucose, work as hair for the tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a recap, trees do not have all human characteristics. In fact, the emotional range of a tree is limited. They may feel pain, but they do not feel regret, happiness, or anything of that sort. However, they do cry and scream, and although seemingly lack the ability to, can see, hear, feel and communicate. Trees have the needs and anatomy of humans in some ways. Globally, trees have many useful aspects such as improving water and air quality, boosting peoples’ health, keeping global warming in check and so much more. Keeping all this in mind, along with the fact that trees are in some ways similar to us, we should love trees more before they’re gone forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gamesdash.com/pic/130/picture/the-tree-of-human-face&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Gamesdash)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Peter Bui&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Peter Bui</name></author><summary type="html">Trees are a little like humans Peter Bui. 04/03/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/treesCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/treesCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring the bilingual brain</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/18/exploring-the-bilingual-brain.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring the bilingual brain" /><published>2021-03-18T17:00:03-07:00</published><updated>2021-03-18T17:00:03-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/03/18/exploring-the-bilingual-brain</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/18/exploring-the-bilingual-brain.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Exploring the bilingual brain&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nafisa Ishra. 03/26/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/march/brainOne.png&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Above is a graphic that explains some of the advantages of a bilingual brain in children, such as improving the ability to solve problems and making decisions. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.figur8.net/2018/11/15/the-truth-about-the-bilingual-brain/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Nature for the Future)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many people all over the world who can speak more than one language, either out of necessity or simply by choice. Being bilingual can offer so much more than simply the ability to communicate with more people. For example, it can improve brain function and slow down the effects of aging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;How does being bilingual affect brain structure?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Being bilingual can &lt;a href=&quot;https://knowablemagazine.org/article/mind/2018/how-second-language-can-boost-brain#:~:text=As%20bilingual%20individuals%20age%2C%20their,monolingual%20people%2C%20enhancing%20cognitive%20reserve.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;improve one’s executive function&lt;/a&gt;, which is one’s ability to plan, coordinate attention and avoid distractions. This is because the area of the brain that is used to regulate two languages is also used when performing tasks while filtering out distractions. In general, the bilingual brain has greater gray matter (the cell bodies and dendrites in our neurons). Gray matter is connected to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.beingpatient.com/improve-grey-matter-brain-cardio-exercise/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;memory, decision-making, speech&lt;/a&gt;, etc., making gray matter associated with the health of the brain. Additionally, the bilingual brain has stronger neural connections, and its white matter (the axons of the neurons) suffers less damage, which means the communication between neurons is quicker.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medicalnewstoday.com/articles/319642&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Professor Viorica Marian&lt;/a&gt; from Northwestern University conducted a study that revealed that more areas of the brain, specifically the frontal and subcortical areas, were affected in a bilingual person than a monolingual person when they heard similar sounding things. A monolingual brain tends to only think of words in that language while bilinguals have to use more parts of the brain to differentiate between similar sounding words from two different languages. This points to greater neural plasticity, which is the ability of our nervous system to adjust to environmental changes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The bilingual brain also experiences the effects of aging at a slower rate. For one, degradation of white matter is associated with aging, and as stated above, the white matter in a bilingual brain experiences less damage. Being able to coordinate attention to different tasks while avoiding distractions also gives bilinguals an advantage because the inability to control attention is connected to the loss of cognitive function as we age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;How does being bilingual affect children?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are some common misconceptions when it comes to being bilingual that need to be addressed. First, if a child learns two languages together, it will not confuse them or hinder their development. In fact, cognitive flexibility (the ability to switch between different tasks or ideas) in a child’s brain will increase because their cognitive muscles need to work hard to switch from one language to another. Children frequently do this when speaking to different family members, and this can later be applied to other everyday tasks. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.canr.msu.edu/news/advantages_of_a_bilingual_brain&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;results of a 2004 study&lt;/a&gt; conducted by psychologists Ellen Bialystok and Michelle Martin-Rhee highlight that bilingual children could separate objects based on their shape and color more easily than monolingual children which points to a higher functioning command center in the brain of bilingual children. The command center of the brain controls problem-solving and execution of difficult cognitive tasks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, another widely held belief is that children learn a second language faster than adults, but whether or not that is true is still an ongoing debate. Children can pick up the basics of a language faster than adults because their brains can &lt;a href=&quot;https://tessais.org/children-learn-languages-faster-adults/#:~:text=Later%20in%20life%2C%20those%20neural,languages%20at%20a%20faster%20rate&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;create neural connections at a much higher rate&lt;/a&gt;. As a result, they have greater brain plasticity. Another area that children excel at is pronunciation because they have &lt;a href=&quot;https://wp.dinolingo.com/articles/do-children-learn-languages-faster-than-adults/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;greater neuromuscular control&lt;/a&gt;, as their brains are not used to any phonetics yet, making it easier for them to create new sounds. However, when it comes to mastery of a second language, adults are still superior because children are unable to comprehend things such as verb tenses and sentence structure while the adults are bound to focus on those skills when they actively study a second language. Children will pick up vocabulary from their family members without even realizing they are learning something, making their language skills more elementary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many scientists use the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.todayifoundout.com/index.php/2019/11/do-kids-really-learn-languages-faster-than-adults/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Critical Period hypothesis&lt;/a&gt;, by Wilder Penfield and Lamar Roberts, to argue that learning a second language is faster for children. The hypothesis states that there is a critical period of time, which ends when a person reaches puberty, for language learning, but this is only true for a first language. Many &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tradiling.net/a-critical-period-to-learn-a-second-language/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;studies have shown&lt;/a&gt; that the critical period differs based on the category of language learning such as phonology or syntax, and there is no sudden change in our ability to learn a second language right after puberty.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are still so many questions unanswered about the bilingual brain. What other differences are there between a bilingual brain and a monolingual brain that we have yet to discover? Why do the same rules not apply to learning a first and second language for children? Despite all of these mysteries that remain unsolved, there are several benefits to learning a second language that have already been proven for both adults and children. So even if it might seem unfathomable with most of our busy schedules, try setting aside 10 minutes a day, open up Duolingo, start learning some basic vocabulary and go from there.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bhlingual.com/how-does-the-bilingual-brain-work-blog&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Bhlingual)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Nafisa Ishra&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Nafisa Ishra</name></author><summary type="html">Exploring the bilingual brain Nafisa Ishra. 03/26/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/march/brainCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/march/brainCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The seven supercontinents</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/18/the-seven-supercontinents.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The seven supercontinents" /><published>2021-03-18T17:00:03-07:00</published><updated>2021-03-18T17:00:03-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/03/18/the-seven-supercontinents</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/18/the-seven-supercontinents.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The seven supercontinents&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sydney Hollingsworth. 03/19/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/march/supercontinentsOne.png&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;An artist’s rendition of what the early supercontinent, Ur, might have looked like.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.the-dialogue.com/en/en33-earths-supercontinents/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(The Dialogue)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You’ve probably heard of Pangaea, the enormous supercontinent that formed 300 million years ago and broke apart into the continents we know today. But did you know scientists believe that a total of seven supercontinents have formed over the course of Earth’s history?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://earthobservatory.sg/faq-on-earth-sciences/what-supercontinent&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Supercontinents&lt;/a&gt; are single connected continents made up of all or most of the land on the surface of Earth. Plate tectonics under these landmasses float on the molten mantle under the Earth’s crust, slowly pushing continents together and breaking them apart. The plates are moved over long periods of time by changes in temperature, intensity or direction in the flow of the mantle. This results in new supercontinents forming and splitting up about every 400 to 500 million years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But why do supercontinents matter? Plate tectonics move so slowly, about three to five centimeters a year, that their changes are hardly noticeable to humans. In fact, they are so hard to detect that the theory of continental drift wasn’t proposed until the 20th century, and still wasn’t accepted until the 1960s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, we now know that over billions of years, continental drift has shaped &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=KfYn9KVya-Q&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;almost every aspect of the Earth&lt;/a&gt; as we know it. Extinction events and climate changes are closely tied to plate tectonics. For example, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://cosmosmagazine.com/earth/earth-sciences/tectonic-timelapse/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Snowball Earth&lt;/a&gt; theory hypothesizes that two ice ages about 720 million years ago were caused by erosion of mountain ranges that pushed nutrients into the sea, resulting in an explosion of oxygen-producing bacteria. This drastic change in Earth’s atmosphere would have had many effects on the climate, and eventually led to the surface of the Earth becoming covered in glaciers, as well as one of the planet’s earliest mass extinctions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even after the possibility of supercontinents was accepted, it was nearly impossible to find evidence of the supercontinents before Pangaea. Since &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.livescience.com/43220-subduction-zone-definition.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;subduction&lt;/a&gt; (the movement of plates under each other and into the mantle) and seafloor melt replace plate tectonic material, nearly all of the land that makes up the Earth’s crust is less than 200 million years old.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, thanks to research into the mineral distribution and carbon dating, we can piece together what past supercontinents might have looked like, how they formed and how they broke apart. Although all models of early Earth’s plate tectonics are very theoretical, scientists can generally agree that there have been a total of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=http://www.the-dialogue.com/en/en33-earths-supercontinents/&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1616228929288000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw25c5VGA4_JEWNLTPmFwbRR&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;seven supercontinents&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first and earliest supercontinent to have existed is the most theoretical. The supercontinent Vaalbara is suspected to have formed 3.6 billion years ago from the Kaapvaal and Pilbara &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/science/craton&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;cratons&lt;/a&gt; (stable blocks of Earth’s crust that form the center of a continent). These cratons can now be found in South Africa and Western Australia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The supercontinent Ur, its name meaning “original” in German, formed shortly after Vaalbara from the same cratons approximately 3 billion years ago. The specifics of this continent are also very theoretical, and despite its supercontinent status, the land mass would have been smaller than modern-day Australia. Ur remained intact as a part of other supercontinents until Pangaea split apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About 300 million years after Ur’s formation, the supercontinent &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thearmchairexplorer.com/geology/kenorland.php&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Kenorlan&lt;/a&gt; came together from the merging of Vaalbara and the newly formed continental crust along the planet’s equator. At this time, eukaryotic organisms were emerging in the world’s oceans. As the supercontinent split apart, geologic events and the rise of oxygen-producing, single-celled life created the conditions for the Earth’s first glaciers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next supercontinent only existed for a short while: Colombia, also called Nuna or Hudsonland, formed about 1.8 billion years ago and broke up 1.5 billion years ago. During this time, the first plants colonized land in the form of red algae.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the time of the rise of the next supercontinent, &lt;a href=&quot;https://carnegiescience.edu/news/one-supercontinents-different-others-it%E2%80%99s-rodinia&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Rodinia&lt;/a&gt;, 1.1 billion years ago, the Earth’s landmasses began to loosely resemble our current continents. Differently from most other supercontinents, Rodinia formed from two-sided subduction, where both tectonic plates involved are pushed down into the mantle, rather than just one. Unfortunately, this means the supercontinent’s formation did not involve much volcanic activity, leaving less preserved mineral evidence of the event. However, we do know that during Rodinia’s existence, the first multicellular organisms began to appear in oceans around the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;About 100 million years after Rodinia split in two, the supercontinent, Pannotia came together while most land was located at the Earth’s poles in glacier form. Two oceans, the Panthalassa and Pan-African, formed and later merged into one. Pannotia eventually split apart into four pieces: Gondwana, Baltica, Siberia and Laurentia. &lt;a href=&quot;http://earthguide.ucsd.edu/eoc/teachers/t_tectonics/p_pangaea2.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gondwana&lt;/a&gt; is sometimes considered its own supercontinent due to its large size, but it was not connected to the three other fairly large continents of the time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before the formation of Pangaea, life began to make its way from the ocean onto land. So, when the continents came together, these diverse forms of life which had evolved separately for over 100 million years were introduced to each other and began to spread and adapt to their new environments. The collision of the northern half, Laurasia, and southern half, Gondwana, also created many of the mountain ranges we see on our planet today. The end of Pangaea saw the rise of the dinosaurs. As landmasses drifted apart, species were separated and quickly evolved to adapt to their new, respective continents. By the time they came back together or were reconnected via land bridges, the dinosaurs would be long extinct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From Pangaea, the landmasses of Eurasia and North America would form from the Northern half, and Africa, South America, India, Australia and Antarctica would form from the Southern half. In the meantime, a continuous ocean ran across the entire equator, producing a very different global landscape than what we have today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Because of research into past supercontinents and plate tectonics, we can guess what our planet could look like someday in the distant future. Three such theories of how the next supercontinent will come together are the Pangaea Ultima, Amasia and Novopangaea theories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.nasa.gov/science-news/science-at-nasa/2000/ast06oct_1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Pangaea Ultima&lt;/a&gt; theory is the most commonly mentioned. In this scenario, Africa and Australia will continue their northward courses until they smash into Europe and Asia. Over millions of years, the Atlantic Ocean will widen, creating a new underwater mountain range down its center, until the Americas come full circle and collide with the Euro-African continent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Amasia supercontinent theory is similar to Pangaea Ultima as it also involves the expansion of the Atlantic, but it instead predicts that the continents will join together as they move to the North Pole. The Novopangaea theory is based on this idea but predicts Australia and Antarctica will join where the Pacific Ocean is today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study of past supercontinents and plate tectonics gives us insight into the inner workings of the Earth. Our planet is larger and older than we can comprehend, with more history than we can hope to learn. Understanding how it has changed can shed light on valuable information about almost every aspect of the Earth and the creatures that have lived on it, showing us how far we’ve come and where we might be headed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thoughtco.com/supercontinents-of-the-past-and-future-1441117&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Mark Garlick / Getty Images)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Sydney Hollingsworth&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sydney Hollingsworth</name></author><summary type="html">The seven supercontinents Sydney Hollingsworth. 03/19/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/march/supercontinentsCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/march/supercontinentsCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Brain on Fire: A disease almost undocumented in medical history</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/18/brain-on-fire-a-disease-almost-undocumented-in-medical-history.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Brain on Fire: A disease almost undocumented in medical history" /><published>2021-03-18T17:00:03-07:00</published><updated>2021-03-18T17:00:03-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/03/18/brain-on-fire-a-disease-almost-undocumented-in-medical-history</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/18/brain-on-fire-a-disease-almost-undocumented-in-medical-history.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Brain on Fire: A disease almost undocumented in medical history&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joan Joe. 03/19/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/march/brainOnFireOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This image of a brain on fire depicts the inflammatory symptoms of this autoimmune disease.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://lions-talk-science.org/2014/05/07/brain-attacks-what-happens-when-the-immune-system-targets-the-brain/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Lion Talks Science)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Imagine being a journalist juggling several articles, conducting multiple interviews, learning intensely and more, just to have your life turned completely upside down in a matter of months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2012/12/23/books/review/brain-on-fire-by-susannah-cahalan.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Susannah Cahalan&lt;/a&gt;, a 24-year-old reporter for the New York Post, knows what it’s like to be in that situation. She started to experience numbness, paranoia, light sensitivity and abnormal behavior in 2009. Seizures, hallucinations, increasingly erratic actions and even catatonia started to plague her. Her symptoms alarmed her relatives and perplexed several doctors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“An interesting case” is something you don’t want to be to your doctor. Cahalan had the misfortune of becoming a one-of-a-kind and perplexing case: she was gravely ill and rapidly deteriorating, but her MRIs, brain scans and blood tests were all fine. She took $1 million worth of blood tests and brain scans that were inconclusive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Grandiosity, hysteria, fits of irrational anger, nonsensical utterances and flat catatonic-like effect were among the signs of the condition, which were mostly indistinguishable from one another throughout their early stages. There were also seizures with “blood and foam” spurting from Cahalan’s mouth, indicating a neurological condition rather than mental illness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cahalan was seen by Dr. Souhel Najjar, a Syrian-American neurologist, after a month in the hospital. He asked her to draw a clock on a piece of paper. She drew the circles and the numbers one to 12 all on the right-hand side of the clock, but the left-hand side was blank. It revealed that she had left-side spatial neglect and that the right side of her brain, which controls her left field of vision, was inflamed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Najjar simply told her parents that her brain was on fire. This observation led to her getting diagnosed with &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anti-NMDA_receptor_encephalitis#:~:text=Anti%2DNMDA%20receptor%20encephalitis%20is,%2C%20headache%2C%20and%20feeling%20tired.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;anti-NMDA receptor encephalitis&lt;/a&gt;, a very rare autoimmune disease that is almost undocumented in the medical literature. Dr. Josep Dalmau and colleagues at the University of Pennsylvania first discovered anti-NMDA receptor encephalitis in 2007.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The disorder was portrayed in the 2016 Netflix film &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=VZn6G0M9wNs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Brain on Fire&lt;/a&gt; in which Susannah Cahalan was played by Chloe Grace Moretz. This film was based on Susannah’s book called “&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Brain_on_Fire&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Brain on Fire: My Month of Madness&lt;/a&gt;” after chronicling her experience in a 2009 New York Post report.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/march/brainOnFireTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Above is the movie poster for Netflix’s film “Brain On Fire”.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netflix.com/title/80128245&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Netflix)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Anti-NMDAR encephalitis induces confusion, memory loss and seizures, which are often accompanied by altered consciousness and changes in blood pressure, heart rate and temperature, as portrayed in the film. The film’s graphic depictions of these symptoms – hallucinations, delusions and aggression – shocked audiences, but were true.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The entire event (in the hospital) lasted one month, but Susannah has no recollection of what happened to her, except for sporadic, almost hallucinatory flashbacks, such as being strapped to her hospital bed as a “flight risk.” Her only knowledge of what had happened to her and her behavior came from a journal kept by her father, mother and boyfriend when they were watching over her in the hospital. After her diagnosis, Susannah was quickly on the mend, and after several months, she was able to return to work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young women like Susannah are the majority of those who experience anti-NMDA receptor encephalitis. The average age is 20 years old. Since people’s behavioral changes can be very drastic, it’s not uncommon for them to be admitted to a psychiatric facility first. Physicians usually know the issue isn’t mental when neurological signs occur, such as seizures or a lack of responsiveness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nearly every neuron in the brain contains NMDA receptors. These receptors are necessary for the development of new memories in the hippocampus of humans and animals, and have been linked to several neurological and psychiatric disorders such as Alzheimer’s disease, schizophrenia and depression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/march/brainOnFireThree.png&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;A schematic diagram of an NMDA receptor.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Anti-NMDA_receptor_encephalitis&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Wikipedia)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antibodies are components of the immune system that protect the body from infection and illness. They respond with proteins in the body when they don’t function properly, resulting in an autoimmune disorder. Autoimmune encephalitis is a condition in which the body reacts to proteins in the brain. An assault on the NMDA receptor, one of the most important neurotransmitter receptors in the brain, prompts the adverse side effects that come with the condition. Intellectual changes, extreme memory loss, seizures and even death are all symptoms of the disorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/march/brainOnFireFour.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;A graphical representation of the symptoms of autoimmune encephalitis.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.med.upenn.edu/autoimmuneneurology/nmdar-encephalitis.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Perelman School Of Medicine)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Anti-NMDA receptor encephalitis manifests itself in a variety of ways, with varying degrees of severity. Patients usually begin with milder symptoms and quickly progress to a condition that necessitates hospitalization. Clinical signs are often used to diagnose anti-NMDA receptor encephalitis. The diagnosis is validated by analyzing the cerebral spinal fluid (CSF) or blood serum in the lab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The medication for this condition varies by patient but usually involves a combination of first and second-line treatments. The first-line treatment consists of tumor removal (if present), steroids, plasma exchange (plasmapheresis) and intravenous immunoglobulin (IVIG). The second-line treatment is generally &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webmd.com/drugs/2/drug-4067-2108/cellcept-oral/mycophenolate-mofetil-oral/details&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CellCept&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medicinenet.com/rituximab/article.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Rituximab&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rxlist.com/cytoxan-drug.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Cytoxan&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recovery is gradual and usually happens in the same order as the onset of symptoms. The most serious symptoms usually go away first, although cognitive, behavioral and memory issues take longer. Within two years of onset, the majority of patients will be completely recovered. The prompt diagnosis and aggressive treatment, including second-line therapies, are all predictors of positive outcomes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even if we do not know the exact cause of this disease, we can hope for significant advances in this field of study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.netflix.com/title/80128245&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Netflix)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Joan Joe&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Joan is a freshman in St. Antony’s Public School, India. She is intrigued by psychology and neuroscience and aspires to join research in neuroscience and STEM-related works. She hopes to help others pursue their passion for STEM through her platform. In her free time, she plays the piano, sings, and loves to read Dan Brown’s books.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Joan Joe</name></author><summary type="html">Brain on Fire: A disease almost undocumented in medical history Joan Joe. 03/19/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/march/brainOnFireCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/march/brainOnFireCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Time dilation: The nature of space-time</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/11/time-dilation-the-nature-of-space-time.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Time dilation: The nature of space-time" /><published>2021-03-11T16:00:05-08:00</published><updated>2021-03-11T16:00:05-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/03/11/time-dilation-the-nature-of-space-time</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/11/time-dilation-the-nature-of-space-time.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Time dilation: The nature of space-time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aryav Nagar. 03/13/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/march/timeDilationOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The diagram above shows Earth’s effect on spacetime curvature.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://thescienceexplorer.com/universe/how-gravity-changes-time-effect-known-gravitational-time-dilation&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Science Explorer)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;What is time dilation?&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Einstein’s theory of relativity suggested a new outlook of space-time itself. He described time as modified; rather than time being a constant moving parameter, it moves relative to an object’s path. Time can be warped or changed by high gravitational forces and immense speeds. Essentially, speed and force can alter the fabric of space-time entirely. Timewarp predominantly causes time to slow down or speed up in the observer’s perspective, which is otherwise known as time dilation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Speed and time dilation&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;To understand the effects of time dilation, we need to understand the true nature of light. The reason behind light’s immense speed is the nature of photons. Since photons are massless, outside forces cannot affect the path these particles take. Their massless nature causes not only immense speeds but also instant acceleration. Unlike time itself, light is a constant moving wave, meaning however fast the initial light source is moving, the photons themselves always travel at a constant rate. This speed is also known as the speed of light. Regardless of whether they are emitted from a moving car or a stationary street lamp, the photons all travel at the same speed. On Earth, every second, light travels one light second. Because no feasible mass can travel fully at this speed, let alone an aircraft, let us suppose humanity is, in general constructs, a space carrier capable of achieving speeds that are a large percentage of the speed of light. Since the light on this aircraft, emitted from integrated light sources (such as control panels, inner light bulbs, etc.) can never exceed the speed of light, the photons aboard this high-speed craft travel a greater distance than on a stationary object such as Earth. The light within the aircraft is moving normally, but its journey amplifies due to the craft’s exterior movement. Per every light-second (relative to Earth) onboard the craft, the photons themselves are traveling a light second plus the ship’s velocity. How is this possible? If light always travels at a constant speed, why does one light-second on board the vessel differ from on Earth? This is essentially breaking the laws of physics. To precisely understand how space-time is affected by this inconstant light speed, we need to understand Isaac Newton’s laws of motion and James Clerk Maxwell’s law of electromagnetism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Newton’s laws described the movement as a relative constant, and his equations refer to these magnitudes as “with respect to.” For example, a train is traveling 40 mph with respect to someone at rest. However, it only travels 20 mph with respect to another train traveling 20 mph in the same direction. Now let us imagine the man at rest was watching the train from space. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/how-fast-is-the-earth-mov/#:~:text=Thus%2C%20the%20surface%20of%20the,or%2067%2C000%20miles%20per%20hour.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Considering Earth’s orbital speed&lt;/a&gt;, with respect to the man in space, the train moves 67,000 mph. On the other hand, Maxwell found the speed of an electromagnetic wave, such as light, is fixed. It always &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.space.com/15830-light-speed.html#:~:text=The%20speed%20of%20light%20in,7.5%20times%20in%20one%20second.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;travels at 670,616,629 mph&lt;/a&gt; regardless of who observes it. When faced with inconsistent lightspeed, either Newton’s laws were incomplete and constant speeds did exist, or Maxwell was wrong about light being a universal constant. Einstein realized both laws could coexist by tweaking Newton’s formula. He suggested time itself, for the craft members, must slow down to compensate for the immense speeds such that the magnitude, or one light second, remains constant on both Earth and onboard the ship. Essentially, the closer one travels to the speed of light, the slower time travels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Time dilation thought experiments - The twin experiment&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Since time itself slows down to compensate for light’s uneven magnitude, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/how-does-relativity-theor/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;processes affected by time also slow down&lt;/a&gt;. To put this into perspective, imagine two identical twin babies are part of this thought experiment. One baby is left on Earth and another is launched in a rocket traveling at 99.999999999 percent (eight zeros) of the speed of light. Abiding by Einstein’s special theory of relativity, the two twins will experience time very differently. Eighty years go by, respective to Earth, and the near lightspeed rocket lands. Both twins are brought into a room. The baby on Earth would have grown into an older man, but the baby on board the rocket would have only aged one day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Time and Dilation&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Space-time is not only affected by speed but also by gravity. As the force of gravity increases, with larger mass objects, its gravitational field grows stronger. Einstein predicted how this &lt;a href=&quot;http://thescienceexplorer.com/universe/how-gravity-changes-time-effect-known-gravitational-time-dilation&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;strengthened gravitational field&lt;/a&gt; curves the fabric of space. Since every mass has a gravitational field, any object in the universe affects the fabric of space. Although confusing, we can simulate this curvature with an experiment. By holding a piece of paper by its edges and placing a small weight in the center, we see how the page bends or curves down. The curvature, again, has a direct effect on the light itself. Rather than traveling in a straight path, the light itself must curve with respect to space-time curvature. Imagine two light waves are shined from point A to point B. These points are precisely one light-second apart. One path is directly in a straight line whilst the other is under the influence of gravity. The lightwave taking the straight path will reach point B in exactly one second. Due to the curved path the second light wave must travel, it will take light longer than one second to get to point B. As discussed with dilation speed, time itself must compensate for this uneven light path by slowing down. As time passes slower for the bent lightwave, it can travel further within a shorter period of time, therefore reaching point B in one second. The speed of this light wave does not change, but time does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Applying time dilation to the real world&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Although this concept of relativity dilation seems inapplicable to modern technology, as humanity is not near the development of near light-speed intergalactic travel, the idea of time dilation is still used in daily processes. Satellite communication and projection technology take time dilation into account. Since GPS satellites orbit 12,400 miles away from Earth’s surface at a velocity of 17,000 miles per hour, both their high speeds and weakened gravity slow the time around these satellites. This results in a difference of roughly 38 microseconds between the clocks on Earth and the clocks in space (the space-clocks are ticking at a slower rate). GPS satellites use a hyper-precise clock to determine exact locations on Earth’s surface (more information about GPS location can be found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.faa.gov/about/office_org/headquarters_offices/ato/service_units/techops/navservices/gnss/gps/howitworks/#:~:text=GPS%20satellites%20carry%20atomic%20clocks,time%20the%20signal%20was%20broadcast.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). To the naked eye, &lt;a href=&quot;https://physicscentral.com/explore/writers/will.cfm#:~:text=Einstein's%20general%20relativity%20theory%20says,about%2038%20microseconds%20per%20day.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;38 microseconds&lt;/a&gt; are unnoticeable, but this delay can account for a 6-mile offset for GPS satellites. GPS travel would be much worse than simple unreliability. For example, a six-mile inaccuracy in terms of air travel could potentially be dangerous. Aircraft might be directed away from safe airports, and air traffic control would be nearly impossible. To account for time dilation, satellites’ clocks tick 38 microseconds faster than the clocks on Earth. This allows both clocks to tick at the same rate as the faster-paced clocks cancel the slowed time. So next time you look up and see an aircraft, know that Einstein’s theory of relativity helps it travel safely and accurately.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.livescience.com/why-is-space-a-vacuum.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Live Science)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Aryav Nagar&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Aryav Nagar</name></author><summary type="html">Time dilation: The nature of space-time Aryav Nagar. 03/13/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/march/timeDilationCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/march/timeDilationCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why listening to music has more beneficial effects for your health than you thought</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/11/why-listening-to-music-has-more-beneficial-effects.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why listening to music has more beneficial effects for your health than you thought" /><published>2021-03-11T16:00:03-08:00</published><updated>2021-03-11T16:00:03-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/03/11/why-listening-to-music-has-more-beneficial-effects</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/03/11/why-listening-to-music-has-more-beneficial-effects.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Why listening to music has more beneficial effects for your health than you thought&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Volodymyr Prylepa. 03/13/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/march/musicOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;(Shutterstock / Merla)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As opposed to popular belief, music isn’t only used for entertainment, as it has numerous applications in arts and sciences. However, as it turns out, it can take a toll on our physical and psychological well-being.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first glance, it may seem surprising, but many people overlook the impact music has had on their lives; instead, they only perceive music as a way of biding their time. A good mixtape is especially important during these times, where everyone is bound to an inactive, home-restricted lifestyle. Starting with its impact on general productivity and mental health to its impact on cardiovascular immunity and neurogenesis, one could argue that music is one of the most effective yet underrated “medicinal drugs” of our time. British neurologist Robert Sacks said it best: “The power of music to integrate and cure is quite fundamental. It is the most profound non-chemical medication.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be it Bruno Mars, Ariana Grande or Juice Wrld, any musical piece you listen to can and will affect your body and mind. Listening to music allows stimulation of &lt;a href=&quot;https://psychcentral.com/news/2018/12/23/music-soothes-anxiety-reduces-pain#1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;specific sensory brain pathways&lt;/a&gt; that decentralize the cognitive focus from other sensory paths responsible for making us feel pain. It creates a positive emotional response and helps reduce pain stimuli by shifting our center of attention from pain to music. So if you are suffering, listen to some tune you enjoy, and it will help you manage the pain. You may find yourself turning to music once again to diminish your levels of stress. &lt;a href=&quot;https://myscena.org/newswire/the-science-behind-why-classical-music-is-good-for-mental-health/#:~:text=Neurologist%20Dr.%20Michael%20Schneck%20found%20that%20classical%20musichelps,26%25%2C%20laughter%20by%2016%25%20and%20relaxation%20by%2011%25.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Natural sounds, flat musical notes and classical western music&lt;/a&gt; reduce cortisol, a hormone responsible for stress and anxiety, in the body.
Now, whether you are doing homework, studying for a test or working on a project, you will often try to eliminate any distractions, including music, to avoid severe procrastination. However, music does influence the mindset with which we will tackle a task. Yes, you heard it right: listening to your favorite bopping Lady Gaga song will not only motivate you to complete an assignment but also make you more &lt;a href=&quot;https://psychologenie.com/effects-of-music-on-mind-brain#:~:text=%20Effects%20of%20Music%20on%20the%20Mental%20State,of%20learning%20and%20thinking.%20Listening%20to...%20More%20&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;productive and confident&lt;/a&gt;! It will heighten your performance and put a stop to procrastination, which will have a positive effect on your mental health and self-esteem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly enough, music has shown to be quite a factor in fighting certain mental and brain illnesses. When exposed to gentle music, the human brain produces lots of serotonin (a neurotransmitter) the lack of which causes depression. Consequently, relaxing and soothing notes are the weapon of choice in a fight against depression. Moreover, patients that are victims of Alzheimer’s disease and dementia will benefit from musical performances. Their brain cells, the ones that play a role in their memory capacity, will be activated, which would allow the patients to fight the obliviousness brought by their disease. Similarly, &lt;a href=&quot;https://neuro.hms.harvard.edu/centers-and-initiatives/harvard-mahoney-neuroscience-institute/about-hmni/archive-brain-1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;researchers at Harvard&lt;/a&gt; noticed that when people with Parkinson’s disease heard rhythmic music, the brain canals responsible for physical movement dynamized, partially relieving their condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, music has a remarkable curative effect on the human body. Listening to music can increase the chances of a positive post-surgery outcome. When listening to our favorite melody, our bodies produce endorphins, which speed up the curative process of healing. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/22828457/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt; shows that working out without a beat will make reaching our full physical potential harder and increases the quantity of oxygen we use. On the other hand, a workout with music in the background allows us to maximize our effectiveness with less oxygen consumption. Listening to music has been shown to reduce &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.healthline.com/health/benefits-of-music#takeaway&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;fatigue&lt;/a&gt;, allowing a longer physical activity, even in patients with cancer. According to the following &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/18692321/#:~:text=We%20propose%20that%20listening%20to%20music%20facilitates%20the,of%20steroid%20hormones%2C%20ultimately%20leading%20to%20cerebral%20plasticity.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;study&lt;/a&gt;, music can even make our brains create more neurons, which leads to cerebral plasticity, an element that affects child and adult development. Listening to music is recommended to people with various diseases, such as the previously mentioned cancer or high blood pressure. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.health.harvard.edu/newsletter_article/using-music-to-tune-the-heart&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Patients with heart conditions had their blood pressure lowered and their heart rate slowed down simply from listening to music for 30 minutes&lt;/a&gt;. According to epidemiology professor at &lt;a href=&quot;http://medicine.wvu.edu/News/Story?headline=wvu-innews-uniting-power-of-music-during-isolation&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;West Virginia University School of Public Health&lt;/a&gt; Kin Innes, “music seems to selectively activate neurochemical systems and brain structures associated with positive mood, emotion regulation, attention and memory in ways that promote beneficial changes.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Music has come a long way, with its styles changing throughout history frequently. The one thing to remain unfazed about it is that any interaction music ever had with the human ear has resulted in a physical or psychological impact on the human body. It is crucial to remember the effects of music on our healthiness, especially now that everyone is at home, barely going outside, mostly working during the day and watching television or YouTube in the evening. Listening to music while working, during a workout or before going to sleep instead of binge-watching a series would have more beneficial effects on our health. Of course, we won’t stay perfectly fit and healthy just by listening to music now and then, but it would be one of the steps that lead us towards a better, more durable way of living.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Getty Images)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Volodymyr Prylepa&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Volodymyr Prylepa</name></author><summary type="html">Why listening to music has more beneficial effects for your health than you thought Volodymyr Prylepa. 03/13/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/march/musicCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/march/musicCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>