<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-02-27T00:37:15-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">InterSTEM</title><entry><title type="html">All about phobias</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/25/diy-snowflake-crystals.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="All about phobias" /><published>2021-02-25T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-25T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/25/diy-snowflake-crystals</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/25/diy-snowflake-crystals.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;All about phobias&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mehri Sadri. 02/26/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/february/snowflakeOne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Individuals can enjoy crafting their work not only into snowflake shapes, but also as 3D objects pictured above. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sweetpaulmag.com/crafts/lets-make-borax-crystal-ornaments&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Sweet Paul)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
With InterSTEM being based in Southern California, many of the volunteers, including myself, suffer from not-so-serious snow deprivation. Reminiscing the idea of frozen crystals falling from the sky, I took it into my own hands to create an alternate winter wonderland, one that anyone, regardless of their geographical location, can experience and enjoy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This project is inspired by &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sweetpaulmag.com/crafts/lets-make-borax-crystal-ornaments&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sweet Paul&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Ingredients needed&lt;/b&gt;:
  &lt;br /&gt;-Pipe cleaners to shape the designs
  &lt;br /&gt;-Thin metal or wooden sticks
  &lt;br /&gt;-Invisible thread that’ll be used to prop up the finished product (The thinner the material, the less noticeable it’ll be if you’d like to hang up your creations)
  &lt;br /&gt;-Spoons, forks or any other mixing material needed (I recommend that your material is one-time use, as one of the vital ingredients to this craft, borax, can be abrasive to touch.)
  &lt;br /&gt;-Borax (This is a common ingredient used during laundry. If you are doing this craft with kids, please make sure that they do not consume any, as it is toxic.)
  Hot water (It can be room temperature, but the borax dilutes faster in a higher degree liquid.)
  &lt;br /&gt;-Equipment that can be used to heat up substances (microwave or stove)
  &lt;br /&gt;-Tools to measure with (cup, spoons, etc) as all the ingredients need to be added in somewhat exact measurements
  &lt;br /&gt;-A foil or lid to cover the water&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Steps:&lt;/b&gt;
  &lt;br /&gt;1. Get six cups of your water (I will be making a big portion, but please feel free to scale down if you’d like to make less). If you’d like to speed up the borax dissolving process, then put the water in a microwave (in a safe container) or bring your water to a boil.
  &lt;br /&gt;2. Once you have your finished water, add your borax, mixing with a spoon or wooden stick. For six cups of water, I had to use 18-20 tablespoons of borax. Just in case, please wear gloves when handling the powder, and make sure that all children are supervised if participating.
  &lt;br /&gt;3. After adequately mixed (should have an off-white color), go ahead and let the solution sit for 20-50 minutes. If possible, seal the product with a towel or cap.
  &lt;br /&gt;4. Now, grab your pipe cleaner and start shaping it in the shape of your desired crystal. Afterward, get your invisible thread and tie one end of it to the pipe cleaner and the other one to the wooden or metal stick portion.
  &lt;br /&gt;5. Once your water solution is done sitting, you can take the lid off and dip your pipe cleaner into the solution by balancing the stick on the opening of the container. Avoid placing the stick in the crystal solution, but place the pipe cleaner in a position that leaves it steady and stable.
  &lt;br /&gt;6. Cover the container holding your solution with the submerged pipe cleaner inside. Your solution will likely be a rather milky-white color. Go ahead and put your solution in a room-temperature area, allowing the crystals to slowly grow for the next several hours (this shouldn’t take more than a day, but keep an eye on it).
  &lt;br /&gt;7. Over time, the solution should become clearer, and you should be able to see your crystals forming. After they reach a desirable size, go ahead and carefully take the pipe cleaner out. Make sure to dry it on some sort of rack so that it can dry and cool. Your creation will remain fragile as it dries, so make sure it doesn’t encounter any disturbances.
  &lt;br /&gt;8. Once the crystal creation is dried, you’re done! Feel free to hang your art, or place it as a nice, flat piece on a table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;So, how is this possible?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Crystals grow when a saturated liquid (a liquid that can vaporize) with some sort of mineral cools. In this instance, our saturated liquid would be the borax water, while the mineral is the borax itself (borax is actually what is known as a soft crystal). When the water starts hot (hence why hot water works better for this activity), the rapidly moving molecules cling onto the borax in a sense, which is why it seems dissolved and unseen. As the solution gets colder and colder (during the few hours you wait), water molecules move farther from each other (since they bounce off of each other less and less), meaning that the water cannot hold onto the dissolved borax well. Water lets go of the borax, and it evaporates, thus creating the crystal shape you should see if the craft is done properly. In other words, as the water cools down, borax cannot sustain itself in the molecules, so it protrudes outwards, forming crystals that grow increasingly bigger as the water cools down. Thus, the longer you wait, the larger the crystals get.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether it be room decor or on the next Christmas tree, this simple yet elegant craft makes great use out of only a few simple ingredients.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cmosc.org/borax-crystals/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Children’s Museum of Sonoma County)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/Mehri_Sadri.JPG&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Mehri Sadri&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Mehri is a senior at Scripps Ranch High School in San Diego, California. Although she has always been more inclined in humanities subjects, Mehri has found a love for combining science and art and their practicalities, and hopes to spread this same love to others with her articles.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Mehri Sadri</name></author><summary type="html">All about phobias Mehri Sadri. 02/26/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/snowflakeCover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/snowflakeCover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Engineering bacteria into insulin-producing factories genetically</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/25/engineering-bacteria-into-insulin-producing-factories-genetically.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Engineering bacteria into insulin-producing factories genetically" /><published>2021-02-25T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-25T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/25/engineering-bacteria-into-insulin-producing-factories-genetically</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/25/engineering-bacteria-into-insulin-producing-factories-genetically.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Engineering bacteria into insulin-producing factories genetically&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nadwa Atwi. 02/19/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/february/engineeringBacteriaOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The illustration shows a farmer growing ordinary corn (left) and a geneticist growing genetically modified corn (right). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mauimagazine.net/rooting-for-the-wrong-side/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Maui Magazine)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Ever since the concept of genetic engineering emerged in the early 1970s, various genetic discoveries have ensued. And although genetic engineering has stirred up plenty of controversy over the years, it remains the most important tool of biotechnology and one that has proved to be very promising, especially in the medical field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;What is genetic engineering?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Genetic engineering, also known as genetic modification, is the process of altering the DNA in an organism’s genome by swapping base pairs, deleting them or even introducing a whole gene to modify or enhance certain traits of the organism.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This technology has been applied in various areas. A simple example of genetic engineering in plants is providing them with herbicide resistance, which allows farmers to spray for weeds without damaging their crops. The first herbicide-resistant soybeans were introduced in 1996 by the American agrochemical company Monsanto under the title “Roundup Ready”. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.beyondpesticides.org/programs/genetic-engineering/herbicide-tolerance#:~:text=Monsanto%20first%20introduced%20glyphosate%2Dresistant,engineered%20to%20be%20glyphosate%20resistant.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Beyond Pesticides&lt;/a&gt;, these crops have become prevalent in American agriculture with 93% of soybeans, 82% of cotton and 85% of corn engineered to be herbicide-resistant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In medicine, a number of breakthroughs were made through genetic engineering. In addition to synthesizing human insulin using bacteria, scientists were also able to get bacteria to produce human growth hormone, alpha interferon and the hepatitis B vaccine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Gene therapy is also a recent technology closely associated with genetic engineering. It involves manipulating human genes to treat genetic diseases as opposed to genetic engineering’s purpose of enhancing already normal genes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://courses.lumenlearning.com/boundless-microbiology/chapter/genetic-engineering-products/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Lumen Learning&lt;/a&gt;, gene therapy has been used lately in clinical trials to treat conditions like cystic fibrosis, AIDS and cancer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The history of insulin&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diabetes is a disorder that causes the body’s blood glucose levels to rise to dangerously high levels. It’s a very common condition that can be treated by injecting insulin, which allows glucose to be taken up by the liver and other tissues. Consequently, cells obtain the glucose they require and blood glucose levels remain normal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Initially, insulin was obtained from the pancreases of animals, primarily pigs and cows, and used safely to manage diabetes for years. But it came with its drawbacks and over time, cases of adverse reactions associated with animal-derived insulin were reported. Also, extracting insulin from animals wasn’t exactly cost-effective. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gene.com/stories/cloning-insulin&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gene&lt;/a&gt;, 8,000 pounds of pancreas glands from 23,500 animals were required to make one pound of insulin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1978, the biotechnology firm “Genentech” produced human insulin using the bacteria E. coli, making insulin the first-ever human protein manufactured through biotechnology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And in 1982, the pharmaceutical company, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lilly.com/company/about-lilly/milestones-of-caring-and-discovery&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Eli Lilly&lt;/a&gt;, introduced the first-ever genetically-engineered human insulin under the brand name “Humulin”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;How the process works&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/february/engineeringBacteriaTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The diagram shows the steps leading up to the production of human insulin.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yourgenome.org/facts/what-is-genetic-engineering#:~:text=The%20genetic%20engineering%20process&amp;amp;text=The%20gene%20for%20human%20insulin,rapidly%20and%20starts%20making%20insulin.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(YourGenome)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Since the bacterium E. coli is known for having the fastest reproduction rate among bacteria (they can double in number every 20 minutes!), it is the preferred organism for human insulin production.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, the human insulin gene found in the human DNA is cut using a restriction enzyme.
A small part of the bacterial plasmid (a circular piece of DNA independent from the bacterium’s chromosome) is also cut out using a restriction enzyme.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ligase enzymes are used to insert the human insulin gene into the plasmid and join the two together. A recombinant plasmid, assembled out of fragments from various sources, is obtained.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/february/engineeringBacteriaThree.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The insulin gene is inserted into the plasmid and its ends are joined together with the plasmids using DNA ligase. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.khanacademy.org/science/ap-biology/gene-expression-and-regulation/biotechnology/a/overview-dna-cloning&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(KhanAcademy)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The recombinant plasmid, now containing the insulin gene, is injected into a bacterial cell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The human insulin gene is treated just like any other bacterial gene and is therefore transcribed into mRNA and then translated into proteins following the ordinary molecular machinery of protein synthesis. In this case, the protein of interest is called human insulin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bacteria are put in a fermenter (also known as a fermentation tank), which provides optimal conditions for bacterial growth. Bacteria can then reproduce rapidly in the tank, resulting in millions of insulin-gene-bearing bacteria that synthesize human insulin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since bacteria synthesize their own bacterial proteins in addition to the human insulin protein, the latter must be extracted and purified before packaging.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Biotechnology has drawn plenty of controversy despite all the breakthroughs it has led to. Several aspects of genetic engineering, in particular, were questioned. While the benefits of this field could be tremendous, many showed their apprehension over the consequences such a powerful tool can bring about. Since genetically-engineered organisms are still novel and not entirely understood, their release could present an ecological imbalance. And an accident in engineering the genetics of a bacteria or a virus, for example, could result in an unmanageable type of microorganisms that could lead to a fatal epidemic when released. There is no doubt that genetic engineering will still continue to raise many debates over the years, so further research will always be required in order to ensure the safety of any product produced using this precious but destructive tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://futureoflife.org/background/benefits-risks-biotechnology/?cn-reloaded=1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Future of Life Institute)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Nadwa Atwi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Nadwa is a pharmacy student from Lebanon. She is a science enthusiast that loves to feed her curiosity by probing into the most unusual medical conditions. Through InterSTEM, Nadwa aspires to let people recognize just how fascinating science can be, and hopes to share her passion with them as well. In her free time, she enjoys reading novels and reviewing them on her blog, binge-watching anime and fangirling over her favorite Kpop groups.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Nadwa Atwi</name></author><summary type="html">Engineering bacteria into insulin-producing factories genetically Nadwa Atwi. 02/19/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/engineeringBacteriaCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/engineeringBacteriaCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The evolution of machine learning</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/18/the-evolution-of-machine-learning.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The evolution of machine learning" /><published>2021-02-18T16:00:01-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-18T16:00:01-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/18/the-evolution-of-machine-learning</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/18/the-evolution-of-machine-learning.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The evolution of machine learning&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Omar Dajani. 02/19/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/february/machineLearningOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This illustration showcases the variety of topics and functions related to Machine learning and demonstrates how expansive this field has become.
(Dataversity)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Being one of the most popular computer science fields, machine learning (ML) has come a long way since &lt;a href=&quot;https://labelyourdata.com/articles/history-of-machine-learning-how-did-it-all-start/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;its inception back in the 1940s&lt;/a&gt;. It has been expanding ever since then and will likely continue to do so. But wait, what is ML? &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ibm.com/cloud/learn/machine-learning&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;According to IBM&lt;/a&gt;, it “focuses on applications that learn from experience and improve their decision-making or predictive accuracy over time.” ML is a branch of the much bigger artificial intelligence (AI) field in both computer science and technology in general, and it has a central focus on algorithms. The better the algorithm, the more efficient the ML will be in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the field’s inception technically being in the 1940s, it did not truly start becoming the ML we know today until the 1950s. To be more specific, &lt;a href=&quot;https://labelyourdata.com/articles/history-of-machine-learning-how-did-it-all-start/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1956&lt;/a&gt; marked the year of the Dartmouth Workshop, which has been credited countless times as &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/cantors-paradise/the-birthplace-of-ai-9ab7d4e5fb00&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“the birthplace of AI”&lt;/a&gt; over the years. During this workshop, 20 of the most intelligent minds in computer and cognitive science were brought together to work on a project seeking to uncover the degree to which computers and other machinery could push themselves. The event lasted approximately seven weeks and acted as one giant brainstorming session to figure out ways to push computers to their full potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/cantors-paradise/the-birthplace-of-ai-9ab7d4e5fb00&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Some outcomes&lt;/a&gt; of this workshop included John McCarthy (the event’s main organizer) coining the term ‘artificial intelligence’ during the conference and Arthur Samuels (one of the intelligent minds) eventually coining the term ‘machine learning’ three years later in 1959. Samuels would go on to create the Samuel Checkers-playing program, which was one of the world’s first self-learning programs. &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/rla-academy/dartmouth-workshop-the-birthplace-of-ai-34c533afe992&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Other outcomes&lt;/a&gt; involved Herbert Simon and Allen Newell (more of the intelligent minds) showing off Logic Theorist, which was the first program designed to copy the problem-solving skills of a human being after observing them in action and committing them to memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though the Dartmouth Workshop was centered around the advancement of AI, it had numerous outcomes, one of these being the creation of ML. Thus, the event not only was the birthplace of AI, but it was also technically the birthplace of ML as well. From there, the ML field continued its &lt;a href=&quot;https://labelyourdata.com/articles/history-of-machine-learning-how-did-it-all-start/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ever-growing expansion&lt;/a&gt;, eventually reaching another milestone during the 1980s and 1990s. This milestone was a change of focus from gaining more knowledge (which was ML’s main purpose before) to a new approach centered around data. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.doc.ic.ac.uk/~jce317/history-machine-learning.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;This new paradigm&lt;/a&gt; would make it so computers would learn from batches of data, rather than storing them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This new approach in the ML field was mainly centered around neural networks and support vector machines (SVM), with the former being the bigger focus. While the term ‘neural networks’ may seem daunting at first, it actually is not too hard to understand. Essentially, &lt;a href=&quot;https://victorzhou.com/blog/intro-to-neural-networks/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a neural network&lt;/a&gt; is a bundle of neurons all clumped together that work towards a specific goal. When it comes to ML, that ‘specific goal’ is making sure computers and other machinery can take various groups of data and learn from them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/february/machineLearningTwo.jpg&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This illustrates a simple neural network. Yes, this is what exists inside all computers and other machinery!
&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/coinmonks/the-artificial-neural-networks-handbook-part-1-f9ceb0e376b4&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Medium - VIASAT)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As for &lt;a href=&quot;https://towardsdatascience.com/support-vector-machine-introduction-to-machine-learning-algorithms-934a444fca47&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;SVMs&lt;/a&gt;, these act, as their name suggests, primarily for support. They help organize all the different data they come across through the use of margins and hyperplanes (which are used for &lt;a href=&quot;https://towardsdatascience.com/https-medium-com-pupalerushikesh-svm-f4b42800e989&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;data separation&lt;/a&gt;), which work together to classify data. SVMs are also big on math. There is a wide variety of functions (mainly ones relating to calculus) used in relation to SVMs, which are used for problem solving, and they may be even more sophisticated than neural networks as a result of this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ever since this new focus on neural networks and SVMs, ML has found itself being used for a variety of applications. For example, Facebook created the &lt;a href=&quot;https://labelyourdata.com/articles/history-of-machine-learning-how-did-it-all-start/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;DeepFace technology in 2014&lt;/a&gt; with the use of neural networks, which is used to recognize user facial features. In 2017, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2017/11/7/16615290/waymo-self-driving-safety-driver-chandler-autonomous&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Waymo introduced autonomous cars&lt;/a&gt; and used ML to learn from user feedback.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;ML is impressive. Even though it started out as a spinoff of the much popular AI field, it has now become just as popular. This popularity has yielded its own spinoff in the form of deep learning, as mentioned before. Many discoveries were made within a short period of time after its inception, and many more are surely still on the horizon. This optimism contributes to the positive and exciting outlook that ML is always changing, never staying the same for a prolonged period of time due to the constant discoveries. This only makes the field ever more popular, &lt;a href=&quot;https://codeburst.io/what-is-the-future-of-machine-learning-f93749833645&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;as its applications will only continue to increase&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://becominghuman.ai/an-introduction-to-machine-learning-33a1b5d3a560&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Becoming Human)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Omar Dajani&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Omar Dajani is an international student from Jerusalem, Palestine. He is currently a sophomore at Fullerton College and is majoring in English with a minor in Computer Science. He enjoys gaming, blogging, journaling, meditating, and going on walks. He intends on transferring to UC Berkeley for Fall 2021.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Omar Dajani</name></author><summary type="html">The evolution of machine learning Omar Dajani. 02/19/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/machineLearningCover.JPG" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/machineLearningCover.JPG" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">All about phobias</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/18/all-about-phobias.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="All about phobias" /><published>2021-02-18T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-18T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/18/all-about-phobias</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/18/all-about-phobias.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;All about phobias&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Omar Dajani. 02/19/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/february/phobiaOne.PNG&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Depicted above are six of the most common phobias.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/most-common-phobias-4136563&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Emily Roberts - Verywell)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mentalhealth.gov/what-to-look-for/anxiety-disorders/phobias&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Characterized as an anxiety disorder&lt;/a&gt;, a phobia is defined as an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/what-is-a-phobia-2795454&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;irrational and excessive fear of an object or situation&lt;/a&gt;. People with phobias feel an incredibly high sense of danger or harm in response to different contexts. The National Institute of Mental Health estimates that 8% of American adults have some type of phobia, with women experiencing them more often than men. The majority of people know what phobias are, but there is a wide range of information about them that the average person likely would not know.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The exact cause of phobias is unknown. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.news-medical.net/health/Causes-of-phobias.aspx&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;They are theorized&lt;/a&gt; to develop starting in childhood, adolescence or early adulthood and are typically caused by a traumatic reaction to an object, animal or situation. Even then, the phobia is usually developed towards something that is not harmful, with the person only believing it to be due to their anxiety. The main aspect of phobias that triggers the phobic reactions is still unclear, even with years of research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/most-common-phobias-4136563&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Some of the most common phobias&lt;/a&gt; include arachnophobia (the fear of spiders), aerophobia (the fear of flying), cynophobia (the fear of dogs), trypanophobia (the fear of injections) and agoraphobia (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/agoraphobia/symptoms-causes/syc-20355987&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the fear of being alone in a situation where escape seems impossible&lt;/a&gt;). All these phobias have logical explanations for occurring, such as arachnophobia being passed down from our ancestors who did not understand spiders and cynophobia developing due to traumatic experiences with the animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other common phobias include acrophobia (the fear of heights), mysophobia (the fear of germs), social phobia (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/social-phobia-or-anxiety-disorder-3024447&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;which is the same as social anxiety disorder&lt;/a&gt;), coulrophobia (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/clown-phobia-2671682&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the fear of clowns&lt;/a&gt;) and glossophobia (&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.healthline.com/health/glossophobia&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the fear of public speaking&lt;/a&gt;). Just like the majority of the others mentioned above, the development of these phobias can occur because of a traumatic experience. However, social phobia is more unique, as it occurs due to various other factors besides just experiences. The same applies to some of the other aforementioned phobias as well, as those can be the result of evolution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While ten of the most common phobias are highlighted in this article, there are many more that were not mentioned. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/list-of-phobias-2795453&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;list&lt;/a&gt; containing all known phobias is massive, and more are still being discovered today (such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.livescience.com/59879-trypophobia-fear-of-bubbles-evolutionary-reason.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;trypophobia&lt;/a&gt;). There are so many phobias to the point where four categories were created to assign each phobia. The four categories are phobias related to nature, phobias related to animals, phobias related to medical treatment and phobias related to various situations. These are almost universal categories, housing many different phobias inside them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/february/phobiaTwo.PNG&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Shown above are the four major phobia categories, along with the most common phobias from each category.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/list-of-phobias-2795453&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Verywell - JR Bee)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
But wait, where does the word ‘phobia’ even come from? Where do each of the specific names come from as well, and why some of them sound foreign? Well, the names of the various phobias come from the Greek word of whatever the fear is from. So, aerophobia, for example, combines the Greek word for wind, Aero, with the phobia suffix. This is true for all the other phobias, such as hydrophobia/aquaphobia being a combination of hydro/aqua (Greek words for water) and the suffix. The word ‘phobia’ itself is also taken from a Greek word. The word in question means aversion or fear.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As mentioned before, phobias are actually a type of anxiety disorder. As a result, there are arrays of symptoms associated with them, some of which might not be obvious. For example, it is likely obvious that someone with a phobia will feel anxiety and restlessness when confronted by whatever it is they fear, but if the situation is really dire, then they might lose touch with reality for a brief period and get an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/what-is-a-phobia-2795454&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;anxiety attack&lt;/a&gt;. This might sound silly considering some phobias appear to be random and strange, but they genuinely appear as a threat to the person experiencing the fearful reactions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/treatment-options-for-phobias-2672022&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;treatment options for phobias&lt;/a&gt;. Cognitive behavioral therapy is the most common form of treatment, helping the victim learn to not let their fears control them. Other options include medications such as antidepressants and beta blockers, but these are not recommended as they have a lot of unpleasant side effects (such as a dry mouth, headaches and drowsiness). &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apa.org/ptsd-guideline/patients-and-families/exposure-therapy&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Exposure therapy&lt;/a&gt; is an option as well, which literally exposes the victim to the subject of their phobia(s) in an effort to heal them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The world of phobias is interesting. What might appear normal to one person may appear as life-threatening to another. Even though there are many scientists who still do not completely understand phobias, our level of knowledge is increasing with time, ensuring a future where all phobias might get the proper medical attention they deserve.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.news-medical.net/health/Causes-of-phobias.aspx&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(News Medical - Vectorium - ShutterStock)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Omar Dajani&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Omar Dajani is an international student from Jerusalem, Palestine. He is currently a sophomore at Fullerton College and is majoring in English with a minor in Computer Science. He enjoys gaming, blogging, journaling, meditating, and going on walks. He intends on transferring to UC Berkeley for Fall 2021.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Omar Dajani</name></author><summary type="html">All about phobias Omar Dajani. 02/19/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/phobiaCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/phobiaCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Exploring social networks</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/exploring-social-networks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring social networks" /><published>2021-02-04T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-04T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/exploring-social-networks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/exploring-social-networks.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Exploring social networks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simone Rothaupt. 02/06/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/february/socialNetworkOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Student social networks in U.S. high schools contain racial divides and variations in the number of friendships each individual has. In the model above, the color of the dot represents the race of each student: white dots for white students, gray dots for black students, light gray dots for Hispanic students and black dots for students of other races.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.3982/ECTA7528&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Econometrica)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Humans are inherently social beings. According to Domènec Melé and César González Cantón in their book “&lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1057/9781137462619_10&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Human Foundations of Management&lt;/a&gt;,” sociability is one of the core characteristics of humankind, as communication and collaboration initiate relationships between individuals. In InterSTEM’s third speaker lecture, Dr. Matthew Jackson — an economics professor at Stanford University and an extensive researcher in game theory, microeconomics and social networks — discussed the economic implications of our social networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Dr. Jackson explained, a social network can vary in size and density. While many individuals would expect a social network to be relatively uniform with equal connections across all individuals, the reality is quite different. He conducted a study with fellow researchers Sergio Currarini and Paolo Pinarini for &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.3982/ECTA7528&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the Econometrica Journal&lt;/a&gt; on a high school friendship network. They found that the high school was heavily segregated between black and white students, as few friendships existed between these races. In addition, certain students had a significantly greater number of friendships than others within the separate friend groups that formed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These findings also hold true for other cultures. For instance, another research study conducted by Dr. Jackson, along with Abhijit Banerjee, Arun Chandrasekhar and Esther Duflo for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/system/files/working_papers/w17743/w17743.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the National Bureau of Economic Research&lt;/a&gt;, revealed that villages in Karnataka, India contain segregation and a wide range in the number of connections for each person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Jackson asserts that this variability of relationships affects the diffusion of information and disease, which can result in both greater interconnectedness and polarization. Thus, research on this topic has become popular due to its potential to yield a vast wealth of information on human nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using analysis techniques like degree centrality, eigenvector centrality and diffusion centrality that measure the connectedness of individuals within social networks, Francis Bloch, Jackson and Pietro Tebaldi suggest in their 2017 paper “&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1608.05845.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Centrality Measures In Networks&lt;/a&gt;” that the spread of information and contagion can be traced throughout the world quantitatively. For instance, in an inaugural article for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/content/112/50/15277.abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America&lt;/a&gt; in 2015, Dr. Jackson and Stephen Nei were able to measure connectedness between countries throughout the past by examining international trade treaties since the early 1800s. They found that before World War II, the average country had 2.5 allies, and their treaties had a 67% chance of lasting five years. After World War II, the average country had 10.5 allies, and their treaties had a 95% chance of lasting five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On its own, the data collected on social networks appears to hold little real-life significance. However, these studies reveal much information on how human society functions and how the world can work better. The study on world treaties demonstrates that from the 1950s and beyond, the greater integration of trade between countries has correlated with less volatile and more steady relationships with nearly one-tenth as many wars per pairs of countries as before. Thus, increased trade and alliances can result in decreased conflicts as a certain threshold of trade is reached. As Daniel Griswold of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cato.org/speeches/can-free-trade-promote-peace-middle-east&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CATO Institute&lt;/a&gt; elucidates, promoting trade among countries, such as in the Middle East, has the potential to foster peace among warring nations. Even with these benefits, Christine Lagarde — the Managing Director of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imf.org/en/News/Articles/2015/09/28/04/53/sp091913&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;International Monetary Fund&lt;/a&gt; (IMF) — explains that the interconnected global economy also results in negative consequences where financial shocks in one market can reverberate around the world. Another &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.imf.org/2018/10/03/lasting-effects-the-global-economic-recovery-10-years-after-the-crisis/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;IMF&lt;/a&gt; article highlights the danger of such a globalized market, when the 2008 United States Housing Crisis resulted in the economic downturn in Europe, Asia and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the data collected for the study conducted by Dr. Jackson and his colleagues on social networks in India also contains valuable economic information. This research helps microfinance campaigns so that banks loaning money to those in poverty can effectively reach out to those in need by finding the most interconnected person in each village. Therefore, research on social networks contains valuable information for companies and organizations seeking to expand their influence and grow their market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the growing global social network of humans will promote interconnectedness and peace, yet it will still result in segregation among racial and political party lines and enable crises to proliferate across the globe. As new networking platforms like social media rise in popularity and give new modes of connection for society, we must learn to keep the negative consequences in check while still maximizing the potential benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Shutterstock/Optimarc)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Simone Rothaupt &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Simone is a sophomore at Thousand Oaks High School in Ventura, California. She is interested in exploring STEM related topics, such as medicine, and she also hopes to spread this passion to others through writing.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Simone Rothaupt</name></author><summary type="html">Exploring social networks Simone Rothaupt. 02/06/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/socialNetworkCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/socialNetworkCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mars rovers: Past, present and future</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/mars-rover-past-present-and-future.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mars rovers: Past, present and future" /><published>2021-02-04T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-04T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/mars-rover-past-present-and-future</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/mars-rover-past-present-and-future.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Mars rovers: Past, present and future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sydney Hollingsworth. 02/06/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/february/marsOne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The image above is the concept art for NASA’s Mars 2020 Perseverance rover.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.space.com/mars-2020-rover-naming-contest-semifinalists.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Space / NASA)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Since the dawn of humanity, people have turned their gazes to the heavens time and time again. The stars and planets of the night sky have always been things of mystery. The more we learn about our own solar system, the more questions seem to arise. In recent years, astronomers have turned their attention to our closest neighbor, the Red Planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once thought to be a barren, dusty expanse, Mars is now believed to provide our best chance at an off-world settlement. With the discovery of frozen water and the possibility of past life on Mars, plenty of questions have been plaguing scientists and will most likely be answered with the help of the same technology that dug them up in the first place: Martian rovers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The topic of Mars rovers has graced headlines many times since the Sojourner rover and Pathfinder lander first touched the planet’s dusty surface. Civilians and researchers at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory alike have grown a sentimental attachment to these scientific instruments working away so far from home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been a total of four successful Mars rovers, all by NASA’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jpl.nasa.gov/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Jet Propulsion Laboratory&lt;/a&gt; located in Southern California. The use of rovers gives an advantage over landers, which are stationary, and orbiters, which can only observe the surface of Mars from the upper atmosphere. They also give mission control the ability to direct rovers towards new, promising areas and collect samples from multiple locations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first Mars rover, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jpl.nasa.gov/missions/mars-pathfinder-sojourner-rover/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sojourner&lt;/a&gt;, was launched on Dec. 4, 1996 and landed on the Red Planet on July 4th of the following year. Sojourner was accompanied by the Pathfinder lander, which relayed the rover’s gathered information back to Earth. A scientific innovation of its time, the lander relied mostly on a parachute and airbags rather than its rockets to land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mission was only meant to last seven days, but the Sojourner rover spent a total of 83 days studying the surface of Mars, never venturing further than 40 feet from the Pathfinder lander. The rover finally stopped responding on Sept. 27, 1997, likely due to a failed battery. Sojourner was able to capture the first photos from the surface of Mars, as well as collect measurements of chemicals in the planet’s atmosphere and dust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalgeographic.com/science/2019/02/nasa-mars-rover-opportunity-dead-what-it-gave-humankind/#close&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mars Exploration Rovers&lt;/a&gt;, launched just one month apart towards opposite sides of the planet, were built in just 34 months by the same laboratory. The team took eight-hour shifts to work 24 hours a day, 7 days a week to complete the sizable project and even continued to send software updates while the rovers were en route to Mars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first twin was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://solarsystem.nasa.gov/missions/spirit/in-depth/&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1612603012570000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw0Kc4vgSx-fbVB3ThltciQL&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Spirit&lt;/a&gt;, which was launched on June 10, 2003 and landed on Jan. 4, 2004. Unlike Sojourner, Spirit boasted a built-in lander, eliminating the need to stay close to a stationary lander in order to relay information back to Earth. The main goals of the mission were to investigate the geological features of Mars and areas that may have once had water, take pictures of the surface with a 360-degree camera and send these discoveries back to Earth with the help of NASA’s 2001 Mars Odyssey satellite. Three course corrections, a landing that was eight miles off the target and a brief radio silence just 17 days into the mission had Spirit off to a rough start, but the rover ended up lasting over six years and traveled just under five miles before succumbing to the harsh Martian winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://mars.nasa.gov/news/8414/six-things-to-know-about-nasas-opportunity-rover/#:~:text=It%20was%20the%20first%20rover,late%20from%20rising%2C%20acidic%20groundwater.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Opportunity&lt;/a&gt; rover landed on the rocky surface of Mars on Jan. 25, 2004. This rover would go on to discover water and sedimentary rock on Mars, inspiring the search for possible life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the Spirit rover, Opportunity’s life expectancy was estimated at 90 to 100 days, at which point, dust build-up on the solar panels would presumably cut off its power supply. However, NASA was unable to take into account the extremely strong winds of Mars. These winds kept Opportunity’s solar panels clean for 14 and a half years, longer than every other Mars rover combined. During this time, it traveled over 28 miles across the treacherous Martian plains. The rover’s famous last transmission to Earth in June of 2018 - “My battery is low and it’s getting dark” - tugged at the heartstrings of people around the world when Opportunity found itself caught in a strong dust storm that blocked out the sun. NASA finally concluded attempts for reconnection after nearly eight months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth and only currently active martian rover, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.space.com/17963-mars-curiosity.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Curiosity&lt;/a&gt;, landed on Aug. 6, 2012 and is still relaying information back to Earth today. As the largest rover ever sent to space, as it is about the size of an SUV, its landing brought up a few unique challenges. Airbags alone would not be enough to break the rover’s fall, so a parachute and precise rockets had to be used instead. Curiosity’s mission is to gather information on Martian geology and climate and answer the question of whether or not Mars could have ever supported life, all to better prepare NASA for a future human settlement on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013, the Curiosity rover discovered that Mars had previously supported conditions favorable to life and further confirmed this in 2014 when it found organic material, the building blocks of life as we know it. In 2017, Curiosity was updated with a software called Autonomous Exploration Gathering Increased Science (AEGIS), allowing it to choose targets by itself and making it the first artificial intelligence on a faraway spacecraft. The rover currently works with multiple international Mars orbiters to relay information back to Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Jet Propulsion Laboratory’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://mars.nasa.gov/mars2020/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mars 2020&lt;/a&gt; mission aims to search for ancient microbial life on Mars, measure radiation levels, gather information on climate and collect rock and soil samples to be returned to Earth in the future with the help of a collaboration between NASA and the European Space Agency (ESA).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The star of this mission will be NASA’s most advanced rover yet, named &lt;a href=&quot;https://mars.nasa.gov/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Perseverance&lt;/a&gt;. The rover will utilize technology expected to be used in future Mars settlements, such as a system to produce oxygen from the Martian atmosphere. Perseverance will also be transporting a helicopter drone called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/feature/jpl/6-things-to-know-about-nasas-ingenuity-mars-helicopter/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ingenuity&lt;/a&gt;, the first aircraft in another world. If the drone succeeds, NASA will consider future aerial missions on Mars. Perseverance and Ingenuity were launched on July 30, 2020 and are expected to land on Feb. 18 of this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future of humanity’s relationship with Mars will likely depend on what Perseverance finds. Every past Mars rover has made discoveries that have completely changed our understanding of the planet, and as the first rover to take into account the possibility of past life on Mars, Perseverance has its work cut out for it. Hopefully, whatever it finds will shed further light on the many mysteries of the Red Planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.360cities.net/image/curiosity-rover-martian-solar-day-2#35.47,-7.67,110.0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(360 Cities)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Sydney Hollingsworth&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sydney Hollingsworth</name></author><summary type="html">Mars rovers: Past, present and future Sydney Hollingsworth. 02/06/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/marsCover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/marsCover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Antibiotic resistance: A growing threat to global health</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/a-growing-threat-to-global-health.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Antibiotic resistance: A growing threat to global health" /><published>2021-02-04T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-04T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/a-growing-threat-to-global-health</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/a-growing-threat-to-global-health.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Antibiotic resistance: A growing threat to global health&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nadwa Atwi. 02/12/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/february/globalHealthOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;In the image, penicillium is growing on a Petri dish and neutralizing the bacteria.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@yeonjoon.kim/module10-eid100-technological-breakthrough-penicillin-f5a58fed2d0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Medium)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For decades, antibiotics have been considered the wonder drug that cures all infections. It all started when Alexander Fleming, a Scottish microbiologist, came back from a two-week vacation in 1928 only to accidentally discover green mold (now known as Penicillium) developing on his culture plates and killing some bacteria he’d been growing. Since then, the discovery of Penicillin (a substance produced by Penicillium) has changed the course of medicine and enabled physicians to treat formerly brutal and life-threatening diseases. The overuse of antibiotics, however, propelled the evolution of resistance. As a result, plenty of bacteria have become unresponsive to antibiotics, and consequently, a number of infections have become incredibly challenging to treat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;What are antibiotics?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antibiotics are drugs specifically targeted to damage the essential parts of a bacterial cell or disrupt its critical functions. They are usually prescribed to prevent or treat bacterial infections like strep throat and pneumonia. Although the body can occasionally fight off infections on its own, in instances where a bacterial infection is already severe enough to cause a high-grade fever, antibiotics become the primary choice of treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what happens when bacteria become resistant to a certain antibiotic? Well, according to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/drugresistance/about.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Centers for Disease Control and Prevention&lt;/a&gt; (CDC), a patient would expect longer-lasting illnesses, extended hospital stays, additional follow-up doctor visits and more costly treatments. Such alternative treatments usually display more adverse side-effects and occasionally even fail to treat the infection, resulting in death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;How do bacteria become resistant to antibiotics?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yourgenome.org/facts/what-is-antibiotic-resistance&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;two major pathways&lt;/a&gt;: DNA mutations and horizontal gene transfer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When DNA mutations result in a favorable change in the organism, this leads to its evolution, a natural process that occurs in all living beings. One example is a bacterium that has recently acquired a certain trait that allows it to resist an antibiotic’s assault. This ‘upgraded’ bacterium would grow and divide just like its siblings, but up until now, it’s very unlikely that it would overrule them in number, considering it’s pretty new. When the antibiotic is introduced, however, all the ‘traditional’ bacteria targeted by this antibiotic die, whereas the ‘upgraded’ bacteria are left unscathed with a greater chance of survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although mutations are a natural way for bacteria to acquire antibiotic resistance, certain factors can still increase its prevalence. Those include excessive use of antibiotics, their inappropriate handling (like taking antibiotics to treat viral and fungal infections) and a discontinued course of antibiotic treatment. Recently, the overuse of antibiotics in agriculture has started to gain attention too, especially in food-producing animals. In many countries, the major reasons for antibiotic use in animals are growth promotion and disease prevention rather than the treatment of sick animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another pathway for bacteria to obtain resistance is horizontal gene transfer. Simply stated, it involves a resistant bacterium gifting its resistance to a susceptible bacterium through plasmids. A plasmid is a small naturally-occurring DNA molecule distinct from a bacterial cell’s chromosomal DNA. The genes carried in plasmids often provide bacteria with genetic enhancements, such as antibiotic resistance. By undergoing a process called conjugation, bacterial cells can share plasmids, and thus their advantageous add-ons, with each other to increase their chances of survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/february/globalHealthTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
The transfer of the plasmid containing the mutated gene spreads antibiotic resistance between different bacteria.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://labtestsonline.org/articles/antibiotic-resistance-bacteria&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Lab Tests Online)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Antibiotic-resistant Bacteria&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some bacteria have acquired resistance to antibiotics that were once commonly used to treat them. The most prominent examples are Staphylococcus aureus (also known as golden staph or MRSA) and Neisseria gonorrhoeae (which causes gonorrhea).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the most serious concern with antibiotic resistance right now is that some bacteria have become resistant to almost all of the easily available antibiotics. In some countries, the alternative treatment options for these bacteria are expensive and not always available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These ‘superbugs’ are now capable of causing serious illnesses, which has become a major public health problem. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/news-room/q-a-detail/tuberculosis-multidrug-resistant-tuberculosis-(mdr-tb)&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Multi-drug-resistant Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/a&gt; (MDR-TB) is a strain of Mycobacterium tuberculosis that has adapted to the most powerful tuberculosis drugs and became resistant to them. Further drug resistance of the bacteria at some point in the future could eventually render it untreatable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;So what’s the next step?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/campaigns/world-antimicrobial-awareness-week&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;World Health Organization&lt;/a&gt; (WHO) has been working on spreading awareness about antibiotic resistance. They have even dedicated an entire week in November for World Antimicrobial Awareness that aims to promote awareness of global antimicrobial resistance and to inspire proper practices among health workers and the general public to deter further emergence and spread of drug-resistant infections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year since 2015, posters are put up to inform people about the proper use of antibiotics. Notable instructions include only using antibiotics for bacterial infections, as they aren’t effective for common colds and bronchitis (which are mainly caused by viruses), practicing proper hygiene and finishing the full prescribed course of treatment even if the patient starts feeling better. Farmers are also encouraged to stop antibiotic abuse in livestock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/february/globalHealthThree.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
An assortment of posters is put up by NPS MedicineWise to educate people about antibiotic resistance. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.science.org.au/curious/people-medicine/fighting-back-antimicrobial-resistance&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1613210506458000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw0vSdpXcLxLIOyvSaeGLXdN&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Australian Academy of Science)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Antibiotic resistance resulting from antibiotic misuse is putting modern medical advancements and medicine at risk of becoming ineffective. Procedures such as organ transplants, chemotherapy and surgeries become increasingly dangerous without effective antibiotics to prevent and treat infections. Reducing the improper use of antibiotics and making sure to adhere to the proper policies will make a difference and will help prevent antibiotic resistance in the future. However, this is all dependent on how willing people are to follow the given advice for their future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (BioPharma Reporter)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Nadwa Atwi &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Nadwa is a pharmacy student from Lebanon. She is a science enthusiast that loves to feed her curiosity by probing into the most unusual medical conditions. Through InterSTEM, Nadwa aspires to let people recognize just how fascinating science can be, and hopes to share her passion with them as well. In her free time, she enjoys reading novels and reviewing them on her blog, binge-watching anime and fangirling over her favorite Kpop groups.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Nadwa Atwi</name></author><summary type="html">Antibiotic resistance: A growing threat to global health Nadwa Atwi. 02/12/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/globalHealthCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/globalHealthCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What is citizen science?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/what-is-a-citizen-science.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is citizen science?" /><published>2021-02-04T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-04T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/what-is-a-citizen-science</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/what-is-a-citizen-science.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;What is citizen science?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emily Richter. 02/12/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/february/citizenScienceOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Volunteers with the Monarch Butterfly Monitoring Project engage in an organized citizen science event by recording data on tagged monarch butterflies.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fs.fed.us/wildflowers/pollinators/Monarch_Butterfly/citizenscience/index.shtml&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(U.S. Forest Service)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Scientific research, especially when it is regarding ecology or biology, can be a daunting task. Researchers often have to collect vast amounts of data in a short amount of time, a task that proves itself to be difficult. How can researchers ease this burden by outsourcing this work to willing and reliable sources? The answer lies in something called citizen science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States’ &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nps.gov/subjects/citizenscience/citizen-science.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Park Service&lt;/a&gt; defines citizen science as “the voluntary involvement of the public in scientific research”. What exactly is the “voluntary involvement of the public”, and precisely how can everyday people contribute to complex research projects? The answer to this query is multifaceted and complex, ultimately outlining a system that connects scientific enthusiasts to researchers in need of a hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes citizen science involves recruiting volunteers to participate in outlined data collection. Scientists and other research leaders teach willing citizens how to collect data in a way that is consistent with a particular research project, and then the volunteers complete specific assigned tasks. One event structured in this way is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fs.fed.us/wildflowers/pollinators/Monarch_Butterfly/citizenscience/index.shtml&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Monarch Butterfly Monitoring Project&lt;/a&gt; based in Kansas. Every fall, volunteers across the United States gather in designated Monarch butterfly migration and breeding sites to collect data on everything from the presence of Monarch eggs on host plants like milkweed to parasites on adult butterflies. After undergoing a training process led by professional biologists, volunteers spend hours counting, capturing, tagging, observing and photographing Monarchs. Already, the efforts of thousands of dedicated citizen scientists have helped researchers at the University of Kansas and the University of Wisconsin-Madison understand the lives these elusive insects live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the usefulness of organized citizen science events, many people do not have the free time to participate in events such as these. Several are multiple-hour commitments that take place far away from cities or suburban areas. Semi-organized events such as the Cornell Lab of Ornithology’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://nestwatch.org/about/overview/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;NestWatch&lt;/a&gt; can be great compromises for people who want to take part in structured data collection without having to clear their calendars. Prospective NestWatch volunteers are trained by ornithologists and professional researchers. The training covers the basics of bird biology and explains how NestWatch citizen scientists should collect and report data on birds’ nests. For each recorded nest, NestWatch aims to collect data regarding the nesting trends of different species of birds. With the help of thousands of dedicated citizen scientists, the project aims to understand how the changing environment is impacting birds and their breeding habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organized and semi-organized volunteer projects are helpful, but they can only collect so much data. How do researchers use citizen science to collect large amounts of data from all around the world? The answer lies with cameras and cell phones. In big cities, people walk to work and take pictures of the eye-catching plants and animals that cross their paths. Those who live in rural areas take pictures that outline the ecosystems playing out around them. Visitors of protected areas of nature marvel at the living wonders around them, taking pictures of everything from the smallest butterfly to the tallest tree. What if those pictures could be used to contribute to professional research and advance science?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Citizen science websites like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inaturalist.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;iNaturalist&lt;/a&gt; use a format similar to social media to collect data on a wide variety of species. Contributors submit pictures along with basic information about when and where the picture was taken, and the post is released to the website, where viewers can add to the post and comment on it. If enough people interact with the post, the picture and associated information can be tagged as “Research Grade”. Citizen science websites like iNaturalist bring together people from different backgrounds with different knowledge and different skills, creating a thriving community that contributes significantly to scientific research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists all over the world consistently use data from iNaturalist to answer their questions about the range and habits of different organisms. Another similar citizen science website, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ebird.org/home&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;eBird&lt;/a&gt;, has allowed scientists at the Cornell Lab of Ornithology and Colorado State University to &lt;a href=&quot;https://ebird.org/news/less-light-more-trees-help-migrating-birds&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;discover patterns&lt;/a&gt; that reflect the novel needs of migratory birds in a world full of changing environments. As of early 2021, citizen scientists on eBird have cataloged over 10,000 species of birds, helping biologists, ecologists and ornithologists gain an understanding of specific species at a groundbreaking rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most often used within ecological and biological fields, citizen science has also been applied to other areas of scientific study, including astronomy. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.nasa.gov/get-involved/citizenscience/five-extraordinary-citizen-science-discoveries&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;United States National Aeronautics and Space Administration&lt;/a&gt; (NASA) regularly uses the observations of astrological citizen scientists as starting points for various projects and studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone interested in participating in any type of citizen science can easily find a way to do so. The National Park Service houses a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nps.gov/subjects/citizenscience/be-a-citizen-scientist.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;large database&lt;/a&gt; of different organized volunteer events on their website, complete with filters based on location, project type and event format. To participate in citizen science via iNaturalist, eBird or NestWatch, one can simply make an account for free and begin participating immediately. A database including other internet-based citizen science opportunities can be found through the website of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.citizensciencealliance.org/index.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Citizen Science Alliance&lt;/a&gt;. Citizen science pushes scientific research forward like nothing else, and every person who participates in the crowd-sourced form of data collection is immeasurably valuable to the scientific community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nps.gov/knri/learn/news/biodiversity-project-at-knri.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(National Park Service)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Emily Richter&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Emily is a junior from Maria Carrillo High School in Sonoma County. She loves chemistry and the environmental sciences and plans to be an environmental chemist when she gets older. Through InterSTEM, she hopes to combine her experience in writing with her interest in STEM in order to help others enjoy and understand STEM. In her free time, she likes playing the flute, and baking and cooking.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Emily Richter</name></author><summary type="html">What is citizen science? Emily Richter. 02/12/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/citizenScienceCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/citizenScienceCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Starlink’s journey to 1,000 more</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/28/starlinks-journey-to-1000-more.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Starlink’s journey to 1,000 more" /><published>2021-01-28T16:00:03-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-28T16:00:03-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/28/starlinks-journey-to-1000-more</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/28/starlinks-journey-to-1000-more.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Starlink’s journey to 1,000 more&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mehri Sadri. 01/29/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/starlinksOne.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Starlink satellites are often seen traveling parallel to one another.
(DIY Photography)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It’s a clear spring night, and you decide to go stargazing with some friends. You gather some pillows, blankets and board games, laying them on the lawn grass. Laying down on the cushions, you see some faint stars in the distance, nothing too unusual. Hoping to perhaps see a shooting star, your eyes rapidly jerk up in response to what looks like a link of stars traveling through the night sky. Not 10 or 20, rather 100 or 200 rapidly beaming circles rushing in and out of your view. You turn to your friends, who look anything but worried about what you perceive as a potential alien invasion, instead calmly admiring the crazy view. “Starlink, huh?” one exclaims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is Starlink? Well, it is no alien invasion, rather a movement of satellites that stream around Earth at all times. Get lucky, and you may even see them making their way around your home. Though simply aesthetically pleasing to some, these futuristic-looking sky sequins serve an important purpose: giving everyone on Earth access to faster Internet speeds and data. But, of course, they also obstruct an astronomer’s view, which is more controversial than you may think! In the latest Starlink launch on Jan. 20, SpaceX reached the large 1,000 satellite mark, totaling 1,015 beams of light fluttering across the sky. Though this may already seem like an impressively large number, SpaceX founder and CEO &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/how-elon-musk-42000-starlink-satellites-earth-effects-stars-2020-10&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Elon Musk&lt;/a&gt;, is nowhere near finished, as he wants to include at least another 41,000 satellites to the bunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the capabilities of wireless satellites, Musk desires to cut out the lag often associated with typical telecommunications products, providing a profit for not only those companies if successful, but also for SpaceX. The satellites will be at different proximities to Earth, as this allows the greatest range and network efficiency for individuals around the globe. The first satellite was launched in May 2019, and the first set had a successful altitude launch of 340 miles from the ground. Starlink serves to create faster proximities of Internet speed, and it will work up to a gigabit per second with a latency of 25 to 35 milliseconds, with 5 trillion bytes a day of data generated as of June 2020. For comparison, the speeds that Starlink will eventually offer stand &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@ankushborkar/starlink-vs-5g-f69b1dcdd8ab&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;10 times faster than typical 4G networks, but not as fast as 5G&lt;/a&gt;. Starlink has a goal to serve individuals who may struggle to find good connections due to their geographic location, a number Musk estimates to be between 3% to 4% of the world population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be curious as to what operating system SpaceX uses to control Starlink. Currently, the network system known as Linux is being put into full force, with each satellite &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yahoo.com/entertainment/5-trillion-bytes-day-spacex-232141318.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;containing around 4,000 Linux computers&lt;/a&gt;. Linux is no stranger in the world of networking and communication; it has been an open-source operating system in use since 1991. Linux has had a rivalry with Windows operating systems, such as Windows 10, with Linux claiming it runs &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.softwaretestinghelp.com/linux-vs-windows/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“faster and smoother” than its counterpart.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SpaceX’s project is one of innovation; however, they are not the only company with an equally ambitious project. &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@ankushborkar/starlink-vs-5g-f69b1dcdd8ab&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Companies like Vodafone, Samsung and even Amazon’s Blue Origin&lt;/a&gt; rocket launching company are currently striving to create similar satellite networks, attempting to provide the internet to more people than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though these competitors may bring out full-force systems similar to Starlink in the future, for now, we can all credit that nightly-chain of rapidly expanding ‘stars’ to none other than SpaceX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Nurphoto / Getty Images)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/Mehri_Sadri.JPG&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Mehri Sadri&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Mehri is a senior at Scripps Ranch High School in San Diego, California. Although she has always been more inclined in humanities subjects, Mehri has found a love for combining science and art and their practicalities, and hopes to spread this same love to others with her articles.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Mehri Sadri</name></author><summary type="html">Starlink’s journey to 1,000 more Mehri Sadri. 01/29/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/starlinksCover.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/starlinksCover.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Great Filter</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/28/the-great-filter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Great Filter" /><published>2021-01-28T16:00:02-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-28T16:00:02-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/28/the-great-filter</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/28/the-great-filter.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The Great Filter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Famesh Patel. 01/29/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/greatFilterOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Fermi’s Paradox states that there is an apparent contradiction between lack of alien encounters and the highly probable chance of their existence.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantamagazine.org/galaxy-simulations-offer-a-new-solution-to-the-fermi-paradox-20190307/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Quanta Magazine)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Water. Where the start and end of alien life occurs. You may think that water is highly limited, maybe even to just our own Earth, but actually, we’ve discovered tons of it. Hydrogen is the most abundant element in the universe, and oxygen is the third most abundant (the second most is helium, which is highly unreactive). Thus, when these elements come into close contact with each other, they form water. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drake_equation#:~:text=The%20Drake%20equation%20is%20a,in%20the%20Milky%20Way%20galaxy.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Drake Equation&lt;/a&gt;, the numerical range for the number of aliens in the universe can range from one to tens of millions. With such a large range, we would expect to have made some contact with a higher intelligence being, but we haven’t. This is exactly what &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enrico_Fermi&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Enrico Fermi&lt;/a&gt; was thinking when he came up with Fermi’s Paradox, which states the contradiction between the lack of alien encounters and the high chance of their existence. This led Fermi to ask one question (and maybe the one you’re thinking right now): where is everybody?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are multiple ways to approach this. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GdqcVjCe0bc&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Aperture&lt;/a&gt;, one of those ways was proposed by Robin Hanson. He figured that we’ve been asking the wrong question: instead of expecting that the universe should be filled with human life forms, he thought that we should accept that life is extremely rare and our time might be limited. If he is right, we have miscalculated the steps necessary to create life, either in difficulty or correctness. Through this re-consideration of our objectives for life, we created the Great Filter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Great Filter could be anything in the timeline that created humans. It could be whatever started abiogenesis (the origin of life), the first proper replication of DNA with enough mutations that it caused evolution, the first creation of organized eukaryotic cells or even the creation of a moon to cause a proper atmosphere. It could be anything. Well, we passed it. We made it past the Great Filter. Give yourself a pat on the back…but, what if it’s ahead of us?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if there was life teeming in the universe that was killed by a filter that exceeds our current position in time? Maybe we will witness the Great Filter when the Andromeda Galaxy smashes into our own, and we get pushed into the darkness of space. The concept behind the Great Filter is that maybe life had grown in a different place in the universe, but was never able to grow to an intergalactic scale because of some major event that wiped it out. Some relatively recent events that humanity has endured that had the potential to be the Great Filter are coronal mass ejections, a geomagnetic storm from the sun, a large meteor and a global pandemic. Just some of the ways humanity could meet its end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the idea of the Great Filter is extremely flawed, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://mason.gmu.edu/~rhanson/greatfilter.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Robin Hanson&lt;/a&gt;. We are extrapolating this entire theory from a single data point: Earth. This is the only data point for life that we’ve ever known. What if other life forms don’t have a colonialist mindset and don’t want to find other planets with life? What if, instead of water, aliens live off of liquid mercury? The extrapolation of every variable is extremely hard to take into account when it’s all just based on speculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe there isn’t any Great Filter and the lack of life elsewhere just shows that our existence is a coincidence, and we are simply lucky. We are lucky to understand our reality. We are lucky that the universe is so fine-tuned for our existence - from our location in the solar system to the abundance of water. Maybe we are the only ones in our universe and we’re lucky to be here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Universe Today)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Famesh Patel&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Famesh is a senior at BASIS Peoria High School who enjoys all parts of science. Explaining the world around us with science has always seemed interesting to him from metamorphosis to the Higgs Boson. He hopes to help bring more youth to STEM fields so they can understand the natural world around us and appreciate the world for its uniqueness.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Famesh Patel</name></author><summary type="html">The Great Filter Famesh Patel. 01/29/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/greatFilterCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/greatFilterCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>