<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-12-31T21:19:50-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">InterSTEM</title><entry><title type="html">Boyan Slat and the ocean cleanup</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/24/boyan-slat-and-the-ocean-dump.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Boyan Slat and the ocean cleanup" /><published>2020-12-24T16:00:01-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-24T16:00:01-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/24/boyan-slat-and-the-ocean-dump</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/24/boyan-slat-and-the-ocean-dump.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Boyan Slat and the ocean cleanup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sydney Hollingsworth. 12/25/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/boyanSlatOne.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Boyan Slat addresses the media in Vancouver on Dec. 12, 2019.
(Jason Payne)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Covering 70% of the Earth’s surface and containing 50 to 80% of life as we know it, the ocean is our most valuable resource, but it is in danger. Although the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencehistory.org/the-history-and-future-of-plastics&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Science History Institute&lt;/a&gt; reports observations of plastic pollution as early as the 1960s, the threat of irreversible damage due to pollution has become increasingly obvious in the past decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year, over eight million tons of plastics enter the ocean and wreak havoc on marine life. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.noaa.gov/education/resource-collections/ocean-coasts/ocean-pollution&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration&lt;/a&gt; (NOAA), plastics of all sizes can be deadly. Large, floating tangles of netting and trash can trap sea creatures or provide transportation for invasive species across the ocean. Smaller pieces can wrap around animals or be confused for food. Over time, plastics may seem to break down, but in reality, they only break apart into tiny pieces. These microplastics absorb harmful chemicals and are often mistaken for plankton by predators and make their way up the food chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, the ocean plastics accumulate in one of the world’s five massive rotating current systems called gyres. Once they’ve reached the gyres, the plastics form patches of concentrated debris. The most famous is the Great Pacific Garbage Patch which covers nearly 1.6 million square kilometers, or three times the size of France.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how can we remove these mini-continent-sized garbage patches? This question is being asked by scientists everywhere and is especially important to young people, who believe if a solution is not found soon, the damages will haunt them for the rest of their lives and generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most notable young people in ocean conservation is 26-year-old Boyan Slat from the Netherlands. His non-profit, &lt;a href=&quot;https://theoceancleanup.com/about/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Ocean Cleanup&lt;/a&gt;, aims to remove 50% of the Great Pacific Garbage Patch over the course of five years and nearly all ocean plastics by 2050, much sooner than previously predicted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slat’s plan is unique in that it cleans the ocean directly by removing trash from the garbage patches rather than focusing on prevention or coastal cleanups. In a 2012 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ROW9F-c0kIQ&amp;amp;list=WL&amp;amp;index=3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TED Talk&lt;/a&gt;, Slat, just 18 years old at the time, explained his plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He attributed his inspiration for his plan to a scuba diving trip in Greece two years earlier when he noticed more plastic in the water than fish. Later, as a school project, he and a friend pulled fine, mesh netting through ocean water and spun the nets’ contents in a centrifuge to separate plankton from microplastics. In doing this, Slat found a simple, efficient way to safely remove tiny pieces of plastic from the ocean without harming the smallest of marine life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slat’s new discoveries turned his attention to the ocean’s five polluted gyres; with the help of professors from the University of Delft, Utrecht and Hawaii, he estimated there would be 7.25 million tons of plastics in the surface layers of the gyres alone by 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous removal plans required boats with nets to capture floating trash and were far too expensive to be practical. Slat proposed a design with several strategically placed, floating platforms, anchored to the seafloor, with nets suspended between them. The design would use the gyres’ own currents to push the plastic into the nets, removing an estimated 55 shipping containers of trash a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an interview with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qQQffhWdihs&amp;amp;list=WL&amp;amp;index=4&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;NowThis News&lt;/a&gt;, Slat shared how he executed his plan. In 2013, he left the University of Delft, to start The Ocean Cleanup. With only 300 euros and no sponsors, his plan seemed impossible, but with the help of crowdfunding, Slat was able to launch the largest scale plastic cleanup ever attempted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first challenge Slat and his team faced was the complex design of the anchor lines needed to attach the platforms to the seafloor, five kilometers below. The proposed systems were complicated and required too many lines to be cost effective. The team was ready to quit when two interns suggested a drifting design. The new plan was drastically different and involved several smaller systems scattered throughout the patch that would use wind and waves to move towards larger concentrations of plastics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ocean Cleanup released their first system (001) into the Pacific in September of 2018, and after extensive durability testing, released System 001/B in June of 2019. Slat hopes to have System 002 ready by 2021 and would like to refine the design further before launching a total of 60 systems to tackle the Great Pacific Garbage Patch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The organization has since started a new line of sunglasses made from the collected plastics and sells them on their website to fund the continuation of the cleanup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slat and his team’s newest project focuses on removing plastics before they can reach the ocean in the first place. Appropriately named the Interceptor, this system intercepts trash in rivers before they enter the ocean. The Ocean Cleanup has identified a total of 1,000 rivers responsible for 80% of ocean plastics. The system is positioned on the side of the river that the current pushes towards, collecting floating debris while still allowing boats to pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slat’s discoveries and inventions have opened a world of possibilities to save the ocean from permanent plastic pollution. What started as an idea of a 16-year-old high school student has grown into a global project. Slat continues to push the boundaries of ocean cleaning technology while inspiring young scientists everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (USA Today)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Sydney Hollingsworth&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sydney Hollingsworth</name></author><summary type="html">Boyan Slat and the ocean cleanup Sydney Hollingsworth. 12/25/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/boyanSlatCover.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/boyanSlatCover.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The secret to learning a language</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/24/secret-to-learning-a-language.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The secret to learning a language" /><published>2020-12-24T16:00:01-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-24T16:00:01-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/24/secret-to-learning-a-language</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/24/secret-to-learning-a-language.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The secret to learning a language&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reagan Smith. 12/25/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/learningLanguageOne.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Languages can all be connected to one another utilizing a “tree” as a visual representation. From here, we can see how the Romance languages, Spanish, Portuguese, Italian, French, and Catalan, as well as other minor ones, stem from the same branch. &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/swlh/towards-a-larger-view-of-information-architecture-2a7bd6ebafb7&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Medium)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There’s no doubt that in today’s fast paced, multicultural, connected world, it’s beneficial to know more than one language. Over half the world– estimated to be between 60 and 75%– speak at least two languages, according to Gaia Vince from BBC’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20160811-the-amazing-benefits-of-being-bilingual&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Future&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, our brains have evolved to understand multiple languages, to look for clues and to decipher foreign words we have seldom encountered. Language is a complex combination of sounds and symbols that all come together to represent a group of people connected by culture, and, if one follows the signs, they can unlock a world of understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latin is a unique language to learn because it is no longer spoken, only written and read. We can trace thousands of our words back to their Latin roots and witness the long-lasting presence of the Romans in our governmental structure, art and literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings me to today, where I sat down with Latin teacher Dr. Jeffrey Feland, a faculty member of Sage Hill School in Newport, CA. He works with students in Latin classes one through four, runs the Junior Classical League, a club that participates in annual challenges and competitions and is a favorite amongst the students. A common theme that emerged from our interview was how important patterns are to a language, and he explained how seeing them helped him excel in his learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Reagan Smith&lt;/b&gt;: So starting off, how many languages do you know, and what are they?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jeffrey Feland&lt;/b&gt;: Well, I would say I know Latin and Ancient Greek, but I’ve never had to speak to others in them. Then, I can understand, read and speak Spanish and know basic conversational Italian, French and German. I feel fairly fluent in modern Greek– but then of course that brings up the question of how to define “fluency.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;RS&lt;/b&gt;: Of course. So in total, that’s eight languages, including English, obviously. Wow, that’s a lot. How did you begin learning your first foreign language, and what pushed you to become fluent?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;JF&lt;/b&gt;: At the end of your 7th-grade year, your teacher can recommend you to take high-school classes during the summer before 8th grade, and there was the option for Algebra 1 and Spanish 1. Now I only got the recommendation to do Algebra 1, and I went to my language arts teacher in 7th grade, being the precocious 12 year old I was, and asked why I didn’t get a recommendation to do Spanish 1, even though I had A’s in her class. She told me to my face that she didn’t feel that my English skills were strong enough and that I would never be good at a foreign language, in her opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;RS&lt;/b&gt;: That’s shocking, considering you now know eight languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;JF&lt;/b&gt;: Yes, I was stunned, and I didn’t know how to respond, so I just assumed that she was right, coming from a place of authority. Eventually, during freshman year I was in my Spanish 1 class. I remember feeling pretty disoriented the first month in that class, but then one day I looked at everything on the page and thought, “This is just patterns. I can just repeat patterns and rules again and again.” Spanish is a pretty straightforward language, so if you learn the rules for it and how the sounds change, you can predict words you’ve never heard before. I started teaching myself all fourteen verb tenses, and on the back of my tests, I would take a random verb and conjugate it into a chart that would take up the whole piece of paper. My teacher finally asked me, “who taught you this; why are you in Spanish 1– this is, like, everything.” I said to her, “I just figured it was patterns.” They moved me up to Spanish 2, where I had the highest grade in the class, and I decided I had one thing left to do freshman year, which was to revisit my 7th grade language teacher. I told her, “Remember how you told me Spanish 1 would be really hard for me and I would struggle? Well, that first month was pretty hard, but then something clicked, they moved me up to Spanish 2, and I’m acing every test. I wanted to tell you to never tell another student they would be bad at a foreign language because that is not how to encourage a student.” Everybody can do a foreign language, you just have to have the right teacher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;RS&lt;/b&gt;: Where did you go from there, a freshman in Spanish 2?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;JF&lt;/b&gt;: I did Spanish 3 and 4 sophomore year, and because my school didn’t offer AP Spanish, I taught it to myself in the library with a tape recorder and got a four on the AP test. I then taught myself French, since it’s related to Spanish and there’s some overlap, and senior year I was helping French 4 students with their homework because they just couldn’t see the patterns. Still, somehow I graduated as a math-science person and planned on majoring in biochemical engineering at UC Davis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;RS&lt;/b&gt;: So how did you get into the linguistic route in life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;JF&lt;/b&gt;: I took a class in Latin and Greek roots in medical vocabulary, to help me become a doctor. I loved the course and the teacher, I could recognize the roots, and I saw how the words changed. Then, I decided to switch to a classics major and double in English, with a focus on creative writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;RS&lt;/b&gt;: Have you come up with some patterns that help you organize the various Romance languages you’ve learned over the years?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;JF&lt;/b&gt;: So, I enjoy following the etymology of words and seeing how they change from Latin to French to English, because of course, French was the official language of England when they conquered the land. The hard c in Latin turns into a soft c in French and then turns into a “ch” in English. One of my favorites is the words “carus” and “ergos” in Latin, which mean “hand” and “work” respectively. They come together to mean “work of the hand.” French takes this and has the word “chirurgie,” and this translates to “surgery” in English. It blew my mind that you could still see it in a way if you took the patterns and identified them. There’s sound, places where things have softened or simplified, and, of course, dealing with word families, where you can take a root word and learn all related words and paths to learn a huge section of words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;RS&lt;/b&gt;: Do you have any guidelines or a general process for learning a language? What has been the most helpful?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;JF&lt;/b&gt;: I always say to learn the verbs first, because those are the words of action. You can identify the patterns, see when the action is happening, see who’s doing the action. That’s essential, especially with Romance languages. Once you’ve mastered the verbs, it’s really a matter of some grammatical constructions, the subjunctive mood and vocabulary. Verbs are just so central to a language because if you can understand the action of the sentence, you can understand what other words are coming into play and can add on and play with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;RS&lt;/b&gt;: As a teacher, you teach new students Latin every year.  What is the difference between learning a language and teaching a language?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;JF&lt;/b&gt;: When you start teaching to someone else, you really learn it. The two [learning and teaching] are aligned. When you learn a language, you sometimes become your own teacher; you learn what your strengths and challenges are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a teacher, I try to demystify the language and be as straightforward and honest, now that I’m on the far end of the spectrum of knowing the language. It’s a language: it’s complicated and there are lots of moving pieces. This is where my scientific brain comes into play, where I try to make it “x plus y equals z” and find rules and patterns to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;RS&lt;/b&gt;: What do you think has been the most helpful language to know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;JF&lt;/b&gt;: Latin- it gives us two-thirds of our English vocabulary, and about 90% of our technical vocabulary (science, math, medicine, legal system and government). It is so foundational and so important to English, so knowing those greatly opens up your English ability. English is a weird and important juncture of languages– heavily influenced by French and taking vocabulary from the Latin family– which is what makes it so difficult but also what gives it huge flexibility and creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://culturesconnection.com/translating-history-why-you-should-learn-latin/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Cultures Connection)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/Reagan_Smith.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Reagan Smith&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Reagan is a junior from Sage Hill School. She is passionate about all things related to science, especially biology and medicine. She also loves being able to use her talents and knowledge to help others and make a difference in the world.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Reagan Smith</name></author><summary type="html">The secret to learning a language Reagan Smith. 12/25/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/learningLanguageCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/learningLanguageCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dark energy: Summarized</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/24/dark-energy-summarized.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dark energy: Summarized" /><published>2020-12-24T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-24T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/24/dark-energy-summarized</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/24/dark-energy-summarized.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Dark energy: Summarized&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teddy Rosenthal. 12/25/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/darkEnergyOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This image depicts the cosmic microwave background. (Wikipedia)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Intergalactic Repulsion&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
First, let’s take a look at how we know that the universe is expanding. In 1925, American astronomer Edwin Hubble saw that galaxies that were farther away from Earth emitted light with spectral lines that had shifted towards the red end of the electromagnetic spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This phenomenon is now known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.space.com/25732-redshift-blueshift.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;redshift&lt;/a&gt;, where light waves experience the &lt;a href=&quot;https://imagine.gsfc.nasa.gov/features/yba/M31_velocity/spectrum/doppler_more.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Doppler effect&lt;/a&gt;. Light takes longer to reach the Earth when the object emitting the light is moving away from the Earth. Since the light takes a longer time to reach a certain point, the waves appear longer because they are stretched out. If these galaxies appeared to be redshifted from Earth, that meant that they were moving away from Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1929, Hubble was able to study the rate at which galaxies travel by observing a direct proportionality between a galaxy’s distance and the velocity at which it travels away from us (as shown in the image down below). This is summarized in &lt;a href=&quot;https://courses.lumenlearning.com/astronomy/chapter/the-expanding-universe/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hubble’s Law&lt;/a&gt;, v=Hd, where ‘v’ is velocity, ‘H’ is the Hubble constant and ‘d’ is the distance of a galaxy. This law is used to calculate the velocity of any galaxy given its distance, or vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/darkEnergyTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hosting.astro.cornell.edu/academics/courses/astro201/hubbles_law.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Cornell)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;An Expanding Universe&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
A similar pattern to the repulse between galaxies is shown in atoms or molecules filling a vacuum. The law that governs this principle is known as entropy and it causes particles to fill in a space until the system is homogeneous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can then be deduced that galaxies are moving away from each other to fill some sort of empty space. The fact that galaxies are moving away from one another must mean there is a background force acting as some repulsive form of gravity that causes space itself to expand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term ‘dark energy’ was conceived in 1998, as a way to refer to this phenomenon. In 1915, Albert Einstein published his paper on his general theory of relativity, and with it, his field equations. His equations were supposed to find a link between the geometry of spacetime and the mass density of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/darkEnergyThree.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The diagrams show the expansion rate in relation to time for each possible shape of space. &lt;a href=&quot;https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/cgro/epo/brochures/new_win/nw3.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(NASA)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In 1917, Einstein decided to add a value known as the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scholarpedia.org/article/Cosmological_constant&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;cosmological constant&lt;/a&gt;, ‘Λ,’ to his equation. It would assume that the universe is static and not expanding. Its value was set to 0 by Einstein but later repurposed with a new value that would represent the newly observed expansion and acceleration of the universe. A simple rearrangement of the constant (moving it from one side of the equation to the other) turned it from a geometric value to a contribution to the total mass density of the universe. This means that the cosmological constant represents something that exists and is now understood as the simplest and most coherent realization of dark energy. It is used in Einstein’s field equation to predict its own effect on the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Energy in Empty Space&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does dark energy affect our understanding of the universe?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it is understood that there is energy residing in empty space between particles and in outer space, the cosmological constant has a positive value. The energy in empty space is also recognized by quantum theory as vacuum energy and is represented by the cosmological constant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vacuum or dark energy takes up 70% of the composition of the universe, meaning that its value is significant alongside the density of the matter, dark matter and radiation in the universe. Since it is also used in Einstein’s field equation (which is used to predict the geometry of the universe given the total energy density and the cosmological constant), there must have been dramatic changes in the accepted geometry as the cosmological constant gained positive value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this is true, predictions were made involving the needed mass and energy for the universe to be flat (in 3-dimensions where space can be understood as vast amounts of adjacent cubes of space and where parallel lines never cross), which requires the total energy to equate to the integer ‘1,’ and the predicted energy constant of dark energy allows it to equal one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, many predictions have been made to explain the shape of the universe, and the existence of dark energy presently supports the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7ImvlS8PLIo&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;theory of a flat universe&lt;/a&gt;, though nothing is certain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Substantial mysteries involving dark energy are still yet to be answered. One such example is the density of dark energy in any given region remaining constant over time, even though its density should be decreasing similar to matter and radiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite scientists working day and night to solve the obscurity of this “anti-gravity,” all that is known is the existence of dark energy, which will determine the future of the universe and humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/darkEnergyFour.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The pie chart shows the composition of the universe. &lt;a href=&quot;https://wmap.gsfc.nasa.gov/universe/uni_matter.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(NASA)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nbcnews.com/mach/science/what-dark-energy-ncna1061206&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(NBC News)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Teddy Rosenthal&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Teddy is a sophomore at Westlake High School who enjoys learning about math and science related topics. Through InterSTEM, Teddy's goal is to spread knowledge of the most interesting STEM topics in hopes to popularize science. He also enjoys music, wrestling, and hiking.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Teddy Rosenthal</name></author><summary type="html">Dark energy: Summarized Teddy Rosenthal. 12/25/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/darkEnergyCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/darkEnergyCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Science behind cryptids</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/17/science-behind-cryptids.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science behind cryptids" /><published>2020-12-17T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-17T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/17/science-behind-cryptids</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/17/science-behind-cryptids.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Science behind cryptids&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Omar Dajani. 12/18/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/cryptidsOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This image displays a variety of cryptids, some of which you may be familiar with. (Edge of Orion)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you are an American, you likely have heard the name “Bigfoot” here and there in addition  to the names “Yeti” and “Loch-ness Monster.” All three of these names correspond to “cryptids,”  which are monsters that apparently roam our world. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalgeographic.com/news/2013/9/130907-cryptid-crytozoology-bigfoot-loch-yeti-monster-abominable-science/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Geographic&lt;/a&gt;, science has had a long battle with the existence of these monsters, due to the circumstantial evidence documenting their existence. Such evidence, which includes blurry pictures, strange footprints and eyewitness reports, is not enough for scientists to confirm their existence. While both factions are at war with each other, it is safe to say that science is the clear winner. Even so, the lore behind these cryptids and how they tie into the human psyche is interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some examples of cryptids were listed above, but it is important to know exactly what they are. Donald R. Prothero, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalgeographic.com/news/2013/9/130907-cryptid-crytozoology-bigfoot-loch-yeti-monster-abominable-science/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;paleontologist&lt;/a&gt; who has written over 250 scientific reports, including a  book discussing cryptids, defined them as “any animal that has never been described by science,  usually something very unusual along the lines of a Loch Ness monster or Bigfoot, something that  stretches the limits of what is scientifically plausible.” Prothero’s definition helps us understand that these cryptids cannot exist, as they seem to stretch what is scientifically possible within our world.  Daniel Loxton, Prothero’s partner who helped him write the aforementioned book, added on to his definition, stating “It’s based on the word cryptozoology, which means hidden life or animals. It  implies a creature that’s been recorded through folklore, something that we have reason to suspect  exists.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that being said, how can science help us understand the world of cryptozoology more?  First, for cryptids to exist, there cannot only be one cryptid of that species. Basically, Bigfoot is an offspring of other Bigfoot. The “monster” did not come into existence out of nowhere. The same goes for the other variety of cryptids. Speaking of which, the second way science can help us understand cryptids more is by their size. Many cryptids, such as giant squids and giant okapi, are abnormally large in size, so how is it possible that they have not been recently sighted at all? How would it be possible for them to avoid the public eye for as long as they have? Technology has been rapidly improving each year, making it so that finding these types of creatures should be no problem as of this point in time. The third and final way science can help us understand cryptids is not actually directly related to science itself, but rather the folklore and myths of old. In these stories, a lot of animals, such as bears, would exhibit human-like characteristics. People who know of these folklore stories and myths, upon seeing a weird looking bear, might not realize it is just a bear and think it is something more mystical as a result of these old stories. This is a solid example of the complexities of the human psyche and is also why it is important to take people’s eye-witness reports with a  grain of salt. Our senses (especially that of sight) can sometimes fool us into thinking we saw something mysterious when it was but a mere shadow of some normal animal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/cryptidsTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;An image displaying a variety of information on cryptids, with the standout info being that of how
big some of the cryptids are. This ties directly into the previous point of them being too large to not notice. (Paranormal Encounters)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
With all the above, it is quite obvious that cryptids are not actually real. Why then do some people still practice cryptozoology? Well, some think that by studying the stories and urban legends behind monsters like the Flat-Woods Monster, &lt;a href=&quot;https://cosmosmagazine.com/society/science-history-the-weird-world-of-cryptozoology/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;they are conserving parts of Earth’s history&lt;/a&gt;.  Regardless of whether or not these monsters are real, the tales behind them and their sightings are definitely quite interesting, which is why these cryptozoologists want to make sure the legends never die out and are always available for people to be fascinated by and ponder about.  Cryptozoology is also important as it might highlight humanity’s curiosity about the natural world.  Even then, it is important to note that some monsters who were labeled as cryptids at one point turned out to be actual real-life animals. Animals such as the platypus, manatee, okapi, and even
gorillas were all thought to be, at one point or another, mythological beasts. Might be hard to believe or imagine, but it is the truth. People disregarded their existence until it was made clear that the stories were not mere fiction, which led to the animals being scientifically recognized as real species with due time. The platypus especially has had a long and rough history with whether or not it was actually a real animal, with it finally being confirmed and scientifically recognized in the year 1799. With this piece of information, maybe creatures like the Yeti, Ningen, and even mermaids do actually exist after-all. It just might be that their discovery is around the corner and that they too will soon be scientifically recognized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Storenvy)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Omar Dajani&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Omar Dajani, an international student from Palestine, is currently a sophomore at Fullerton College. He used to be an English major but changed into a Computer Science major not too long ago. He enjoys gaming, blogging, journaling, meditating, and going on walks. He intends on transferring to UC Berkeley for Fall 2021. Currently learning Python, HTML, and CSS.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Omar Dajani</name></author><summary type="html">Science behind cryptids Omar Dajani. 12/18/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/cryptidsCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/cryptidsCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Cravings and connections</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/10/cravings-and-connections.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cravings and connections" /><published>2020-12-10T16:00:05-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-10T16:00:05-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/10/cravings-and-connections</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/10/cravings-and-connections.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Cravings and connections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carly Schinhofen. 12/11/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/cravingsOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Groundbreaking research shows humans’ innate desire for connections with others is surprisingly similar to hunger cravings.  
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uri.edu/features/neuroscience/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(The University of Rhode Island)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Just as hungry brains crave food, lonely brains crave people, new research suggests. This interesting connection between the two types of deprivation is increasingly important as COVID-19 isolates us all, demonstrating how social distancing can have detrimental effects on our lonely brains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Livia Tomova and her team at MIT created an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41593-020-00742-z&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;experiment&lt;/a&gt; to test the cognitive response to cravings. Participants volunteered to go without food for 10 hours so Tomova could determine which nerve cells responded to the need for food. Certain neurotransmitters became excited at the sight of junk food, and the neurons subsequently released dopamine as a positive reaction. This happy chemical is released frequently as a type of reward for the human brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on this initial segment of the experiment, Tomova wanted to test exactly how the brain responds to social deprivation, and how it differed from food deprivation. The same subjects were placed in a room entirely alone for 10 hours. After the isolation time ended, Tomova exposed the subjects to pictures of people and social gatherings. The subjects’ brains were immediately activated and produced dopamine, the same chemical that indicates a reward. In other words, they responded almost identically to the need for food as to the need for human contacts, indicating a fundamental connection between the two necessities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some subjects, the loneliness was more difficult, and this was reflected in their neural response to the hours of isolation. Others reported that the experience was not nearly as challenging for them, as it reflected their daily lifestyle. Therefore, environmental impacts such as general isolation or loneliness throughout life can make a human brain more accustomed to the feeling, thus not feeling much of a reward when exposed to social situations. Similarly, people tolerate hunger differently, since some generally have a greater tolerance for pain, which can come from a lack of food. They may feel the hunger on varying degrees, in the same way they experience loneliness, so people should remember that everyone’s circumstances in COVID-19 are inconsistent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A thought to keep in mind, however, is that those who have stronger wills to combat suffering may still be in pain, although it may not be obvious to others. During COVID-19, all people should still receive empathy for the loneliness they may be feeling, since they can still be hurting at the same degree as those that express their feelings more. It is important to remember that a coping mechanism for many is to push their struggles deep inside and ignore that something is missing in their lives, which may give others the illusion that they are unaffected by these times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The physiological connection between the need for food and social interactions demonstrates how humans’ brains react similarly when we are deprived of certain needs that our bodies require. Tomova’s experiment reflects how people’s brains are different from those of other individuals and therefore have varying responses to isolation. But overall, the deprivation of social connections can have an adverse effect on the brain as dopamine is an essential chemical to positive mental health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomova stressed the importance of being understanding in our current time, as isolation can put mental and physical health at stake, so everyone should respect the situations of others, as isolation impacts everyone in various ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Denison)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Carly Schinhofen&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Carly is a junior at Woodbridge High School. She is intrigued by biology and geology, and aspires to hold a career in science. Through her platform, she hopes to help others pursue their love for STEM. In her free time, she enjoys playing volleyball and trips to the beach.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Carly Schinhofen</name></author><summary type="html">Cravings and connections Carly Schinhofen. 12/11/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/cravingsCover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/cravingsCover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Invisible bruises: PTSD</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/10/invisible-bruises-ptsd.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Invisible bruises: PTSD" /><published>2020-12-10T16:00:04-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-10T16:00:04-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/10/invisible-bruises-ptsd</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/10/invisible-bruises-ptsd.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Invisible bruises: PTSD&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joan Joe. 12/11/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/ptsdOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The graphic above depicts several symptoms of PTSD.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newstartrecoverysolutions.com/what-is-ptsd/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(New Start Recovery Solutions)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Introduction&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) is an anxiety disorder that develops after a traumatic experience. A certain trigger after the incident may cause a person to recall the horrifying event, which in turn may cause them to become distant with those they once were close to. Everything from a mugging, threats, scarring incidents, robbery, and natural catastrophes can be a traumatic experience. Depression and drug misuse also exacerbate the condition. Different individuals encounter novel experiences that are more traumatic than others. This makes it difficult to precisely determine what particular event is traumatic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the period from just after the traumatic incident to six months later, acute stress disorder occurs. PTSD begins at the six-month mark and persists thereafter. However, not all trauma patients develop PTSD immediately following exposure. Some individuals respond rapidly to traumatic exposure, while others remain unscathed only to experience the sudden onset of PTSD symptoms months or years later. Flashbacks, extreme anxiety and uncontrollable thoughts about the incident can all be symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;PTSD Amongst Veterans&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have seen a dramatic rise in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/25077185/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;number of Iraq and Afghanistan war veterans&lt;/a&gt; seeking help for PTSD over the past few years, shining a spotlight on this chronic condition and posing crucial questions about adequate treatment services and care barriers. At any given point, the disorder affects millions: about 8% of individuals in the United States will experience it at some point in their lives. Military veterans are extremely vulnerable: 20% of those who served in Iraq and Afghanistan returned home with PTSD or depression. And since the year 2000, over 350,000 service members have been diagnosed with traumatic brain injury, many of whom have cognitive or behavioral disabilities. The alarming suicide rate among veterans is a testament to psychic wounds that linger long after the war ends: 20 end their lives every day.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/ptsdTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This graph shows the percent of war veterans suffering from mental disorders.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/figure/Prevalence-of-veterans-self-reported-postdeployment-driving-difficulties-by-clinical_fig1_51784252&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Research Gate)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Impacts of Mental Trauma on Memory and the Brain&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abuse of children and other causes of severe stress may have permanent effects on the areas of the brain involved in memory and emotion. In particular, the hippocampus appears to be very stress-sensitive. Not only will stress damage to the hippocampus cause difficulty in coping with memories and other consequences of prior traumatic events, but it can also hinder new learning. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK3874/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Research&lt;/a&gt; has shown that as part of its regular function, the hippocampus can regenerate nerve cells, but stress impairs the process by preventing or slowing down the regeneration of neurons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/ptsdThree.png&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The hippocampus (in blue) is shown within the context of the brain.
(Wikipedia)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/253494116_The_Invisible_Epidemic_Post-Traumatic_Stress_Disorder_Memory_and_the_Brain&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A study&lt;/a&gt; was carried out to see whether the symptoms of PTSD matched the observable loss of neurons in the hippocampus. Vietnam war veterans with declaratory memory issues caused by PTSD were first tested. These war veterans were found to have an 8% decrease in right hippocampal volume, assessed with magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and brain imaging. However, there were no changes in other areas of the brain.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/ptsdFour.png&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The MRI scans are of the Vietnam war veterans who have declaratory memory issues.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/253494116_The_Invisible_Epidemic_Post-Traumatic_Stress_Disorder_Memory_and_the_Brain&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Research gate)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study found that reduced right hippocampal volume was associated with short-term memory loss in patients with PTSD. When looking at PTSD patients who were victims of physical or sexual assault during their childhood, similar findings were observed. According to more recent studies that have reported hippocampal volume reduction in PTSD, these studies also indicate that the reduction in hippocampal volume is unique to PTSD and is not correlated with conditions such as anxiety or panic disorders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Damage to the hippocampus, following exposure to the strain brought on by childhood abuse, results in distortion and fragmentation of memories. In linking and arranging various aspects of memory, the hippocampus plays an important role and is assumed to be responsible for locating the memory of an occurrence in its proper time, place and context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if a person was a victim of childhood abuse due to alcohol and was locked away in a closet of old clothes, he or she may only remember the smell of alcohol or that of the old clothes, but not the part about having been locked in the closet. He or she may experience a sudden flashback or have a panic attack when the smell of alcohol hits them. Psychotherapy (talk therapy) or an experience that causes similar feelings will help the patient rebuild memories in these situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another significant area is the amygdala, a region of the brain involved in associative learning, value encoding and emotional responses. PTSD symptom intensity can be independently predicted by both smaller amygdala volume and less reliable monitoring of the negative value of face stimuli (negative surprises in the environment) in the amygdala.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nimh.nih.gov/news/science-news/2019/brain-biomarkers-could-help-identify-those-at-risk-of-severe-ptsd.shtml&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A study&lt;/a&gt; conducted by Daniela Schiller, Ph.D. and Ilan Harpaz-Rotem, Ph.D. on combat veterans offered the conclusion that the severity of PTSD symptoms is mirrored in how combat veterans react to negative external shocks when the anticipated results are not as planned, and how the way the brain is tuned to these stimuli is different.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/ptsdFive.png&quot; width=&quot;20%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The regions of interest (functionally defined amygdala) used in the study of computational imaging are shown in red.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nimh.nih.gov/news/science-news/2019/brain-biomarkers-could-help-identify-those-at-risk-of-severe-ptsd.shtml&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(NCBI)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Variations between those with or without PTSD were also shown in other brain regions involved that are related to danger learning, such as the striatum (a part that coordinates multiple aspects of cognition) and the dorsal anterior cingulate cortex (a brain region that subserves cognition and motor control).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Treatments&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To minimize symptoms and improve function, having appropriate care after the development of PTSD symptoms may be crucial. The ideal PTSD treatment, which is secure, safe, fast-acting and has minimal side effects, has been elusive. And, as with many mental health conditions, patients often have difficulty embracing or adhering to any of the available solutions. For years, the military department and healthcare experts have sought a range of options for effective treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rti.org/impact/stellate-ganglion-block-new-treatment-ptsd#:~:text=SGB%20is%20a%20true%20breakthrough,a%20deterrent%20to%20seeking%20treatment&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;One of the recent procedures&lt;/a&gt; is the stellate ganglion block (SGB) procedure, which was discovered to be effective in the fall of 2019. The operation involves injecting the stellate ganglion with a local anesthetic. This community of neck nerve cells helps control the “fight or flight” function of the body. Some military medical facilities started offering this treatment to PTSD patients in the early 2010s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the SGB procedure was studied by more researchers and patients, the results appeared positive. But the proof of its efficacy was still required by the medical community. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rti.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;RTI International&lt;/a&gt;, a nonprofit research institution, launched a randomized, controlled SGB trial in 2014, and gave an official report by the end of 2019. A suggested reason for the sustained efficacy of SGB on PTSD, as well as the effects of hot flashes and complex regional pain syndrome, is that local anesthetic application to the stellate ganglion contributes to a decrease in the growth factor of the nerve and subsequently, a decrease in the amount of sympathetic nerve sprouting and norepinephrine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/ptsdSix.png&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The diagram above illustrates the stellate ganglion.
(Anatomy of the Human Body)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Psychotherapy and drugs that are short- and long-term will also treat PTSD well. Sometimes, the two types of treatment are more successful together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way of treating PTSD is by using &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognitive_processing_therapy&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Cognitive Processing Therapy (CPT)&lt;/a&gt;. It is a particular method of cognitive-behavioral therapy that has been effective in minimizing PTSD symptoms. Over 12 hours, CPT is administered; the process helps patients learn how to question and change harmful trauma-related assumptions. In doing so, the patient develops a new perception and conceptualization of the traumatic incident so that its ongoing detrimental effects on current life are minimized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exposure to a traumatic stimulus is another method of intervention widely used to help people confront fears in cognitive-behavioral therapy. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apa.org/ptsd-guideline/treatments/prolonged-exposure&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Prolonged exposure (PE)&lt;/a&gt; is a special form of cognitive-behavioral therapy that helps people gradually handle memories, emotions and circumstances relevant to their trauma. Most individuals try to stop something that reminds them of the trauma they have endured, but their anxiety is intensified by doing so. An individual may minimize PTSD symptoms by consciously learning that the memories and signs related to trauma are not dangerous and do not need to be prevented by confronting what has been avoided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concerning physical treatment, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webmd.com/drugs/2/drug-6969-9095/paroxetine-oral/paroxetine-oral/details&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;paroxetine&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webmd.com/drugs/2/drug-1/sertraline-oral/details&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;sertraline&lt;/a&gt; are the only drugs to have been approved by the FDA for treating PTSD. Since different people react to drugs differently, and not everyone’s PTSD is the same, the doctor can also prescribe other “off label” medicines, meaning that the manufacturers of those medicines have not requested the FDA to review drug trials proving the drug is specifically effective for PTSD. These may include &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webmd.com/depression/guide/depression-medications-antidepressants&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;antidepressants&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monoamine_oxidase_inhibitor&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;monoamine oxidase inhibitors&lt;/a&gt; (MAOIs), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK519503/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;antipsychotics or second-generation antipsychotics&lt;/a&gt; (SGAs), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medicalnewstoday.com/articles/173068&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;beta-blockers&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medicinenet.com/benzodiazepines_sleep-inducing-oral/article.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;benzodiazepines&lt;/a&gt;. Medications do not remove the symptoms, but they may make them more manageable by decreasing their severity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National PTSD Center provides self-help resources, including the PTSD Coach Online app and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mobile.va.gov/app/ptsd-coach&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PTSD Coach app&lt;/a&gt;. These provide therapy to deal with depression, anxiety and other symptoms that can be formed by people who have been through trauma. When PTSD patients feel depressed, the apps can help them relax, boost their mood, teach them how to solve tough issues and help change their thought patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Taking Action&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An individual who is subjected to a traumatic event may feel powerless, causing a concerned partner to take action to assist them. Perhaps the most effective approach is being there for the person, showing acceptance and concern, and listening without being judgmental or providing advice. It is necessary to promote healthy living, such as adherence to the diet, exercise and refraining from smoking and excessive alcohol use. Arranging fun recreational activities is another way to help those with PTSD live a happier and more relaxed life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.health.harvard.edu/mind-and-mood/how-to-recover-from-post-traumatic-stress-disorder&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Harvard Health Publishing)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Joan Joe&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Joan is a freshman in St. Antony’s Public School, India. She is intrigued by psychology and neuroscience and aspires to join research in neuroscience and STEM-related works. She hopes to help others pursue their passion for STEM through her platform. In her free time, she plays the piano, sings, and loves to read Dan Brown’s books.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Joan Joe</name></author><summary type="html">Invisible bruises: PTSD Joan Joe. 12/11/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/ptsdCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/ptsdCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The importance of keystone species</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/10/importance-of-keystone-species.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The importance of keystone species" /><published>2020-12-10T16:00:03-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-10T16:00:03-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/10/importance-of-keystone-species</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/10/importance-of-keystone-species.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The importance of keystone species&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emily Richter. 12/11/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/keystoneSpeciesOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;A mother grey wolf and her cubs in present-day Yellowstone National Park. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nrdc.org/issues/protect-keystone-species&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(James Michael Kruger / iStock)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The year was 1924. Barren dirt replaced the characteristic native plants of Yellowstone National Park. Streams running through the plains and forests of the park eroded the land away at an alarming rate. Bird populations flew off to faraway lands, leaving their former home— now a wasteland— behind. What could be the cause of this catastrophic decline in the beloved National Park? What sparked this event that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nrdc.org/issues/protect-keystone-species&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Geographic&lt;/a&gt; calls a “top-down trophic cascade”? It turns out the cause of the ecological disaster was the loss of only one species: the grey wolf. The grey wolf happened to be very important because it was a keystone species.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A keystone species is any species that has a niche, or ecological job, so specific that other organisms in its environment cannot fulfill that same role. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.oursafetynet.org/2020/02/07/what-are-keystone-species/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Canadian National Environmental Treasure&lt;/a&gt; notes the term as being first used by ecologist Robert T. Paine. Paine observed the relationship between ochre sea stars and their prey, mussels, and determined that a loss in the ochre sea star population would trigger an uncontrolled growth in the mussel population, which in turn would negatively affect other aspects of the environment. National Geographic notes that other well-known species that serve as keystone species in their environment include grey wolves, salmon and elephants. Keystone species can be found at every level of the food pyramid, from producer to apex predator.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the case of the Greater Yellowstone Ecosystem, the grey wolf was the only predator of elk. Without the wolves, the elk population exploded. Elk overgrazed the vegetation in Yellowstone, leaving the ground barren and the stream banks lacking the native plants that usually prevented erosion. The elk population took food away from other herbivores and omnivores, leaving them to starve. Just as a keystone keeps an arch from collapsing, the grey wolf kept Yellowstone from collapsing. When the wolves were taken away from Yellowstone, the ecosystem fell apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Keystone species may be the most important species in an ecosystem, but they are not always the most aesthetic or well-known creatures. Many people take up rallying cries to save animals considered cute, but few take up the rallying cry to save the lumpy and veined ochre sea star. Despite their adorable appearances, if some popular animals disappeared from the wild, the environmental impact would not be as extreme. Since society collectively does not understand the importance of keystone species, more and more keystone species are becoming endangered while conservation efforts focus on the most popular species. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nrdc.org/issues/protect-keystone-species&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;United States Natural Resources Defense Council&lt;/a&gt; (NRDC) also cites human development and the environmental mismanagement of governments as reasons for the decline of keystone species. The NRDC argues that listening to the advice of ecologists on the topic of conservation is the only way forward.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After scientists and the government alike watched the Yellowstone ecosystem collapse, they realized that something had to be done. National Geographic reports that in 1990, nearly seventy years after the top-down trophic cascade in Yellowstone began, the United States government started a program to reintroduce grey wolves to the Greater Yellowstone Ecosystem. Since then, the ecosystem has sprung back to life. Despite the fact that the Greater Yellowstone Ecosystem was in shambles less than thirty years ago, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalparks.org/explore-parks/yellowstone-national-park&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Park Foundation&lt;/a&gt; (NPF) describes present-day Yellowstone as an “otherworldly” and “truly unique” place with “plentiful wildlife”. Visitors to the park are sometimes lucky enough to see one of the keystone species in the distance, as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalparks.org/our-work/programs/yellowstone-wolf-impact-study&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Yellowstone Wolf Impact Study&lt;/a&gt; from the NPF reports that the grey wolf population has grown to over 400 individuals, each one helping to hold the Greater Yellowstone Ecosystem together. Almost a century later, many species that migrated from the Greater Yellowstone Ecosystem have returned. Communities of animals that nearly went extinct are thriving again, their population numbers constant. Plants cover the ground again, feeding animals and holding streams in place. Thanks to the return of its keystone species, the Greater Yellowstone Ecosystem is once again intact.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The story of the wolves illustrates the importance of protecting keystone species. If keystone species are not protected and consequently disappear from the world’s ecosystems, the world’s environment would shatter. This type of ecological disaster can be avoided if governments work with scientists to prioritize the protection of keystone species. If society begins to understand the importance of keystone species and advocates for their protection, the world can move forward, united against environmental ruin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalparks.org/our-work/programs/yellowstone-wolf-impact-study&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(National Park Foundation)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Emily Richter&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Emily is a junior from Maria Carrillo High School in Sonoma County. She loves chemistry and the environmental sciences and plans to be an environmental chemist when she gets older. Through InterSTEM, she hopes to combine her experience in writing with her interest in STEM in order to help others enjoy and understand STEM. In her free time, she likes playing the flute, and baking and cooking.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Emily Richter</name></author><summary type="html">The importance of keystone species Emily Richter. 12/11/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/keystoneSpeciesCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/keystoneSpeciesCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dual function: Converting trash to electricity</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/10/dual-function-converting-trash-to-energy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dual function: Converting trash to electricity" /><published>2020-12-10T16:00:02-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-10T16:00:02-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/10/dual-function-converting-trash-to-energy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/10/dual-function-converting-trash-to-energy.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Dual function: Converting trash to electricitys&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reagan Smith. 12/11/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/dualFunctionOne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;A look inside Copenhill shows the same sleek design, created to burn huge amounts of waste and convert it to clean energy for citizens of Denmark. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.archpaper.com/2020/11/copenhill-bigs-skiable-waste-to-energy-power-plant-gets-sweeping-new-photos-from-hufton-crow/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(The Architect’s Newspaper)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In a quickly-shrinking world where space and resources are limited, we find ourselves being forced to choose. Convenient or reusable? Cheap or clean? Beautiful or eco-friendly? However, a new group of thinkers are emerging: ones who question why we have to pick one or the other. They are combining environmentally-conscious thinking with state-of-the-art technology and engineering to create products and buildings that are multifunctional and can integrate into day-to-day life. Copenhill, the creation of Danish architect Bjarke Ingels, fits this mindset perfectly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This building is the cleanest waste-to-energy plant in the world, Copenhagen’s tallest and largest structure, and also the home of Denmark’s first ski slope, as stated by an article about the project in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.archdaily.com/925966/copenhill-the-story-of-bigs-iconic-waste-to-energy-plant&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ArchDaily&lt;/a&gt;. Copenhill combines functionality with fun, efficiency with elegance and sustainability with sustenance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Created by Bjarke Ingels Group (BIG), the idea for Copenhill first arose in 2002, when the company, then called PLOT, imagined a public space in one of Denmark’s most dense urban areas that utilized space by placing a ski slope on top of a department store. While PLOT never saw the project through, it did inspire the concept for a waste-to-energy plant that won an international design competition in 2011.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, 170,000 square feet of ski slopes and parks that comprise Copenhill’s roof neatly cover the plant. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.power-technology.com/projects/amager-bakke-waste-energy-plant/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Power Technology&lt;/a&gt;, the roof itself was designed by Stig L. Andersson Landscape Architects, a Danish architectural lab. In addition to the slopes and parks, the public has access to a running path, a café and a forest, all atop the building. The outside covering shows off aluminum bricks (1.2 meters by 3.3 meters) all overlapping each other to create a sleek and elegant facade that doubles as a recreational rock climbing wall.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the exterior itself is unique and interesting, it is what is on the inside that showcases Ingel’s mind and the abilities of technology and engineering. As explained in an article by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.power-technology.com/projects/amager-bakke-waste-energy-plant/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Power Technology&lt;/a&gt;, the waste-to-energy process begins by dumping trash into a containment area, where a large crane transfers it to a hopper (a large pyramidal shaped container designed to hold loose material, which then brings it to a combustor grate). For this plant specifically, Ingel utilized DynagGrate, an advanced, water-cooled combustor grate made by the company &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.babcock.com/products/combustion-grates-stokers&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Babcock and Wilcox&lt;/a&gt;. The grate is designed to agitate the fuel bed the waste sits in when it burns to increase the rate of combustion and limit wear on the mechanical parts by preventing contact between the individual grate bars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/dualFunctionTwo.jpg&quot; width=&quot;30%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The image above depicts a combustion grate. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.babcock.com/en/products/combustion-grates-stokers&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Babcock and Wilcox)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
After the waste is heated, the energy it produces is used to heat up water in a boiler, which travels through a steam drum to a turbine. The steam turbine powered by water vapor produces electricity, while the hot gas itself heats homes, depicted in a diagram from &lt;a href=&quot;https://deltawayenergy.com/2018/08/waste-to-energy-how-it-works/&quot; target=&quot;_blanK&quot;&gt;Deltaway Energy&lt;/a&gt; down below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/dualFunctionThree.jpg&quot; width=&quot;30%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://deltawayenergy.com/2018/08/waste-to-energy-how-it-works/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Deltaway Energy)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Copenhill uses flue gas condensation technology to recover 100 million liters of water that would otherwise exit the plant as water vapor, cool it down and filter out 100,000 liters of bottom ash (made from the combustion of the waste) to be used as road materials every year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Collecting waste from 500,000 to 700,000 people and 46,000 companies in and near Copenhagen, the plant has a 107% energy efficiency, overstepping its designed goal to utilize 100% of energy content. It is also twice as efficient in producing energy than Europe’s older waste-to-energy plants, generating steam at 440°C and at a pressure of 70 bars (unit of pressure).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The plant exemplifies the architectural concept of hedonistic design, which is the idea that sustainability can come without compromise. Best summed up in an article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://bigthink.com/endless-innovation/designing-a-hedonistic-and-sustainable-future&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Big Think&lt;/a&gt; by Dominic Basulto, hedonistic design asks the question, “What if you can do something that is good for the environment while doing something good for yourself and for the economy?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copenhill is a building that finally manages to satisfy everyone and everything, from the economy to the environmentalists and people young and old. Ingels, the mastermind behind the project and founder of BIG, says it is “a crystal clear example of hedonistic sustainability – that a sustainable city is not only better for the environment – it is also more enjoyable for the lives of its citizens.” Ingles is well-known as an innovator and outside-the-box thinker, as exemplified in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ted.com/talks/bjarke_ingels_hedonistic_sustainability#t-37601&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TEDx&lt;/a&gt; talk he gave in New York City. To him, it is an example that “we have the power to give form to the future that we want to live in.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project is in line with the city of Copenhagen’s goal of becoming carbon-neutral by 2025.  Parameters for carbon neutrality are laid out by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.europarl.europa.eu/news/en/headlines/society/20190926STO62270/what-is-carbon-neutrality-and-how-can-it-be-achieved-by-2050&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;European Parliament&lt;/a&gt;, which explains it as “having a balance between emitting carbon and absorbing carbon from the atmosphere in carbon sinks.” A carbon sink is a system that acts as storage for carbon by absorbing more carbon than it creates; examples of this are soil, forests and oceans. Copenhagen’s carbon-neutrality goal is part of a larger climate policy put into place by the European Union, which aims to become carbon neutral by 2050.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Copenhill perfectly sums up what architecture can – and will – do. Its completion signifies the beginning of a new age of architecture, where buildings move beyond simple skeletons for activities and transform into meaningful structures that work with the environment, rather than against it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.trendhunter.com/trends/copenhill&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Trend Hunter)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/Reagan_Smith.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Reagan Smith&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Reagan is a junior from Sage Hill School. She is passionate about all things related to science, especially biology and medicine. She also loves being able to use her talents and knowledge to help others and make a difference in the world.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Reagan Smith</name></author><summary type="html">Dual function: Converting trash to electricitys Reagan Smith. 12/11/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/dualFunctionCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/dualFunctionCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The reality of robotics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/10/the-reality-of-robotics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The reality of robotics" /><published>2020-12-10T16:00:01-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-10T16:00:01-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/10/the-reality-of-robotics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/10/the-reality-of-robotics.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The reality of robotics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simone Rothaupt. 12/11/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/roboticsOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Robots have already greatly benefitted countless industries, such as automation, and can potentially be applied to many more. &lt;a href=&quot;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;
(Technavio)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Popular culture has long warned humankind that robots will soon take over. From Pixar movie “WALL-E” to the science-fiction book “Humans, Bow Down,” robots are seemingly within reach of reigning the world. However, in the InterSTEM Speaker Series, Professor Heiko Hoffmann debunked this fear and revealed the true state of robotics to be far from those dystopian expectations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although not as advanced as Hollywood’s predictions, robots are still present across the globe. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.therobotreport.com/6-industries-demand-robotics-developers-grow-2025/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Robot Report&lt;/a&gt;, robots have been implemented into various industries, such as automation, food, agriculture, healthcare and manufacturing, as the technology can perform precisely and efficiently to pick and place motions in controlled settings. In just the third quarter of 2019, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.industryweek.com/technology-and-iiot/article/22028667/2020-future-of-manufacturing-technology&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Industry Week&lt;/a&gt; reported that orders for robots totaled over $1.3 billion, demonstrating how widespread robotics has become.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Robots can vary in structure and function, but Dr. Hoffmann clarifies that most robots, especially ones in manufacturing, consist of robotic arms on a moving unit that utilizes linear grippers which open and close. For example, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mars.nasa.gov/mars2020/mission/facts/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Aeronautics and Space Administration&lt;/a&gt; (NASA) explains that their space exploration robots have linear grippers and wheels, as well as complex machinery like drills to conduct soil analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Several products that seek to address the issues of current robots, such as limited flexibility and autonomy, are under development. For instance, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bostondynamics.com/atlas&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Boston Dynamics&lt;/a&gt; has designed a human-sized robot named Atlas that specializes in locomotion, such as backflips and jumping, and can move up to 1.5 meters per second. In addition, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/the-education-of-brett-the-robot/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;WIRED&lt;/a&gt; explains that the Berkley robot for the Elimination of Tedious Tasks (BRETT) employs imitation and reinforcement learning to teach itself new skills on its own, such as putting pegs into holes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But how do these robots work? According to Dr. Hoffmann, robots function using three steps. First, the robot must understand its location in a 3D and relative to the objects around it, a process which includes examining the depth of its surroundings, distinguishing the outline of objects and interpreting its scene through a computer. A robot’s perception system often includes a depth sensor, light detection and ranging (Lidar) and cameras. Second, the robot must plan several collision-free trajectories and choose the fastest or most direct option. Finally, the robot must execute movements by controlling the power and speed of the actuators and motors. A robot often has to simultaneously perform all three tasks in order to adapt to new environments and obstacles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/wired-guide-to-robots/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;WIRED&lt;/a&gt;, sensors, actuators and artificial intelligence (AI) are responsible for allowing robots to develop so much in recent years. Sensors, especially Lidar, have enabled robots to obtain better quality sensory data and thus, quickly identify the world around them. Actuators, such as the ones powered by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wired.com/story/a-clever-new-robotic-muscle-seriously-lifts-bro/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;electricity flowing through oil-fueled pouches&lt;/a&gt;, have given robots greater strength and smoother mobility. AI allows for information and complex calculations to be processed rapidly in real-time and enables the machine to ‘learn’ from its mistakes. Together, these three innovations improve the accuracy, flexibility and power of robots.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In order for robots to become commercially viable and more effective, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.therobotreport.com/10-biggest-challenges-in-robotics/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Robot Report&lt;/a&gt; explains that robots need to become cheaper, more flexible, more durable, better suited for handling delicate materials, be able to communicate faster and have an improved sense of touch. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.technologyreview.com/2019/07/19/678/ai-machine-learning-makes-robots-cheaper-with-same-abilities/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;MIT Technology Review&lt;/a&gt;, transfer learning could reduce the cost of testing robots without sacrificing quality. Transfer learning is where robots are first trained with higher-grade sensors and in a controlled environment. Afterward, these robots are able to apply what they learned from the previous testing, and they can then navigate a new chaotic environment with poor sensors faster than a robot without prior training. Furthermore, testing conducted by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.tri.global/news/sensing-is-believing-more-sensitive-robot-hands-t-2020-9-9/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Toyota Research Institute&lt;/a&gt; has developed a plausible technique for improving a robot’s ability to handle delicate objects. By using grippers with air-filled elastic bubbles instead of metal or other rigid materials, a robot could gently hold objects. While these solutions will help to address some of the current issues with robots, additional research is required to advance robots enough for complete integration into our everyday lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For the future of robots, Dr. Hoffman detailed some viable achievements we may see in the coming years. Fully autonomous driving has become a realistic possibility because more companies like Tesla are investing in this area, and researchers continue to improve machine learning and computer vision. Fully autonomous warehouses and distribution centers, like Amazon, are potentially within reach as the relatively controlled environment of a shipping center is the optimal environment for a robot to function. Moreover, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.roboticsbusinessreview.com/news/infographic-the-evolution-of-robotics-and-automation/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Robotics Business Review&lt;/a&gt; claims the future may see a shift in more automation in manufacturing, especially for wielding together metal and handling rigid objects. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://ark-invest.com/analyst-research/robots-will-save-manufacturing-billions/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ARK Invest&lt;/a&gt;, although initially more costly, the use of robots in manufacturing has the potential to break even in less than a year and lower employee injury rates. Although real robots do not resemble pop culture, they hold great future potential for enhancing our lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simone Rothaupt
Simone is a sophomore at Thousand Oaks High School in Ventura, California. She is interested in exploring STEM related topics, such as medicine, and she also hopes to spread this passion to others through writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.istockphoto.com/photo/thinking-robot-gm986497102-267585335&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(iStockphoto/iLexx)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Simone Rothaupt&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Simone is a sophomore at Thousand Oaks High School in Ventura, California. She is interested in exploring STEM related topics, such as medicine, and she also hopes to spread this passion to others through writing.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Simone Rothaupt</name></author><summary type="html">The reality of robotics Simone Rothaupt. 12/11/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/roboticsCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/roboticsCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Aliens almost definitely exist. Here are the facts to prove it</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/03/aliens-almost-definitely-exist.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Aliens almost definitely exist. Here are the facts to prove it" /><published>2020-12-03T16:00:02-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-03T16:00:02-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/03/aliens-almost-definitely-exist</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/03/aliens-almost-definitely-exist.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Aliens almost definitely exist. Here are the facts to prove it&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ramizah Tayiba. 12/04/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/aliensExistOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The image above is an illustration of alien life imagined by humans. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nbcnews.com/mach/science/discovery-alien-life-might-not-bring-response-you-d-expect-ncna849046&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Apostoli Rossella / Getty Images)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The human species is intelligent, brave and ambitious but not unique. The building blocks of our existence are the same as those of a beetle, a tree or a star. Carbon, hydrogen, nitrogen, oxygen and sulfur are the foundation of the entire universe. If these unoriginal elements happen to arrange themselves to form life here on Earth, it is more than likely they have done so somewhere else. The foundations of our being can be traced to stars billions of miles away. With new technologies, like the powerful telescopes such as  Hubble and the study of spectroscopy, “we are now able to map the abundance of all of the major elements found in the human body across hundreds of thousands of stars in our Milky Way,” &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sdss.org/press-releases/the-elements-of-life-mapped-across-the-milky-way-by-sdssapogee/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;professor at The Ohio State University Jennifer Johnson said.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Simple statistics also demonstrate the likelihood of alien existence. There are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/feature/goddard/2016/hubble-reveals-observable-universe-contains-10-times-more-galaxies-than-previously-thought/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;two billion&lt;/a&gt; known galaxies; each galaxy has billions of stars. The Milky Way Galaxy is home to one hundred billion stars, each with hundreds of orbiting planets. These numbers continue to grow after the launch of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://solarsystem.nasa.gov/missions/kepler/in-depth/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Kepler space telescope in 2009&lt;/a&gt;, which can detect planets millions of light-years away. Kepler orbits our sun to monitor surrounding stars and compares the data with the observations from ground observatories to process the number of possible planets. Kepler not only detects planets but can detect Earth-like planets that are in the Goldilock zone (a safe distance from the Sun.) According to Kepler’s findings, 40 billion planets have the potential to sustain life.  The number of habitable planets can also be estimated by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.space.com/25219-drake-equation.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Drake equation&lt;/a&gt;, a famous equation created by astronomer Frank Drake to estimate the potential number of habitable planets in the universe.  The equation factors in the rate of expansion of the universe, the average rate of star formation,  along with other factors to estimate that there might be 100 million examples of alien life in the Milky Way alone. Furthermore, the number of planets discovered continues to grow. With these numbers, it is unlikely that humans were the only ones who got lucky.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The existence of aliens is sometimes discredited because most planets are too hostile to sustain any form of life. Many argue that the number of planets may be grand, but the number of planets like our own is a little rarer. But studies from our own planet are debunking this notion and proving that life may thrive somewhere else. We are constantly finding life in the most hostile places on Earth (like the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newscientist.com/article/dn10336-gold-mine-holds-life-untouched-by-the-sun/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;nematode worm&lt;/a&gt;, a specimen found six kilometers below South Africa’s deepest gold mines). Life has also been found deep in the ice in Antarctica, on top of scorching hot volcanoes and all the way in the deep dark ocean. These specimens are called extremophiles (lovers of the extreme) and can survive in extreme cold, heat, acidity and toxicity.  This means it is possible for life to adapt to the freezing temperatures of Neptune, the scorching heat of Mercury, the toxicity of gaseous clouds in Venus and the salty lakes of Mars. Life can sustain itself in the most hostile environments, proving that planets don’t necessarily have to be Earth-like to support organisms. This makes every speck in the night sky a possible home for life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For many people, the idea of other living beings thriving somewhere beyond Earth seems far-fetched. This notion puts us all on a pedestal of uniqueness. But science, math, and logic ground us. They make us believe that we are not alone. That we are just one small piece of the giant galactic puzzle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/alien-life-is-out-there-but-our-theories-are-probably-steering-us-away-from-it-124042&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Shutterstock&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Ramizah Tayiba&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Ramizah Tayiba is a junior at Francis Lewis High School. She is passionate about STEM and enjoys writing articles about the advances in the fields. She writes articles ranging from the smallest atoms to the ever-expanding universe. She hopes her articles will allow others to gain insights into the world of STEM. In her spare time, Ramizah enjoys painting, reading, and playing hockey.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ramizah Tayiba</name></author><summary type="html">Aliens almost definitely exist. Here are the facts to prove it Ramizah Tayiba. 12/04/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/aliensExistCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/aliensExistCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>