<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-12-03T17:52:15-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">InterSTEM</title><entry><title type="html">Could gum disease be the cause of Alzheimer’s disease?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/27/gum-disease.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Could gum disease be the cause of Alzheimer’s disease?" /><published>2020-11-27T16:00:05-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-27T16:00:05-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/27/gum-disease</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/27/gum-disease.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Could gum disease be the cause of Alzheimer’s disease? &lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joan Joe. 11/27/2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/alzheimerOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Alzheimer's disease is a progressive condition that causes the degeneration and death of brain cells. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.pmlive.com/pharma_intelligence/Detecting_Alzheimers_ahead_of_a_cure_1301233&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(PMLiVE)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nia.nih.gov/health/alzheimers-disease-fact-sheet&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Institutes of Health&lt;/a&gt; (NIH), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alz.org/alzheimers-dementia/what-is-alzheimers&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Alzheimer’s disease&lt;/a&gt; is the most prevalent type of dementia, affecting more than 5.5 million Americans. Abnormal protein accumulation, called amyloid plaques and tau tangles, steadily kill brain cells and the connections between them in the brains of people with Alzheimer’s, hindering the capacity of individuals to think and remember. The effects are permanent, and there is no treatment yet for Alzheimer’s. To find one, scientists worldwide are working in high gear, but most medicines that have entered clinical trials have failed.
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/alzheimerTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The difference between a healthy brain and a brain with Alzheimer’s disease&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lifespan.io/news/distinct-amyloid-beta-prion-strains/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; (Life Extension Advocacy Foundation)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There are two types of Alzheimer’s: early-onset and late-onset.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Typically, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alz.org/help-support/i-have-alz/younger-onset&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;early-onset Alzheimer’s&lt;/a&gt; affects individuals before age 65, with the signs typically occurring in a person’s 40s or 50s. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/alzheimers-disease/symptoms-causes/syc-20350447&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mayo Clinic&lt;/a&gt;, this type of disorder is rare, affecting only 5% of all people with Alzheimer’s. It is a direct result of hereditary mutations in one of the three genes: APP, PSEN1 or PSEN2. What researchers have discovered from these unusual mutations that cause early-onset Alzheimer’s is that the mutation of the gene leads to the overproduction of a rogue, harmful beta-amyloid protein. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alz.org/alzheimers-dementia/what-is-alzheimers/brain_tour&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The beta-amyloid&lt;/a&gt; build-up in the brain develops plaques that are one of the disease’s hallmarks. Just as plaques in the arteries can affect the heart, plaques in the brain can have dire effects on the function of the brain. For the disease to manifest, a person needs to inherit only one of these genes from one parent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/alzheimerThree.png&quot; width=&quot;30%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The image models an amyloid-beta protein.&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lifespan.io/news/distinct-amyloid-beta-prion-strains/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; (Jeff Brender)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
However, the vast majority of Alzheimer’s cases are the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webmd.com/alzheimers/guide/alzheimers-types&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;late-onset&lt;/a&gt; type, which usually affects individuals over 65 years of age. Alzheimer’s late-onset condition is not usually inherited; instead, it is likely to be derived from a combination of genetic, environmental and lifestyle causes. It is believed that a mutation in a gene called ApoE raises the likelihood of a person developing late-onset Alzheimer’s, but does not cause it. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ghr.nlm.nih.gov/gene/APOE&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;NIH&lt;/a&gt;, ApoE affects how cholesterol flows through the blood. Research indicates that there is an increased risk of developing Alzheimer’s in people with elevated blood pressure and high cholesterol. Radiation, concussions, injuries and exposure to some contaminants are possible environmental factors.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, what is the cause of Alzheimer’s disease?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Headlines of revolutionary news have reverberated through the network in recent years- Alzheimer’s disease is not just a disease, it’s an infection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hypothesis that bacterial or viral infections could play a role in Alzheimer’s development was unpopularized until about a year ago. However, recently, as scientists have worked out potential pathways for how an infection could lead to the development of these irregular protein buildups in the brain, this concept has gained traction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers announced the discovery of &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Porphyromonas_gingivalis&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Porphyromonas gingivalis&lt;/a&gt; – the pathogen behind &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Chronic_periodontitis&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;chronic periodontitis&lt;/a&gt;, or gum disease – in the brains of deceased Alzheimer’s patients, in a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC6357742/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;paper&lt;/a&gt; led by senior author Jan Potempa, a microbiologist from the University of Louisville. Although experts are still trying to isolate the exact causes of this illness, a litany of papers argues that the deadly spread of Alzheimer’s goes far beyond what we used to think.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The report that spurred the headlines was published in the journal &lt;a href=&quot;https://dx.doi.org/10.1126/sciadv.aau3333&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Science Advances&lt;/a&gt;. It was reported that gum disease could be a cause of Alzheimer’s. It’s not the first time that the two variables have been &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/full/10.1111/j.1532-5415.2010.02788.x&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;related&lt;/a&gt;, but the researchers have gone further. Oral infection with the pathogen led to brain colonization by bacteria in separate experiments with mice, along with increased development of amyloid-beta (Aβ), a sticky protein usually associated with Alzheimer’s. Additionally, in the brains of Alzheimer’s patients, the team identified toxic enzymes called &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gingipain&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gingipains&lt;/a&gt; secreted by bacteria. But these tests were conducted after the patients have been deceased. In other words, although P. gingivalis and the disease have been related before, it has never been known whether gum disease causes Alzheimer’s, or whether dementia leads to poor oral treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/alzheimerFour.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;P. gingivalis' gingipains (red) are among neurons in the brain of a patient with Alzheimer's.&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencealert.com/new-evidence-reveals-an-unexpected-culprit-behind-alzheimer-s-disease&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; (Science Alert)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The researchers write &lt;a href=&quot;https://advances.sciencemag.org/content/5/1/eaau3333&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;in their paper&lt;/a&gt; that their discovery of gingipain antigens in the brains of people with  AD and also with AD pathology indicates that a P. gingivalis brain infection is not a consequence of late-stage disease, but rather an early occurrence. This may explain the pathology observed before cognitive impairment in middle-aged people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many experiments have been performed on mice looking at late-stage Alzheimer’s; some have been successful, some have not. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cortexyme.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Cortexyme&lt;/a&gt;, a clinical-stage biopharmaceutical company, is currently advancing its lead therapeutic candidate, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cortexyme.com/pipeline/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Atuzaginstat (COR388)&lt;/a&gt;, in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://gaintrial.com/en/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GAIN Trial&lt;/a&gt; (an ongoing Phase 2/3 clinical trial in patients with mild to moderate Alzheimer’s disease). In experiments with mice, COR388 showed that it could minimize the bacterial load of existing brain infection with P. gingivalis while also reducing the development of amyloid-beta and neuroinflammation (inflammation of the nervous tissue).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in humans, even the successful ones have failed. From 1998 to 2017, there were around 146 unsuccessful attempts to develop Alzheimer’s medications, and another half-dozen or so were &lt;a href=&quot;http://phrma-docs.phrma.org/files/dmfile/AlzheimersSetbacksSteppingStones_FINAL_digital.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;registered&lt;/a&gt; in 2018. A drug, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.alzforum.org/therapeutics/crenezumab&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Crenezumab&lt;/a&gt; seemed successful, but the interim review indicated that the drug was unlikely to reach the primary endpoint of the Clinical Dementia Rating-Sum of Boxes (CDR-SB) Score improvement from baseline. So the tests conducted in mice shouldn’t yet be considered as proof that it is a cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many scientists in this area expect that they will soon discover that the causes of Alzheimer’s are vast. While most medications that have been developed to target Alzheimer’s have failed early in clinical trials, there are still many trials underway, and more to come in the future. Scientists expect that they will soon discover that Alzheimer’s causes are many and believe that we are entering the golden age of Alzheimer’s research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So what can we do?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/aging/aginginfo/alzheimers.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Centers for Disease Control and Prevention&lt;/a&gt;, there is growing evidence that physical, mental and social behaviors decrease the likelihood of developing Alzheimer’s. The ability to reliably track memory and other cognitive functions in later life is a crucial factor in avoiding the onset of impairment of Alzheimer’s and other dementias. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cambridgecognition.com/products/digital-healthcare-technology/cantab-mobile/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CANTAB Mobile&lt;/a&gt; is a diagnostic software available to GPs that is easy to use to objectively test memory in older adults who are concerned about their risk of dementia. For now, individuals should lead a healthier lifestyle to lower their risk of contracting the disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gatesnotes.com/Health/The-unexpected-way-we-might-one-day-diagnose-Alzheimers&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Gates Notes)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Joan Joe&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Joan is a freshman in St. Antony’s Public School, India. She is intrigued by psychology and neuroscience and aspires to join research in neuroscience and STEM-related works. She hopes to help others pursue their passion for STEM through her platform. In her free time, she plays the piano, sings, and loves to read Dan Brown’s books.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Joan Joe</name></author><summary type="html">Could gum disease be the cause of Alzheimer’s disease? Joan Joe. 11/27/2020.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/alzheimerCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/alzheimerCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dark matter: The most influential mystery in the universe</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/27/dark-matter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dark matter: The most influential mystery in the universe" /><published>2020-11-27T16:00:02-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-27T16:00:02-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/27/dark-matter</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/27/dark-matter.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Dark matter: The most influential mystery in the universe&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Satyam Mehta. 11/27/2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/darkMatterOne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This is an AI-generated image of a dark matter map.
(Milennium-II Simulation / U.S. Department of Energy National Laboratory)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
One of the biggest and most influential mysteries in the universe is dark matter. Although a lot of people are probably familiar with the topic of dark matter itself, seldom do people understand its correlation to the universe. Dark matter affects the universe in ways that cannot be fully interpreted by scientists and astronomers on Earth. In fact, only five percent of the universe is occupied by normal matter, and the rest of it is occupied by dark matter and dark energy. Dark matter occupies 26 percent of the universe while dark energy (the force which results in the expansion of the universe) occupies 68 percent of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But now let us take a look at what dark matter is. Dark matter has not been defined yet, and cannot be defined until and unless its existence can be justified with 100% definitive proof. Although there are various pieces of evidence that support the existence of dark matter, its presence has not been verified. Until then, all that has been observed are glimpses of its properties. Some of the properties are as follows: dark matter interacts with normal matter only on a gravitational and weak level, does not emit or absorb light, and its particles move much slower than the speed of light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These are some of the basic properties that have been observed and dark matter is expected to have. Now, the question that arises is, why are we not able to detect dark matter? And how are we able to interpret the chance of its existence if we could not detect it? To address the first question, since dark matter cannot interact directly with light, it cannot interact with or be identified by electromagnetic radiation, which is the way normal matter is identified. Despite this, scientists have been able to theorize the presence of dark matter through the unknown additional mass discovered while evaluating the mass of a particular galaxy. One of the most significant theories is that dark matter is essential for binding a galaxy together. How? Dark matter exerts a gravitational force, which results in the attraction of matter towards it. Since there is so much dark matter in the universe, it helps in meshing galaxies together, like a giant spider web.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/darkMatterTwo.jpg&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;A global team of scientists finishes assembling a next-generation dark matter detector.
(Matt Kapust / Phys)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
But again, all of these are circumstantial theories put out by scientists, and nothing can be confirmed until the presence of dark matter is proven. Thankfully, we are getting closer and closer to finding the truth as technology advances. Scientists have identified particular hotspots in the universe where dark matter could be accumulated, and have termed these as dark matter maps. There are also dark matter labs made on Earth, which have been seated deep underground in order to collect the tiniest and most insignificant signals from the universe to help provide evidence of the existence of dark matter. People from all over the world are trying to piece this jigsaw together, and once it is complete, it may change the entire notion of the cosmos for us.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (New Atlas)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Satyam Mehta&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Satyam is a sharp class XI student with an entrepreneurial bent of mind. He is a kind, enthusiastic and compassionate self-starter with great innovative and leadership skills. He has initiated various social services such as Pravahkriti, a project aiming to promote better menstrual health and hygiene management among females of various ages. He has also started an initiative called Junkguards, which aims at proper and effective e-waste disposal. He has a passion for spreading awareness on various topics such as Financial literacy too.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Satyam Mehta</name></author><summary type="html">Dark matter: The most influential mystery in the universe Satyam Mehta. 11/27/2020.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/darkMatterCover.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/darkMatterCover.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Memories and the effects of time</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/27/memories-and-effects-of-time.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Memories and the effects of time" /><published>2020-11-27T16:00:02-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-27T16:00:02-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/27/memories-and-effects-of-time</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/27/memories-and-effects-of-time.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Memories and the effects of time&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tania Firouzabady. 11/27/2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/memoriesOne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This is an image of neuron activity in the brain. &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.mit.edu/2017/new-tool-offers-snapshots-neuron-activity-0626&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(MIT News)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Memories have been a subject of interest to scientists from an early age. In fact, the study of memories dates back over 2,000 years to Aristotle’s disquisition “On the Soul”, outlining the belief that humans are born without knowledge. Today, the study of memory is a part of the field of cognitive neuroscience, and the ways in which memories change over time are of particular interest to researchers. Understanding these concepts is vital to developments in research concerning the causes of memory loss, particularly with regards to Alzheimer’s disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1968, scientists Richard Atkinson and Richard Shiffrin created the Atkinson-Shiffrin memory model that introduced three general types of memory: sensory memory, short-term memory and long-term memory. Although alternate theories exist, this model has been the most widely used and accepted. Following these three types, there are three stages of memory processing: encoding, storage and retrieval, each playing a vital role in the overall structure of memories.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sensory memory is the first stage in memory storage and is responsible for retrieving physical and chemical stimuli from our surroundings. Examples of stimuli include visual, audible and tactile experiences. Every environmental stimulus triggers neuronal activities, transmitting the information to the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What allows these stimuli to be transformed into memories? According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://qbi.uq.edu.au/brain-basics/memory/how-are-memories-formed&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Queensland Brain Institute&lt;/a&gt;, the answer lies in synaptic plasticity, the process by which the strength of connections between brain cells—known as synapses—undergo changes. The frequency of activating the synapses controls their strength. And when a neuron is stimulated, it can begin an action potential, a change in the electrical potential of a neuron. If the cell’s membrane reaches the threshold potential, the signal is transmitted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, according to cognitive psychologist George Sperling, sensory memory has limited capacity and duration. In fact, the majority of stimuli are not strong enough to begin the encoding process necessary to turn an experience into a memory. But if the information does become sensory memory, it continues on to the second stage: short-term memory. Though longer than sensory memory, short-term memory only lasts 15 to 30 seconds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/memoriesTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This model provides a summary of the stages of memory. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.opentextbooks.org.hk/ditatopic/27122&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Open Textbooks of Hong Kong)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Short-term memory has been studied extensively in the past. In 1956, George Miller researched the capacity of short-term memory. He ran studies on how people respond to a variety of stimuli. In one trial, he presented each participant with 10 different sounds varying in pitch and had the participant respond to each pitch with a corresponding response previously learned. Miller summarized his studies in his paper “The Magical Number Seven, Plus or Minus Two”. He concluded that the majority of humans can process between five and nine units of information in their short-term memory. Miller’s theory provides great insight into the limited nature of memory, helping explain why people have such difficulty remembering large amounts of information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although short-term memory is significantly limited, long-term memory has the potential to store an unlimited amount of information for one’s entire life. Scientist Alice Preston of the University of Texas explained how the passage of time is required for short-term memory to become long-term memory. Time allows the memory to become resistant to other stimuli that may be competing to be turned into long-term memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition, Preston detailed that molecular changes alter the structure of neurons. Although these changes also occur for sensory and short-term memory, they take much longer for information that needs to be converted to long-term memory (sometimes taking years). Ironically, time, the factor responsible for preserving memories, is also the factor that can cause memory loss. As outlined by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3898682/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Center for Biotechnology Information&lt;/a&gt;, a study performed by Holger Jahn on “Memory loss in Alzheimer’s disease” explores the relationship between memories and Alzheimer’s disease, focusing on the factors that influence this loss of memory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is vital to note that the termination of synapses is a major contributor to memory loss. During this discussion, Jahn scripts, “Variations in the genes encoding the amyloid precursor proteins, presenilin-1 and presenilin-2, can directly cause Alzheimer’s disease.” Presenilin 1 is responsible for cleaving other proteins into peptides, a process called proteolysis. Hence, when these variations occur, the presenilin proteins stop functioning, resulting in an inability to digest certain proteins, particularly the amyloid β-peptide. This ultimately leads to an increase in the vulnerability of the brain, contributing to the early phases of Alzheimer’s disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/memoriesThree.jpg&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This image compares the brain of a healthy individual with the brain of a patient with atrophy as a result of Alzheimer’s disease. (Research Gate)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Jahn also notes, “The neuropathological hallmarks of the atrophy process in AD are the presence of senile plaques (amyloid deposits) and neurofibrillary tangles in autopsied brains.” Senile plaques and neurofibrillary tangles are natural components of the brain, but large numbers of them are a characteristic of Alzheimer’s disease.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Neurofibrillary tangles block the neuron transport system, impairing connectivity and communication between brain cells through synapses. As mentioned previously, these connections are vital to memory storage, illustrating the consequences of the buildup of neurofibrillary tangles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the exact nature of such atrophy is not completely understood, a variety of factors may be at play. Common causes of Alzheimer’s disease include age, genetics and environmental factors, depending on the individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the uncertainty over its cause, it is evident that memories are a fundamental component of Alzheimer’s disease. Evidently, further research is required for advancements to be made in this field. Memory loss impacts the world we live in and can bring many difficulties to people’s lives in the form of Alzheimer’s disease. Thus, scientists and researchers must continue to study the nature of memory loss and ways to prevent it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;http://brain.harvard.edu/hbi_events/brain-computer-interfaces/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Harvard Brain Science Initiative)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Tania Firouzabady&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Tania Firouzabady</name></author><summary type="html">Memories and the effects of time Tania Firouzabady. 11/27/2020.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/memoriesCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/memoriesCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Artificial neurons to cure chronic disease</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/27/artificial-neurons.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Artificial neurons to cure chronic disease" /><published>2020-11-27T16:00:01-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-27T16:00:01-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/27/artificial-neurons</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/27/artificial-neurons.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Artificial neurons to cure chronic disease&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;/blog/translations/artificial-neurons-in-spanish&quot;&gt;&lt;i&gt;Oprima aquí para leerlo en inglés.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Valeria Rivadeneyra. 11/27/2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/artificialNeuronsOne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This image shows the silicon chip and how small it is compared to a coin. (University of Bath)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Neurons are an essential part of our nervous systems and bodies. Imitating a neuron is a difficult task; however, thanks to science, it has become a reality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.dailymail.co.uk/sciencetech/article-7751179/Artificial-neurons-help-cure-number-chronic-diseases.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;neuron or a nerve cell&lt;/a&gt; is an electrically excitable cell that develops different processes and transmits information through electrical and chemical signals. It is essential for the functionality of the nervous system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists from the University of Bath have created a first-of-its-kind artificial neuron on a silicon chip that behaves like a real biological neuron. The discovery was published on Dec. 3, 2019, in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41467-019-13177-3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nature Communications&lt;/a&gt;, introducing a technology that seeks to cure chronic diseases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers used large-scale electrophysiological recording data to understand the activity of neurons so that they could successfully model their behavior on a silicon chip. Incredibly, the silicon neurons can mimic the activity of individual ion channels on neurons, and so far, they’ve created silicon mimics of respiratory and hippocampal neurons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The artificial neurons receive electrical signals from healthy cells and relay them to neurons in other muscles and organs in a person’s body. It sounds easy, but on the contrary, creating artificial neurons was a challenging task because it was difficult to predict how neurons would respond. “Until now neurons have been like black boxes, but we have managed to open the black box and peer inside. Our work is paradigm-changing because it provides a robust method to reproduce the electrical properties of real neurons in minute detail,” physicist Alain Nogaret from the University of Bath said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These artificial neurons are ideal for use in medical implants and other bioelectric devices. “Our neurons only need &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bath.ac.uk/announcements/world-first-as-artificial-neurons-developed-to-cure-chronic-diseases/#:~:text=Artificial%20neurons%20on%20silicon%20chips,other%20diseases%20of%20neuronal%20degeneration.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;140 nanoWatts of power&lt;/a&gt;. That’s a billionth the power requirement of a microprocessor, which other attempts to make synthetic neurons have used,” explained Nogaret. This discovery opens up the chance to cure conditions where neurons are not working properly or have died, and thus is extremely beneficial to those with chronic diseases. For example, these artificial neurons can be used to replace damaged neurons in spinal cord injuries or dysfunctional neurons in the brain that fail to send the correct signals to the heart in cases of heart failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This study is an exciting development that opens up many opportunities in the biomedical field. This includes opportunities for smarter medical devices that allow for personalized treatments over a range of different diseases and disabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In fact artificial neurons could theoretically be integrated into biological systems and allow scientists to replace our damaged nerve cell. Being able to use the device to restore function to paralyse patients or heal brain damage, would be an exceptional advancement in medicine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the potential for treating neurological disorders is incredibly exciting, artificial neurons may even &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencealert.com/scientists-build-an-artificial-neuron-that-fully-mimics-a-human-brain-cell&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;supplement our mental abilities by adding memory storage or offer faster processing in our brain&lt;/a&gt; in the foreseeable future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, in heart failure, loss of coupling in the brain and nervous system results in incorrect signaling to the heart, leading to heart malfunction. “We’re developing smart pacemakers that won’t just stimulate the heart to pump at a steady rate but use these neurons to respond in real-time to demands placed on the heart - which is what happens naturally in a healthy heart,” Nogaret said.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it seemed impossible a few years back, this great discovery has helped many people around the world overcome diseases and disabilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (ComputerHoy)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Valeria Rivadeneyra &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Valeria is a sophomore in Peru. She loves STEM-related topics, so she plans to study industrial engineering in the future. In her free time, she likes watching series on Netflix and talking with her friends about anything.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Valeria Rivadeneyra</name></author><summary type="html">Artificial neurons to cure chronic disease Oprima aquí para leerlo en inglés. Valeria Rivadeneyra. 11/27/2020.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/artificialNeuronsCover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/artificialNeuronsCover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dispelling common myths about epilepsy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/19/myths-about-epilepsy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dispelling common myths about epilepsy" /><published>2020-11-19T16:00:02-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-19T16:00:02-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/19/myths-about-epilepsy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/19/myths-about-epilepsy.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Dispelling common myths about epilepsy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emily Richter. 11/20/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/epilepsyOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Despite the fact that many people have heard of it before, epilepsy is one of the most misunderstood neurological disorders. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/epilepsy/about/index.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(CDC)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Epilepsy. Everyone has heard of it, but few have a complete understanding of what this neurological disorder entails. November is Epilepsy Awareness Month, so let’s examine and dispel some of the most common myths about the brain disorder that shows itself mainly through seizures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Myth #1&lt;/b&gt;: Very few people have epilepsy.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Truth&lt;/b&gt;: The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/epilepsy/data/index.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Center for Disease Control&lt;/a&gt; (CDC) notes that there are 3.4 million people in the United States currently living with an epilepsy diagnosis. This is about 1.2% of the population of the United States and is equivalent to the population of Uruguay. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epilepsy.com/learn/about-epilepsy-basics/who-gets-epilepsy&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Epilepsy Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, more than 65 million people worldwide lived with epilepsy as of 2014, and that number continues to grow as hundreds of thousands of people are diagnosed each year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Myth #2&lt;/b&gt;: There is only one type of epilepsy.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Truth&lt;/b&gt;: The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epilepsy.com/learn/types-epilepsy-syndromes&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Epilepsy Foundation&lt;/a&gt; currently recognizes 26 different types of epilepsy. Some types are more severe than others, and many types of epilepsy that appear in children are temporary. The International League Against Epilepsy reclassifies types of epilepsy almost every year, so the number of recognized epilepsy types changes often.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Myth #3&lt;/b&gt;: All seizures are the same.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Truth&lt;/b&gt;: According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epilepsy.com/learn/types-seizures&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Epilepsy Foundation&lt;/a&gt;, there are dozens of different types of seizures. They can be classified into two categories: generalized onset seizures and focal onset seizures. Generalized onset seizures affect both halves of the brain, while focal onset seizures only affect one. When most people think of seizures, they think of generalized onset tonic-clonic seizures. These are the types of seizures that usually involve shaking and muscle spasms. However, some seizures involve completely different symptoms. Some focal seizures result in a complete loss of movement and awareness, and no muscle spasms are involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Myth #4&lt;/b&gt;: Seizures are always a sign of epilepsy.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Truth&lt;/b&gt;: Although many seizures do happen because of epilepsy, not all seizures are caused by epilepsy. Seizures can sometimes be a sign of a brain tumor, stroke or nutrition deficiency. Seizures can also be a side effect of many medications. Anyone who has experienced a seizure should seek medical advice to find out why the seizure happened and how future seizures could be avoided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Myth #5&lt;/b&gt;: Biological children of parents with epilepsy will have epilepsy as well.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Truth&lt;/b&gt;: Epilepsy can either be genetically inherited or caused by a form of brain trauma. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://health.clevelandclinic.org/13-common-epilepsy-myths-debunked/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Cleveland Clinic&lt;/a&gt;, genetically inherited epilepsy “usually involves a combination of multiple gene defects”. The chance of a child inheriting all of these gene defects is extremely low. People controlling epilepsy with medication usually have to talk to a doctor or specialist before having their own biological children, not because of the possibility of their child inheriting epilepsy but because epilepsy medications often increase the risk of birth defects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Myth #6&lt;/b&gt;: People with epilepsy will have a seizure if exposed to flashing lights.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Truth&lt;/b&gt;: Seizures can be triggered by many different things. For some people with epilepsy, flashing lights really do trigger seizures. For others, lack of sleep, hyperventilation or many other internal or external factors can trigger a seizure. People with epilepsy have to know what triggers their seizures in order to prevent themselves from having a seizure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Myth #7&lt;/b&gt;: Epilepsy is a mental disability.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Truth&lt;/b&gt;: Epilepsy is a neurological disorder, but because it causes seizures, it is often classified as a physical disorder or disability. Different countries and different states choose to classify epilepsy differently. In the United States, individuals with epilepsy are classified as disabled and protected under the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.eeoc.gov/laws/guidance/epilepsy-workplace-and-ada&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Americans with Disabilities Act&lt;/a&gt; (ADA), which mostly serves to protect them from discrimination in the workplace. The United States military does not have to follow the rules outlined in the ADA, so individuals with epilepsy cannot serve the United States in the armed forces. Epilepsy can also be a major problem when it comes to healthcare. Many independent healthcare providers will charge people with epilepsy more money for their coverage because people with epilepsy often have higher medical costs due to expensive treatment and the constant doctor and neurologist visits. In specific cases, people with epilepsy can collect government-issued disability checks to help with their medical costs, though not all epilepsy patients qualify for these programs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Myth #8&lt;/b&gt;: Epilepsy cannot be controlled.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Truth&lt;/b&gt;: Epilepsy can often be effectively controlled with medication or brain surgery. Sometimes these methods do not completely eradicate epilepsy, but they often suppress it well. Many epilepsy medications for severe forms of epilepsy have serious side-effects, but unlike severe epilepsy, these side-effects can be managed by changes in lifestyle. Epilepsy medications for less-severe forms of epilepsy can have serious side-effects, but it is less common. Brain surgery, which is commonly used on patients who develop epilepsy as a result of brain trauma, can sometimes be effective for certain types of epilepsy. New medications and surgeries for epilepsy are being discovered and tested every day. Although many people have epilepsy, there was minimal research on the condition until the late twentieth century.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://health.clevelandclinic.org/13-common-epilepsy-myths-debunked/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Cleveland Clinic)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Emily Richter&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Emily is a junior from Maria Carrillo High School in Sonoma County. She loves chemistry and the environmental sciences and plans to be an environmental chemist when she gets older. Through InterSTEM, she hopes to combine her experience in writing with her interest in STEM in order to help others enjoy and understand STEM. In her free time, she likes playing the flute, and baking and cooking.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Emily Richter</name></author><summary type="html">Dispelling common myths about epilepsy Emily Richter. 11/20/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/epilepsyCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/epilepsyCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">2020 Nobel Prize in Physics: Black holes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/19/nobel-prize-in-physics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="2020 Nobel Prize in Physics: Black holes" /><published>2020-11-19T16:00:02-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-19T16:00:02-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/19/nobel-prize-in-physics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/19/nobel-prize-in-physics.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;2020 Nobel Prize in Physics: Black holes&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ana Monsalud. 11/20/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/novelPrizeOne.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The 2020 Nobel Prize in Physics was awarded to astrophysicists Roger Penrose Reinhard Genzel and Andrea Ghez. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Niklas Elmehed / Nobel Media)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
On Oct. 6th, 2020, the Royal Swedish Academy of Sciences &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/physics/2020/summary/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;announced the recipients of the Nobel Prize in Physics&lt;/a&gt;. The English physicist Roger Penrose received half the prize “for the discovery that black hole formation is a robust prediction of the general theory of relativity.” The other half of the prize was divided between German astrophysicist Reinhard Genzel and American astronomer Andrea Ghez “for the discovery of a supermassive compact object at the centre of our galaxy.” Their work provides a deeper understanding of the least understood phenomena in the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Roger Penrose&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;In 1915, Albert Einstein presented his theory of general relativity. He explained that gravity wasn’t an invisible force but an effect of the fabric of spacetime. And depending on the mass of an object, that object warps the fabric of spacetime to a different degree. The effect is similar to if four people held up the corners of a blanket and placed an object, like a basketball, onto the blanket. The basketball rolls to the middle and significantly warps the blanket, whereas an object like a golf ball would barely make an indent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black holes form when enough matter is compacted into a small amount of space and creates an area of space with a gravitational pull strong enough to prevent light from escaping. Most black holes form when massive stars die and collapse into themselves. Interestingly enough, Einstein &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalgeographic.com/magazine/2014/03/black-holes-einstein-star-eaters/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;didn’t believe that black holes existed&lt;/a&gt; because he thought the idea seemed too outlandish. But in 1965, ten years after Einstein’s death, Penrose claimed that black holes were a natural consequence of Einstein’s theory of relativity. Plus, he had the evidence to prove it. In a paper titled “Gravitational Collapse and Space-Time Singularities,” he proved “&lt;a href=&quot;https://astrobites.org/2020/10/15/the-nobel-prize-in-physics-2020-roger-penrose/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a star of sufficient mass [would] always collapse into a black hole.&lt;/a&gt;”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/novelPrizeTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The image provides visualization of how objects with different masses warp spacetime according to Einstein’s theory of general relativity.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://astronomytopicoftheday.wordpress.com/2015/11/25/november-25th-centenary-for-einsteins-general-theory-of-relativity/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Astronomy Topic of the Day)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Using mathematical proofs and new methods that he invented, Penrose demonstrated how the collapse into a black hole was inevitable within our understanding of Einstein’s theory of general relativity. One example of his revolutionary ideas was his introduction to the complicated idea of conformal transformations. The idea of conformal transformations leads to Penrose diagrams that depict the circumstances under which a star collapses into a black hole. Penrose not only described in fine detail what happens during the formation of a black hole but also how &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/physics/2020/press-release/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;all the known laws of nature cease&lt;/a&gt; within black holes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/novelPrizeThree.png&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;A Penrose diagram of a star’s collapse into a black hole.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/physics/2020/advanced-information/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(The Nobel Prize)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Reinhard Genzel and Andrea Ghez&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;For over twenty years, Dr. Genzel and Dr. Ghez have led teams observing the behavior of stars surrounding the radio source at the center of the Milky Way known as Sagittarius A*. They concluded that the only possible explanation for the narrow orbit paths of the stars in the vicinity of Sagittarius A* was the existence of a supermassive black hole at the center of the galaxy.
Two separate observational teams led by Genzel and Ghez have observed stars orbiting the center of the milky way since the early 1990s. By mapping the paths of these stars, both teams found that the stars surrounding Sagittarius A* moved at astonishing speeds. These stars moved at a speed of &lt;a href=&quot;https://100.ucla.edu/timeline/supermassive-black-hole-discovery&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;12,000km per second&lt;/a&gt;, a number which doesn’t even compare to theEarth’s speed of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/how-fast-is-the-earth-mov/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;460km per second&lt;/a&gt;. Although Sagittarius A* is unobservable directly, the current theory of gravity shows that the only explanation for these heavy stars orbiting at such fast speeds is a supermassive black hole.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/novelPrizeFour.png&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;NASA’s Chandra X-ray Observatory observed the supermassive black hole Sagittarius A*. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/chandra/multimedia/black-hole-SagittariusA.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(NASA)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The mass of black holes is referred to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/vision/universe/starsgalaxies/Black_Hole.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;in units of solar masses&lt;/a&gt;. A solar mass is equal to the weight of the sun, which is a value of about 2 x 10^30 kilograms. Typical black holes are incredibly heavy with a mass of three to ten solar masses. However, supermassive black holes are even heavier. They can have a mass ranging from millions to even billions of solar masses. The black hole at the center of the universe is quite conservative compared to those possibilities, as observations reveal that Sagittarius A* would need &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/10/06/science/nobel-prize-physics.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a mass of four million solar masses&lt;/a&gt; to create the orbital patterns of surrounding celestial bodies. The conclusions made by Dr. Genzel and Dr. Ghez provide the best evidence so far of a supermassive black hole at the heart of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Conclusion&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Thanks to the dedication of these three astrophysicists and their contributions, scientists have a stronger base for speculation and research on black holes. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/physics/2020/press-release/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Nobel Prize&lt;/a&gt;, Penrose’s discovery is “still regarded as the most important contribution to the general theory of relativity since Einstein.” The conclusion drawn by Genzel and Ghez’s research is the clearest evidence of both a black hole at the center of the Milky Way and the effect of black holes on the masses in their close vicinity. Ghez is also the fourth woman to receive a Nobel Prize in Physics, a title that she is proud to embrace. Ghez, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnn.com/videos/world/2020/10/07/amanpour-nobel-physics-black-hole-andrea-ghez.cnn&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;who takes great pride in her ability to be a role model for young women&lt;/a&gt;, hopes that she can help inspire the next generation of female scientists to work in a male-dominated field. These groundbreaking discoveries helped improve people’s understanding of black holes and will lead to more discoveries in the near future. In the words of Ghez, “We’re just in the beginning.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencenews.org/article/newfound-black-hole-milky-way-is-weirdly-heavy&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Science News)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Ana Monsalud&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Ana is a junior from Cambridge Virtual Academy who is a huge nerd for pretty much everything related to math and science. Through InterSTEM, she hopes to inspire others with her same love for learning and curiosity about the world. In the future, she hopes to pursue a career in healthcare and contribute to change in her community.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ana Monsalud</name></author><summary type="html">2020 Nobel Prize in Physics: Black holes Ana Monsalud. 11/20/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/novelPrizeCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/novelPrizeCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mapping the human genome</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/12/mapping-human-genome.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mapping the human genome" /><published>2020-11-12T16:00:05-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-12T16:00:05-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/12/mapping-human-genome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/12/mapping-human-genome.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Mapping the human genome&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reagan Smith. 11/13/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/mappingHumanGenomeOne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Scientists undertook a massive project in the 90s: mapping the entire human genome.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.genome.gov/human-genome-project&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(National Human Genome Research Institute)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
On Oct. 1, 1990, scientists undertook one of the most significant explorations of the universe to this date. Instead of aiming upwards at the stars, researchers looked into our cells and began the arduous process of mapping the entire human genome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project took a total of thirteen years to complete and was first outlined by the National Academy of Sciences. Later, the National Institutes of Health and the Department of Energy collaborated to create a detailed outline for the project, which was funded by Congress. With James Watson at the helm of the NIH branch, which was renamed the National Center for Human Genome Research, the project was soon underway. The seven areas the project looked into were Mapping and Sequencing the Genome, Mapping and Sequencing the Genomes of Model Organisms, Data Collection and Distribution, Ethical, Legal, and Social Considerations, Research Training, Technology Development and Technology Transfer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists looked at the genomes of both homo sapiens and a set of model organisms to compare the functions and purpose of the human genome, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.genome.gov/human-genome-project/What&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Understanding Our Genetic Inheritance, The First Five Years&lt;/a&gt;. The data they acquired would be used to treat genetic diseases, and the specific technology they developed could be applied to other fields of science in agriculture and environmental science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.genome.gov/human-genome-project/What&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The National Human Genome Research Institute&lt;/a&gt; (NHGRI) reports that researchers successfully determined the sequence of every single base of DNA in the human genome, made maps showing the locations of various genes in the chromosomes and created linkage maps (maps that track inherited traits over generations). Human genome researchers sequenced a total of 3 billion DNA letters, covering about 99% of the portion of the human genome that contains genes, with 99.99% accuracy. They also mapped the genomes of E. coli, S. cerevisiae, C. elegans, D. melanogaster, C. briggsae, D. pseudoobscura, mouse and rat organisms, putting their findings into context amongst other organisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/mappingHumanGenomeTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This is a mapped sequence of the E. coli DNA. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/figure/Insertion-of-the-reporter-cassette-into-the-E-coli-K-12-MG1655-genome-The-chromosome_fig6_265558006&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(ResearchGate)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
According to an article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/scitable/topicpage/dna-sequencing-technologies-key-to-the-human-828/#:~:text=The%20shotgun%20phase%20of%20the,and%20establish%20a%20contiguous%20sequence&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Scitable&lt;/a&gt;, the process of sequencing the DNA began with creating genetic clones of separate human chromosomes using ligated (individually cut) DNA segments bonded to chromosome vectors. The vector-segment combos were then placed into bacteria to reproduce and form colonies. The DNA fragments were separated from the bacterial organisms and placed into agarose (a sugar-based gel substance), in which the fragments’ size could be measured by gel electrophoresis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november//mappingHumanGenomeThree.png&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Gel electrophoresis of three separate DNA segments is visible in agarose gel.
(Wikipedia)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Francis Collins, the director of the NHGRI in February of 2001, stated that the genome is “a history book– a narrative of the journey of our species through time. It’s a shop manual, with an incredibly detailed blueprint for building every human cell. And it’s a transformative textbook of medicine, with insights that will give health care providers immense new powers to treat, prevent and cure disease.” His view of the project dictates its significance in today’s world of medicine and science, and having this large bank of data increases efficiency and progress in other related undertakings. Scientists have a better understanding of what makes humans look and act the way they do, and they are able to utilize this information to better treat and prevent diseases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;http://sitn.hms.harvard.edu/flash/2019/lessons-from-the-human-genome-project/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Harvard University)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/Reagan_Smith.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Reagan Smith&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Reagan is a junior from Sage Hill School. She is passionate about all things related to science, especially biology and medicine. She also loves being able to use her talents and knowledge to help others and make a difference in the world.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Reagan Smith</name></author><summary type="html">Mapping the human genome Reagan Smith. 11/13/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/mappingHumanGenomeCover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/mappingHumanGenomeCover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Left and right-brained characteristics and striving for dominance</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/12/left-and-right-brain.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Left and right-brained characteristics and striving for dominance" /><published>2020-11-12T16:00:04-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-12T16:00:04-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/12/left-and-right-brain</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/12/left-and-right-brain.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Left and right-brained characteristics and striving for dominance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joan Joe. 11/13/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/leftRightBrainOne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The graphic above depicts the left and right-brained characteristics.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aliexpress.com/item/32493963509.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(AliExpress)&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you are like me, we belong to the 90 percent of the world’s population of right-handed people. This is in fact genetically determined although it isn’t clear why our evolution has led to more righties than lefties. It is a major belief that lefties and righties are right and left brained respectively. According to a new research, the idea of people being either left or right brained may not be as fixed as we thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a widely acknowledged fact that most animals have an anatomically and functionally asymmetric brain. While some of the differences are learned others are inherited.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It may be a random assignment of which side of the brain is dominant but a spectrum of possibilities that are available indicates that there might be something more than just randomness working.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studies conducted on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2729063/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;zebrafish embryos&lt;/a&gt; about their developing brain suggest that there might be a fight of dominance between the hemispheres. Researchers have known that neurons migrate long distances in a developing brain. It is controlled by a gene called fibroblast growth factor 8 (FGF8). It creates a protein and the protein acts as a magnet to attract nerve cells to one hemisphere of the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The absolute differences in the number of cells are very less but what differ are the types of neurons on left and right and in their connections. Both sides of the brain contain FGF8, leading to a tug-of-war to attract certain migrating nerve cells. But this is an unfair fight. FGF8 in the left-brain as an ally, another protein, called Nodal, is present only on the left side of the brain. When it teams up with FGF8, the pair wins, causing a predictable pattern of neuron connections in the left hemisphere that helps to explain why there is consistent handedness between individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/leftRightBrainTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;FGF8 Protein &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/FGF8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Wikipedia)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The decision to become right-brained or left-brained is due to a competition between the two sides of the brain. If the competition was fair and equal, then half the population would be left-brained and half would be right-brained. However there are signals on the left side of the brain that give it an advantage so in most cases it wins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of the right handers process language in their left hemisphere. At the same time many of the left handed people also have the language proficiency localized to the left. Some people throw a ball right-handed but write with the left. Others have a certain preference for which arm goes on top when folded. Others have a dominant eye.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some of these asymmetries might be genetically determined, some may be reinforced by behavior and some might be randomly assigned based on one or more tug-of-war battles between the two sides of the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In theory the people being left or right brained is just an indication of which side of their brain is more dominant. This theory became known thanks to the psychobiologist and Nobel Prize winner Roger W. Sperry in the 1960s. The left brain is more analytical, verbal, logical and orderly than the right brain. The right brained thinkers are known to be more creative free thinkers. The left brained people may give more attention to details and rule by logic. There’s a long-standing myth, related to Rocky Balboa’s heroics in the ring, that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.livescience.com/655-lefty-myths-mysteries-persist.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;left-handers&lt;/a&gt; (who have always made up 10 to 12 percent of the human population) are better fighters. True or not, handedness might be tied to a war of sorts, in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is true that some of the functions reside on one part of the brain more than others. Damage to the front part of the brain is linked with reduced motivation, difficulty planning, and impaired creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, the back of the brain (the occipital cortex) integrates visual information from the eye. Damage to this area can cause partial or complete blindness. These are just a few examples of how certain parts of the brain appear responsible for specific functions. Much of our knowledge in this area comes from the study of so-called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/science/split-brain-syndrome&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;split brain&lt;/a&gt; patients. So, location does matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/leftRightBrainThree.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;An Evaluation of the Left-Brain vs. Right-Brain Hypothesis with Resting State Functional Connectivity Magnetic Resonance Imaging.
The above image shows that there is functional asymmetry in the brain. This &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0071275#abstract0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;test&lt;/a&gt; was conducted with 1011 individuals between the ages of 7 and 29 at resting state under researchers from Beijing Normal University, China.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
But for individual creativity there has been little or no evidence that dominance plays a role. In fact if you take an &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0071275&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;MRI scan&lt;/a&gt;, a CT scan, etc of a mathematician and an artist, it is very unlikely that you would find much difference. Math, for example, requires logical thought and, thus, is generally said to reside in the left brain, far away from all those artsy right-brain abilities. But mathematics is a profoundly creative endeavor in addition to being a logical one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why is this myth popular? It may be because it gives us a scientific way to talk about our favorite subjects – ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Joan Joe&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Joan is a freshman in St. Antony’s Public School, India. She is intrigued by psychology and neuroscience and aspires to join research in neuroscience and STEM-related works. She hopes to help others pursue their passion for STEM through her platform. In her free time, she plays the piano, sings, and loves to read Dan Brown’s books.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Joan Joe</name></author><summary type="html">Left and right-brained characteristics and striving for dominance Joan Joe. 11/13/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/leftRightBrainCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/leftRightBrainCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Gene editing and the future of human evolution</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/gene-editing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gene editing and the future of human evolution" /><published>2020-11-06T16:00:04-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-06T16:00:04-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/gene-editing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/gene-editing.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Gene editing and the future of human evolution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simone Rothaupt. 11/07/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/geneEditingOne.png&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Gene editing with CRISPR technology will revolutionize human evolution and cure countless diseases. (Adobe Stock / Andriano_cz)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Over the course of millions of years, homo sapiens have evolved into the dominant organism across the globe because humans are the only animals capable of working flexibly and creatively in large groups, according to bestselling author and doctoral graduate from the University of Oxford &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/transcripts/468882620&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Yuval Harari&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though we have developed such advanced cognitive function and physical abilities, scientists like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencealert.com/are-humans-still-evolving#:~:text=Evolution%20can't%20be%20stopped,natural%20selection%20is%20always%20happening.&amp;amp;text=Humans%20are%20still%20evolving%2C%20and,to%20change%20in%20the%20future.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dr. Alywyn Scally&lt;/a&gt; of the University of Cambridge assert humans are still evolving. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/05/humans-are-still-evolving-and-we-can-watch-it-happen&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Scientists from Stanford University&lt;/a&gt; revealed, using data from 3,000 genomes collected across the United Kingdom, that height, head circumference in infants and hip size in females (factors relevant to birth) have undergone selection in the past 2,000 years. In another study by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/05/humans-are-still-evolving-and-we-can-watch-it-happen&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Stanford University&lt;/a&gt;, researchers found that traits like lactose intolerance and blond hair and blue eyes have spread rapidly in the past 2,000 years. An &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.2002458&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;investigation&lt;/a&gt; by evolutionary geneticists Joseph Pickrell and others claims that the ApoE4 allele, which is connected to Alzheimer’s disease, has dropped in frequency over time as carriers die earlier on in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the traditional methods of evolution, humans have now finally harnessed a technique known as gene editing, which controls life down to the genetic level void of natural influence. The most familiar version of gene editing, known as clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeats-associated protein 9 (CRISPR-Cas9), utilizes a naturally-occurring bacterial complex. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.genome.gov/about-genomics/policy-issues/Genome-Editing/How-genome-editing-works&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Human Genome Research Institute&lt;/a&gt; explains that bacteria creates CRISPR arrays, or DNA snippets, from segments of an invading virus’ DNA, allowing for the bacteria to form RNA segments to recognize the same virus if it returns. Once the virus is located, the Cas9 enzyme is used to cut the virus’ DNA apart to destroy it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For human application, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://medlineplus.gov/genetics/understanding/genomicresearch/genomeediting/#:~:text=Genome%20editing%20(also%20called%20gene,to%20change%20an%20organism's%20DNA.&amp;amp;text=The%20bacteria%20then%20use%20Cas9,works%20similarly%20in%20the%20lab.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;US National Library of Medicine&lt;/a&gt; states that scientists create, with CRISPR-Cas9, an RNA segment that can be used to recognize the part of DNA that needs to be edited. Once the correct DNA location is found, the Cas9 enzyme cuts the DNA, and the cell’s built-in methods for repairing damaged DNA, such as base repair excision, are manipulated to customize the sequence. The Cpf 1, CasX, Cas Y, and other enzymes are also used for cutting DNA as they can be more precise and accurate. Though other gene-editing methods exist such as homologous recombination and zinc-finger nucleases (ZFN), CRISPR-Cas9 has become the most popular as it is more accurate, efficient, cheaper and faster than most alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cancer.gov/news-events/cancer-currents-blog/2020/crispr-cancer-research-treatment&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Cancer Institute&lt;/a&gt;, gene editing has the potential to cure genetic diseases such as sickle cell, Huntington’s, and even cancer. &lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5642755/crispr-gene-editing-humans/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Time&lt;/a&gt; reported that Editas Medicine and Allergan, both prominent pharmaceutical companies, are working on testing CRISPR-Cas9 for congenital vision diseases, such as Leber congenital amaurosis 10. Similarly, Vertex Pharmaceuticals and CRISPR Therapeutics are attempting to utilize gene editing for curing blood diseases, such as beta thalassemia and sickle cell anemia. For the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ir.editasmedicine.com/news-releases/news-release-details/allergan-and-editas-medicine-announce-dosing-first-patient#:~:text=AGN%2D151587%20(EDIT%2D101)%20is%20an%20experimental%20medicine,protein%20290%20(CEP290)%20gene.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Allergan and Editas Medicine&lt;/a&gt; Leber congenital amaurosis 10 treatment study, a single mutation in the centrosomal protein 290 gene can be removed through CRISPR technology so that photoreceptor cells can detect light properly. For the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ir.crisprtx.com/news-releases/news-release-details/crispr-therapeutics-and-vertex-announce-progress-clinical&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CRISPR Therapeutics and Vertex&lt;/a&gt; beta thalassemia study, diseased bone marrow cells will be replaced with stem cells altered with CRISPR technology to turn on fetal hemoglobin production as the adult hemoglobin production genes for patients of this disease do not function properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2019/dec/08/gene-editing-will-let-us-control-our-very-evolution-we-must-use-it-wisely&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Guardian&lt;/a&gt; proposes that humans will now evolve more rapidly and in more ways than ever before. Changes to the human genome will no longer occur across thousands of years, but in a single lifetime. Previously, the selection of a single gene was considered a massive shift in evolution, but with gene editing, thousands of genes can quickly be altered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though it appears that the potential for gene editing is limitless, debates loom large in this field. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-00673-1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nature Research&lt;/a&gt; warns that scientists must be extremely careful when choosing genes to alter as genes can have three to four unrelated functions. This means that removing a gene could have unintended and often unpredictable consequences, such as a weakened protection against lungs, liver and brain diseases. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.genome.gov/about-genomics/policy-issues/Genome-Editing/ethical-concerns&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Human Genome Research Institute&lt;/a&gt;, the field of gene manipulation is filled with controversy, such as fears that only the wealthy will have access to genome editing, as well as moral and religious objections to the testing of human embryos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though CRISPR-Cas9 can cure countless diseases, the threat of unethical misuse has prevented the rapid adoption of this novel technology. For the first time, an organism will be able to dictate its own evolution, and gene editing will hopefully be able to change the world for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (iStockphoto / Vitaliy Smolygin)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Simone Rothaupt&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Simone is a sophomore at Thousand Oaks High School in Ventura, California. She is interested in exploring STEM related topics, such as medicine, and she also hopes to spread this passion to others through writing.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Simone Rothaupt</name></author><summary type="html">Gene editing and the future of human evolution Simone Rothaupt. 11/07/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/geneEditingCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/geneEditingCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Fermi paradox: Possibilities of extraterrestrial life</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/fermi-paradox.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Fermi paradox: Possibilities of extraterrestrial life" /><published>2020-11-06T16:00:03-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-06T16:00:03-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/fermi-paradox</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/fermi-paradox.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The Fermi paradox: Possibilities of extraterrestrial life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ana Monsalud. 11/07/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/fermiParadoxOne.png&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Mars 2020 Mission will land in the Jezero Crater on Mars, which contains an ancient delta system where NASA scientists are hoping to find evidence of ancient life. &lt;a href=&quot;https://planetaria.ca/2018/12/15/high-res-view-of-mars-2020-landing-site-jezero-crater/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Planetaria)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.esa.int/Science_Exploration/Space_Science/Herschel/How_many_stars_are_there_in_the_Universe&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;tens of billions of galaxies&lt;/a&gt; in our observable universe, each containing millions of stars. Scientists estimate that each star has an average of about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/startswithabang/2018/03/13/space-is-full-of-planets-and-most-of-them-dont-even-have-stars/?sh=4ce74893b2a1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ten planets&lt;/a&gt;, an approximation calculated just from the planets that have survived throughout the 4.5 billion years of our universe’s existence. With hundreds of billions of planets, is it really possible that humans are alone in the universe?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even before there was concrete evidence that could quantify the size of the universe, it was clear how vast it was. Scholars were already incredibly fascinated by the possibilities that lay beyond our planet prior to modern technology. In the 17th century, Galileo used the revolutionary development of the telescope to observe the characteristics of the Milky Way. And in 1923, Edwin Hubble discovered concrete evidence for the existence of galaxies other than the Milky Way. But even with these groundbreaking discoveries, many were left feeling like something was missing. One mystery surfaced above the rest: “Where is everybody?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This dilemma was the reason for Enrico Fermi’s lunchtime remark that sparked decades of research and speculation. Named after the famous physicist, the Fermi paradox is the contradiction between the high probability for extraterrestrial life and the lack of evidence supporting the existence of aliens. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seti.org/press-release/how-many-habitable-planets-are-out-there&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;SETI Institute&lt;/a&gt;, as many as 300 million planets may be habitable in just the Milky Way. Billions of planets orbit within the habitable zones of stars and scientists have even discovered several planets that resemble Earth. The Fermi paradox perplexes even the most knowledgeable scientists today, and there is still no viable answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Numerous theories debate this paradox, with a few of the most popular speculating that aliens see no reason to visit Earth, they have already visited Earth undetected, we don’t have the correct technology to contact aliens, or that life itself is unlikely, and the possibility of it developing into intellectual species is even more so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dozens of other theories exist, each with its own fair amount of counterarguments and doubt. For over 70 years, researchers and scientists have published papers and debated the viability of various theories. One method that scientists rely on when debating the Fermi paradox is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://exoplanets.nasa.gov/news/1350/are-we-alone-in-the-universe-revisiting-the-drake-equation/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Drake Equation&lt;/a&gt;. Developed in the 1960s, it calculates the number of civilizations in the Milky Way galaxy of which humans could theoretically communicate with. The Drake Equation multiples together evidential factors, like the number of planets per solar system that can support life, and hypothetical ones, such as the length of time that these civilizations actually release detectable signals into space. However, the indefinite nature of both the Fermi paradox and any attempts to supplement the issue means that any papers published can only be, at best, regarded as speculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each new decade brings more and more uncertainty about the possibility of life outside of Earth. Even with new technologies capable of taking pictures of stars as far as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/feature/new-horizons-captures-record-breaking-images-in-the-kuiper-belt/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;3.79 billion miles away from Earth&lt;/a&gt;, humans are unable to find any evidence supporting the possibility of extraterrestrial life. Despite this discouraging amount of progress, many scientists stand by their belief that aliens do indeed exist. But whether or not scientists can find conclusive evidence of extraterrestrial civilizations, humanity will surely continue to explore deeper into space and uncover the mystery of our own existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Tech Explorist)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Ana Monsalud&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Ana is a junior from Cambridge Virtual Academy who is a huge nerd for pretty much everything related to math and science. Through InterSTEM, she hopes to inspire others with her same love for learning and curiosity about the world. In the future, she hopes to pursue a career in healthcare and contribute to change in her community.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ana Monsalud</name></author><summary type="html">The Fermi paradox: Possibilities of extraterrestrial life Ana Monsalud. 11/07/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/fermiParadoxCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/fermiParadoxCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>