<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-17T20:02:08-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">InterSTEM</title><entry><title type="html">Ancient stardust discovered in meteorite</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/14/ancient-stardust-discovered-in-meteorite.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Ancient stardust discovered in meteorite" /><published>2021-01-14T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-14T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/14/ancient-stardust-discovered-in-meteorite</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/14/ancient-stardust-discovered-in-meteorite.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The causes, symptoms and treatment for social anxiety&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tania Firouzabady. 01/15/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/stardustOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This image is of presolar silicon carbide grains found in the Murchison meteorite.
(NASA, W. Sparks (STScI) / R. Sahai (JPL) / Inset Janaina N. Avila)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In September 1969, a meteorite fell near the town of Murchison in Victoria, Australia. Weighing 100 kilograms, this massive rock was initially overlooked as an ordinary meteorite. However, scientists have recently discovered that it contains the oldest material on Earth: 7-billion-year-old stardust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The dust is composed of presolar grains, which are microscopic dust particles older than our sun. Though the primary molecule found in the grains was silicon carbide, the traces of neon-21 that were also found played a key role in unveiling the age of the dust. Neon-21 is produced when silicon carbide is struck by galactic cosmic rays. These rays are high-energy protons and nuclei that move through space at extremely high speeds. They can be produced by the sun, outside the solar system and even in other galaxies. The larger the neon-21 concentration in the grains, the more time that has passed since it was created.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/content/117/4/1884&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences&lt;/a&gt; (PNAS) outlines the importance of the interstellar dust: “[interstellar dust] carries a large fraction of the elements heavier than He, including the elements that form terrestrial planets and are essential for life.” Its potential to reveal the habitability of planetary systems makes interstellar dust highly valuable to researchers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the PNAS highlights the methods used to analyze the dust found within the Murchison meteorite. Astronomical spectroscopic observations (based on measuring the spectrum of electromagnetic radiation) are used to determine the composition, structure and size of the dust particles, while a variety of theoretical models are used to find the dust’s lifespan. In this particular instance, scientists approached the challenge by finding the interstellar lifetimes of individual presolar silicon carbide grains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;No presolar grains have ever been discovered in rocks on Earth, making the grains on the meteorite very valuable to researchers. As explained by scientist Philipp Heck, the reason for this can be found in Earth’s geological processes: volcanism and plate tectonics transform any presolar dust that may have been left during Earth’s formation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To better understand the nature of the stardust, the team measured the size of the grains. The majority of presolar grains are one micron long. In contrast, those found on the meteorite ranged from 2 to 30 microns. Their astounding size led the team to call them ‘boulders.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/stardustTwo.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Above is a scanning electron microscope image of the presolar grains found in the Murchison meteorite.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://earthsky.org/space/ancient-stardust-older-than-earth-australian-meteorite&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(EarthSky)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Heck and his colleagues analyzed 40 of the boulders by first grinding pieces of the meteorite and then using acid to dissolve the minerals and silicate. This ultimately allowed them to determine which of the grains were acid-resistant. As outlined by the PNAS, “These grains are identified as presolar by their large isotopic anomalies that exclude an origin in the solar system.” The majority of presolar grains are destroyed during thermal metamorphosis and aqueous altercation, processes stimulating their growth in the parent bodies they come from. Hence, they are among the most ancient materials in the solar system and are of great value to scientists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once the grains have been isolated, mass spectrometry, a technique used for measuring the mass to charge ratio of ions, is utilized to determine the number of nuclides produced by the grains during reactions with galactic cosmic rays. Nuclides are a specific type of atom or nucleus characterized by the number of protons and neutrons they contain. When they come into contact with high-energy particles, some of them break apart and those that are left accumulate in the presolar grains. The nuclide concentration is proportional to the timespan the grains were exposed to radiation, revealing various properties that indicate how old the dust is.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These techniques ultimately revealed that the grains date to before the formation of our solar system. According to Heck, the grains “formed in an episode of enhanced star formation. There was a time before the start of the solar system when more stars formed than normal.” To clarify, the grains allow scientists to better understand stellar evolution, the ways in which stars change with time, particularly with regards to bursts of star formation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another unusual finding was that the stardust particles appeared to be stuck together. This phenomenon can be explained by the dust’s electrical charge. As explained by &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.nasa.gov/science-news/science-at-nasa/2000/ast31jul_2m&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;NASA&lt;/a&gt;, “Gravity pulls dust and gas in interstellar clouds together, but because the electrostatic force over short distances is so much stronger than gravity, even a small electrostatic repulsion between dust grains can influence (and possibly prevent) a cloud’s collapse.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When the Murchison meteorite was discovered in 1969, no one could have imagined the remarkable material it kept hidden. At first glance, it would appear to be an ordinary meteorite. But as revealed by Philippe Heck and his colleagues, the stardust it contains, which is invisible to the naked eye, provides clues to the origins of stars and the history of the solar system. Though the exact age of the dust is unclear, its significance to astronomical research is evident.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://newatlas.com/space/extraterrestrial-protein-meteorite/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(New Atlas)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Tania Firouzabady&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Tania is a junior at Dana Hills High School. She enjoys learning about STEM topics and plans to be a scientist in the future. Through InterSTEM, she hopes to share this passion with others.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Tania Firouzabady</name></author><summary type="html">The causes, symptoms and treatment for social anxiety Tania Firouzabady. 01/15/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/stardustCover.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/stardustCover.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Chemistry behind love</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/07/chemistry-behind-love.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Chemistry behind love" /><published>2021-01-07T16:00:05-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-07T16:00:05-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/07/chemistry-behind-love</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/07/chemistry-behind-love.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Chemistry behind love&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rheigina Quijote. 01/08/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/loveOne.png&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Oxytocin is commonly referred to as the ‘love hormone’ because it is released when we engage in activities that stimulate attraction. This image presents the molecular structure of oxytocin. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ambiopharm.com/articles/in-honor-of-valentines-day-we-introduce-the-celebritide-oxytocin-also-known-as-the-love-hormone/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(AmbioPharm)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The sky is painted a dark blue with small specks of light barely visible within it. The soft drops of rain cascade onto you. They stand a foot from you, looking at you in such a way that it makes your heart race and palms sweat. Suddenly, all rationality is gone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You can’t help but think, “Why do I have these butterflies in my stomach?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although literature and films provide an understanding of the concept of love that we all wonder about, it can also be described from a scientific point of view. The reason for the sleepless nights and endless conversations can be explained by multiple different hormones and neurochemicals that cause the joyous feeling known as love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;http://sitn.hms.harvard.edu/flash/2017/love-actually-science-behind-lust-attraction-companionship/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Harvard University&lt;/a&gt;, a study at Rutgers led by Helen Fisher indicates that there are three categories that define romantic love. These categories - lust, attraction and attachment - all contain their own set of hormones that act on us when we experience the giddy feeling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Lust&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Lust is defined as an intense desire for something and is the basis for all organisms’ need to reproduce. There are two main hormones that are produced by the hypothalamus of the brain: testosterone and estrogen. These are also referred to as the ‘male’ and ‘female’ hormones, though they are prominent in both genders. The stimulation and production of these hormones are what drive procreation within humans.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Attraction&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;The attraction stage is more commonly associated with the feeling of butterflies and fear of rejection. Romantic passion is the more distinct phase we come across that we question or deny once we have fallen head over heels. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://asdn.net/asdn/chemistry/chemistry_of_love.php#ref&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Atomic Scale Design Network&lt;/a&gt; (ASDN) states during the first attraction, we deal with the neurochemicals that oversee our neural activity: norepinephrine, dopamine and phenylethylamine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Love can possibly even be addictive. Similarly to lust, the prefrontal cortex, which is the region of the brain that regulates rational behavior, shuts off during attraction. These regions that light up during attraction are the same that signal addiction to materialistic items or drugs such as cocaine. This may be why attraction to another person can be described as an addiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The brain pathways that control the reward behavior are involved in attraction. The reward pathways in the brain contain dopaminergic neurons that tell us whether something is aversive or rewarding. During attraction, neurons release dopamine, or the feel-good chemical, which makes our brain correlate happiness to the person and ensures the desire to see them more. When we are participating in activities that feel good to us, such as bonding or spending time with our friends, dopamine is released. With attraction, high levels of dopamine are responsible for the beginning of a relationship to have that exhilarating feeling, hence why the ‘honeymoon’ or ‘cupcake’ phase of a relationship can occur.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dopamine affects the parts of the brain that control emotional response, as well as pain. It is found to be both a precursor for norepinephrine and a neurotransmitter. A precursor goes through chemical reactions to produce another chemical. Norepinephrine is another chemical involved in attraction and it cannot be produced without dopamine. In order for the effects of norepinephrine to occur, which include sweating, increased heart rate and adrenaline, there must first be enough dopamine produced. Neurotransmitters are what send chemical messages throughout the body to specific cells to perform a function. Our bodies contain a dopamine neurotransmitter system allowing us to feel good by the activation of the dopamine receptors that collaborate with our brain’s pleasure system. This gives us the motivation to continue to do activities that produce dopamine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dopamine does not act alone in the beginnings of romantic attraction; there is also norepinephrine. The reason we get sweaty palms when we are with someone we are infatuated with is the result of the neurochemical norepinephrine, or noradrenaline, which plays a role in the fight or flight response. This neurochemical is what stimulates the production of adrenaline. The norepinephrine system acts as the body’s chemical messengers and, when activated, does a variety of actions to specific cell types. This system increases our experience of joy, reduces appetite and also involves cortisol maintenance and initiation. In other words, it is responsible for sustaining the stress hormone, cortisol. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.reagent.co.uk/the-chemistry-of-love/#:~:text=The%20initial%20spark%20of%20falling,pleasure%2C%20energy%20and%20focussed%20attention&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ReAgent&lt;/a&gt;, Richard Schwartz claims that when you are in love, your levels of cortisol are raised, thus suppressing immune function. Maybe love does make us a little sick.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where cortisol is increased, serotonin is also decreased. Serotonin, a neurotransmitter related to our feelings of happiness, is what affects our body’s functions of mood, memory, sleep and appetite. Communication is disrupted by lower levels of serotonin and causes anxiety, compulsiveness and obsessiveness. This is often why when people are infatuated, they feel that person is all-consuming of their thoughts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, the last major neurochemical that is involved with attraction is phenylethylamine (PEA). PEA is what releases norepinephrine and dopamine, and is what makes our tummies do somersaults at the antics of our significant other. The more PEA that is produced, the more dopamine is released. PEA is a neuromodulator compared to the other two neurochemicals; it modulates the initiation of the norepinephrine system and increases the levels of dopamine. Though it is not proven, it is assumed that PEA resides in the presynaptic vesicles and takes dopamine’s usual spot, leading to an increase in circulating dopamine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe love at first sight is slightly overrated, but there’s definitely chemistry when two people first start out in a relationship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Attachment&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;After couples have gone through the honeymoon phase and it feels like the spark has died out, the final stage of love sets in. Attachment is the indicator of long-lasting relationships and is not only limited to romantic affiliations, unlike lust and attraction. Though the butterflies are gone, that does not mean the chemistry is gone. The release of dopamine and norepinephrine is exchanged with oxytocin and vasopressin.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As attachment occurs, the ‘puppy love’ act lessens and the neurotransmitter oxytocin increases. Through this, a calmer, more mature form of love is presented with concrete bonds.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long term relations also include family and friends, forming the emotional bond between people and partners. Oxytocin which is commonly referred to as the ‘cuddle hormone’ or the ‘love hormone’ is produced in the hypothalamus of the brain like dopamine. This hormone deals with the emotional and cognitive behaviors of a person and is prominent in adapting to emotional situations. It’s produced in high quantities when participating in activities that encourage bonding and reducing stress response and anxiety. However, it can also stimulate jealousy and irrationality.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vasopressin partners with oxytocin within long term relationships to establish closeness and bondage. From these two, there is a disruption of the dopamine and norepinephrine pathways, causing passion to fall and attachment to grow. These hormones help raise health benefits for married couples and decrease depression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While these hormones provide the development of relationships with others, it can be the downfall of them as well. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2442436/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Library of Medicine&lt;/a&gt; stated that studying drugs MDMA (Molly or Ecstasy) and GHB (Liquid Ecstasy) assumed that oxytocin may be the reason for the ‘high’ that is produced. It is shown that an overabundance of oxytocin can cause dissociation and reckless behavior. While oxytocin and dopamine may benefit our attraction towards people, a surplus of it can cause an unhealthy emotional dependence and irrational behavior similar to when one is addicted to binge eating and substance abuse. Only at stable doses can these hormones cause the warm, bubbly feeling we know when we fall in love.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like any science, there is more complexity than what we can really pinpoint. There is a limited amount of what science can explain about the chemistry between people. Whether or not it’s hormones that allow us to find our soulmate rather than fate, or if it really comes from the head instead of the heart, we can’t blame high school teenagers for thinking they have met their matches when we are all dealing with the same hormones and chemistry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Give oxytocin some love for matchmaking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Melissa Moseley / New Line Productions)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/Rheigina_Quijote.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Rheigina Quijote&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Rheigina is a junior at Bridgeland High School from Houston, Texas. She loves to do focused writing around STEM to expand her interests but also others like her who are still finding their passions in the field. Rheigina also loves spending time with her family by watching movies, trying new foods with her friends, and reading an excessive amount of YA novels when she has the free time.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Rheigina Quijote</name></author><summary type="html">Chemistry behind love Rheigina Quijote. 01/08/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/loveCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/loveCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The causes, symptoms and treatment for social anxiety</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/07/the-causes-symptoms-and-treatment-for-social-anxiety.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The causes, symptoms and treatment for social anxiety" /><published>2021-01-07T16:00:03-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-07T16:00:03-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/07/the-causes-symptoms-and-treatment-for-social-anxiety</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/07/the-causes-symptoms-and-treatment-for-social-anxiety.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The causes, symptoms and treatment for social anxiety&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Omar Dajani. 01/08/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/socialAnxietyOne.PNG&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This illustration shows the different ways someone might develop social anxiety disorder.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/social-anxiety-disorder-causes-3024749&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Brianna Gilmartin / Verywell)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Many people are shy when it comes to social situations. They might feel hesitant to meet new people and feel overwhelmed by social gatherings such as parties. These feelings are completely normal, but they can reach a point of severity where they are not. Some people feel terrified of the mere idea of meeting new people, and they might completely avoid social gatherings as a result. These people likely have what is known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://childmind.org/article/what-is-social-anxiety/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;social anxiety disorder&lt;/a&gt; (SAD), which they can either be born with or develop over time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes referred to as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.healthline.com/health/anxiety/social-phobia&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;social phobia&lt;/a&gt;, SAD causes a plethora of irrational feelings for whoever suffers from it. People with the disorder realize a lot of their feelings are hyperbolic, but sometimes, they may feel powerless to do anything about how it influences their cognition towards the world. Although it was compared to shyness previously, SAD is far more damaging. It can seriously deteriorate someone’s relationship with themself, their family, friends, work and school.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With SAD &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mhanational.org/conditions/social-anxiety-disorder&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;impacting 7% of Americans (15 million of the overall population)&lt;/a&gt;, a large number of people’s lives are negatively impacted due to the disorder. The high percentage indicates this is one of the most common mental disorders in America. With such prevalence, it is important to know some of the symptoms of SAD. This can help you assist someone who may have it, or even yourself. Some symptoms include &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.healthline.com/health/anxiety/social-phobia#symptoms&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;trembling or shaking, rapid heart rate and dizziness&lt;/a&gt;. Those are just physical symptoms— some psychological ones include worrying deeply about social situations, concerning yourself with upcoming social activities days or weeks before they even occur and potentially using drugs to calm down any fear related to social contexts. These symptoms only become worse with the assumptions that the disorder gives you: that everyone notices everything you do and silently judges you at every chance they get. This can cause an unrelenting feeling of exhaustion for the person with SAD, so getting the proper support is in that person’s best interest.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/socialAnxietyTwo.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This illustrates something common that a lot of people with SAD experience: the feeling that everyone around you is focused on you in negative ways.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://stayprepared.sg/mymentalhealth/articles/social-anxiety-and-the-new-normal/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(My Mental Health)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Such a detrimental mental health disorder can develop in a variety of ways, all of which are shown in the illustration at the top of the article. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/social-anxiety-disorder-causes-3024749&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The most common way to develop the disorder&lt;/a&gt; is by simply being born with it. If they are born with a specific set of genes, they may be more prone to SAD, especially if they have a relative with it. This also ties into the way the person’s brain is structured and how their neurotransmitters are balanced. A second way to get it is largely dependent on a variety of social situations. Did people make fun of you today? Do they constantly keep making fun of you? Does this get to you on an extremely personal level, so much so you evaluate your entire self-worth? If a person answers yes to these questions, as well as any other questions of that nature, there is a chance they have the disorder and should continue looking into these feelings. A third way to become socially anxious depends on your upbringing. If a person has extremely strict parents who strongly limit their opportunities to have social interactions or be in social situations, their experience when it comes to these two areas will be largely stilted, which may manifest into SAD when the person grows older.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How would a person go about getting the proper support? There is a multitude of ways, with one being a prescription medication. A wide variety of drugs can help lessen the impact SAD, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/treatments-for-social-anxiety-disorder-3024949&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;but all medications have side effects&lt;/a&gt;, so the medication someone decides to use is largely dependent on the specific individual. Some examples of these drugs are Zoloft, Prozac, Cymbalta, Marplan, Tenormin and Valium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other ways to lessen the impact of SAD include psychotherapy, such as Cognitive Behavioral Therapy (CBT). This common treatment focuses on influencing your behaviors and thoughts in a positive way to stop negative emotions by using techniques, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/treatments-for-social-anxiety-disorder-3024949&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;exposure, cognitive restructuring and social skills training&lt;/a&gt;. The first technique allows the person to practice being in social situations, the second involves evaluation of existing negative thoughts and the third deals with the improvement of several soft skills needed for a variety of social situations. The third technique is similar to the first but focuses on what a person would do rather than having them act on the spot. Social skills training is usually reserved for extreme cases of the disorder, so most people can be treated with just the first two techniques. There are other ways to counteract the impact of SAD, but these three techniques are the most well-known.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though it may seem difficult for a person to beat social anxiety, it is important to consistently receive treatment or support. The aforementioned treatment options &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.healthline.com/health/anxiety/social-phobia#outlook&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;have been proven to help lessen the control the disorder has on your life&lt;/a&gt;, and the positive outlook gained from undergoing one of the treatment options will only cause a ripple effect that is sure to expand into a higher self-esteem. As someone who had SAD myself and went to therapy for it, I can tell you that CBT has been of great help. If you have social anxiety or suspect that you may, I highly recommend that you look into receiving CBT and going from there. Social anxiety is strong, but you are stronger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Nimble / Dribbble)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Omar Dajani&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Omar Dajani is an international student from Jerusalem, Palestine. He is currently a sophomore at Fullerton College in California. He has a passion for English as well as Computer Science. He enjoys gaming, blogging, journaling, meditating, and going on walks. He intends on transferring to UC Berkeley for Fall 2021.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Omar Dajani</name></author><summary type="html">The causes, symptoms and treatment for social anxiety Omar Dajani. 01/08/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/socialAnxietyCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/socialAnxietyCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The benefits of retrieval through testing</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/07/the-benefits-of-retrieval-through-testing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The benefits of retrieval through testing" /><published>2021-01-07T16:00:01-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-07T16:00:01-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/07/the-benefits-of-retrieval-through-testing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/07/the-benefits-of-retrieval-through-testing.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The benefits of retrieval through testing&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Audrey Lee. 01/08/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/testingOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt; Students begin to write their responses to test questions in a classroom setting.
(Getty Images / iStockphoto)

&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In the United States, assessments at school often trigger stress, anxiety and fear within students. Parents and teachers have also been against testing because it forces teachers to focus specifically on material that will be on exams rather than helping students improve upon critical thinking. Despite the opposition, recent studies have proven that taking tests, a form of retrieval, helps students remember what they have learned with more success compared to other techniques often favored by educators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2011/01/21/science/21memory.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The New York Times&lt;/a&gt;, research published on &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/331/6018/772.abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Science&lt;/a&gt; showed that those who took a test after reading a passage could recall the information with more success later on compared to students who repeatedly studied the material or drew concept maps (diagrams that connect terms and information in briefly organized boxes or circles).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This test-taking method was referred to as a retrieval practice test. To retrieve information is to access information previously learned when needed. In other words, it is to recall memories stored in one’s brain. The second and third methods are probably familiar, as students often cram the night before by repeatedly studying material or even hours before the exam, and teachers often encourage the use of concept maps so that students can draw connections between several seemingly unconnected concepts taught in class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When students were asked how much information they thought they would remember a week later, those who took the test predicted they would remember less than those who were assigned the other two methods of studying; however, the results proved otherwise. A week later, students took exams that asked for short answer questions as well as a concept map. Contrary to the expectation that the concept-mappers would perform better since they already made one before, students who took the retrieval practice test were more successful since they could recall more information. Thus, this study shows that retrieval practices are much more effective and efficient in comparison to elaborative studying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Moreover, an article from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.edutopia.org/article/what-does-research-say-about-testing&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Edutopia&lt;/a&gt; provides further examples of research studies that proved retrieval practice tests before exams allowed students to remember a greater percentage of the content compared to those who simply studied. Additionally, tests can be beneficial when given frequently because they provide immediate feedback, allowing students to focus on specific concepts they did not clearly understand or need assistance with.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fact that cramming the day before a test is often less successful compared to other studying techniques can be supported by two reasons. First, cramming the day before is often a result of procrastinating, which will typically lead to a lack of sleep since the student will most likely study late at night. This supports the idea that many students who cram will not have sufficient sleep before the day of an exam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people have been told that in order to do well on a test, they need a good night’s sleep. So why is this related to how well one can recall information? An article from &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.innerdrive.co.uk/why-you-need-to-know-about-retrieval-practice#:~:text=Why%20is%20Retrieval%20Practice%20Effective,to%20the%20long%2Dterm%20memory.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;InnerDrive&lt;/a&gt; states that retrieval practices help improve memory since they “create stronger memory traces” and increase the chances of the information becoming long-term memory. The transfer of short-term memory to long-term memory is called consolidation. In short, there are three steps in the process of memory according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webmd.com/sleep-disorders/sleep-deprivation-effects-on-memory&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;WebMD&lt;/a&gt; and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC3768102/#:~:text=Encoding%20and%20consolidation%20might%20be,time%20window%20for%20consolidating%20memories.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Center for Biotechnology Information&lt;/a&gt; (NCBI): encoding (when a new memory trace forms based on the information perceived), consolidation (where memories are stabilized and less susceptible to being forgotten) and retrieval (when previously stored information is recalled). Sleep is correlated with the second step, consolidation, since there are considerably fewer distractions in the brain when you are asleep compared to when you are awake, when the brain is preoccupied with constant encoding or retrieval.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Second, these students often study by repeatedly reading the material. The popularity of this study technique can be linked to the false sense of confidence it provides to students. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.innerdrive.co.uk/why-you-need-to-know-about-retrieval-practice#:~:text=Why%20is%20Retrieval%20Practice%20Effective,to%20the%20long%2Dterm%20memory.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;InnerDrive&lt;/a&gt;, re-reading a passage will increase the “ease or fluency with which it is read and can lead to the student believing they have mastered its content - when really all they have done is familiarise themselves with the text and the ordering of the words.” While students will have the illusion that they know a lot of the information, using this method as the only way to study is risky, as students can easily forget the information without practices such as quizzes or simply writing down the material.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cramming the night before a test is not an efficient study method, but it is unrealistic to set the expectation of remembering something for a longer period of time after just one retrieval practice. While
it is not expected that students will be excited about a test, assessments are crucial and beneficial, as they are made in order to increase the chances of retaining the information for a long period of time, possibly for years or even decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gse.harvard.edu/news/uk/17/11/when-testing-takes-over&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Harvard Graduate School of Education)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Audrey Lee&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Audrey Lee</name></author><summary type="html">The benefits of retrieval through testing Audrey Lee. 01/08/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/testingCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/testingCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why do we cry?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/07/Why-do-we-cry.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why do we cry?" /><published>2021-01-07T16:00:01-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-07T16:00:01-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/07/Why-do-we-cry</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/07/Why-do-we-cry.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Why do we cry?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Angela Zhang. 01/08/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/cryOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;A toddler cries in distress.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.parent4success.com/2012/02/16/25-ways-to-calm-a-crying-baby/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Parent 4 Success)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
We usually associate crying with those who are vulnerable or those who are too helpless to help themselves. Babies and small children, who are notorious for bursting straight into tears whenever they are presented with any sort of upsetting situation, usually come to mind. But this is understandable—they cry to communicate since their limited capacity of language falls short. However, even when you’ve grown well past that age and you’re expected to solve your problems with words and actions instead of sitting and weeping about them, you might still find yourself sitting and weeping every now and then. The question today is why shedding tears is our bodies’ natural response to various events in our lives. What exactly makes human beings cry?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/4254089/science-crying/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Jonathan Rottenberg&lt;/a&gt;, an emotion researcher and psychology professor at the University of South Florida, “crying signals to yourself and other people that there’s some important problem that is at least temporarily beyond your ability to cope.” Interestingly enough, there are many different tear-inducing problems you can face, and they will give rise to varying kinds of tears.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First, we have reflex tears, which are tears unrelated to emotion and induced when your body senses something is wrong in the environment. The lacrimal gland, located between the eyeball and the eyelid, will produce reflex tears to protect your eyes from threatening air particles like dust, smoke or most infamously: the stinging fumes of an onion. When you blink, the teardrop spreads across the surface of your eye and accumulates into a pool, which is when your eyes well up. Once too much liquid collects together, the pool overflows and sends tears trickling down your face, thereby washing out any irritants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, we have psychic tears. These are the kind caused by a surge of strong emotion, which could range anywhere from pure joy to utter devastation. You could shed psychic tears because you’re feeling stressed beyond comparison, because you’re overwhelmed with nostalgia, or even because your friend’s jokes are just way too hilarious. The reason why all of these unrelated situations produce the same tearful outcome is due to the work of a neurotransmitter called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.independent.co.uk/life-style/why-do-we-cry-the-science-of-tears-9741287.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;acetylcholine&lt;/a&gt;. Acetylcholine links the autonomic nervous system, which is the neural system that you can’t control, to the lacrimal tear system. When your body undergoes a particularly emotional response to any kind of stimulus, your nervous system will release acetylcholine, which will then move to trigger tear production in the lacrimal apparatus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/cryTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This diagram of the lacrimal apparatus depicts the pathway of tear production. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.landaeyecare.com/tearing/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Landa &amp;amp; Landa)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The noteworthy part of this process is the uncontrollability of its origin. Most people cry when they lose control over their emotions, when their bodies take over and react for them. This can often be because they encounter something that is out of their realm of control in the first place, and all they can do is succumb to an emotional response. But that begs the question, why crying as an emotional response? What will crying attain for us that no other bodily function can?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer brings us back to the very beginning of our discussion: crying for help. Regardless of whether you are a small child or a grown person, weeping makes you look vulnerable. Those watery eyes, woeful sniffles and dampened cheeks—all signs point to a guard that has fallen, which can in turn cast a very strong emotional effect on surrounding people. Most individuals tend to feel more sorry for those who are visibly crying, and as a result, they are more inclined to help those people. This idea is supported by a &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.sagepub.com/doi/pdf/10.1177/147470491301100114#:~:text=The%20even%20faster%20recognition%20of,be%20investigated%20in%20the%20future&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2013 study&lt;/a&gt; held by Tilburg University in which participants were shown photographs of people with sad and neutral expressions with and without tears. In both rounds of the study, the participants showcased a higher perceived need for social support amid the people depicted with tears. This study indicates that tears do serve as a prominent visual cue for sadness and the need for outside care, and they help promote person-to-person connection.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not to mention, scientists have found &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S1542012412701842&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;higher protein content&lt;/a&gt; in psychic tears than in reflex tears, which causes them to be thicker and stickier. This makes it more likely for people to notice them as they run slowly down your face, helping you procure any emotional support or comfort that you need.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Among these greater levels of proteins reside adrenocorticotropic hormones, which are associated with increased stress levels. Some scientists deduce that people cry to purge these stress-associated chemicals from their bodies and restore their bodies to an emotional balance. And although studies heretofore have not been fully conclusive, it’s widely accepted that turning on the waterworks can be a truly cathartic experience. You get to release all those bottled-up feelings through your tears, and it could feel like letting out one big sigh of relief. It’s also noteworthy that when you cry in response to physical pain, like stubbing your toe or getting a papercut, your body will release &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.healthline.com/health/why-do-we-cry#relieving-pain&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;endorphins and oxytocin&lt;/a&gt;, which are feel-good natural chemicals that can help placate your discomfort and improve your mood.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The takeaway from all of this is that we cry to make ourselves feel better. This improved condition can be achieved through supportive interpersonal connection or through the act of crying itself as an inherently self-soothing procedure. Even though we cannot control how it begins, we can control what we get out of it, and that is healing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webmd.com/balance/rm-quiz-benefits-crying&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(WebMD)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/Angela_Zhang.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Angela Zhang&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Angela Zhang is a junior at Beckman High School. She is an aspiring storyteller who hopes to make a profound impression on her audience with her writing. She is also a passionate cactus enthusiast and has a soft spot for cheesy puns.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Angela Zhang</name></author><summary type="html">Why do we cry? Angela Zhang. 01/08/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/cryCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/cryCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Uncovering the low demand for monoclonal antibody treatments for COVID-19</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/07/uncovering-the-low-demand-for-monoclonal-antibody-treatments-for-covid-19.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Uncovering the low demand for monoclonal antibody treatments for COVID-19" /><published>2021-01-07T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-07T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/07/uncovering-the-low-demand-for-monoclonal-antibody-treatments-for-covid-19</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/07/uncovering-the-low-demand-for-monoclonal-antibody-treatments-for-covid-19.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Uncovering the low demand for monoclonal antibody treatments for COVID-19&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ashley Lee. 01/08/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/monoclonalOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The U.S. Food and Drug Administration has recently authorized the use of monoclonal antibodies (y-shaped protein depicted in the image) for COVID-19.
(Dr_Microbe / iStock / Getty Images Plus)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
With the vaccination process beginning a few weeks ago, the approval and use of monoclonal antibodies for treating COVID-19 is still new to many. Many people were not fully aware of the development of these drugs until President Donald Trump received an experimental antibody cocktail earlier in October.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An antibody is a protein that is used by the immune system to recognize and neutralize antigens, any substances the body identifies as foreign. And monoclonal antibodies are created in labs by cloning a white blood cell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On Nov. 9, the U.S. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fda.gov/news-events/press-announcements/coronavirus-covid-19-update-fda-authorizes-monoclonal-antibody-treatment-covid-19&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Food and Drug Administration (FDA)&lt;/a&gt; issued an emergency use authorization (EUA) for monoclonal antibody therapy using a drug called bamlanivimab. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fda.gov/news-events/press-announcements/coronavirus-covid-19-update-fda-authorizes-monoclonal-antibodies-treatment-covid-19#:~:text=Monoclonal%20antibodies%20are%20laboratory%2Dmade,harmful%20pathogens%20such%20as%20viruses.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;FDA&lt;/a&gt; issued another EUA for Regeneron’s monoclonal antibody cocktail (REGN-COV2) combining casirivimab and imdevimab on Nov. 21. Both treatments were intended for patients with moderate symptoms and who are at high risk for COVID-19; therefore, patients who were already hospitalized or required oxygen treatment could not receive this therapy. There were additional requirements as well. For example, patients had to be of at least 12 years of age and weigh at least 40 kilograms. Patients at a higher risk for COVID-19, such as those with chronic medical conditions, were also eligible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The FDA stated that after clinical trials, both treatments were shown to “reduce COVID-19-related hospitalization or emergency room visits in patients at high risk for disease progression within 28 days after treatment when compared to placebo.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2020/10/28/coronavirus-us-in-375-million-deal-with-eli-lilly-for-antibody-drug.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CNBC&lt;/a&gt;, the United States purchased 300,000 doses of bamlanivimab in October. They later purchased another 650,000 doses. And according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biospace.com/article/regeneron-antibody-cocktail-wins-eua-from-the-fda/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;BioSpace&lt;/a&gt;, the United States plans on providing 300,000 doses of REGN-COV2 to patients at no cost by January 2021. Due to Trump’s appraisal regarding his treatment, many health officials were concerned about the potential of a high demand for these drugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, administering these drugs has been a challenge in many hospitals nationwide, despite the number of drugs available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/highly-touted-monoclonal-antibody-therapies-sit-unused-in-hospitals-11609087364&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Wall Street Journal&lt;/a&gt; explains that only 20% of the doses are being administered. There is a prominent divide regarding the use of these treatments. Some disease specialists such as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.covid19treatmentguidelines.nih.gov/statement-on-casirivimab-plus-imdevimab-eua&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Institute of Health&lt;/a&gt; do not recommend the antibody treatments because of the insufficient amount of data from trials. In contrast, officials from Operation Warp Speed encourage health professionals to use the doses. In fact, chief scientific adviser of the operation Moncef Slauoi said that he found the use of monoclonal antibodies “disappointing,” as his data revealed that only 5 to 20% of the doses had been used.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, the treatments should be given within 10 days after the patients’ first symptoms. Health officials must isolate the patients and observe them for about an hour after the infusion, so the lack of staff or space in a hospital can be another contributing factor to the lack of treatment administered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Antibody therapies always work best the earliest they’re given,” immunologist at Johns Hopkins Bloomberg School of Public Health Arturo Casadevall said to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/covid-19-treatment-monoclonal-antibodies-promise-challenges-2020-12&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Business Insider&lt;/a&gt;. “This has been known for 130 years.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The only patients eligible for the treatments are those who exhibit mild COVID-19 symptoms, so ensuring that those patients come to the hospital for the infusion can be a difficult task in itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“As they are infectious, they can’t just hail a ride-sharing app and show up at the infusion center,” member of the Medstar Health system in Washington, D.C., Dr. Princy Kumar said to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2020/12/22/948874701/low-demand-for-antibody-drugs-against-covid-19&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;NPR&lt;/a&gt;. “And many of them are reluctant to put a family member, who has to ride with them in the car, at risk. So that’s what we’ve identified to be our main challenge.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, some scientists are concerned about how virus mutations may negatively impact the efficacy of the treatments. Research from COVID-19 cases in France suggests that certain mutations may cause the virus to escape the antibodies from REGN-COV2, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-00502-w&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nature&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The monoclonal antibodies are modeled based on naturally occurring antibodies. However, mutations of the virus affect the receptor-binding domain, the protein segment the virus uses to enter cells. A mutation of this type is known to be prevalent in Europe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, many scientists remain optimistic about the use of monoclonal antibodies for treatment, despite the mutations. Casadevall explains how the antibody cocktails can be effective against multiple strains. Many also see this treatment as a back-up plan, as not everyone will have access to the COVID-19 vaccines in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“These antibodies will find a niche in the arsenal as long as we have COVID around,” Casadevall said. “My hope is that the companies continue to produce them and to make even better cocktails.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Getty Images)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/executive/ashleylee.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Ashley Lee&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Ashley is a junior at Northwood High School who enjoys writing news articles and features. Through InterSTEM, Ashley hopes to provide students a platform where they can find their interests and understand the relevance of STEM-related topics to the changing world. Additionally, she enjoys reading classic literature, watching films, and going to the beach during sunsets.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ashley Lee</name></author><summary type="html">Uncovering the low demand for monoclonal antibody treatments for COVID-19 Ashley Lee. 01/08/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/monoclonalCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/monoclonalCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why can’t we perfectly predict weather on Earth?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/why-can't-we-perfectly-predict-weather-on-earth.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why can’t we perfectly predict weather on Earth?" /><published>2020-12-31T16:00:04-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-31T16:00:04-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/why-can't-we-perfectly-predict-weather-on-earth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/why-can't-we-perfectly-predict-weather-on-earth.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Why can't we perfectly predict weather on Earth?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ana Monsalud. 01/01/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/weatherOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;We often overlook the role that weather plays in our lives. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2020/1/14/21065095/google-ai-weather-forecast-predictions-rainfall-research&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(The Verge)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Have you ever wondered why weather reports don’t show the weather more than a week into the future? And sometimes, predictions are wildly inaccurate for even just three days from when they’re announced. With the technology we have today, why is this the case?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Modern Weather Forecasting&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Weather forecasting today is possible due to a mix of technology, observation and educated guessing. The educated guesses, however, aren’t made by humans: they’re made by computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a process called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.discovermagazine.com/planet-earth/how-weather-forecasts-are-made&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;numerical weather prediction&lt;/a&gt;, meteorologists input current weather conditions into a computer model. These conditions are measured through various weather instruments such as thermometers, weather balloons, weather satellites and more to evaluate the conditions of factors like current temperature, air pressure, humidity, rainfall and wind. The computer model will then be able to simulate the current atmosphere and allow meteorologists to predict the weather for the next few hours or days. Weather models use a complex process that can track weather on a larger scale, like in the case of a large storm, or with more accuracy for a smaller area. Models for a smaller region are more expensive to compute, however, and can only predict up to one or two days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different weather models also use different factors. This could mean that two models form two different predictions because of slight differences between provided data, the way the model simulates the atmosphere, or the difference in which factors are prioritized. So even when provided the same exact data, different models might have different predictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it may seem like there’s no place for humans in this process anymore, meteorologists still play a part in weather prediction. Human judgment is still an important factor for various reasons. If a meteorologist is familiar with an area and knows about common weather irregularities that don’t appear on a model, then they could use their own judgment to provide a possibly more accurate forecast. Certain factors could be early signs of intense weather and not be picked up on by the computer, but be easily noticed by a meteorologist. Even though modern weather prediction is effective, the human touch is still extremely helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;But why are models unable to predict future weather with complete certainty?&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Despite their accuracy and reliability, weather models aren’t able to perfectly simulate the environment. This is because it’s difficult enough to measure every aspect of the current atmosphere. But even if we were able to make observations of all the factors in the atmosphere, those observations would most likely not be perfect. So with the imperfect and limited observations that can be made today, we’re able to create an accurate, but not flawless, model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;So how accurate are weather forecasts?&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;The farther into the future a prediction is made, the less of a chance that it’s accurate. However, weather forecasts are still reliable for predicting about a week into the future. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scijinks.gov/forecast-reliability/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) Scijinks website&lt;/a&gt;, a five-day forecast is accurate about 90% of the time. That accuracy drops to 80% for a seven-day forecast. Yet, a 10-day forecast falls to an accuracy of around 50%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This happens due to a phenomenon known as the butterfly effect. The most famous example of this effect is per its namesake: where a butterfly flapping its wings causes a typhoon. The butterfly effect refers to when a small action causes a large effect. And with the weather, it means that it isn’t possible to know whether a tiny updraft might have bigger effects after a week. Observing the average temperature to be even just one degree higher than the actual average, or if the average recorded wind speed in the frame of an hour is one or two mph under what it was throughout most of the day, might change the long term model significantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Then how technically accurate is modern weather prediction?&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;All factors considered, modern weather prediction is actually an impressively accurate feat of science. By combining new technology and science, it’s possible to predict the weather at a very reliable rate. Even though it isn’t possible today, and probably ever, to perfectly predict the weather to an exact degree, it’s still extremely helpful to have predictions that are normally less than a few degrees off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern weather prediction allows us to do more than just have a better idea of what we should wear for the day, though. These models allow meteorologists to predict the patterns of large storms, intense weather and more. The accuracy of these models means that people can be safer in the case of severe weather and that scientists are able to study changes to climate and hypothesize possible causes. Even though we aren’t able to have weather forecasts perfectly accurate to the degree, modern technology has come a long way in allowing us to understand our complex earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencenewsforstudents.org/article/explainer-weather-and-weather-prediction&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Science News for Students)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Ana Monsalud&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Ana is a junior from Cambridge Virtual Academy who is a huge nerd for pretty much everything related to math and science. Through InterSTEM, she hopes to inspire others with her same love for learning and curiosity about the world. In the future, she hopes to pursue a career in healthcare and contribute to change in her community.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ana Monsalud</name></author><summary type="html">Why can't we perfectly predict weather on Earth? Ana Monsalud. 01/01/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/weatherCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/weatherCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The history of vaccines</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/the-history-of-vaccines.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The history of vaccines" /><published>2020-12-31T16:00:03-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-31T16:00:03-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/the-history-of-vaccines</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/the-history-of-vaccines.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The history of vaccines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sydney Hollingsworth. 01/01/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/vaccinesOne.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Edward Jenner vaccinates eight-year-old James Phipps in 1796.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.history.com/news/the-rise-and-fall-of-smallpox&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(DEA Picture Library / Getty Images)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As news of the COVID-19 vaccine floods headlines, the spread of myths and misconceptions surrounding vaccines is at an all time high. Many cringe at the thought of introducing foreign substances into their bodies, and wordy lists of molecules used in vaccines circulate the internet to elicit angry responses from the masses. The bases of these fears are simple: we are afraid of what we do not understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The science behind vaccines is complicated, and resistance against advancements in medicine is certainly not a new phenomenon. To many, vaccines seem like a magic, ‘too-good-to-be-true’ fix to deadly diseases, and the decision to take them boils down to a question of trust. Perhaps, to combat hesitancy, a quick trip through history will remind us of what vaccines have done and help us understand the necessity of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nlm.nih.gov/exhibition/smallpox/sp_variolation.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;inoculation&lt;/a&gt;, or creating immunity by introducing the immune system to a disease, is far from new; evidence of a similar procedure has been traced all the way back to ancient China. A method called variolation involved the drying and powdering of smallpox scabs which were then inhaled through the nose. Patients contracted a mild form of smallpox and were left immune once they recovered. By the 18th century, the procedure had spread to India, Africa and the Ottoman Empire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Variolation came to Europe in the early 1700s when the wife of a British ambassador observed the procedure in Constantinople. Soon after, the royal family was vaccinated against smallpox and variolation became popular among the upper class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although resulting in similar effects, vaccination and its predecessor, variolation, are quite different. Variolation had a much higher mortality rate because the patient had to have been able to recover from the infection, and the procedure was often done without proper sterilization. Variolation also used the actual disease rather than a weakened or similar form and is no longer used in modern medicine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The invention of modern vaccination is often credited to Edward Jenner in 1796, but could more accurately be attributed to &lt;a href=&quot;https://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/pediatrics/139/4/e20162833.full.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Benjamin Jesty&lt;/a&gt;, a farmer from Dorset, England. At the time, milkmaids were known for their smooth skin, which was not covered by the smallpox scars that many adults had, and they were able to care for relatives who were sick with smallpox without contracting the disease themselves. Jesty hypothesized that the immunity had something to do with the cowpox that milkmaids were prone to, a mild disease similar to smallpox that came from touching the udders of affected cows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1774, 22 years before Jenner conducted his famous experiment, Jesty vaccinated his family with cowpox in response to a smallpox outbreak in Dorset. Unfortunately, his wife’s arm became infected at the site of the puncture wound. Although she recovered quickly, the news of Jesty’s experiment had spread through the community like wildfire. He and his family were run out of town by a mob who believed Jesty wanted to turn them all into half-human, half-cow monsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1805, after Jenner’s findings had been published, Jesty was invited to London by the Original Vaccine Pock Institution where he proved that his vaccine worked by infecting his oldest son, who had been vaccinated 31 years earlier with smallpox. The Institution declared Jesty’s success in September of 1805 in the Edinburgh Medical and Surgical Journal and rewarded him with a portrait, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(06)69878-4/fulltext&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;rediscovered in 2004&lt;/a&gt; by the U.K.’s Wellcome Trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/historic_figures/jenner_edward.shtml&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Edward Jenner&lt;/a&gt; conducted his famous experiment in 1796 when he came to a similar conclusion as Jesty and tested the idea on his gardener’s eight-year-old son. After continued experimentation, Jenner’s findings were published in 1798 but were met with the same backlash Jesty received. Uneasiness at the idea of introducing material from a sick animal into one’s body overwhelmed the potential of his discovery. Newspaper cartoons in 1802 even depicted people with cow heads but as the vaccine was proven effective, ridicule declined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.historyofvaccines.org/timeline/all&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Vaccines were brought to the U.S.&lt;/a&gt; in 1800 by Benjamin Waterhouse with President Thomas Jefferson’s support. As vaccination was proven effective, laws were proposed to require children attending school to be vaccinated against smallpox, inspired by similar laws in Europe and efforts towards eradication of the disease. However, these laws were met with protests. Parents, in particular, were opposed to the procedure as it involved an incision in their child’s arm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the 1890s, as cases of smallpox became increasingly rare and vaccines were made more effective and safe, the occasional adverse reactions became much more obvious. Even in the wake of multiple deadly outbreaks, growing opposition to vaccines would resurface amongst government efforts to require them. This trend would continue through the next century, with measles, diphtheria, tuberculosis, polio and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, as public opinion rose and fell, advancements in vaccination technology continued. In 1879, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/biography/Louis-Pasteur/Vaccine-development&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Louis Pasteur&lt;/a&gt;, best known for his invention of pasteurization, used live, weakened cultures of chicken cholera to vaccinate chickens against the infection. This was the first use of a weakened microbe as a vaccine. He later extended this principle to anthrax and discovered a vaccine with the help of funding from local farmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1882, Pasteur once again extended this principle of milder vaccines to rabies. At first, he incorrectly assumed the disease was caused by a microbe rather than a virus and began preserving the spinal cords of infected rabbits to better observe it. Instead, he found that his preservation method had actually neutralized the virus, creating the first neutralizing antibody and paving the way for a new type of vaccine called inactivated vaccines. The first use of Pasteur’s rabies vaccine was on a nine-year-old boy who had been bitten by a dog. His success marked the beginning of preventative medicine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through the years, it seems as if there were two sides to the history of vaccines. On one hand, the scientific advancement of vaccines has been clearly, steadily improving. On the other hand, responses to vaccines have been varied, as the fear of deadly diseases and interference wrestle for control over public opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to understand that science does not exist in a vacuum; whether or not the public accepts a scientific advancement is just as important as the advancement itself. The natural reaction to avoid what we do not understand has become more apparent in recent history as science has quickly surpassed the awareness of the average person. Understanding how far vaccines have come and all the good they’ve done is imperative if one wishes to manage the science behind them. It helps to remember that the discoveries of today were not made overnight; they have been built on years of hard work by people attempting to understand the world around them in order to help the people they care for most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.historyofvaccines.org/content/1920s-immunization&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Metropolitan Life Insurance Co.)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Sydney Hollingsworth&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sydney Hollingsworth</name></author><summary type="html">The history of vaccines Sydney Hollingsworth. 01/01/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/vaccinesCover.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/vaccinesCover.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Can science and religion coexist?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/can-science-and-religion-coexist.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can science and religion coexist?" /><published>2020-12-31T16:00:01-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-31T16:00:01-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/can-science-and-religion-coexist</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/can-science-and-religion-coexist.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Can science and religion coexist?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emily Richter. 01/01/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/scienceAndReligionOne.png&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Many scientists believe that it is possible for religion and science to harmoniously coexist. (Emily Richter)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Science and religion seem to always be at odds. In the 1500s, when Nicolaus Copernicus announced that his observations about other planets supported the idea that Earth is a round planet revolving around the sun, the Catholic Church strongly objected to his findings because they contradicted the words of the Bible. Even today, some people doubt the roundness of Earth, pointing to the Bible as evidence against the proven idea. Throughout history, scientists and religious leaders have clashed as both point to different types of evidence to support their ideas about the world. History repeats itself today. Many religious people do not believe in human-caused climate change, while most scientists do. The conflict between science and religion has created deep fissures in society. Is it possible for the two subjects to peacefully coexist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common point of contention between scientists and theologists is likely evolution. When naturalist and biologist Charles Darwin introduced the theory of evolution in the nineteenth century, religious leaders everywhere panicked. Darwin’s theory of evolution, which states that all living things evolved from a common ancestor, seemed to disprove many religious texts. As many religions preach that humans were created by a god as unique and superior beings, the idea that humans, animals, bacteria and every other living thing come from the same ancestor does not sit well with many religious people. However, &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2007/03/can-science-religion-coexist-in-peace/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Harvard professor Martin A. Nowa&lt;/a&gt; believes that evolution poses “as little problem for religion as [the concept of] gravity.” Nowak notes the evolution of what he calls “human cooperation” is evidence for the theological belief of human superiority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowak’s concept of human cooperation starts with the most obvious thing that sets humans apart from other living things. As of now, scientists have not discovered any other species that communicates using a language with specific grammatical rules. Nowak also notes the widespread human belief that “close relations have the highest social importance” and the fact that humans are “hopeful, generous, and forgiving” set humanity apart in the realm of communication. Since scientific evidence suggests that humanity carries these three unique communication traits due to evolution, Nowak suggests that evolution does not refute human superiority. Instead, he believes that the concept of evolution actually supports religious belief and provides an explanation for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many theologists believe that religious texts are best understood as metaphors that aid humanity in its understanding of higher powers. While science and religion can clash when religious texts are taken as fact, science peacefully coexists with metaphorical understandings of religious texts. If the creation of humanity is understood not as a fact but as a metaphor, evolution and religion can both easily find a place in the universe’s timeline. Nowak says that “to say science disproves God goes beyond what science really says.” As both a scientist and a religious man, he believes that relying solely on either science or religion to explain the world makes a person insatiable in their understanding of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.huffpost.com/entry/religion-and-science-can-coexist_n_974116&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2011 study&lt;/a&gt; at Rice University led by sociologist Elaine Ecklund revealed that about 70% of faculty members associated with science at research universities believed that science and religion are sometimes in conflict. In addition to polling research university faculty, Ecklund polled and interviewed hundreds of scientists. Her 5,000 pages of transcribed interviews reveal that overall, scientists believe that while some specific strains of religions and some specific religious people often clash with science, religion as a whole is usually able to successfully coexist with science. Scientists who did not believe religion and science could coexist usually had “a narrow view of religion, identifying it most with conservative strains of American evangelical Christianity” and not with other religions, or even other branches of Christianity. Scientists whose views of religion included other religions and “non-institutionalized spiritual practices, such as meditation” were likely to identify science and religion as compatible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the interview process, scientists were asked to review their religious colleagues. Many scientists reviewed their religious colleagues favorably, and some even cited scientists like Christian geneticist Francis Collins as examples that religious people can make good scientists. Ecklund’s findings agree with Nowak’s belief that science and religion both strive to make sense of the world in different ways and that both are “valid avenues of knowledge”. While the divisions in society created by conflict and religion cannot be completely fixed in the near future, the fact that many scientists believe that religion and science should be able to peacefully coexist is comforting and hopeful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Emily Richter)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Emily Richter&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Emily is a junior from Maria Carrillo High School in Sonoma County. She loves chemistry and the environmental sciences and plans to be an environmental chemist when she gets older. Through InterSTEM, she hopes to combine her experience in writing with her interest in STEM in order to help others enjoy and understand STEM. In her free time, she likes playing the flute, and baking and cooking.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Emily Richter</name></author><summary type="html">Can science and religion coexist? Emily Richter. 01/01/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/scienceAndReligionCover.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/scienceAndReligionCover.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Holidays and mental health</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/holidays-and-mental-health.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Holidays and mental health" /><published>2020-12-31T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-31T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/holidays-and-mental-health</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/holidays-and-mental-health.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Holidays and mental health&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Omar Dajani. 01/01/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/mentalHealthOne.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This infographic shows how many people are impacted by the ‘holidays blues’ yearly. &lt;a href=&quot;https://churchandmentalhealth.com/holiday-blues-infographic/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Church and Mental Health)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This holiday season, many of us were having fun celebrating and being safe around family. Many of us were likely enamored by the ‘holiday spirit,’ but some may have not felt very strongly towards this holiday. Part of the reason can be attributed to the ongoing COVID-19, but there are other causes that may contribute to this as well. One cause seems to be what is called the ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://ct.counseling.org/2019/12/positive-actions-to-prevent-the-holiday-blues/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;holiday blues&lt;/a&gt;,’ which are feelings of anxiety and depression that occur during the holidays. These feelings impact a person’s enjoyment of a holiday in a variety of negative ways, which may make them feel even worse. How does someone get these feelings, though? Is there a way to get rid of them? How is the current pandemic impacting the holiday blues, if at all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People may experience the holiday blues for a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/stress-management/in-depth/stress/art-20047544&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;variety of reasons&lt;/a&gt;, some of which include cooking that needs to be done, decorations that need to be bought, outfits that need to be coordinated, people that need to be seen, among many more. A person also may not be able to celebrate with family, and thus may &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.healthline.com/health/depression/holidays&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;compare themselves to others&lt;/a&gt; and feel as if they barely have anyone to be festive with as a result. All of these factors can cause a person to feel bad during the holiday season, which, as mentioned before, may lead to guilt for not enjoying a holiday. This only causes the holiday blues to become stronger. It is, effectively, a never-ending cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/mentalHealthTwo.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This picture illustrates some of the most common feelings of someone going through the ‘holiday blues.’ &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thefamuanonline.com/2020/12/05/how-to-cope-with-a-mental-illness-during-the-holidays/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(The Flinn Foundation)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As the picture at the top of this article illustrates, quite a large number of people experience holiday blues. This makes it so this issue has a sense of universality to it, as it seems like people from all walks of life can get the holiday blues. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mcleanhospital.org/essential/mcleans-guide-managing-mental-health-around-holidays&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;American Psychological Association&lt;/a&gt; conducted a survey asking people about how they feel during the holiday season. Around 38% of people surveyed said their stress increased during the holiday seasons, which shows how prominent this issue really is. In a strange way, remembering you are not alone in feeling this way may actually be very encouraging and helpful when it comes to not letting these feelings get to you. Knowing that there are others experiencing the same things you are can be reaffirming and comforting, even if the context behind why you are getting these emotional boosts can feel upsetting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is obvious that holiday blues is a problem, so how can you go about handling it? What else can you do besides remembering you are not alone? There are a &lt;a href=&quot;https://churchandmentalhealth.com/holiday-blues-infographic/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;variety of ways&lt;/a&gt;, including getting light exercise, trying to stick to your normal schedule as much as possible, eating in moderation, trying to set reasonable goals and making a budget when it comes to buying presents. It also helps to remind yourself how holidays are only temporary and that they will be over soon enough. The way you are feeling right now is not here to stay! Just because you experienced the holiday blues before does not necessarily mean you will experience them again later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, COVID-19 is its own problem when it comes to the holiday blues. Usually, people seem to get the holiday blues because they might feel as if &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.huffpost.com/entry/therapist-predict-holidays-mental-health_l_5fca573ec5b6787f2a977639&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;they are not doing enough&lt;/a&gt; to celebrate the holidays, or they are comparing themselves to other families and seeing how happy those families are. With the pandemic, people might get the holiday blues because they cannot see their families at all in the first place. They may want participate in the holiday festivities, but sadly cannot due to what is going on in the world. This puts a spin on how the holiday blues usually occur, and there is sadly no real solution to combat this specific problem. All people can do is remain safe and hope that next year’s holidays will not be like 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with the mindset that holidays blues is only temporary, it seems like the issue itself often repeats. It certainly helps that it only happens during holidays, but there is no proper way to get rid of the holiday blues once and for all. Every person is different, and a person who was unhappy during Christmas one year can be over the moon the next year. It seems to be based on context, which is why it is important for someone experiencing these types of feelings to do whatever they can to not let their holiday experience be ruined. If it does become very difficult to deal with, the option of calling a mental health professional is always available. There are ways to combat your holiday blues, as long as you try to be as proactive as possible and not let these feelings overwhelm you before you get the chance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sacmag.com/health/curing-the-holiday-blues/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Sacramento Magazine)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Omar Dajani&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Omar Dajani is an international student from Jerusalem, Palestine. He is currently a sophomore at Fullerton College in California. He has a passion for English as well as Computer Science. He enjoys gaming, blogging, journaling, meditating, and going on walks. He intends on transferring to UC Berkeley for Fall 2021.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Omar Dajani</name></author><summary type="html">Holidays and mental health Omar Dajani. 01/01/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/mentalHealthCover.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/mentalHealthCover.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>