<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-04-23T23:54:40-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">InterSTEM</title><entry><title type="html">The science behind note-taking: Preferences between handwriting and typing notes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/22/the-science-behind-note-taking.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The science behind note-taking: Preferences between handwriting and typing notes" /><published>2021-04-22T17:00:03-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-22T17:00:03-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/22/the-science-behind-note-taking</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/22/the-science-behind-note-taking.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The science behind note-taking: Preferences between handwriting and typing notesh&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nadwa Atwi. 04/23/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking notes is one of the most important parts of the learning process. Students often spend a lot of time considering how to take notes, only to end up choosing a technique unfit for the material they’re tackling. So here we’ll be covering the pros and cons of each and discussing the right font-color combination for ideal note-taking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Comparison&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. Accuracy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to accuracy, typing certainly wins out as it’s much faster to type than to write something down. However, this definitely depends on the material one is taking notes on. If it demands that notes be taken down verbatim then transcribing the lecturer’s speech, this would call for a laptop. But it’s very important to note that taking down notes in the form of a transcript isn’t effective for all subjects. A study was conducted by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychologicalscience.org/news/releases/take-notes-by-hand-for-better-long-term-comprehension.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;psychology scientists Pam Mueller and Daniel Oppenheimer&lt;/a&gt; in which students were asked to write down notes on a number of TED talks using the method that they normally used to take notes. The results showed that although the two types of note-takers did equally well on questions that required facts-citation, laptop note-takers performed particularly worse on the conceptual questions. That made the scientists suggest that students who took down handwritten notes were involved in more information processing than laptop users. As a result, they sorted through the information and opted for the more relevant ones to add to their notes. Additionally, the study suggests that writing by hand improves memory retention and understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conclusion was that students who took more notes scored higher on the test, but that also applied to those who had less verbatim overlap. This proposes that unconscious transcription nullifies the advantage of having more content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. Legibility, organization and accessibility&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typing notes on a laptop offers a more aesthetic structure, easier editing and instant spelling check. So laptop users have the advantage of not having to worry about bad handwriting or making a mess of their notes when they make a mistake. While sharing handwritten notes could be a hassle, sharing digital notes is a piece of cake. Not to mention syncing them across devices makes them accessible anytime and anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3. Distractions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ease and simplicity laptops offer come at a price. Although the extra tools and resources they provide save the note-taker the inconveniences that other note-takers face, that also means more distractions. For example, many people cannot resist checking social media while they’re in a lecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studies also show that the laptop user is not the only one affected by those distractions. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gse.harvard.edu/news/uk/17/08/note-taking-low-tech-often-best&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Harvard University&lt;/a&gt;, researchers at York and McMaster conducted an experiment in which they had students watch a lecture and then take a comprehension test. Some students were randomly asked to carry out a couple of short tasks on their laptops during the lecture, like looking up movie times. The rest of the students were allowed to focus on the lecture. All seats were randomly assigned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, the multitasking students scored about 11% lower on the test than those who focused on the lecture. But interestingly, the students sitting near the multitaskers also got affected. Students who weren’t multitasking but could view the screen of a multitasker’s laptop scored 17% lower on comprehension than those who had no distracting view. So it’s important to note that by choosing typing as a method of note-taking, one could potentially distract those around them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Factors to consider when deciding which method to use when taking notes:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. The type of learning that is called for&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://effectiviology.com/handwriting-vs-typing-how-to-take-notes/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Effectiviology&lt;/a&gt;, note-taking through typing works better when the material requires factual learning, which involves memorizing specific details and merely entails a shallow understanding of the material. However, conceptual learning, which involves securing a rigorous understanding of the fundamental concepts in the material, calls for taking notes manually by hand.
On that account, the student must first determine the kind of material they’re dealing with and choose the note-taking method accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. The length and type of notes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another aspect a student should take into consideration is the length of the text they’ll eventually end up with. Writing notes down by hand proves to be a physically exhausting method when there’s a lot to write down, and of course, there’s a certain limit to how fast a person can write. Consequently, this method demands the note-taker to be more concise, which can be convenient since it means that only the more relevant aspects of the material are included in the notes. But the student could also end up leaving out significant details in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, typing notes allows the student to write more details, as typing is a faster process than writing. This definitely comes in handy when there are lots of points to cover. However, it’s crucial to note that there’s the disadvantage of writing too much that the unnecessary details end up overriding the important ones. That makes it more difficult to study the notes at a later time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, this depends on the type of learning that we previously discussed.
Another point worth mentioning is the type of notes the student is taking. For example, mathematical formulas are definitely faster to write down than to type. The same thing applies to sketching and labeling figures, as handwritten notes allow more freedom with the graphics and thus are more flexible in that aspect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Font color&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something that applies to both handwritten and typed notes is the font color. Color is a form of visible light, essentially a portion of the electromagnetic spectrum. Each color has its own wavelength that can affect neurological pathways in the brain, creating a biochemical response. Consequently, using the right color, along with the right selection and arrangement, can have a significant impact on feelings, concentration and behavior when learning. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://effectiviology.com/handwriting-vs-typing-how-to-take-notes/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Shift Learning&lt;/a&gt;, although it isn’t definite science, each color can elicit its own unique biological response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green promotes tranquility and calm and improves concentration, as it’s a low-frequency color. In a study led by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smh.com.au/technology/seeing-green-boosts-your-concentration-research-shows-20150525-gh8udh.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dr. Kate Lee&lt;/a&gt;, 150 university students were given a tedious task, which involved pressing a key as a series of numbers repeatedly flashed on a computer screen. They were asked not to press the key when the number three popped up on the screen. The students were given a short break halfway through the task to look at a city rooftop scene. Half of the students looked at a green roof whereas the other half viewed a bare concrete roof. After the break, students who looked at the greener scenery made considerably fewer errors and showed better concentration than those who viewed the concrete roof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orange is a mood lifter and a stimulator, as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scienceofpeople.com/color-psychology/#:~:text=Orange%20is%20a%20color%20of,effect,%20and%20stimulates%20brain%20activity.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;it has been found&lt;/a&gt; to increase oxygen supply to the brain, producing an energizing effect. It is best used for highlighting and accentuating certain parts in notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blue promotes productivity. Some research suggests that people with particularly intellectual work like programmers and academics are more productive in the presence of blue surroundings. Blue is best used for learning situations that are challenging and ones that require substantial comprehension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/notetakingOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;A student highlights words in different colors. &lt;a href=&quot;https://study.com/blog/5-tips-for-color-coding-your-notes.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Study)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;The verdict&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to the learning method, it all comes down to preference! And the type of material one is dealing with. Both techniques have their pros and cons, but if the material equally allows for either method to be used, then writing by hand is surely the way to go because it allows learners to comprehend and retain information better than typing does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s also worth mentioning is the fact that recently, tablets have become the go-to device for students, as it bears some of the best aspects of both methods: handwritten notes that can be easily organized and shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding the font color, notes shouldn’t be kept too monochrome, so it is best to use blue along with one or two other colors. In any case, trial and error is key so remember to stay open-minded and try out different techniques with different materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.psu.edu/siowfa16/2016/10/18/notes-by-hand-or-laptop/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Penn State)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Nadwa Atwi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Nadwa Atwi</name></author><summary type="html">The science behind note-taking: Preferences between handwriting and typing notesh Nadwa Atwi. 04/23/2021 Taking notes is one of the most important parts of the learning process. Students often spend a lot of time considering how to take notes, only to end up choosing a technique unfit for the material they’re tackling. So here we’ll be covering the pros and cons of each and discussing the right font-color combination for ideal note-taking.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/notetakingCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/notetakingCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dopamine: The molecule that drives addiction</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/22/dopamine-the-molecule-that-drives-addiction.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dopamine: The molecule that drives addiction" /><published>2021-04-22T17:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-22T17:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/22/dopamine-the-molecule-that-drives-addiction</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/22/dopamine-the-molecule-that-drives-addiction.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Dopamine: The molecule that drives addiction
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arul Loomba . 04/23/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/dopamineOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Dopamine is a neurotransmitter that is released into the brain’s reward system (right) and is released into cells (left) initiating a response. Often, an increase in the release of dopamine creates a feeling of pleasure.
(Getty Images / Verywell Health)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The brain craves pleasure. Going on a vacation, jumping out of a plane or even taking a bite of ice cream stimulates the action of billions of neurons - the cells in our brains that send signals throughout our body to do everything from helping us walk to reading a book. There is one chemical that does consistent and important signaling using the brain’s neurons, especially when it comes to sending information about pleasure: the neurotransmitter &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencenewsforstudents.org/article/explainer-what-dopamine&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;dopamine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/topics/neuroscience/nucleus-accumbens&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Neurotransmitters&lt;/a&gt; are small molecules that neurons use to communicate with one another, and they help elicit certain responses like happiness from opening a gift. They also play a substantial role in our everyday actions, including moving, running and most importantly, thinking. Dopamine, a significant neurotransmitter in the brain, influences emotional activity and response. For example, it stimulates the brain so people can concentrate on certain enjoyable actions and ignore those that don’t provide the same feeling. The molecule acts on the brain’s reward system, a neuronal pathway in the brain used for transmitting emotions; when doing an activity that brings pleasure, the reward system creates feelings of joy and craving. After the consistent release of these emotions, a person’s attention span will change: “You can’t pay attention to everything, but you want to be adept as an organism at recognizing things that are novel,” Director of the National Institute of Drug Abuse &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/4001507&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nora D. Volkow&lt;/a&gt; said. Dopamine is a chemical that allows a person to concentrate on novel and attractive things - ones that we hope to receive pleasure from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, dopamine plays a significant role in motivating a person to participate in pleasurable activities. This can range from exercising to watching a movie - anything that prolongs the release of dopamine. While many times this prolongation can be healthy (as a source of motivation and effort), too much of anything can have a dark side: uncontrolled amounts of dopamine are the primary cause of drug addiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent study by Dr. Volkow illustrates that drug abuse is associated with the increased “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/27/science/27angier.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;intensity and duration&lt;/a&gt;” of dopamine release. Street drugs like opiates and cocaine are major drivers of addiction because they increase the concentration of dopamine that cells put out. These drugs inhibit the natural mechanisms the body has to maintain balance, which in this case regulates dopamine concentration, providing the users with a burst of satisfaction or “high.” The mechanisms that keep the levels of dopamine under control involve proteins that take excess dopamine out of circulation. By imitating the shape of the molecular repressors that inhibit reuptake proteins, drugs can have a significant effect. Long-term consequences of inhibition, include the brain growing accustomed to greater concentrations of dopamine. Moreover, in many cases, this environmental change can result in the brain stopping the natural release of dopamine, creating a reliance on drugs to maintain its concentration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discovery that drug addiction stems from the increased presence of dopamine in the brain also has significant treatment implications. Frequent drug users often rely on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5171207/%23:~:text%3DThe%2520incentive%252Dsensitization%2520theory%2520posits,an%2520amplification%2520of%2520%27liking%27.&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1619249325183000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw3msOfZe9-ITtTf6UVBcdt3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;euphoric feeling&lt;/a&gt; that dopamine provides to fuel their addiction - it gives them “motivation” to abuse certain substances. Volkow’s research opens up new treatment options for these addicts. For example, creating new medications that limit the dopamine “reward” that addicts feel from abused drugs can effectively eliminate the cause of addiction. Once available frequently, these treatments could be combined with rehab and therapy to encourage addicts to seek rewards from alternative sources like exercise or positive social interactions. Dopamine is naturally released at times of excitement, so gaining this in other ways would stimulate the normal neuronal pathways, and not ones related to drugs. These simple, yet important solutions, are key to fixing a problem present in many developing communities around the world. The safest, most effective way to address the issue would be changing its source: availability and composition drugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volkow is optimistic about the implications of her research: “Our findings suggest that interventions designed to enhance [dopamine] brain function in drug abusers,” noting that none of this will be successful unless treatment can “provide them with non-drug alternatives” with the ultimate goal to “help the addicted subject overcome the strong drive to take the drug.” With new treatments, the brain’s craving can be overcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Getty Images / Stock Photo)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Arul Loomba&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Arul is currently a sophomore at Rancho Cucamonga High School in California. He has a deep passion for biomedicine and is looking to pursue regenerative medicine in the future. Currently, he is trying to research articles and data collected by many professors to formulate his theories and ideas! Arul is also a fan of cooking, playing tennis, and writing.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Arul Loomba</name></author><summary type="html">Dopamine: The molecule that drives addiction Arul Loomba . 04/23/2021 Dopamine is a neurotransmitter that is released into the brain’s reward system (right) and is released into cells (left) initiating a response. Often, an increase in the release of dopamine creates a feeling of pleasure. (Getty Images / Verywell Health) The brain craves pleasure. Going on a vacation, jumping out of a plane or even taking a bite of ice cream stimulates the action of billions of neurons - the cells in our brains that send signals throughout our body to do everything from helping us walk to reading a book. There is one chemical that does consistent and important signaling using the brain’s neurons, especially when it comes to sending information about pleasure: the neurotransmitter dopamine.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/dopamineCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/dopamineCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Social media and its effects on mental health</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/22/social-media-and-its-effects-on-mental-health.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Social media and its effects on mental health" /><published>2021-04-22T17:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-22T17:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/22/social-media-and-its-effects-on-mental-health</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/22/social-media-and-its-effects-on-mental-health.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Social media and its effects on mental health&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rheigina Quijote. 04/23/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/socialMediaOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;In this age of social networking, there are many platforms that lead to the decline of mental health for adolescents and adults.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/chart/19262/impact-of-social-media-on-mental-health/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Statista)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In today’s world, social media plays an active role in the mental health of an individual. Throughout our lives, humans seek interaction with others since being social can foster positivity in a person. But during this era of technology and growing digital interaction, social media has made its way into everyone’s daily lives. Social media brings exposure to all users, as a craving for attention is now an active figure in the lives of many. What is regarded as a source of entertainment and a form of efficient communication for humans is also the source of increasing mental illness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A research article by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Shabir-Bhat/publication/323018957_Effects_of_Social_Media_on_Mental_Health_A_Review/links/5a7c9e97aca272341aeb7472/Effects-of-Social-Media-on-Mental-Health-A-Review.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the International Journal of Indian Psychology&lt;/a&gt; states that similarly to the human body, which seeks nutrition, the human mind seeks to be nurtured by thoughts. As social media life separates a person from others in the real world, it affects their mental health and social interaction. The journal found that the younger generation is more susceptible at an embryonic stage of their life. This indicates that because the youth is more easily swayed and most active on social media, they are at a larger risk of serious mental health effects. By being easily influenced by social media, they’re exposed to situations of bullying and comparing themselves with others online. Online activity has become an essential part of daily life, and while it does contain its benefits like an increase in communication, it can strongly impact the well-being of its users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media is known to cause an increase in anxiety and depression as stated by the International Journal of Indian Psychology. About 45% of British adults have felt restlessness because of a lack of accessing social media sites. The same was found with adolescents. Adolescents are unable to decipher the difference between a notification they receive and one someone else does, a condition known as phantom vibration syndrome. There is a positive correlation between social media and mental health: the longer you spend on social media the more likely you are at risk of depression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another look at the topic at hand is the current global situation of COVID-19. Because of the virus outbreak, people are forced to live in isolated circumstances, which leads to a rise in technological use. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id%3D10.1371/journal.pone.0231924&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1619248925761000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw0-TYccMD_hzv4rzkOYRw4S&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Plos One&lt;/a&gt; brings an insight into mental health problems and their association with social media exposure during COVID-19. By conducting their experiment and surveying the results, it is shown that because of  COVID-19, a rise in misinformation through social media has been an underlying effect of increasing mental illness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their investigation, they examined 4,872 Chinese citizens under 18 through online surveys. It was found that about 48% were depressed, 22% had anxiety and 19% had a combination of the two. Shown from the data, it’s believed social media exposure was associated with high anxiety within individuals, and the increase of social media exposure, in general, was due to the COVID outbreak. From this extended use of social media, it was concluded that misinformation that was fueled by social media was an indirect cause of anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study had the participants report any experience of positivity in the last two weeks and those that scored less than 13 on their 6-point scale represented depression. Similarly, their study over anxiety had initially the same rating scale where they reported signs of anxiousness during the last two weeks. Those with scores greater than one were assumed to have an anxiety disorder. They determined social media uses by how often the respondents had seen news or information regarding COVID-19 on social media. In the results, the increase of social media exposure corresponded to increased odds of depression as was with anxiety and the combination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, the two main reasons to describe the association of social media exposure and mental health is the misinformation in social media, not only the COVID outbreak but in this generation overall. This is likely because of the lack of privacy and expectancy of attention of users that the increase of self unimportance or anxiousness. As a way to prevent such problems and help those who have felt as such, both research articles and studies encourage seeking professional counseling and user age restrictions. In hopes of enlightening others on the harms that social media may cause to one’s health and for your benefit and growth, monitor and limit your time around the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (The Digital Age)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Rheigina Quijote&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Rheigina Quijote</name></author><summary type="html">Social media and its effects on mental health Rheigina Quijote. 04/23/2021 In this age of social networking, there are many platforms that lead to the decline of mental health for adolescents and adults. (Statista) In today’s world, social media plays an active role in the mental health of an individual. Throughout our lives, humans seek interaction with others since being social can foster positivity in a person. But during this era of technology and growing digital interaction, social media has made its way into everyone’s daily lives. Social media brings exposure to all users, as a craving for attention is now an active figure in the lives of many. What is regarded as a source of entertainment and a form of efficient communication for humans is also the source of increasing mental illness.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/socialMediaCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/socialMediaCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Kepler-452b: An Earth-like planet light-years away from us</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/15/kepler-452b-an-earth-like-planet-light-years-away-from-us.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kepler-452b: An Earth-like planet light-years away from us" /><published>2021-04-15T17:00:03-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-15T17:00:03-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/15/kepler-452b-an-earth-like%20planet-light-years-away-from-us</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/15/kepler-452b-an-earth-like-planet-light-years-away-from-us.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Kepler-452b: An Earth-like planet light-years away from us&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Bui. 04/16/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/keplerOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Above is an image of Kepler-452b.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gettyimages.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Getty Images)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://exoplanets.nasa.gov/exoplanet-catalog/5471/kepler-452-b/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Kepler-452b&lt;/a&gt; is a planet that exists light-years away from us. The planet can and most likely once did support life. But what exactly does this planet have to offer? Are there any downsides that may disrupt the possibility of the planet supporting life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin with, Kepler-452b is an &lt;a href=&quot;https://exoplanets.nasa.gov/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;exoplanet&lt;/a&gt; located 1,402 light-years away from Earth. Its appearance is similar to Earth, having an atmosphere, water and land. And similar to how the Earth has the sun, Kepler-452b orbits around Kepler-452, a star 6 billion years old, which is pretty old in comparison to the solar system’s sun, aged 4.5 billion years. But Kepler-452 has around the same temperature as the sun, which can support the idea that Kepler-452b can still harbor life. Whether or not it has a moon is unknown as of now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it may sound bizarre that Kepler-452b and Earth are similar, it’s true. Other than the facts stated previously, what other aspects do both planets have? First off, water. Last year, water was discovered on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-02751-1#:~:text=The%20discovery%2C%20reported%20on%2028,orbiting%20spacecraft%2C%20called%20Mars%20Express.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mars&lt;/a&gt;. This was a huge discovery because it hints that Mars once supported life. But Kepler-452b is an especially unique case because it has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.space.com/30034-earth-cousin-exoplanet-kepler-452b-life.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;lakes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.space.com/30034-earth-cousin-exoplanet-kepler-452b-life.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;rivers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.space.com/30034-earth-cousin-exoplanet-kepler-452b-life.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;pools&lt;/a&gt;. There were once oceans, but unfortunately, all of them have dried up. Unlike &lt;a href=&quot;https://coolcosmos.ipac.caltech.edu/ask/80-Can-we-breathe-on-Mars-#:~:text=Mars%20does%20have%20an%20atmosphere,with%20oxygen%20to%20work%20outdoors.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mars&lt;/a&gt;, the atmosphere might be actually breathable. The air on Mars is 100 times thinner than that of Earth, compared to Kepler-452b where the air is pretty similar to that of Earth. However, this topic is still in &lt;a href=&quot;https://education.abc.net.au/newsandarticles/blog/-/b/3345118/curious-kids-could-humans-live-on-kepler-452-b&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;debate&lt;/a&gt; because we do not know what is in the air, especially if there is something more dangerous in it than Earth’s nitrogen and oxygen. The temperature on Kepler-452b is slightly &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kepler-452b#:~:text=The%20planet%20takes%20385%20Earth,a%20little%20warmer%20than%20Earth.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;warmer&lt;/a&gt; than Earth but is still as livable as a warm day on Earth. The appearance, as mentioned, is almost exactly the same. The majority of the outside view is blue, indicating water, with patches of land. Both orbit around a star that is roughly the same temperature and have clouds. But just because they are similar in a handful of aspects doesn’t mean Kepler-452b is Earth. In fact, they are pretty different in quite a few ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off, the sun of Kepler-452b or Kepler-452contrasts with our sun. Kepler-452 is also 20% brighter than the sun, as well as 11% larger. The terrain of Kepler-452b is rocky, which is different from Earth’s variety of landforms. Not only are the landforms bigger, Kepler-452b is actually &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/press-release/nasa-kepler-mission-discovers-bigger-older-cousin-to-earth/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;60%&lt;/a&gt; larger in diameter, meaning it is 1.6 times bigger than Earth. The gigantic size difference between both planet and exoplanet is what gives Kepler-452b the title of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://exoplanets.nasa.gov/what-is-an-exoplanet/planet-types/super-earth/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Super-Earth&lt;/a&gt;. The exoplanet is also rather massive, having &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kepler-452b#:~:text=Kepler%2D452b%20has%20a%20probable,exoplanets%20are%20only%20rough%20estimates.&amp;amp;text=Its%20radius%20is%2050%25%20bigger,zone%20of%20its%20parent%20star.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;5 times&lt;/a&gt; as much mass as the Earth. The surface gravity is about 2 times as much as the gravity on Earth, resulting in jumping being twice as hard. A complete revolution on the Earth, 365 days, is considered a year. For Kepler-452b however, it takes &lt;a href=&quot;https://exoplanets.nasa.gov/resources/282/comparison-between-earth-and-kepler-452b-and-their-host-stars/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;385&lt;/a&gt; days to complete a full revolution around its star, resulting in a 385 day year. Earth has “only” existed for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalgeographic.org/topics/resource-library-age-earth/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;4.54&lt;/a&gt; billion years, but Kepler-452b is estimated to have the age of &lt;a href=&quot;https://exoplanets.nasa.gov/exoplanet-catalog/5471/kepler-452-b/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt; billion!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kepler-452b is by no means Earth. Earth has all of our needs: natural fruits and vegetables, food sources such as meat, oceans for trade— the full bundle. Kepler-452b has a handful of that. Whether or not Kepler-452b has life or had life is not known yet. The question of whether humans can live on this planet, even if they did bring their own supply, is in debate. The temperature is nice, sure, but is the environment habitable? Will the air have any metals that are potentially lethal or just not safe? Can it really harbor human life? The short answer for this is yes, no, maybe so. We do not know if the planet has everything we need, but one thing can be sure: it comes really close to that point, with water, land, weather and all. Maybe someday in the future, we’ll know for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, Kepler-452b is more or less similar to Earth. In fact, there are dozens upon dozens of Kepler planets! Kepler is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/kepler/overview/index.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;NASA mission&lt;/a&gt; to discover hundreds of Earth-like planets, and to this point up to 24 potential exoplanets may be even better than the conditions of Earth, but of all of them Kepler-452b will always be one of the likeliest candidates, and for good reason too! However, although all these amazing planets have been found, remember that they are not in our solar system, and by no means within reach. Being thousands of light-years is too far for human travel, and all purposes of looking for them are merely to answer the question “Are we alone in this universe?” or “Are there others like us?”. So even though planets as amazing as Kepler-452b and all of the other exoplanets are out there, the chance of actually inhabiting one of the candidates is near impossible. However, it is important to know that somewhere out there, such an amazing planet actually exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (NASA / Ames / JPL-Caltech)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Peter Bui&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Peter Bui</name></author><summary type="html">Kepler-452b: An Earth-like planet light-years away from us Peter Bui. 04/16/2021 Above is an image of Kepler-452b. (Getty Images) Kepler-452b is a planet that exists light-years away from us. The planet can and most likely once did support life. But what exactly does this planet have to offer? Are there any downsides that may disrupt the possibility of the planet supporting life?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/keplerCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/keplerCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The genius of Bitcoin, a revolutionary currency</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/08/the-genius-of-bitcoin-a-revolutionary-currency.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The genius of Bitcoin, a revolutionary currency" /><published>2021-04-08T17:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-08T17:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/08/the-genius-of-bitcoin-a-revolutionary-currency</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/08/the-genius-of-bitcoin-a-revolutionary-currency.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The genius of Bitcoin, a revolutionary currency&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rachel Huang. 04/09/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/btcOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The high stakes involved with Bitcoin have only made its value soar higher than ever before. &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/four-factors-driving-the-price-of-bitcoin-87244&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(The Conversation)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Launched in 2009 from the anonymous Satoshi Nakamoto’s whitepaper, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/b/bitcoin.asp&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bitcoin&lt;/a&gt; (BTC) was created to be an electronic payment system “based on cryptographic proof instead of trust.” Bitcoin is now the world’s largest cryptocurrency (digital currency) with an astonishing value of over $55,000 for a single coin and is also the first application of blockchain technology, an innovative creation that allows it to be distributed, traded and stored. A blockchain is essentially a collection of “blocks,” files that record all of the transactions that occur, making them transparent and visible to all of the computers that run Bitcoin’s code and store its blockchain. The creation of Bitcoin has united thousands of people around the world over a common goal: obtaining bitcoin and turning a profit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are currently 12,000 computers connected to Bitcoin’s blockchain; these computers are called nodes, while the owners of the computers are called miners - the miners control Bitcoin’s release into circulation via a process called Bitcoin mining and are rewarded with coins adding blocks to the blockchain. Bitcoin mining requires the solving of complex computational puzzles in order to discover a new block, and expensive mining rigs (elaborate mining processors and hardware) increase a miner’s ability to earn more rewards. Mining rigs are available for purchase in the form of computer chips like Application-Specific Integrated Circuits (ASIC) and Graphic Processing Units (GPUs). All of these Bitcoin transactions are verified by cryptographic proof, making the system very secure. For example, a person with malicious intent would need to operate 51% of the total computing power that makes up Bitcoin to cheat the system. With miners acting as Bitcoin’s decentralized authority, miners are motivated to add to the growing blockchain because of the prospect of reward, and the blockchain benefits by growing and developing even more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While David Zeiler, cryptocurrency expert for Money Morning, describes Bitcoin as “the best-known crypto and a secure, decentralized currency that has become a store of value like gold,” there may be more exaggeration than truth in his statement. The long-term security that Zeiler describes only refers to Bitcoin’s official certification and verifiability, not Bitcoin’s prices. Cryptocurrency is a highly speculative investment, with the potential for intense price swings, or as described in the words of CEO of Digital Currency Group Barry Silbert, “It is pretty much the highest-risk, highest-return investment that you can possibly make.” As a safeguard against these risks, it is highly recommended that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/advisor/investing/what-is-cryptocurrency/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;investors&lt;/a&gt; trade on official cryptocurrency exchanges, such as Coin base and Bitfinex. Potential investors and traders are enticed by Bitcoin’s high exchange rate, lower transaction fees and instant payments that are a result of its “peer-to-peer” technology that grants instant rewards. In addition, Bitcoin can also be exchanged for traditional currencies and act as an alternative to national fiat money and traditional commodities like gold. The overall success of Bitcoin has triggered the release of a slew of other cryptocurrencies, amounting to over 5,000 different types released into circulation, collectively referred to as altcoins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As another facet of its multipurpose nature, Bitcoin can also be used to buy things! Bitcoin can be split into smaller units to make transactions easier - the common unit of Bitcoin used in everyday transactions is called the Satoshi, which is 100 millionths of a Bitcoin, currently worth approximately 0.02 cents. In response to the growing Bitcoin community, many retailers have begun to accept bitcoin with the proper hardware terminal and/or wallet address through QR codes and touch screen apps. Keys are the main form of hardware terminal through which Bitcoin can be transferred: there are public and private keys, both of which are long strings of numbers and letters linked through the mathematical encryption algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/btcTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;An example of Bitcoin’s private and public keys.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://coinsource.net/private-keys-public-keys-addresses-and-wallets/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Coinsource)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A &lt;a href=&quot;https://coinsource.net/private-keys-public-keys-addresses-and-wallets/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;public&lt;/a&gt; key’s address is published to the world and others may send bitcoins to it as necessary. On the other hand, private keys are a guarded secret and only used to authorize personal bitcoin transmissions. Keys increase Bitcoin’s liquidity by making Bitcoins less like stocks and more like cash because the private keys needed to authorize spending can be printed out and stored physically. Stores may also accept Bitcoin wallets, a physical or digital device that facilitates the trading of bitcoin and allows users to track ownership of coins with a software program that interacts with the blockchain, allowing users to exchange the currency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin’s appeal has been greatly increasing in recent years, especially because Bitcoin quickly approaches its approvable max of 21 million bitcoin. With a current count of about 18,614,806 in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/tech/what-happens-bitcoin-after-21-million-mined/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;circulation&lt;/a&gt;, there are only about 3 million Bitcoins left to be mined. This makes it seem like Bitcoin will run out soon, sending miners and investors into a frenzy. However, this is not the case because rewards are halved for every 210,000 blocks added to Bitcoin’s blockchain; the current reward for each block discovery has become a meager 6.25 bitcoins (of course, if you take into account the value of a single Bitcoin, then the overall value of the reward is greater than ever). If you think about how a store of 3 million Bitcoins gets depleted by withdrawals of 6.25 bitcoins, you will understand how, in reality, Bitcoin will actually “run out” in around 2140.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin continues to be the leader and definer of the cryptocurrency value cycle; the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/investor/2021/02/12/bitcoin-price-prediction-2021-where-is-the-top/?sh=31480e9c3ed0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;prices&lt;/a&gt; of bitcoin and Ethereum (another cryptocurrency) are currently riding a FOMO-driven high, going almost vertical. The direction and stability of these high prices are very unpredictable, or, in the words of Clem Chambers, “a week is now a long time in crypto” due to its extreme volatility. Investors can monitor transaction fees as a sign of Bitcoin’s upcoming value - transaction fees are now exorbitant; when transaction fees start to fall it will be a signal that the FOMO is falling, and the prices will drop. For now though, the fees continue to rapidly increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/btcThree.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Google Trends shows interest in bitcoin, Ethereum, DeFi (decentralized finance) and stocks.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/investor/2021/02/12/bitcoin-price-prediction-2021-where-is-the-top/?sh=31480e9c3ed0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Forbes)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As a child of the 21st century, Bitcoin is, and will no doubt continue to be at the forefront of the digital currency revolution. Versatile and secure, investable and ever-expanding, Satoshi Nakamoto’s application of blockchain technology has blossomed into proportions that must have been unimaginable before its creation. Microsoft, Home Depot, Burger King, Starbucks: all of these major retailers have started the movement of accepting Bitcoin and other forms of cryptocurrency as a form of payment. Who knows? One day, Bitcoin may become the new dollar bill - as liquid as cash, and accepted anywhere and everywhere. Only time will tell how the wonders of Bitcoin and its siblings will transform the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://coingeek.com/bitcoin-sv-rallies-as-world-record-638mb-block-is-mined/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Coingeek)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Rachel Huang&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Rachel Huang</name></author><summary type="html">The genius of Bitcoin, a revolutionary currency Rachel Huang. 04/09/2021 The high stakes involved with Bitcoin have only made its value soar higher than ever before. (The Conversation) Launched in 2009 from the anonymous Satoshi Nakamoto’s whitepaper, Bitcoin (BTC) was created to be an electronic payment system “based on cryptographic proof instead of trust.” Bitcoin is now the world’s largest cryptocurrency (digital currency) with an astonishing value of over $55,000 for a single coin and is also the first application of blockchain technology, an innovative creation that allows it to be distributed, traded and stored. A blockchain is essentially a collection of “blocks,” files that record all of the transactions that occur, making them transparent and visible to all of the computers that run Bitcoin’s code and store its blockchain. The creation of Bitcoin has united thousands of people around the world over a common goal: obtaining bitcoin and turning a profit.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/btcCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/btcCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Purple sea urchins and California’s kelp forests</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/08/purple-sea-urchins-and-california's-kelp-forests.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Purple sea urchins and California’s kelp forests" /><published>2021-04-08T17:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-08T17:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/08/purple-sea-urchins-and-california's-kelp-forests</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/08/purple-sea-urchins-and-california's-kelp-forests.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Purple sea urchins and California's kelp forests&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sydney Hollingsworth. 04/16/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/urchinOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Where a kelp forest once stood, a “purple carpet” of sea urchins now covers the seafloor.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2021/03/31/975800880/in-hotter-climate-zombie-urchins-are-winning-and-kelp-forests-are-losing&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Steve Lonhart / NOAA Monterey Bay National Marine Sanctuary)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The waters along the Californian coast contain a rich variety of marine life. From seals to colorful crustaceans to whales, thousands of species make their homes in the reefs and kelp forests near the rocky beaches of North America.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, a common theme among delicately balanced ecosystems around the world is the threat of destruction posed by human activities, and California’s marine landscape is no exception. The towering underwater forests, composed of 60 feet tall &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.montereybayaquarium.org/animals/animals-a-to-z/bull-kelp&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;bull kelp&lt;/a&gt; stems, are facing annihilation at the hands of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.montereybayaquarium.org/animals/animals-a-to-z/purple-sea-urchin&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;purple sea urchin&lt;/a&gt; population, which has swung wildly out of control and decimated 95% of California’s kelp forests since 2014.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unlike most other situations where an organism introduced by humans outcompetes an entire ecosystem, the purple sea urchin is actually &lt;a href=&quot;https://goldenstate.is/culling-excess-sea-urchin-to-save-southern-california-kelp-beds/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;native to California&lt;/a&gt;, not an invasive species. This means there is still hope that balance can be reestablished without the removal of the purple sea urchin entirely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The emergence of this problem can be traced all the way back to the 1800s, when sea otters, a main predator of the purple sea urchin, were hunted nearly to extinction for their waterproof skins. More recently, a toxic algal bloom in 2011 killed off many marine species, including the sunflower sea star. Additionally, the sea stars were threatened further in 2013 by a mysterious “&lt;a href=&quot;https://marine.ucsc.edu/data-products/sea-star-wasting/index.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;sea star wasting syndrome&lt;/a&gt;”, which causes the stars to decay and lose their limbs, eventually resulting in death. With its 20 limbs and large diameter of up to one meter, the sunflower sea star was once a fearsome predator of the purple sea urchin but is currently considered critically endangered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another factor contributing to the declining bull kelp population is global warming. Increasingly common heat waves since 2014 mean a less nutrient-rich water supply for all marine life, including the annually released bull kelp spores. The warmer temperatures may also worsen the effects of sea star wasting syndrome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Together, these events have resulted in less than favorable conditions for the keystone species that is the bull kelp and created a virtually predator-free environment for the purple sea urchin. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/2021/03/31/975800880/in-hotter-climate-zombie-urchins-are-winning-and-kelp-forests-are-losing&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Urchin barrens&lt;/a&gt; are vast areas where thick kelp forests have been completely replaced by sea urchins. The hordes of spikey bodies cover the seafloor with what has been called a “purple carpet”, as the healthy number of 2 urchins per square meter has been replaced by 70 individuals in the same space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the California Department of Fish and Wildlife (CDFW), if the bull kelp spores cannot set for more than three years in a row, the forests could &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.com/travel/story/20200310-the-sea-urchin-combatting-the-effects-of-climate-change&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;disappear completely&lt;/a&gt;, and take countless species with them. Besides providing food and shelter for marine life, bull kelp also help control wave activity and reduce coastal erosion. Thus, its disappearance would endanger marine life, as well as harm local commercial fishers and economies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Luckily, marine biologists believe this problem is fixable, and with the right efforts, the purple sea urchin population can be regulated and bull kelp forests can be returned to their former glory.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The main plan of many organizations involved in the bull kelp conservation effort is to remove purple sea urchins by hand until their natural predators can be rehabilitated. Purple sea urchins are edible, and quite delicious when prepared correctly. Urchin removal projects often obtain funding from selling harvested urchins to restaurants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, one problem with this plan is that due to their abundance, most purple urchins are underfed and far too small to compare to the more favorable red sea urchin, which is considerably larger. To find a solution to this, researchers at the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/thesalt/2019/09/09/756929657/saving-californias-kelp-forest-may-depend-on-eating-purple-sea-urchins&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Moss Landing Marine Laboratories Center of Aquaculture&lt;/a&gt; tried feeding captured purple urchins red algae, which helped them grow to market size in just eight weeks. This means purple sea urchins can be captured, fed, and sold to restaurants, all while giving the bull kelp forests a chance to grow back.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The second-largest setback purple sea urchin harvesting groups have encountered is that sea urchin is not a very popular dish, particularly in California. Some organizations, such as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.urchinomics.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Urchinomics&lt;/a&gt;, a Norway-based company that faces a similar problem, ship their urchins to Japan, where urchin gonads, called uni, make a popular dish that tastes similar to the oyster.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, shipping to international markets does not even start to cover all the purple sea urchins that must be removed to restore California’s marine ecosystem. Without local markets, the urchins will end up as compost, and conservation efforts will lose funding opportunities to continue their projects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though the removal of hundreds of millions of purple sea urchins may seem like a substantial feat, most researchers and volunteers agree that it is very plausible if we act soon. In addition, helping restore California’s kelp forests doesn’t have to feel like a chore; trying new foods and supporting small restaurants can benefit everyone involved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With so many crises beyond the control of individuals, especially regarding the current biodiversity crisis, it’s always good to hear there is something you, personally, can do. Bull kelp is essential to the health of California’s wildlife; managing the purple sea urchin population can directly help over 700 species that rely on kelp forests and be fun, too.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://yubanet.com/california/how-disease-warming-waters-and-ravenous-sea-urchins-combined-to-kill-the-kelp-and-close-the-red-abalone-fishery/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Katie Sowul / California Department of Fish and Wildlife)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Sydney Hollingsworth&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sydney Hollingsworth</name></author><summary type="html">Purple sea urchins and California's kelp forests Sydney Hollingsworth. 04/16/2021 Where a kelp forest once stood, a “purple carpet” of sea urchins now covers the seafloor. (Steve Lonhart / NOAA Monterey Bay National Marine Sanctuary) The waters along the Californian coast contain a rich variety of marine life. From seals to colorful crustaceans to whales, thousands of species make their homes in the reefs and kelp forests near the rocky beaches of North America.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/urchinCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/urchinCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">CRISPR-Cas9: The award-winning genetic scissors</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/08/crispr-cas9-the-award-winning-genetic-scissors.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="CRISPR-Cas9: The award-winning genetic scissors" /><published>2021-04-08T17:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-08T17:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/08/crispr-cas9-the-award-winning-genetic-scissors</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/08/crispr-cas9-the-award-winning-genetic-scissors.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;CRISPR-Cas9: The award-winning genetic scissors
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nadwa Atwi. 04/09/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/geneticOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Emmanuelle Charpentier (left) and Jennifer Doudna (right) win the 2020 Nobel Prize in Chemistry for CRISPR gene-editing. &lt;a href=&quot;https://scroll.in/article/975260/what-is-crispr-explaining-the-gene-editing-technology-that-won-the-2020-chemistry-nobel-prize&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Scroll)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Researcher Emmanuelle Charpentier and biochemist Jennifer Doudna were initially studying the immune system of a Streptococcus bacterium in hopes of developing a new antibiotic, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/chemistry/2020/popular-information/#:~:text=Emmanuelle%20Charpentier%20and%20Jennifer%20Doudna,microorganisms%20with%20extremely%20high%20precision.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Nobel Prize&lt;/a&gt;. But akin to other remarkable discoveries, this one didn’t exactly go as planned. Instead, the pair discovered a molecular tool called CRISPR which can be used to make defined cuts in genetic material, presenting an endless array of possibilities for the future of gene-editing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeats, also known as CRISPR, are DNA sequences that are naturally found in bacteria. These repeats are actually a collection of mug shots captured by CRISPR associated proteins (Cas). The mug shots are DNA pieces that Cas cut from invaders that attack the bacteria. The snipped DNA fragment is then stored between the palindromic CRISPR sequences to maintain a genetic memory for halting future infections from the same invader.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Until recently, “CRISPR-Cas9” —often called CRISPR for short— has only been known as genetic information that some bacteria use as part of their defense mechanism against viruses. Now, as a gene-editing tool, CRISPR-Cas9 has reformed biomedical research and may soon enable medical breakthroughs in a way few biological innovations have before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;How it works&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/geneticTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The diagram shows the mechanism of action of CRISPR. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yourgenome.org/facts/what-is-crispr-cas9&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(YourGenome)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Editing genes with CRISPR-Cas9 occurs by cutting DNA at a particular site and then letting the natural DNA repair processes take over.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CRISPR relies on just two components: the molecular scissors (Cas9) and the guide RNA (gRNA), which works as a GPS, guiding Cas9 to the appropriate site. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.synthego.com/guide/how-to-use-crispr/sgrna#:~:text=In%20this%20document%2C%20we%20have,into%20a%20single%20RNA%20molecule.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Synthego&lt;/a&gt;, gRNA itself consists of two parts. These include the CRISPR RNA (crRNA), which is a sequence complementary to the target DNA, and a tracrRNA, which serves as a binding scaffold for the Cas protein. The crRNA part of the gRNA is the customizable one and can be modified into virtually any sequence, which allows specificity in every CRISPR experiment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The guide RNA shepherds Cas9 to the precise spot on DNA where a cut has been called for by pairing up with the region of the DNA it has targeted. Cas9 then locks onto the double-stranded DNA and unzips it, allowing it to snip the DNA at the requested spot. This results in a break in both strands of the DNA molecule.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The cell, sensing a problem, repairs the break. Cells usually repair a break in their DNA by gluing the loose ends back together using DNA ligase. This repair mechanism is not an orderly process, as it typically involves the loss or addition of some nucleotides at the cut site. That often results in a mistake that disables a gene, which may not sound convenient— but sometimes it is. This is why:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists cut DNA with CRISPR-Cas9 to induce changes, also known as mutations. They can understand what a protein’s actual role is by comparing cells with the mutation to ones without the mutation. A new mutation may also help them understand genetic diseases. Additionally, CRISPR-Cas9 can be useful in human cells by disabling certain genes, like ones that play a role in inherited diseases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the RNA biologist &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencenewsforstudents.org/article/explainer-how-crispr-works&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gene Yeo&lt;/a&gt;, Cas9 was originally equivalent to a Swiss army knife that has only one function: cutting. But securing proteins to those jaded blades has turned them into a multifunctional tool. CRISPR-Cas9 can now be used in new ways, such as changing a single nitrogenous base or adding a fluorescent protein to tag a spot in the DNA that scientists want to track.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Applications&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;CRISPR’s potential applications include correcting genetic defects, treating and preventing the spread of diseases and improving crops. Many common diseases, including heart conditions, Alzheimer’s and diabetes, are partly caused by genes; people who inherit the mutated variants of certain genes are more susceptible to the disease. For many of these conditions, the genetic component is complicated because more than one gene is involved. So for now, scientists are looking to treat diseases that are the result of a single mutated gene that is easy to target.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some blood disorders, like sickle-cell anemia, fit the bill.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sickle-cell anemia is an inherited red blood cell disorder in which the round red blood cells become deformed and resemble sickles or crescent moons. This deformation makes the cells prone to sticking in blood vessels and blocking blood flow to the surrounding tissues. Sickle-cell anemia is the result of a mutation in the hemoglobin gene.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/geneticThree.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The diagram shows the difference between normal red blood cells and the mutated ones.&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aboutkidshealth.ca/article?contentid=652&amp;amp;language=english&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(About Kids Health)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
About &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2020/06/23/877543610/a-year-in-1st-patient-to-get-gene-editing-for-sickle-cell-disease-is-thriving&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;two years ago&lt;/a&gt;, a woman called Victoria Gray became the first person to receive an experimental CRISPR treatment for sickle-cell anemia. Her doctors collected blood-producing stem cells from her bone marrow and edited the gene involved in hemoglobin formation found in the DNA they carry. Then they transfused them back. Gray has not needed the regular blood transfusions or hospitalizations her condition previously demanded.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yourgenome.org/facts/what-is-crispr-cas9&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Your Genome&lt;/a&gt;, CRISPR-Cas9 currently stands out as the fastest, cheapest and most reliable gene-editing tool. It is important to mention, though, that it is still unlikely for CRISPR-Cas9 to be used routinely in humans anytime soon. Using this tool along with other gene-editing technologies in somatic cells is well-accepted. In contrast, changes made in germ line cells will be passed on from one generation to another, which has significant ethical implications. The most prominent one is the inability to obtain informed consent, as patients affected by gene edits to germ line cells are embryos and future generations. That aside, CRISPR has shown very promising results in the medical field, and it’s clear that this tool holds great potential for curing diseases we’ve at some point labeled “untreatable.” So for now, we’re just going to have to wait and see what the future holds for such a versatile —and controversial— tool.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.drugtargetreview.com/news/74139/nobel-prize-in-chemistry-awarded-to-scientists-who-discovered-crispr-cas9/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Drug Target Review)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Nadwa Atwi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Nadwa Atwi</name></author><summary type="html">CRISPR-Cas9: The award-winning genetic scissors Nadwa Atwi. 04/09/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/geneticCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/geneticCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Bird-safe glass is the only way forward</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/02/bird-safe-glass-is-the-only-way-foward.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bird-safe glass is the only way forward" /><published>2021-04-02T17:00:03-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-02T17:00:03-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/02/bird-safe-glass-is-the-only-way-foward</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/02/bird-safe-glass-is-the-only-way-foward.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Bird-safe glass is the only way forward&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emily Richter. 04/03/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/birdglassCover.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This Public Health Office in Palma de Mallorca, Spain is both stunning and bird-safe.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://abcbirds.org/glass-collisions/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Boris Pena / American Bird Conservatory)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Birds do not understand windows. Though humans know there is a pane of glass, birds see a reflection of their surroundings or an inviting habitat, like an empty room. As a result, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://abcbirds.org/glass-collisions/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;American Bird Conservatory&lt;/a&gt; (ABC) reports that about one billion birds die every year due to glass collisions, making them a leading cause of avian death. For most animals, humanity’s worst threat comes in the form of habitat loss. For birds, the very buildings people inhabit can be deadly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Birds light up the skies with their beautiful feathers and enhance the sounds of the city and country alike with their beautiful songs. Birds also play important roles in maintaining the balance of the ecosystems humans depend on. Some birds, like hummingbirds, act as pollinators, fostering life in the form of plants. Others, like vultures, scavenge the remains of life, returning necessary nutrients to the soil. Still others, like orioles, spread the seeds of plants far and wide, ensuring the continued success of the natural world. Nature needs birds to function properly. Since humanity depends on the world’s ecosystems for everything from food to oxygen, humans need birds. Anything that hurts birds eventually hurts people as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A new technology promises hope for the feathered friends of the sky. Bird-safe incorporates materials birds can see into the design of the glass in order to prevent birds from flying into it. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.audubon.org/news/what-does-bird-safe-glass-even-mean&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Audubon Society&lt;/a&gt; reports that bird-safe glass is a blanket term, applying to both specially-designed glass and retrofitted glass. Bird-safe glass can be colored, like the glass at the Public Health Office in Palma de Mallorca, Spain (shown above), or it can be virtually transparent, utilizing small dots or lines as a way to alert birds of its presence. The process of retrofitting glass to make it safe for birds often involves adding lines or dots to the surface of the glass. Bird-safe glass and retrofitting buildings can be costly, but in the long run, it can also be beneficial. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://abcbirds.org/glass-collisions/architecture-planning/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ABC&lt;/a&gt; reports the Jacob K. Javits Convention Center near Times Square in Manhattan used to be notorious for the number of bird collisions it caused. However, when bird-safe glass was installed, both bird collisions and heat loss declined. The building went from being an ecological issue to being a model for bird safety and energy efficiency. Bird-safe glass does not only benefit birds; it can benefit its owners as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Codes and ordinances that require new edifices to be built with bird-safe glass are beginning to become common in the United States. New York City, which sees the most yearly bird deaths due to glass collisions, &lt;a href=&quot;https://council.nyc.gov/press/2019/12/10/1847/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;passed a law in 2020&lt;/a&gt; mandating that all new structures meet certain standards of bird safety. A majority of these standards involve glass design. The grassroots organization &lt;a href=&quot;https://birdfriendlychicago.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bird Friendly Chicago&lt;/a&gt; worked for years to introduce bird-safe glass laws to the third most populous city in the United States. They found success in 2019, when a bird-safe glass ordinance was introduced to the Chicago City Council, and again in 2020 when the city council updated Chicago’s Sustainable Development Policy to include information regarding bird-safe glass and its importance. In August of 2020, the city council of Madison, Wisconsin &lt;a href=&quot;https://abcbirds.org/article/madison-bird-friendly-building-ordinance-passed/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;passed an ordinance&lt;/a&gt; requiring bird-safe glass on all new large construction projects. The efforts of committed advocates and the support of the ABC lead to a new rule promising safer skies for Wisconsin’s faster-growing city.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, an organization in Madison &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ibmadison.com/city-sued-over-bird-safe-glass-requirement/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;has taken the city to court&lt;/a&gt;, saying that the new ordinance is unconstitutional. Building codes are updated often, and many new construction ordinances are introduced every year, so the chance of the law being nullified is low. However, the general public’s poor understanding of the importance and benefits of bird-safe glass still remains a threat to protective legislation. Many people who are against laws requiring the specialized glass point at the price, which is often elevated, as reasoning for their opinion. However, like in the case of the Jacob K. Javits Convention Center, bird-safe glass often leads to lower heating and cooling bills. And either way, the loss of bird life comes with a much higher price tag, both in economic and ecological terms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only do birds collide with the windows of large buildings, but they also collide with the windows of ordinary houses. In most areas, glass retrofitting services are not available for homeowners. Luckily, there is a simple solution. Putting stickers, curtains, sheets, or posters can help birds avoid flying into the glass. Protecting birds from glass can provide practical benefits as well! Stickers and posters can be great decorations for a living space, and putting fabric in windows often helps keep a room cooler.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many organizations of all sizes are fighting for a safer future for birds. Local organizations all over the world have had success encouraging the passing of legislation that mandates bird-safe glass in certain construction projects. National organizations like the ABC and Audubon support these grassroots movements and push for federal legislation. By passing laws that make buildings safer for birds with the help of organizations like these, humanity can move forward in a responsible and more sustainable manner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://abcbirds.org/blog/truth-about-birds-and-glass-collisions&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Arenal Observatory Lodge / American Bird Conservatory)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Emily Richter&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Emily Richter</name></author><summary type="html">Bird-safe glass is the only way forward Emily Richter. 04/03/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/birdglassOne.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/birdglassOne.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Auroras: Northern Lights</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/02/auroras-northern-lights.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Auroras: Northern Lights" /><published>2021-04-02T17:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-02T17:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/02/auroras-northern-lights</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/02/auroras-northern-lights.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Auroras: Northern Lights&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Bui. 04/03/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/auroraOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Above is an image of the aurora in Iceland.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://newatlas.com/photography/2020-northern-lights-photographer-of-the-year/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Agnieszka Mrowka)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Chances are, you’ve watched “The Polar Express”. If so, do you remember the bright colorful ribbons in the dark sky? In case you’re not familiar with “The Polar Express”, have you ever seen a picture of a prismatic ribbon across a night sky, specifically in areas where it’s cold? Well, those lights are called auroras.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auroras, or polar lights, are a natural phenomenon characterized by a display of colored light in the sky. This event is caused by a process involving solar wind. Solar wind is the outward expansion of plasma from the sun. The plasma is heated to the extent that the sun’s gravity cannot hold it in anymore. This solar wind then travels the Earth and enters its magnetic field before reaching the ionosphere, the layer of the atmosphere that contains the highest concentration of ions and free electrons. The energy that is released as a result of this collision creates the spectral wonder around the Northern and Southern poles: an aurora. Because auroras can only be visible at the Northern and Southern poles, they are unique and seeing them is often a once-in-a-lifetime experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auroras have many different names, other than polar lights. In the Northern pole, they can be called northern lights, and in the Southern pole, they are often called southern lights. The scientific name of auroras is aurora borealis. Aurora comes from the Latin word for “dawn,” as well as the goddess of dawn in Roman mythology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What causes the colors and patterns of auroras? There are various types of ions and atoms that collide with the atmosphere, resulting in a variety of patterns. The forms resulted from this variety can include ripples, “pulsating globs” and steady glows. The altitude affects the colors of the auroras, known as the aurora’s spectrum. This is because the particles from outer space collide with different gasses at different heights, resulting in different colors. Blue, violet and red colors are produced below 60 miles, and bright green between 60 and 150 miles. Above 150 miles, ruby red colors are seen. There is an infinite variety of shapes, colors, brightness and rays an aurora can form.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The magic of auroras is only visible at specific times. Auroras are always there, but they’re not as visible at certain times. In some places, such as Abisko, auroras are visible for almost 24 hours a day during winter. In other places, it’s rarer. Of course, auroras are only limited to viewing in the Northern and Southern poles. Darkness is vital for auroras to be visible, and they can be seen from late August to early April when the sky satisfies this condition. There are also aurora forecasts for people enthusiastic about seeing the spectacle for themselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the beauty of auroras comes with a price. Auroras can actually be potentially &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=http://www.suntrek.org/sun-earth-connection/the-aurora/aurorae-effect-us.shtml&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1617439859423000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw2_KP9t2Wj0Shn3r--3H6oG&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;dangerous&lt;/a&gt; to the atmosphere. To make a point clear, they have absolutely no negative impact on humans watching from below whatsoever, but the technology and buildings at a higher elevation can be affected by the electrically charged particles that auroras cause. Auroras disturb the atmosphere that they reside in. They can also disrupt communication from radios, signals and so on. The magnetic energy released by solar wind can blow out electricity. When auroras are active, the Earth’s atmosphere expands.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Auroras are beautiful and amazing, despite their negative factors. It’s quite an interesting phenomenon with interesting facts! Although they exist in the sky, sometimes they can come relatively close to the surface of the earth. Did you know that the closest the northern lights have ever come to Earth is 80 kilometers above the surface? To give a little visual aid, 80 kilometers is roughly 50 miles, whereas the atmosphere is 6,214 miles up. Did you know that the International Space Station (ISS) is at the same altitude as the auroras, so they can see the auroras from the side? Multiple planets have auroras, including Jupiter, Saturn, Uranus and Neptune. Southern lights aren’t nearly as popular as northern lights, although they’re nearly the same, because the areas that feature southern lights don’t have much landmass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, auroras are colorful illusions that are created when the sun’s rays hit the Earth’s ionosphere. They come in a variety of shapes and sizes and can be viewed in the Northern and Southern poles. There are different names for auroras, whether it’s specified by the pole it’s in, or its scientific name. In a way, they can have a negative impact on the atmosphere. Now that you know a little more about auroras, maybe one day, you’ll be among the group of people who love them!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://cdn.discover-the-world.com/app/uploads/2018/08/norway-northern-tromso-surrounds-with-aurora-istk.jpg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(CDN)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Peter Bui&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Peter Bui</name></author><summary type="html">Auroras: Northern Lights Peter Bui. 04/03/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/auroraCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/auroraCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Trees are a little like humans</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/02/trees-are-a-little-like-humans.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Trees are a little like humans" /><published>2021-04-02T17:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-02T17:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/02/trees-are-a-little-like-humans</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/02/trees-are-a-little-like-humans.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Trees are a little like humans&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Bui. 04/03/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/treesOne.png&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gettyimages.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Getty Images)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Whether we go outside or just look through the window, chances are we see trees. Trees take in carbon dioxide and release oxygen around the world, giving us clean air. But are trees just there, existing? Research shows that trees have (some) feelings of their own and have quite a few human characteristics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The thought of trees having human characteristics is quite surprising and for good reason. Trees have feelings? That’s crazy! But human characteristics aren’t the limit to what trees can do. In fact, research shows that trees can &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newscientist.com/article/mg21528791-800-plant-senses-sight/#:~:text=The%20obvious%20answer%20is%20that,ultraviolet%20parts%20of%20the%20spectrum.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;see&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smithsonianmag.com/science-nature/the-whispering-trees-180968084/#:~:text=They%20don%27t%20have%20nervous,signals%20like%20wounded%20human%20tissue.%E2%80%9D&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;feel&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.livescience.com/plants-squeal-when-stressed.html#:~:text=In%20times%20of%20intense%20stress,research%2C%20which%20was%20posted%20Dec.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;scream&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://english.mathrubhumi.com/news/columns/faunaforum/trees-do-cry--1.244317#:~:text=02%20AM%20IST-,Do%20trees%20cry%3F,to%20hear%2C%20it%20goes%20unheard.&amp;amp;text=Inside%20tree%20trunks%20are%20bundles,the%20highest%20leaves%20and%20branches.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;cry&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let’s start with the basics. Trees are grown plants, with parts including a trunk, branches, leaves and roots. They, like us, require water and basic needs. A tree takes in water, sunlight and carbon dioxide through a process known as photosynthesis. This process produces glucose, or sugar, which the tree uses for energy, and oxygen as a byproduct (humans then breathe in oxygen and exhale carbon dioxide for the tree to use, continuing the cycle).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trees play a big role in our everyday lives at the cost of their own lives (which could span for hundreds or even thousands of years if left undisturbed) because they are used to create paper, furniture, lumber and so much more. However, they prove more useful while they live by cleaning our air and supplying us with many other benefits such as cleaning the environment. Some trees even produce fruit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But do trees have feelings? Trees lack a nervous system, so they can’t experience emotions that we feel, like happiness or excitement. Even though trees lack a brain, the fact that electric signals can be fired from within the trees hints at consciousness. Botanist author &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pri.org/stories/2014-01-09/new-research-plant-intelligence-may-forever-change-how-you-think-about-plants#:~:text=Pollan%20says%20plants%20have%20all,he%20says%2C%20to%20avoid%20obstacles.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Michael Pollan&lt;/a&gt; explains that they may have a system that produces neurotransmitters, like serotonin, that the human brain also produces. In addition to this, it has been proved that trees do feel a few emotions. Although they don’t experience feelings while being chopped down, they do not like it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The emotional range of a tree is somewhat limited, but that doesn’t mean it doesn’t exist. For instance, they can sense and react to cold, heat, drought, touch and external trouble. When a plant feels that it is too cold, it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lyndontreecare.com/educate/2017/1/28/how-do-trees-survive-winter#:~:text=This%20dormancy%20is%20what%20allows,with%20the%20loss%20of%20leaves.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;initiates responses&lt;/a&gt; that can help to protect the tree from harm. Trees use their bark to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bioinspiration.net/post/bark-of-trees#:~:text=Bark%20of%20trees%20have%20a,between%206%20and%2010%20microns.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;reflect light and disperse heat&lt;/a&gt;. To protect themselves from heat, they use their leaves to shade themselves, as well as use &lt;a href=&quot;https://spatialexperiments.wordpress.com/2016/02/08/coping-with-the-heat-trees/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;conductive and insulative cooling&lt;/a&gt;. They sense drought when they do not have enough water to meet their needs, the equivalent of us being thirsty. In this case, they save water and slow down evaporation. In general, plants can feel touch, but it is debated if being touched is beneficial or harmful for the plant. Some studies even show that touch results in stunted growth of the plant. Trees can even sense insects and internally mix chemicals to create compounds that act as repellants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most human responses that trees can feel are rather sad. This includes trees &lt;a href=&quot;https://english.mathrubhumi.com/news/columns/faunaforum/trees-do-cry--1.244317#:~:text=02%20AM%20IST-,Do%20trees%20cry%3F,to%20hear%2C%20it%20goes%20unheard.&amp;amp;text=Inside%20tree%20trunks%20are%20bundles,the%20highest%20leaves%20and%20branches.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;crying&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.livescience.com/plants-squeal-when-stressed.html%23:~:text%3DIn%2520times%2520of%2520intense%2520stress,research%252C%2520which%2520was%2520posted%2520Dec.&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1617439122668000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw1wb0Gj7etCY8AZW2sBMSLQ&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;screaming&lt;/a&gt; (when they are cut down). The “tears of trees” can have a double meaning: the liquid tears of a tree or the wailing of the tree. The liquid is produced through a process known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.topperlearning.com/answer/why-negative-root-pressure-develops-due-to-excessive-transpiration/d04llzhh%23:~:text%3DRoot%2520pressure%2520is%2520the%2520positive,of%2520nutrients%2520from%2520the%2520soil.%26text%3DThis%2520creates%2520a%2520negative%2520pressure,the%2520roots%252C%2520through%2520the%2520stem.&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1617439274558000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw2bD6a3IfP__AuR0iquYh-N&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;positive root pressure&lt;/a&gt;, where the roots take up water to the limbs of the trees in warm weather so that the buds can break. The wailing of the tree is what occurs when the tree is thirsty. When trees lack water, they suffer and make a noise. The noise, however, is ultrasonic, meaning that it is too high-pitched for the human ear to possibly pick up. Trees will also produce ultrasonic noises between 20 and 100 kilohertz when they’re in pain or when they’re scared, such as when they are being cut down.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Trees, of course, do not have eyes, ears, a mouth or any other means to communicate. But trees can actually &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newscientist.com/article/mg21528791-800-plant-senses-sight/#:~:text=The%20obvious%20answer%20is%20that,ultraviolet%20parts%20of%20the%20spectrum.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;see&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://now.northropgrumman.com/can-plants-hear-the-science-of-sound-sensing-flora/#:~:text=Shhhhhh.,More%20importantly%2C%20they%20can%20react.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;hear&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cannagardening.com/how_plants_communicate#:~:text=Plants%20taste%20and%20smell%20as,far%20away%20other%20plants%20are.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;taste&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smithsonianmag.com/science-nature/the-whispering-trees-180968084/#:~:text=To%20communicate%20through%20the%20network,are%20just%20beginning%20to%20decipher.&amp;amp;text=Trees%20also%20communicate%20through%20the,pheromones%20and%20other%20scent%20signals.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;communicate&lt;/a&gt;. The sight of a plant may exist because they grow towards areas with light, meaning that they can sense the light with their leaves. Plants can also hear to the degree that they can even respond to human voices. Trees use their roots to absorb nutrients and to taste. They also have a wide arsenal of ways to communicate with one another, including sending chemical, hormonal and slow-pulsing electrical signals and communicating through the air using scent. Trees even have senses that we lack, such as being able to sense &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pri.org/stories/2014-01-09/new-research-plant-intelligence-may-forever-change-how-you-think-about-plants&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;gravitational changes, the presence of water or even a block in their roots&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a way, the needs of a tree are similar to that of a human. Trees need water, food and air. In contrast to humans needing water to use their bodies and excrete waste, trees need water to make their food. As stated, trees use water, sunlight and carbon dioxide to create oxygen and glucose using the equation 6CO2 + 6H2O → C6H12O6 + 6O2 where 6 carbon dioxide molecules and 6 water molecules along with sunlight produce glucose (C6H12O6) and 6 oxygen atoms as a waste product. Unlike us, the tree basically inhales carbon dioxide and exhales oxygen, while we inhale oxygen and exhale carbon dioxide. Trees drink water through a natural straw known as their &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/science/xylem&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;xylem&lt;/a&gt;, which brings water to their utmost branches.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The anatomy of a tree is similar to human anatomy as well. The arms of a human can be like the branches of a tree. Trees have tree sap that transports nutrients and water through the tree, very much like how blood transports nutrients and water to our entire body. The bronchi in our lungs are also similar to the roots of trees. The leaves of a tree, aside from producing glucose, work as hair for the tree.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a recap, trees do not have all human characteristics. In fact, the emotional range of a tree is limited. They may feel pain, but they do not feel regret, happiness, or anything of that sort. However, they do cry and scream, and although seemingly lack the ability to, can see, hear, feel and communicate. Trees have the needs and anatomy of humans in some ways. Globally, trees have many useful aspects such as improving water and air quality, boosting peoples’ health, keeping global warming in check and so much more. Keeping all this in mind, along with the fact that trees are in some ways similar to us, we should love trees more before they’re gone forever.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.gamesdash.com/pic/130/picture/the-tree-of-human-face&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Gamesdash)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Peter Bui&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Peter Bui</name></author><summary type="html">Trees are a little like humans Peter Bui. 04/03/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/treesCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/treesCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>