<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-10-24T22:34:38-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">interSTEM</title><entry><title type="html">New Australian study shows low COVID-19 transmission rates in schools</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/18/transmission-rates.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Australian study shows low COVID-19 transmission rates in schools" /><published>2020-09-18T09:00:01-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-18T09:00:01-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/18/transmission-rates</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/18/transmission-rates.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;New Australian study shows low COVID-19 transmission rates in schools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reagan Smith. 9/18/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/september/transmissionOne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;African American citizens of Harlem, New York, are waiting in line to receive food and masks in order to protect themselves and their families against COVID-19. (AP Photo / Matilde Campodonico)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As of Aug. 4, 2020, a study from the University of Sydney found that COVID-19 transmission rates between children and children to adults were low in New South Wales schools and early educational settings, such as preschools and pre-kindergarten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers from the National Centre for Immunization Research and Surveillance (NCIRS) worked with the University of Sydney to examine data from January to April of 2020. The group, led by Professor Kristine Macartney, looked at twenty-five various locations, including fifteen schools and ten childcare/daycare centers. According to Macartney, “COVID-19 transmission in schools appears to be considerably less than that seen for other respiratory viruses, such as influenza.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is good news for Americans as schools reopen, because it means that— when done properly— children can return to school safely. Macartney cites contact tracing, routine cleaning, and temporary closures if a member of the school contract COVID-19 as effective procedures to keep transmission rates low. Other data concerning COVID-19 shows that overall, the disease has a lower transmission and milder effect overall in the younger population. This is seen in the fact that out of 1333 primary and high schools the University and NCIRS studied, only five secondary infections were recorded, meaning COVID-19 had a .04 percent transmission rate in the settings, according to Science Daily. The study is ongoing, and researchers are still collecting transmission data for the July to September block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Australia’s response to COVID-19 after learning of the case in Wuhan, China on Jan. 25, 2020 was different from the US’s. The country surveyed incoming travelers and communities, tested frequently and aggressively, isolated cases, and performed contact tracing. They also closed their borders and put an immediate quarantine in place. However, Australia has kept their schools open throughout the pandemic, with measures in place to help prevent the spread, closing finally on March 23, 2020, at the peak of the pandemic. They did keep early child education and care open for children ages six weeks to five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even before the outbreak, Australia “has done a fair amount of preparation and had the mechanisms in place,” says Dr. Lesley Russel, an Associate Professor at the Menzies Centre for Health Policy, in an interview for Business Insider on Australia’s pandemic response. They have a well-funded infection monitoring system, and the state and federal government has cooperated during this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By comparison, the US has, in recent years, cut funding for the CDC, which is lacking resources and money. Russel says the Trump administration has utilized a “just in time” response, which may be an attempt to help prevent the economy from falling apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Australia’s response to the pandemic has not been politicized, and politicians have let the scientists gauge the situation and appropriate responses. The U.S. government did hold daily briefings on updates about the pandemic, but they fell into disarray as facts were skewed, reporters were berated, and past actions were called into question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to look at Australia as an example of what is possible in these times, and to know that, with proper safety measures, children can go back to schools. While America cannot change its actions in the past in terms of how we have handled the pandemic, moving forward, we need unified, confident, and effective methods to maintain safety while reopening. This study done by the University of Sydney can give us a look into the long-term effectiveness of quarantining compared to keeping certain settings open, and it can give us security as the school year starts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As schools reopen, studies show the transmission rates of COVID-19 are low, with proper distancing and safety requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Kyle Grillot / Reuters)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/Reagan_Smith.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Reagan Smith&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Reagan is a junior from Sage Hill School. She is passionate about all things related to science, especially biology and medicine. She also loves being able to use her talents and knowledge to help others and make a difference in the world.


&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Reagan Smith</name></author><summary type="html">New Australian study shows low COVID-19 transmission rates in schools Reagan Smith. 9/18/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/transmissionCover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/transmissionCover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Halos seen by Hubble</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/12/halos-hubble.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Halos seen by Hubble" /><published>2020-09-12T09:00:01-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-12T09:00:01-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/12/halos-hubble</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/12/halos-hubble.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Halos seen by Hubble&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mehri Sadri. 9/12/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/september/halosOne.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;A close-up view of the Andromeda galaxy and its surroundings taken by Hubble. (Hubble Space Telescope)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It is a symbol of good: the yellow ring that encompasses an individual’s head is traditionally used to symbolize holiness, glory, reverence and other positive attributes. Not only are these bright rings of light called halos, but halos are also what NASA scientists use to describe distinct shells of gas that surround the Andromeda galaxy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This galaxy, also known as M31, is an entity with around 1 trillion stars and is the closest galaxy to our Milky Way. It is an elliptical galaxy and was discovered by Edwin Hubble in 1925 when he discovered a star within the massive cloud of particles. It is around 2.5 million light-years from us, a distance that although may seem astronomical, is very, very close in comparison to other space objects. The halo, which scientists are comprehensively studying right now, is not visible to the naked eye. However, if it was, it would look similar to a giant smudge within the night sky. It would likely be a blue or purple hue shining across the deep blue night. The gaseous halo, although cool looking, is the catalyst of scientific research at American universities. Yale University and the University of Notre Dame are zooming in closely to the gas puddle, as it potentially holds lots of answers to the questions people have about the Milky Way’s closest neighbor. The gas contained within the galaxy is the host of future-star particles; in this sense, researchers may be able to “predict” any new star formation activity. The gas also reveals the history of the galaxy, and with knowledge on the specific formation of Andromeda, we may be able to predict more about our own home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;From what researchers have observed, they’ve noticed a big difference between the properties of the “outer” halo versus the “inner” halo. According to Nicolas Lehner, a researcher from the University of Notre Dame, their team found that “find[ing] the inner shell that extends to about a half-million light-years is far more complex and dynamic,” and the outer shell is a little less chaotic, exhibiting smooth, hot characteristics. To further study the specific areas of halo gas within Andromeda, researchers assembled a project known as Absorption Map of Ionized Gas in Andromeda (AMIGA) to trace absorptions of light coming from different sectors of gas. With these measurements, the size and age of Andromeda can be more accurately calculated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The researchers are determined to use this beautiful piece of space to determine further order for our galaxy, all while publishing breathtaking photos the Hubble telescope has taken.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (NASA, ESA, and E. Wheatley)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/Mehri_Sadri.JPG&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Mehri Sadri
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Mehri is a rising senior at Scripps Ranch High School in San Diego, California. Although she has always been more inclined in humanities subjects, Mehri has found a love for combining science and art and their practicalities, and hopes to spread this same love to others with her articles.

&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Mehri Sadri</name></author><summary type="html">Halos seen by Hubble Mehri Sadri. 9/12/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/haloCover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/haloCover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How African Americans have been affected by COVID-19</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/11/african-americans-covid19.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How African Americans have been affected by COVID-19" /><published>2020-09-11T09:00:02-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-11T09:00:02-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/11/african-americans-covid19</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/11/african-americans-covid19.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;How African Americans have been affected by COVID-19&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Khushi Shah. 9/11/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/september/africanAmericanOne.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;African American citizens of Harlem, New York, are waiting in line to receive food and masks in order to protect themselves and their families against COVID-19. (Bebeto Matthews / The Associated Press)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If COVID-19 is a disease that can affect anyone, then why are people of color more prone to suffering from its repercussions? According to the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention (CDC), there are five principal causes as to why African Americans are at high risk for exposure: discrimination, healthcare access and utilization, occupation, housing and educational/income/wealth gaps.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Robert Wood Johnson Foundation says it best: “Your health care depends on who you are.” The foundation estimated that minority groups such as Latinos and African Americans experience 30 to 40 percent poorer health outcomes than white Americans. African Americans are liable to racial profiling, thus causing their physical or mental pain to be viewed as their own doing or an excuse. Because of these preconceived notions, African Americans can feel discouraged to seek care and ultimately end up harming their well being even more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;African Americans have always had higher uninsured rates in comparison to many other ethnic groups in the United States. Although coverage rates increased from 2010 to 2016 after the Affordable Care Act (ACA) was implemented, African Americans remained 1.5 times more likely to be uninsured than their white counterparts from 2010 to 2018 according to Kaiser Family Foundation (KFF).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another factor that contributes to minority groups being uninsured is that they work essential jobs, such as public transportation or farming, thus forcing them to work long hours and unable to have the luxury of taking time off. Many of these jobs provide pay that causes the annual pay of minority groups to be significantly below the United States average annual income. The average annual income of a black family is roughly $40,000, which is significantly less than other ethnic groups. Families are so focused on putting food on the table and paying rent that they cannot get a babysitter or daycare just for a hospital visit. Because culture and language barriers are inevitable in the United States, this can cause minority groups to feel uncomfortable in health care settings, as they feel that their ethnic differences will cause them to receive limited help.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the biggest effects of COVID-19 is the eviction crisis. In many racial minority groups, it is common for multiple generations of a family to live under one roof. Because these groups tend to live in more crowded conditions, they are at a higher risk for contracting the virus or exposing others to it. The eviction crisis has led to roughly 30 to 40 million Americans being on the verge of getting kicked out of their homes, which is their only source of safety and humanity during the pandemic. The Aspen Institute states that people of color are twice as likely to be renters and make up roughly 80% of people who are facing eviction in the United States of America. All across the country, minority groups have significantly higher eviction rates in comparison to White Americans, and COVID-19 has only made things worse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One would think that after 50 years, the wealth gap between different races would start to shrink, but according to The Washington Post, the wealth gap between White Americans and Black Americans is just as wide as it was in 1968. In other words, the net worth of 11.5 black households is equivalent to the net worth of a white household. More money allows for individuals to further and better their education. Because African Americans are on the lower end of the wealth gap, they are often less educated in comparison to White Americans. In the situation of COVID-19, those without enough education may not have access to crucial information such as the need for social distancing and the usage of masks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, there has not been much change in the status of African Americans since the quarantine started in mid-March. Although, many protests have occurred throughout the nation to spark a change in the treatment of black Americans socially, politically, and economically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: Wired&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Valeria Rivadeneyra
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Khushi Shah</name></author><summary type="html">How African Americans have been affected by COVID-19 Khushi Shah. 9/11/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/AfricanAmericanCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/AfricanAmericanCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Asteroid mining</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/11/asteroid-mining.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Asteroid mining" /><published>2020-09-11T09:00:01-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-11T09:00:01-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/11/asteroid-mining</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/11/asteroid-mining.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Asteroid mining&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ramizah Tayiba. 9/11/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/september/asteroidOne.png&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This is an artist’s interpretation of asteroid mining. (NASA)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Goldman Sachs claims the first trillionaire will be the one who extracts raw materials from outer space. This sentiment is also shared by the astrophysicist Neil deGrasse Tyson.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Asteroid mining. The idea of capturing orbiting asteroids in space and exploiting them of rare earth metals that if made possible, would completely revolutionize the mining industry and even the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Current mining exploits are quite destructive. They can disrupt biodiversity, people and the planet itself. In the United States alone, a country with sufficient safety equipment and regulations, 50 to 60 miners die annually. Falling rocks and being caved in aren’t the only dangers; unseen threats like carbon monoxide and methane gas poisoning can be just as detrimental to one’s health. Throughout history, there have been numerous horrific instances where miners have been killed or trapped in mines. In 2010, one hundred Chinese miners were trapped for eight days. They survived miraculously by eating sawdust. This is one of many stories that show the dangers faced by miners.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earthly mining operations also threaten biodiversity. Tailings (waste rock from mining operations) often make their way into lakes and streams, toxifying the water. Other threats include erosions, contamination and destruction of ecosystems and the creation of sinkholes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings us back to asteroid mining. If this is made possible, it would eradicate all of these other issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So how close are we to extracting materials from outer space?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The answer is admittedly underwhelming, for now. At this time, the process only includes a small sample collection. This is done by space probes such as Hayabusa 2. But the actual mining of an asteroid is still in the works. Nets and harpoons have been considered, but aren’t the best solution as mining in space is more complicated than once thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The low gravity, which holds asteroids together, complicates things. But a team at TransAstra has developed a piece of machinery that utilizes the sun’s rays to vaporize asteroids without even touching them. TransAstra has developed a clever way to then retrieve the vaporized rock. The water that is harvested from the asteroids can then be used as a propellant to come back to Earth. And if this technique is perfected, it will significantly reduce the cost of space exploration, as it will decrease dependence on fuel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This equipment is still being tested. Dr. Sercel at TransAstra hopes to send the first mining vehicles into space in 10 years. This means that although its technological development is still in its infancy, within the next few decades, we might see a whole new era in mining.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Factor-Tech Magazine)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Valeria Rivadeneyra
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ramizah Tayiba</name></author><summary type="html">Asteroid mining Ramizah Tayiba. 9/11/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/asteroidCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/asteroidCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The science of musicians and dancers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/07/science-of-musicians.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The science of musicians and dancers" /><published>2020-09-07T09:00:01-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-07T09:00:01-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/07/science-of-musicians</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/07/science-of-musicians.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The science of musicians and dancers&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Valeria Rivadeneyra. 9/7/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/september/musicOne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Dancers from the Mariinsky Theater Russian Ballet Company perform on stage at the Erkel Theater in Budapest, during a rehearsal of the title 'Cinderella', composed by Russian Sergei Prokofiev. (Healix)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The human brain is designed to seek absolute harmony, and each of its neurons has a rhythm. This is evident in activities such as dance and music.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dancers have wider connections between the sensory and motor regions of the brain and more connection between the two hemispheres of the brain. Musicians, on the other hand, concrete connections were strengthened in musicians.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the results of a study conducted with professionals in music and dance in Canada, musical and dance training strengthen the connections in the brain, but in different ways. Dancing is responsible for strengthening the connections in a general way between different areas of the brain. On the other hand, music strengthens certain areas in particular.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Long afternoons practicing scales on the piano or even aching muscles after spending extensive hours at the ballet bar. All that time spent may seem exhausting, but research confirms what many people and parents, in particular, already believed: this type of activity is good for the mind and body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is according to a recent study published in NeuroImage that was conducted by a group of researchers from the International Laboratory for Sound, Music and Brain Research. It shows that practicing music or dance generates bigger results in the brain than we thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the experiment, high-tech imaging techniques were used to compare what effects music and dance training produced on the white matter structure of experts in both activities. White matter is one of the two components of the central nervous system (CNS). It consists mostly of glial cells and myelinated axons and forms the bulk of the deep parts of the cerebrum and the superficial parts of the spinal cord.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We found that dancers and musicians differed in many regions of white matter, including sensory and motor pathways, at both the primary and higher levels of cognitive processing,” said Chiara Giacosa, a doctoral candidate at Concordia University in Montreal and first author of the study.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Essentially, it was found that dancers possessed more connections between the sensory and motor regions of the human brain, while musicians strengthened specific connections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“This suggests that musical training and dance training affect the brain in opposite directions,” explained Giacosa. “Indeed, while dancers train their entire body, which has a wider representation in the neural cortex, musicians focus their training on specific parts of the body, such as hands, fingers, or mouth, which have a smaller cortical representation in the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some research has already shown that musical training can improve cognitive skills, but dance has not yet been used in a similar way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There’s also an explanation to understand how musicians and dancers synchronize during a performance. A new study concludes that human beings filter out information that will alter the harmony with the group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Synchrony transmits many sensations to your brain. “It generates positive feelings,” said Jesus Porta, vice-president of the Spanish Society of Neurology and member of the Spanish Council of the Brain. According to Porta, the human being reaches synchronicity by putting himself in the other person’s place.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is because the brain has mirror neurons which allow artists to enter synchrony and respond to external or internal stimuli.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was also determined through the study that the practice and activity of the frontal lobe are key in improving and automating the rhythm during a performance. According to Porta, rehearsal allows for proper synchronization and prevents delays.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study concludes that “the human brain is the most complex structure in the universe” because, unlike the animal brain, it is capable of eliminating frustrating signals that hinder synchronization.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“We are only at the beginning of the research,” explained Moti Fridman, the author of the study and a researcher at the Faculty of Engineering and the Institute of Nanotechnology and Advanced Materials at Bar-Ilan University in Israel. “I want to extend the analysis to more violinists, to other instruments and to dance.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, it is undeniable to say that artistic expressions such as dance and music are extremely beneficial for human beings and complement each other in an incredible way, thanks to the brain connections that are generated when practicing these activities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Valeria Rivadeneyra
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Valeria Rivadeneyra</name></author><summary type="html">The science of musicians and dancers Valeria Rivadeneyra. 9/7/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/musicCover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/musicCover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The clock ticks</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/07/clock-ticks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The clock ticks" /><published>2020-09-07T09:00:01-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-07T09:00:01-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/07/clock-ticks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/07/clock-ticks.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The clock ticks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Famesh Patel. 9/7/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/september/clockOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The doomsday clock has always been a standard to see how close we are to the extinction of mankind by the hands of mankind. It has slowly, yet clearly, ticked closer and closer to midnight every year and we are just getting closer. (Janet Loehrke / USA Today)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The scientists who engaged in the Manhattan Project, a major project that was meant to create the first arsenal of nuclear bombs, started publishing a magazine by the name of Bulletin of Atomic Scientists under the liaison of the Chicago Atomic Scientists. This bunch included the likes of Enrico Fermi and J. Robert Oppenheimer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first issue of the Bulletin included a clock in the background with the time set to 7 minutes before midnight. This clock wasn’t any other ordinary clock. According to Aperture, it represented “utter anthropogenic global catastrophe.” The clock represents how close we are to the total obliteration of the world by the hands of mankind. However, the minute hand can go forward or backwards depending on the situation. Ever since that first issue of the Bulletin, the clock has changed multiple times and relies on many factors such as climate change, pandemics or nuclear tension between nations. In 1947, the first year that the Bulletin of the Atomic Scientists was published, the clock was at 7 minutes to midnight. In 1972, it was 12 minutes to midnight and in 2018, 2 minutes from midnight. Now, you may ask, “How far are we from midnight in 2020?” We aren’t 20 minutes, not 10 minutes, not even 5 minutes away. We are a mere 100 seconds away from midnight. Just 1 minute and 40 seconds away from total global obliteration. Let that sink in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When we talk about global obliteration, we usually think of nuclear bombs, asteroids or some sort of large scale explosion. When we measure these explosions, we usually talk about their destructive power through how much TNT is needed to produce an equivalent amount of destruction. At the time of the creation of the Doomsday clock, the two most powerful bombs in existence at the time were Fat Man and Little Boy, the infamous bombs dropped on Nagasaki and Hiroshima respectively. According to Beyond the Bomb, they also respectively had 21 kilotons and 15 kilotons of TNT force in them. However, the frightening thing is that they never actually reached their full potential.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When Fat Man was detonated on Nagasaki, only 1 kilogram (kg) out of the 6.5 kgs of plutonium actually fissioned, which is about 16%. And less than 1 kg of the 64 kgs of uranium in Little Boy actually fissioned, which is barely above 1%. Even though these nuclear weapons never exploded to their full potential, 2 combined kilograms of plutonium and uranium were able to wipe out 200,000 people. That was in 1945. About 75 years later in 2020, more than 125,000 nuclear weapons, which are far worse than Fat Man and Little Boy’s combined potential at 100% fission rate, have been created globally.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Britannica, in 1961, the USSR detonated the Tsar Bomba, the greatest hydrogen bomb to ever be tested, over the Siberian Wilderness. The bomb didn’t have 15,000 or even 20,000 tons of TNT power. It had 50 million tons of TNT power. It was so powerful that buildings that were 1,000 km away from the blast site saw broken windows from the shockwave. The shockwave circled the earth 3 times before it finally weakened and died out. The Tsar Bomba was originally going to be made into a 100 million ton monster, but that was decided against because it could have led the world into a nuclear winter. If 10 Tsar Bombas were blasted on the 10 most populated cities in the world today, we would have 106,200,000 casualties, more than all the casualties from every war in the 20th century combined. Right now, there are a whopping 13,410 nuclear weapons on standby according to the Federation of American Scientists. If one of these bombs is used, then all of them will be used. In an idea called mutually assured destruction (MAD), if a conflict between nations is pushed to the point that nuclear weapons are used, a nation will not hold back on their use of nuclear weapons at all so they can win the battle. The fallout from nuclear weapons being used in a war between just two countries with a decent nuclear arsenal could be so bad that it could lead to global extinction of the human race. Just one percent of the nuclear arsenal (200 nuclear bombs) of the world could cause over a billion deaths, according to Aperture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There was a survey done on a group of scientists on extinction events by the year 2100, by the Global Catastrophic Risk Conference in 2008. This survey concluded that the probability of complete extinction by nuclear warfare was put at one percent. Only a 1 in a 100 chance, right? That’s small, so we should be fine. However, consider this: the chances of you dying in an airplane crash is 1 in 11 million, and dying by a lightning strike is 1 in 84,000. The probability of you dying because of nuclear warfare is the third most likely thing on the list of things that could kill you (right behind cancer and heart disease if you’re curious). Think about that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If the two most loaded nuclear nations, the United States and Russia, went to war against each other, then that would basically mean the end of humanity as we know it. Both countries own about 93 percent of the global nuclear arsenal. A war of this magnitude and scale wouldn’t even be to win, but would be to make sure you don’t lose. The only way to do that would be to wipe the other country off the face of the earth. After these two countries start a nuclear war, there is no end. This type of war has no pause or redo button. It would only end once all of humanity ceases to exist.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now think about it. If a nuclear war does start at all, is there any point in trying to survive? Our livelihoods and entire realities would be altered on such a large scale that life might not even be worth living after such a drastic event. Truly, the best way to win this game of nuclear prowess is to not even start playing because if you do, the clock might tip over midnight.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Flickr / El_Enigma)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Famesh Patel
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Famesh is a rising senior at BASIS Peoria High School who enjoys all parts of science. Explaining the world around us with science has always seemed interesting to him from metamorphosis to the Higgs Boson. He hopes to help bring more youth to STEM fields so they can understand the natural world around us and appreciate the world for its uniqueness.

&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Famesh Patel</name></author><summary type="html">The clock ticks Famesh Patel. 9/7/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/clockCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/clockCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Virtual and augmented reality in surgery</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/07/virtual-augmented-surgery.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Virtual and augmented reality in surgery" /><published>2020-09-07T09:00:01-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-07T09:00:01-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/07/virtual-augmented-surgery</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/07/virtual-augmented-surgery.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Virtual and augmented reality in surgery&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reagan Smith. 9/7/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/september/surgeryOne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Augmedics is one of the many companies that developed an AR platform to perform surgeries more efficiently. (OrthoStreams)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The world of medicine has advanced significantly in recent years. With new technology and surgical procedures, we have uncovered a myriad of ways to treat illnesses and perform surgeries. However, with increased knowledge comes increased risk. Because new surgeries are more complex, surgeons require up to 10 times more training and experience before they can perform the surgery well, and the National Center for Biotechnology Information shows that 30% of graduating general surgery residents are unable to perform these procedures independently. We are falling behind in the medical field as technology outstrips our ability to utilize it, a fact which is evident when medical errors are the third leading cause of death in the nation, according to Stat News.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is where virtual reality comes in; the development has enabled surgeons to practice procedures in a safe and non-consequential environment. Simple, user-friendly VR headsets, like the Oculus Rift, are the direction the field is heading in for practicing surgical procedures before performing them on a patient. While this type of technology is not implemented widely, as there is little data to back up its usage, a study at UCLA by the David Geffen School of Medicine showed that training with VR improved results by 230% in comparison to traditional training. Long-term research is necessary to prove VR’s usefulness, and although the medical community is notoriously slow to adopt new methods or techniques, efficiency and forward-thinking is crucial now more than ever as people depend on healthcare professionals to survive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Augmented reality, AR, is different from virtual reality in that it places a “layer” of data or a screen in the real world (think of the mobile game Pokémon Go from a couple years back). There are various software and technology companies that have developed AR, including Microsoft’s HoloLens, Google’s Google Glass and Facebook’s AR Glasses (still in development). During surgery, AR can connect medical professionals in different locations to provide additional expertise for a surgery, regardless of distance. Instead of receiving help via text, phone, or camera, surgeons can use AR to provide a direct live-streaming experience to the recipient for the most accurate data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One medical technology company, Medivis, has designed a program to alter the surgeon’s vision and overlay images directly onto the operation area, which can reduce human error and increase efficiency. Their learning-based software, AnatomyX, has 2000+ users in over 30 classrooms. XVision, which was developed by the company Augmedics, is a wireless headset that presents anatomical structures that give surgeons an x-ray visual of the operating field without requiring another screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By combining the benefits of VR and AR, we can revolutionize the way that people train for and perform surgeries, minimizing risk and increasing success. All that is needed are open minds and curious learners, which the up-and-coming graduate classes can supply. It’s an exciting time for the field of medicine, as we are recognizing the value of bringing technology and engineering to human-performed operations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Med-Tech Innovation)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/Reagan_Smith.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Reagan Smith
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Reagan is a junior from Sage Hill School. She is passionate about all things related to science, especially biology and medicine. She also loves being able to use her talents and knowledge to help others and make a difference in the world.

&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Reagan Smith</name></author><summary type="html">Virtual and augmented reality in surgery Reagan Smith. 9/7/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/surgeryCover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/surgeryCover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Pseudoscience and COVID-19</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/04/pseudoscience-covid19.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pseudoscience and COVID-19" /><published>2020-09-04T09:00:05-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-04T09:00:05-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/04/pseudoscience-covid19</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/04/pseudoscience-covid19.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Pseudoscience and COVID-19&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carly Schinhofen. 9/4/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/september/pseudoOne.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;As COVID-19 shows no signs of slowing, a consequent surge of misinformation and pseudoscience emerges, and its effectiveness is frightening. (Healix)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
COVID-19 has been labeled as many things: a hoax, a virus not any more harmful than the flu, and a result of 5G wireless technology. The surge of misinformation accompanying the pandemic is preventing people worldwide from addressing COVID-19 as it truly is. COVID-19 is a global emergency that should be treated as such.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The spread of pseudoscience, or beliefs falsely regarded as being based on science, is largely evident in our current pandemic. Many people choose to blindly follow these theories, labeling themselves as insignificant in the spread of the disease. Arguably the most important issue is ensuring that every citizen knows their individual impact on the spread of the virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Scientific American, new research indicates that “between 10 and 20 percent of infected people are responsible for 80 percent of the coronavirus’s spread”. These people are known as superspreaders, and a large percent of these people are unaware that they are carrying COVID-19 since they do not experience any symptoms of the virus. Without proper precautions, these people can spread it to others around them, and are defined as being “unusually contagious”. This can create an explosion of cases from an individual who was unaware they had the virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Therefore, limiting exposure to other people as well as wearing a mask in public can save thousands of lives. Unfortunately, a great number of people simply refuse to accept the science behind the virus and can be great contributors to its spread. These people ignore the well-informed professionals that have spent their lives studying viruses like COVID-19. Some may take fatal measures to avoid care or take dangerous measures to cure themselves because they are scientifically illiterate. Although many people possess the common sense to avoid clearly dangerous acts such as injecting themselves with bleach, they can follow harmful misinformation that can have a great impact on the health of themselves and others. Therefore, the importance of being a well-informed citizen cannot be understated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The scale of the crisis calls for immediate action regarding the spread of misinformation. First, trusted individuals and institutions need to stop legitimizing false COVID-19 theories. When leaders such as the President of the United States claim masks are insignificant in preventing the spread of COVID-19, as many as 10% of Americans (30 million people) will refuse to wear masks. Thus, America remains the world’s leader of cases. Similarly, in Brazil, President Jair Bolsonaro dismissed the epidemic and the legitimacy of the virus. Consequently, Brazil remains a major center for COVID-19 cases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fight against pseudoscience is hopeless if people are unsure who to trust and put their faith in the wrong people. Pseudoscience is unfortunately very effective and gives people a false sense of their place in this pandemic. If people trust well-informed professionals with their care, the world would be better off. Therefore, scientists and medical professionals should be the face of the fight against misinformation. This would hopefully show the general masses that trusting scientists is the best option for their health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the theories themselves are ridiculous, they need to be taken seriously, especially since they are spreading while the world fights a global pandemic. When people believe in pseudoscience, they ignore real medical professionals’ recommendations for their health, such as wearing masks in public. These effects are dangerous to society, and therefore, the general public needs to become more scientifically literate, and politicians and health professionals need to come together against the spread of misinformation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (BBC)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Carly Schinhofen
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Carly Schinhofen</name></author><summary type="html">Pseudoscience and COVID-19 Carly Schinhofen. 9/4/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/pseudoCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/pseudoCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Understanding California’s devastating wildfires</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/04/california-wildfires.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Understanding California’s devastating wildfires" /><published>2020-09-04T09:00:04-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-04T09:00:04-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/04/california-wildfires</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/04/california-wildfires.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Understanding California’s devastating wildfires&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emily Richter. 9/4/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/september/wildFireOne.png&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Firefighters fight the River Fire in Salinas, California. (NBC News)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Destructive wildfires burn through California annually. Every year in the late summer, stories of Californian communities being reduced to ash start showing up on the covers of worldwide newspapers. But why are these fires so devastating? Here are three reasons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reason #1: California’s climate
Anyone who lives in California will remember how the rainstorms of the last three winters have been so severe they caused mudslides. How can wildfires start if the ground absorbs so much moisture in the winter? Scientists of the American Meteorologist Society say that the answer is simple: more rain means more vegetation growth. Water that falls in the winter encourages plants to grow, and these plants dry out over the summer. Over the last decade, California has experienced summers that are longer, hotter and drier than usual. Researchers at the University of Wisconsin-Madison warn that this combination of wet, vegetation-friendly winters and long, hot, dry summers creates plenty of dry vegetation for massive wildfires to thrive off of.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reason #2: Fuel ladders&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/september/wildFireTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;30%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This is a graphic of a fuel ladder. (Living With Fire)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The land of California is designed to survive frequent fires. A large portion of California is composed of ecosystems that depend on fire to encourage the health of their vegetation. In fact, some Californian plants, called fire-induced sprouts, cannot even begin to grow until they have been burned. However, the presence of people has reduced the amount of natural fire activity in California’s fire-dependent ecosystems. As soon as a fire starts, people understandably feel threatened and elect to fight the fire. While well-meaning, this strategy of consistently suppressing fire leads to fuel ladders. When sweeping through an area, a fire feeds primarily on the dead plant matter and excessive ground foliage found on the ground. In a healthy fire-reliant ecosystem, the fire would stay low to the ground and mostly feed off of this fuel. Every so often, it would randomly remove some larger types of vegetation, clearing up space in the ecosystem. However, after decades of fire suppression, crowded ecosystem floors are teeming with saplings and other types of vulnerable vegetation. The fire jumps to these and then to larger and taller trees; this expands the size of the fire, and it also can kill trees that would otherwise be unharmed by wildfire. While ground fires are crucial to much of California’s land, fires that climb fuel ladders lead to uncontrollable fires and devastated ecosystems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Reason #3: People living in fire-prone areas
The number of people on the planet grows every day. As the population increases, the need for housing also increases; as the need for housing increases, houses are starting to be built in areas prone to wildfire. A study from the University of California, Riverside notes that when urban areas and the wilderness meet, the risk of wildfire is higher and the possibility of devastation is greater. Firefighters suppress any fires starting in urban areas, creating severe fuel ladders that have the potential to start fast-moving fires just outside neighborhoods. As more and more Californians move onto land naturally meant to burn, the chance of another community being devastated by fire increases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The countless tragic wildfires of the last five years have brought attention to the issue of fire prevention. Thanks to new research and new policies, there is hope that someday soon, devastating fires will no longer be the norm in California.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (NBC News)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Emily Richter
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Emily is a junior from Maria Carrillo High School in Sonoma County. She loves chemistry and the environmental sciences and plans to be an environmental chemist when she gets older. Through InterSTEM, she hopes to combine her experience in writing with her interest in STEM in order to help others enjoy and understand STEM. In her free time, she likes playing the flute, and baking and cooking.

&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Emily Richter</name></author><summary type="html">Understanding California’s devastating wildfires Emily Richter. 9/4/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/wildFireCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/wildFireCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mysteries surrounding foreign accent syndrome</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/04/accent-syndrome.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mysteries surrounding foreign accent syndrome" /><published>2020-09-04T09:00:03-04:00</published><updated>2020-09-04T09:00:03-04:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/04/accent-syndrome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/04/accent-syndrome.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Mysteries surrounding foreign accent syndrome&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eric Bebenov. 9/4/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/september/mysteriesOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;A person suffering from foreign accent syndrome is experiencing an alteration in their accent. (Health Jade)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Imagine waking up, and when greeting someone with a “good morning”, you suddenly start speaking with an accent depicting a foreign country. Then you think to yourself, “When was the last time that I traveled to a foreign country?” or, “Do I even speak the language that resembles this accent?” Well, some scientists have attached a name to this phenomenon, known as foreign accent syndrome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to researchers at UT Dallas, foreign accent syndrome (FAS) is a speech disorder that alters a person’s native speech to speak as though they have a foreign accent. This could be a result of a stroke, brain lesions, multiple sclerosis or a brain injury that has imposed trauma. In some instances, however, the cause of this phenomenon is unexplained. Timing, intonation, and even tongue placement all contribute to a person’s FAS experience. A person’s abrupt change in tongue or mouth muscle movement can closely resemble that of a specific geographic region in the world, even though they might not share any ties to it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers have identified that in some instances, FAS has been a direct result of damage imposed and directed towards the Broca’s area of the brain. Broca’s area is responsible for regulating the movement of muscles that control a person’s speaking apparatus, and related movements of lips, tongue, larynx and pharynx.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding FAS, it is important to consider what symptoms might emerge when one is subject to this unpredictable condition. Individuals who have difficulty pronouncing clusters of sound, have trouble “tapping” their tongue behind their top front teeth, pronounce vowels differently or even have a different pitch or tone on certain sounds, are all subject to the possibility of FAS. Most of these symptoms can last from months to years or even remain permanent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a case study examined by the US National Library of Medicine and National Institutes of Health, the person of interest experiencing FAS had developed it as a result of a minor head trauma. It was noted that the patient deleted phonemes, which are small sets of speech sounds that are distinguished by the speakers of a particular language, in addition to speaking at a very slow rate. Her once French accent, a syllable-timed language, transformed into a speech rhythm that was qualified as stress-timed. In other words, the change in the rhythm of her speech forced her to take on a different accent that resembled a completely different geographic region.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to treating FAS, treatment revolves around exploring the main cause of the condition in an individual. Since there has been some type of deficiency in the brain that serves as a catalyst for the syndrome, patients may receive medical prescriptions to alleviate and treat the abnormality in the brain or the persisting symptoms. Additionally, a common practice suggested is speech therapy, although symptoms might not completely go away.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, the minuscule number of cases associated with FAS still leaves many questions unanswered concerning this medical phenomenon. Research is still being done to identify the significant connection between neurological damage and the emergence of foreign accent syndrome. Symptoms also continue to be investigated in addition to possible advancements in treatment. Until further discoveries are made, however, medical officials will have to utilize what is available when diagnosing patients and do the best they can to minimize any negative speech alterations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (National Neuroscience Curriculum Initiative)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Eric Bebenov&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;

&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Eric Bebenov</name></author><summary type="html">Mysteries surrounding foreign accent syndrome Eric Bebenov. 9/4/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/mysteriesCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/mysteriesCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>