<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-02-15T19:23:51-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">InterSTEM</title><entry><title type="html">Exploring social networks</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/exploring-social-networks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Exploring social networks" /><published>2021-02-04T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-04T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/exploring-social-networks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/exploring-social-networks.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Exploring social networks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simone Rothaupt. 02/06/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/february/socialNetworkOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Student social networks in U.S. high schools contain racial divides and variations in the number of friendships each individual has. In the model above, the color of the dot represents the race of each student: white dots for white students, gray dots for black students, light gray dots for Hispanic students and black dots for students of other races.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.3982/ECTA7528&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Econometrica)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Humans are inherently social beings. According to Domènec Melé and César González Cantón in their book “&lt;a href=&quot;https://link.springer.com/chapter/10.1057/9781137462619_10&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Human Foundations of Management&lt;/a&gt;,” sociability is one of the core characteristics of humankind, as communication and collaboration initiate relationships between individuals. In InterSTEM’s third speaker lecture, Dr. Matthew Jackson — an economics professor at Stanford University and an extensive researcher in game theory, microeconomics and social networks — discussed the economic implications of our social networks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As Dr. Jackson explained, a social network can vary in size and density. While many individuals would expect a social network to be relatively uniform with equal connections across all individuals, the reality is quite different. He conducted a study with fellow researchers Sergio Currarini and Paolo Pinarini for &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.3982/ECTA7528&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the Econometrica Journal&lt;/a&gt; on a high school friendship network. They found that the high school was heavily segregated between black and white students, as few friendships existed between these races. In addition, certain students had a significantly greater number of friendships than others within the separate friend groups that formed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These findings also hold true for other cultures. For instance, another research study conducted by Dr. Jackson, along with Abhijit Banerjee, Arun Chandrasekhar and Esther Duflo for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nber.org/system/files/working_papers/w17743/w17743.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the National Bureau of Economic Research&lt;/a&gt;, revealed that villages in Karnataka, India contain segregation and a wide range in the number of connections for each person.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Jackson asserts that this variability of relationships affects the diffusion of information and disease, which can result in both greater interconnectedness and polarization. Thus, research on this topic has become popular due to its potential to yield a vast wealth of information on human nature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using analysis techniques like degree centrality, eigenvector centrality and diffusion centrality that measure the connectedness of individuals within social networks, Francis Bloch, Jackson and Pietro Tebaldi suggest in their 2017 paper “&lt;a href=&quot;https://arxiv.org/pdf/1608.05845.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Centrality Measures In Networks&lt;/a&gt;” that the spread of information and contagion can be traced throughout the world quantitatively. For instance, in an inaugural article for the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pnas.org/content/112/50/15277.abstract&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America&lt;/a&gt; in 2015, Dr. Jackson and Stephen Nei were able to measure connectedness between countries throughout the past by examining international trade treaties since the early 1800s. They found that before World War II, the average country had 2.5 allies, and their treaties had a 67% chance of lasting five years. After World War II, the average country had 10.5 allies, and their treaties had a 95% chance of lasting five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On its own, the data collected on social networks appears to hold little real-life significance. However, these studies reveal much information on how human society functions and how the world can work better. The study on world treaties demonstrates that from the 1950s and beyond, the greater integration of trade between countries has correlated with less volatile and more steady relationships with nearly one-tenth as many wars per pairs of countries as before. Thus, increased trade and alliances can result in decreased conflicts as a certain threshold of trade is reached. As Daniel Griswold of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cato.org/speeches/can-free-trade-promote-peace-middle-east&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CATO Institute&lt;/a&gt; elucidates, promoting trade among countries, such as in the Middle East, has the potential to foster peace among warring nations. Even with these benefits, Christine Lagarde — the Managing Director of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imf.org/en/News/Articles/2015/09/28/04/53/sp091913&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;International Monetary Fund&lt;/a&gt; (IMF) — explains that the interconnected global economy also results in negative consequences where financial shocks in one market can reverberate around the world. Another &lt;a href=&quot;https://blogs.imf.org/2018/10/03/lasting-effects-the-global-economic-recovery-10-years-after-the-crisis/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;IMF&lt;/a&gt; article highlights the danger of such a globalized market, when the 2008 United States Housing Crisis resulted in the economic downturn in Europe, Asia and beyond.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Furthermore, the data collected for the study conducted by Dr. Jackson and his colleagues on social networks in India also contains valuable economic information. This research helps microfinance campaigns so that banks loaning money to those in poverty can effectively reach out to those in need by finding the most interconnected person in each village. Therefore, research on social networks contains valuable information for companies and organizations seeking to expand their influence and grow their market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ultimately, the growing global social network of humans will promote interconnectedness and peace, yet it will still result in segregation among racial and political party lines and enable crises to proliferate across the globe. As new networking platforms like social media rise in popularity and give new modes of connection for society, we must learn to keep the negative consequences in check while still maximizing the potential benefits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Shutterstock/Optimarc)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Simone Rothaupt &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Simone is a sophomore at Thousand Oaks High School in Ventura, California. She is interested in exploring STEM related topics, such as medicine, and she also hopes to spread this passion to others through writing.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Simone Rothaupt</name></author><summary type="html">Exploring social networks Simone Rothaupt. 02/06/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/socialNetworkCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/socialNetworkCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What is citizen science?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/what-is-a-citizen-science.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is citizen science?" /><published>2021-02-04T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-04T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/what-is-a-citizen-science</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/what-is-a-citizen-science.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;What is citizen science?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emily Richter. 02/12/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/february/citizenScienceOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Volunteers with the Monarch Butterfly Monitoring Project engage in an organized citizen science event by recording data on tagged monarch butterflies.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fs.fed.us/wildflowers/pollinators/Monarch_Butterfly/citizenscience/index.shtml&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(U.S. Forest Service)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Scientific research, especially when it is regarding ecology or biology, can be a daunting task. Researchers often have to collect vast amounts of data in a short amount of time, a task that proves itself to be difficult. How can researchers ease this burden by outsourcing this work to willing and reliable sources? The answer lies in something called citizen science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States’ &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nps.gov/subjects/citizenscience/citizen-science.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Park Service&lt;/a&gt; defines citizen science as “the voluntary involvement of the public in scientific research”. What exactly is the “voluntary involvement of the public”, and precisely how can everyday people contribute to complex research projects? The answer to this query is multifaceted and complex, ultimately outlining a system that connects scientific enthusiasts to researchers in need of a hand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sometimes citizen science involves recruiting volunteers to participate in outlined data collection. Scientists and other research leaders teach willing citizens how to collect data in a way that is consistent with a particular research project, and then the volunteers complete specific assigned tasks. One event structured in this way is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fs.fed.us/wildflowers/pollinators/Monarch_Butterfly/citizenscience/index.shtml&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Monarch Butterfly Monitoring Project&lt;/a&gt; based in Kansas. Every fall, volunteers across the United States gather in designated Monarch butterfly migration and breeding sites to collect data on everything from the presence of Monarch eggs on host plants like milkweed to parasites on adult butterflies. After undergoing a training process led by professional biologists, volunteers spend hours counting, capturing, tagging, observing and photographing Monarchs. Already, the efforts of thousands of dedicated citizen scientists have helped researchers at the University of Kansas and the University of Wisconsin-Madison understand the lives these elusive insects live.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite the usefulness of organized citizen science events, many people do not have the free time to participate in events such as these. Several are multiple-hour commitments that take place far away from cities or suburban areas. Semi-organized events such as the Cornell Lab of Ornithology’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://nestwatch.org/about/overview/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;NestWatch&lt;/a&gt; can be great compromises for people who want to take part in structured data collection without having to clear their calendars. Prospective NestWatch volunteers are trained by ornithologists and professional researchers. The training covers the basics of bird biology and explains how NestWatch citizen scientists should collect and report data on birds’ nests. For each recorded nest, NestWatch aims to collect data regarding the nesting trends of different species of birds. With the help of thousands of dedicated citizen scientists, the project aims to understand how the changing environment is impacting birds and their breeding habits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Organized and semi-organized volunteer projects are helpful, but they can only collect so much data. How do researchers use citizen science to collect large amounts of data from all around the world? The answer lies with cameras and cell phones. In big cities, people walk to work and take pictures of the eye-catching plants and animals that cross their paths. Those who live in rural areas take pictures that outline the ecosystems playing out around them. Visitors of protected areas of nature marvel at the living wonders around them, taking pictures of everything from the smallest butterfly to the tallest tree. What if those pictures could be used to contribute to professional research and advance science?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Citizen science websites like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inaturalist.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;iNaturalist&lt;/a&gt; use a format similar to social media to collect data on a wide variety of species. Contributors submit pictures along with basic information about when and where the picture was taken, and the post is released to the website, where viewers can add to the post and comment on it. If enough people interact with the post, the picture and associated information can be tagged as “Research Grade”. Citizen science websites like iNaturalist bring together people from different backgrounds with different knowledge and different skills, creating a thriving community that contributes significantly to scientific research.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists all over the world consistently use data from iNaturalist to answer their questions about the range and habits of different organisms. Another similar citizen science website, &lt;a href=&quot;https://ebird.org/home&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;eBird&lt;/a&gt;, has allowed scientists at the Cornell Lab of Ornithology and Colorado State University to &lt;a href=&quot;https://ebird.org/news/less-light-more-trees-help-migrating-birds&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;discover patterns&lt;/a&gt; that reflect the novel needs of migratory birds in a world full of changing environments. As of early 2021, citizen scientists on eBird have cataloged over 10,000 species of birds, helping biologists, ecologists and ornithologists gain an understanding of specific species at a groundbreaking rate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While most often used within ecological and biological fields, citizen science has also been applied to other areas of scientific study, including astronomy. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://science.nasa.gov/get-involved/citizenscience/five-extraordinary-citizen-science-discoveries&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;United States National Aeronautics and Space Administration&lt;/a&gt; (NASA) regularly uses the observations of astrological citizen scientists as starting points for various projects and studies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyone interested in participating in any type of citizen science can easily find a way to do so. The National Park Service houses a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nps.gov/subjects/citizenscience/be-a-citizen-scientist.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;large database&lt;/a&gt; of different organized volunteer events on their website, complete with filters based on location, project type and event format. To participate in citizen science via iNaturalist, eBird or NestWatch, one can simply make an account for free and begin participating immediately. A database including other internet-based citizen science opportunities can be found through the website of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.citizensciencealliance.org/index.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Citizen Science Alliance&lt;/a&gt;. Citizen science pushes scientific research forward like nothing else, and every person who participates in the crowd-sourced form of data collection is immeasurably valuable to the scientific community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nps.gov/knri/learn/news/biodiversity-project-at-knri.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(National Park Service)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Emily Richter&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Emily is a junior from Maria Carrillo High School in Sonoma County. She loves chemistry and the environmental sciences and plans to be an environmental chemist when she gets older. Through InterSTEM, she hopes to combine her experience in writing with her interest in STEM in order to help others enjoy and understand STEM. In her free time, she likes playing the flute, and baking and cooking.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Emily Richter</name></author><summary type="html">What is citizen science? Emily Richter. 02/12/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/citizenScienceCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/citizenScienceCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Antibiotic resistance: A growing threat to global health</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/a-growing-threat-to-global-health.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Antibiotic resistance: A growing threat to global health" /><published>2021-02-04T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-04T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/a-growing-threat-to-global-health</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/a-growing-threat-to-global-health.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Antibiotic resistance: A growing threat to global health&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nadwa Atwi. 02/12/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/february/globalHealthOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;In the image, penicillium is growing on a Petri dish and neutralizing the bacteria.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@yeonjoon.kim/module10-eid100-technological-breakthrough-penicillin-f5a58fed2d0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Medium)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For decades, antibiotics have been considered the wonder drug that cures all infections. It all started when Alexander Fleming, a Scottish microbiologist, came back from a two-week vacation in 1928 only to accidentally discover green mold (now known as Penicillium) developing on his culture plates and killing some bacteria he’d been growing. Since then, the discovery of Penicillin (a substance produced by Penicillium) has changed the course of medicine and enabled physicians to treat formerly brutal and life-threatening diseases. The overuse of antibiotics, however, propelled the evolution of resistance. As a result, plenty of bacteria have become unresponsive to antibiotics, and consequently, a number of infections have become incredibly challenging to treat.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;What are antibiotics?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antibiotics are drugs specifically targeted to damage the essential parts of a bacterial cell or disrupt its critical functions. They are usually prescribed to prevent or treat bacterial infections like strep throat and pneumonia. Although the body can occasionally fight off infections on its own, in instances where a bacterial infection is already severe enough to cause a high-grade fever, antibiotics become the primary choice of treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But what happens when bacteria become resistant to a certain antibiotic? Well, according to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/drugresistance/about.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Centers for Disease Control and Prevention&lt;/a&gt; (CDC), a patient would expect longer-lasting illnesses, extended hospital stays, additional follow-up doctor visits and more costly treatments. Such alternative treatments usually display more adverse side-effects and occasionally even fail to treat the infection, resulting in death.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;How do bacteria become resistant to antibiotics?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yourgenome.org/facts/what-is-antibiotic-resistance&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;two major pathways&lt;/a&gt;: DNA mutations and horizontal gene transfer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When DNA mutations result in a favorable change in the organism, this leads to its evolution, a natural process that occurs in all living beings. One example is a bacterium that has recently acquired a certain trait that allows it to resist an antibiotic’s assault. This ‘upgraded’ bacterium would grow and divide just like its siblings, but up until now, it’s very unlikely that it would overrule them in number, considering it’s pretty new. When the antibiotic is introduced, however, all the ‘traditional’ bacteria targeted by this antibiotic die, whereas the ‘upgraded’ bacteria are left unscathed with a greater chance of survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although mutations are a natural way for bacteria to acquire antibiotic resistance, certain factors can still increase its prevalence. Those include excessive use of antibiotics, their inappropriate handling (like taking antibiotics to treat viral and fungal infections) and a discontinued course of antibiotic treatment. Recently, the overuse of antibiotics in agriculture has started to gain attention too, especially in food-producing animals. In many countries, the major reasons for antibiotic use in animals are growth promotion and disease prevention rather than the treatment of sick animals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another pathway for bacteria to obtain resistance is horizontal gene transfer. Simply stated, it involves a resistant bacterium gifting its resistance to a susceptible bacterium through plasmids. A plasmid is a small naturally-occurring DNA molecule distinct from a bacterial cell’s chromosomal DNA. The genes carried in plasmids often provide bacteria with genetic enhancements, such as antibiotic resistance. By undergoing a process called conjugation, bacterial cells can share plasmids, and thus their advantageous add-ons, with each other to increase their chances of survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/february/globalHealthTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
The transfer of the plasmid containing the mutated gene spreads antibiotic resistance between different bacteria.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://labtestsonline.org/articles/antibiotic-resistance-bacteria&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Lab Tests Online)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Antibiotic-resistant Bacteria&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some bacteria have acquired resistance to antibiotics that were once commonly used to treat them. The most prominent examples are Staphylococcus aureus (also known as golden staph or MRSA) and Neisseria gonorrhoeae (which causes gonorrhea).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the most serious concern with antibiotic resistance right now is that some bacteria have become resistant to almost all of the easily available antibiotics. In some countries, the alternative treatment options for these bacteria are expensive and not always available.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These ‘superbugs’ are now capable of causing serious illnesses, which has become a major public health problem. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/news-room/q-a-detail/tuberculosis-multidrug-resistant-tuberculosis-(mdr-tb)&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Multi-drug-resistant Mycobacterium tuberculosis&lt;/a&gt; (MDR-TB) is a strain of Mycobacterium tuberculosis that has adapted to the most powerful tuberculosis drugs and became resistant to them. Further drug resistance of the bacteria at some point in the future could eventually render it untreatable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;So what’s the next step?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/campaigns/world-antimicrobial-awareness-week&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;World Health Organization&lt;/a&gt; (WHO) has been working on spreading awareness about antibiotic resistance. They have even dedicated an entire week in November for World Antimicrobial Awareness that aims to promote awareness of global antimicrobial resistance and to inspire proper practices among health workers and the general public to deter further emergence and spread of drug-resistant infections.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year since 2015, posters are put up to inform people about the proper use of antibiotics. Notable instructions include only using antibiotics for bacterial infections, as they aren’t effective for common colds and bronchitis (which are mainly caused by viruses), practicing proper hygiene and finishing the full prescribed course of treatment even if the patient starts feeling better. Farmers are also encouraged to stop antibiotic abuse in livestock.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/february/globalHealthThree.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
An assortment of posters is put up by NPS MedicineWise to educate people about antibiotic resistance. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.science.org.au/curious/people-medicine/fighting-back-antimicrobial-resistance&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1613210506458000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw0vSdpXcLxLIOyvSaeGLXdN&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Australian Academy of Science)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Antibiotic resistance resulting from antibiotic misuse is putting modern medical advancements and medicine at risk of becoming ineffective. Procedures such as organ transplants, chemotherapy and surgeries become increasingly dangerous without effective antibiotics to prevent and treat infections. Reducing the improper use of antibiotics and making sure to adhere to the proper policies will make a difference and will help prevent antibiotic resistance in the future. However, this is all dependent on how willing people are to follow the given advice for their future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (BioPharma Reporter)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Nadwa Atwi &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Nadwa is a pharmacy student from Lebanon. She is a science enthusiast that loves to feed her curiosity by probing into the most unusual medical conditions. Through InterSTEM, Nadwa aspires to let people recognize just how fascinating science can be, and hopes to share her passion with them as well. In her free time, she enjoys reading novels and reviewing them on her blog, binge-watching anime and fangirling over her favorite Kpop groups.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Nadwa Atwi</name></author><summary type="html">Antibiotic resistance: A growing threat to global health Nadwa Atwi. 02/12/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/globalHealthCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/globalHealthCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Mars rovers: Past, present and future</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/mars-rover-past-present-and-future.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mars rovers: Past, present and future" /><published>2021-02-04T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-02-04T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/mars-rover-past-present-and-future</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/02/04/mars-rover-past-present-and-future.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Mars rovers: Past, present and future&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sydney Hollingsworth. 02/06/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/february/marsOne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The image above is the concept art for NASA’s Mars 2020 Perseverance rover.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.space.com/mars-2020-rover-naming-contest-semifinalists.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Space / NASA)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Since the dawn of humanity, people have turned their gazes to the heavens time and time again. The stars and planets of the night sky have always been things of mystery. The more we learn about our own solar system, the more questions seem to arise. In recent years, astronomers have turned their attention to our closest neighbor, the Red Planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once thought to be a barren, dusty expanse, Mars is now believed to provide our best chance at an off-world settlement. With the discovery of frozen water and the possibility of past life on Mars, plenty of questions have been plaguing scientists and will most likely be answered with the help of the same technology that dug them up in the first place: Martian rovers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The topic of Mars rovers has graced headlines many times since the Sojourner rover and Pathfinder lander first touched the planet’s dusty surface. Civilians and researchers at the Jet Propulsion Laboratory alike have grown a sentimental attachment to these scientific instruments working away so far from home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been a total of four successful Mars rovers, all by NASA’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jpl.nasa.gov/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Jet Propulsion Laboratory&lt;/a&gt; located in Southern California. The use of rovers gives an advantage over landers, which are stationary, and orbiters, which can only observe the surface of Mars from the upper atmosphere. They also give mission control the ability to direct rovers towards new, promising areas and collect samples from multiple locations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first Mars rover, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.jpl.nasa.gov/missions/mars-pathfinder-sojourner-rover/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Sojourner&lt;/a&gt;, was launched on Dec. 4, 1996 and landed on the Red Planet on July 4th of the following year. Sojourner was accompanied by the Pathfinder lander, which relayed the rover’s gathered information back to Earth. A scientific innovation of its time, the lander relied mostly on a parachute and airbags rather than its rockets to land.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The mission was only meant to last seven days, but the Sojourner rover spent a total of 83 days studying the surface of Mars, never venturing further than 40 feet from the Pathfinder lander. The rover finally stopped responding on Sept. 27, 1997, likely due to a failed battery. Sojourner was able to capture the first photos from the surface of Mars, as well as collect measurements of chemicals in the planet’s atmosphere and dust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The two &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalgeographic.com/science/2019/02/nasa-mars-rover-opportunity-dead-what-it-gave-humankind/#close&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mars Exploration Rovers&lt;/a&gt;, launched just one month apart towards opposite sides of the planet, were built in just 34 months by the same laboratory. The team took eight-hour shifts to work 24 hours a day, 7 days a week to complete the sizable project and even continued to send software updates while the rovers were en route to Mars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first twin was &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://solarsystem.nasa.gov/missions/spirit/in-depth/&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1612603012570000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw0Kc4vgSx-fbVB3ThltciQL&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Spirit&lt;/a&gt;, which was launched on June 10, 2003 and landed on Jan. 4, 2004. Unlike Sojourner, Spirit boasted a built-in lander, eliminating the need to stay close to a stationary lander in order to relay information back to Earth. The main goals of the mission were to investigate the geological features of Mars and areas that may have once had water, take pictures of the surface with a 360-degree camera and send these discoveries back to Earth with the help of NASA’s 2001 Mars Odyssey satellite. Three course corrections, a landing that was eight miles off the target and a brief radio silence just 17 days into the mission had Spirit off to a rough start, but the rover ended up lasting over six years and traveled just under five miles before succumbing to the harsh Martian winter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&quot;https://mars.nasa.gov/news/8414/six-things-to-know-about-nasas-opportunity-rover/#:~:text=It%20was%20the%20first%20rover,late%20from%20rising%2C%20acidic%20groundwater.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Opportunity&lt;/a&gt; rover landed on the rocky surface of Mars on Jan. 25, 2004. This rover would go on to discover water and sedimentary rock on Mars, inspiring the search for possible life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Like the Spirit rover, Opportunity’s life expectancy was estimated at 90 to 100 days, at which point, dust build-up on the solar panels would presumably cut off its power supply. However, NASA was unable to take into account the extremely strong winds of Mars. These winds kept Opportunity’s solar panels clean for 14 and a half years, longer than every other Mars rover combined. During this time, it traveled over 28 miles across the treacherous Martian plains. The rover’s famous last transmission to Earth in June of 2018 - “My battery is low and it’s getting dark” - tugged at the heartstrings of people around the world when Opportunity found itself caught in a strong dust storm that blocked out the sun. NASA finally concluded attempts for reconnection after nearly eight months.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fourth and only currently active martian rover, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.space.com/17963-mars-curiosity.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Curiosity&lt;/a&gt;, landed on Aug. 6, 2012 and is still relaying information back to Earth today. As the largest rover ever sent to space, as it is about the size of an SUV, its landing brought up a few unique challenges. Airbags alone would not be enough to break the rover’s fall, so a parachute and precise rockets had to be used instead. Curiosity’s mission is to gather information on Martian geology and climate and answer the question of whether or not Mars could have ever supported life, all to better prepare NASA for a future human settlement on the planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2013, the Curiosity rover discovered that Mars had previously supported conditions favorable to life and further confirmed this in 2014 when it found organic material, the building blocks of life as we know it. In 2017, Curiosity was updated with a software called Autonomous Exploration Gathering Increased Science (AEGIS), allowing it to choose targets by itself and making it the first artificial intelligence on a faraway spacecraft. The rover currently works with multiple international Mars orbiters to relay information back to Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Jet Propulsion Laboratory’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://mars.nasa.gov/mars2020/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mars 2020&lt;/a&gt; mission aims to search for ancient microbial life on Mars, measure radiation levels, gather information on climate and collect rock and soil samples to be returned to Earth in the future with the help of a collaboration between NASA and the European Space Agency (ESA).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The star of this mission will be NASA’s most advanced rover yet, named &lt;a href=&quot;https://mars.nasa.gov/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Perseverance&lt;/a&gt;. The rover will utilize technology expected to be used in future Mars settlements, such as a system to produce oxygen from the Martian atmosphere. Perseverance will also be transporting a helicopter drone called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/feature/jpl/6-things-to-know-about-nasas-ingenuity-mars-helicopter/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ingenuity&lt;/a&gt;, the first aircraft in another world. If the drone succeeds, NASA will consider future aerial missions on Mars. Perseverance and Ingenuity were launched on July 30, 2020 and are expected to land on Feb. 18 of this year.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The future of humanity’s relationship with Mars will likely depend on what Perseverance finds. Every past Mars rover has made discoveries that have completely changed our understanding of the planet, and as the first rover to take into account the possibility of past life on Mars, Perseverance has its work cut out for it. Hopefully, whatever it finds will shed further light on the many mysteries of the Red Planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.360cities.net/image/curiosity-rover-martian-solar-day-2#35.47,-7.67,110.0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(360 Cities)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Sydney Hollingsworth&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sydney Hollingsworth</name></author><summary type="html">Mars rovers: Past, present and future Sydney Hollingsworth. 02/06/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/marsCover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/february/marsCover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Starlink’s journey to 1,000 more</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/28/starlinks-journey-to-1000-more.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Starlink’s journey to 1,000 more" /><published>2021-01-28T16:00:03-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-28T16:00:03-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/28/starlinks-journey-to-1000-more</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/28/starlinks-journey-to-1000-more.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Starlink’s journey to 1,000 more&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mehri Sadri. 01/29/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/starlinksOne.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Starlink satellites are often seen traveling parallel to one another.
(DIY Photography)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It’s a clear spring night, and you decide to go stargazing with some friends. You gather some pillows, blankets and board games, laying them on the lawn grass. Laying down on the cushions, you see some faint stars in the distance, nothing too unusual. Hoping to perhaps see a shooting star, your eyes rapidly jerk up in response to what looks like a link of stars traveling through the night sky. Not 10 or 20, rather 100 or 200 rapidly beaming circles rushing in and out of your view. You turn to your friends, who look anything but worried about what you perceive as a potential alien invasion, instead calmly admiring the crazy view. “Starlink, huh?” one exclaims.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What is Starlink? Well, it is no alien invasion, rather a movement of satellites that stream around Earth at all times. Get lucky, and you may even see them making their way around your home. Though simply aesthetically pleasing to some, these futuristic-looking sky sequins serve an important purpose: giving everyone on Earth access to faster Internet speeds and data. But, of course, they also obstruct an astronomer’s view, which is more controversial than you may think! In the latest Starlink launch on Jan. 20, SpaceX reached the large 1,000 satellite mark, totaling 1,015 beams of light fluttering across the sky. Though this may already seem like an impressively large number, SpaceX founder and CEO &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/how-elon-musk-42000-starlink-satellites-earth-effects-stars-2020-10&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Elon Musk&lt;/a&gt;, is nowhere near finished, as he wants to include at least another 41,000 satellites to the bunch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the capabilities of wireless satellites, Musk desires to cut out the lag often associated with typical telecommunications products, providing a profit for not only those companies if successful, but also for SpaceX. The satellites will be at different proximities to Earth, as this allows the greatest range and network efficiency for individuals around the globe. The first satellite was launched in May 2019, and the first set had a successful altitude launch of 340 miles from the ground. Starlink serves to create faster proximities of Internet speed, and it will work up to a gigabit per second with a latency of 25 to 35 milliseconds, with 5 trillion bytes a day of data generated as of June 2020. For comparison, the speeds that Starlink will eventually offer stand &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@ankushborkar/starlink-vs-5g-f69b1dcdd8ab&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;10 times faster than typical 4G networks, but not as fast as 5G&lt;/a&gt;. Starlink has a goal to serve individuals who may struggle to find good connections due to their geographic location, a number Musk estimates to be between 3% to 4% of the world population.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be curious as to what operating system SpaceX uses to control Starlink. Currently, the network system known as Linux is being put into full force, with each satellite &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.yahoo.com/entertainment/5-trillion-bytes-day-spacex-232141318.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;containing around 4,000 Linux computers&lt;/a&gt;. Linux is no stranger in the world of networking and communication; it has been an open-source operating system in use since 1991. Linux has had a rivalry with Windows operating systems, such as Windows 10, with Linux claiming it runs &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.softwaretestinghelp.com/linux-vs-windows/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“faster and smoother” than its counterpart.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;SpaceX’s project is one of innovation; however, they are not the only company with an equally ambitious project. &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/@ankushborkar/starlink-vs-5g-f69b1dcdd8ab&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Companies like Vodafone, Samsung and even Amazon’s Blue Origin&lt;/a&gt; rocket launching company are currently striving to create similar satellite networks, attempting to provide the internet to more people than ever before.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though these competitors may bring out full-force systems similar to Starlink in the future, for now, we can all credit that nightly-chain of rapidly expanding ‘stars’ to none other than SpaceX.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Nurphoto / Getty Images)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/Mehri_Sadri.JPG&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Mehri Sadri&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Mehri is a senior at Scripps Ranch High School in San Diego, California. Although she has always been more inclined in humanities subjects, Mehri has found a love for combining science and art and their practicalities, and hopes to spread this same love to others with her articles.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Mehri Sadri</name></author><summary type="html">Starlink’s journey to 1,000 more Mehri Sadri. 01/29/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/starlinksCover.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/starlinksCover.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Great Filter</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/28/the-great-filter.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Great Filter" /><published>2021-01-28T16:00:02-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-28T16:00:02-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/28/the-great-filter</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/28/the-great-filter.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The Great Filter&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Famesh Patel. 01/29/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/greatFilterOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Fermi’s Paradox states that there is an apparent contradiction between lack of alien encounters and the highly probable chance of their existence.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantamagazine.org/galaxy-simulations-offer-a-new-solution-to-the-fermi-paradox-20190307/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Quanta Magazine)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Water. Where the start and end of alien life occurs. You may think that water is highly limited, maybe even to just our own Earth, but actually, we’ve discovered tons of it. Hydrogen is the most abundant element in the universe, and oxygen is the third most abundant (the second most is helium, which is highly unreactive). Thus, when these elements come into close contact with each other, they form water. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drake_equation#:~:text=The%20Drake%20equation%20is%20a,in%20the%20Milky%20Way%20galaxy.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Drake Equation&lt;/a&gt;, the numerical range for the number of aliens in the universe can range from one to tens of millions. With such a large range, we would expect to have made some contact with a higher intelligence being, but we haven’t. This is exactly what &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Enrico_Fermi&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Enrico Fermi&lt;/a&gt; was thinking when he came up with Fermi’s Paradox, which states the contradiction between the lack of alien encounters and the high chance of their existence. This led Fermi to ask one question (and maybe the one you’re thinking right now): where is everybody?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are multiple ways to approach this. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=GdqcVjCe0bc&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Aperture&lt;/a&gt;, one of those ways was proposed by Robin Hanson. He figured that we’ve been asking the wrong question: instead of expecting that the universe should be filled with human life forms, he thought that we should accept that life is extremely rare and our time might be limited. If he is right, we have miscalculated the steps necessary to create life, either in difficulty or correctness. Through this re-consideration of our objectives for life, we created the Great Filter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Great Filter could be anything in the timeline that created humans. It could be whatever started abiogenesis (the origin of life), the first proper replication of DNA with enough mutations that it caused evolution, the first creation of organized eukaryotic cells or even the creation of a moon to cause a proper atmosphere. It could be anything. Well, we passed it. We made it past the Great Filter. Give yourself a pat on the back…but, what if it’s ahead of us?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What if there was life teeming in the universe that was killed by a filter that exceeds our current position in time? Maybe we will witness the Great Filter when the Andromeda Galaxy smashes into our own, and we get pushed into the darkness of space. The concept behind the Great Filter is that maybe life had grown in a different place in the universe, but was never able to grow to an intergalactic scale because of some major event that wiped it out. Some relatively recent events that humanity has endured that had the potential to be the Great Filter are coronal mass ejections, a geomagnetic storm from the sun, a large meteor and a global pandemic. Just some of the ways humanity could meet its end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, the idea of the Great Filter is extremely flawed, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://mason.gmu.edu/~rhanson/greatfilter.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Robin Hanson&lt;/a&gt;. We are extrapolating this entire theory from a single data point: Earth. This is the only data point for life that we’ve ever known. What if other life forms don’t have a colonialist mindset and don’t want to find other planets with life? What if, instead of water, aliens live off of liquid mercury? The extrapolation of every variable is extremely hard to take into account when it’s all just based on speculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maybe there isn’t any Great Filter and the lack of life elsewhere just shows that our existence is a coincidence, and we are simply lucky. We are lucky to understand our reality. We are lucky that the universe is so fine-tuned for our existence - from our location in the solar system to the abundance of water. Maybe we are the only ones in our universe and we’re lucky to be here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Universe Today)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Famesh Patel&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Famesh is a senior at BASIS Peoria High School who enjoys all parts of science. Explaining the world around us with science has always seemed interesting to him from metamorphosis to the Higgs Boson. He hopes to help bring more youth to STEM fields so they can understand the natural world around us and appreciate the world for its uniqueness.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Famesh Patel</name></author><summary type="html">The Great Filter Famesh Patel. 01/29/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/greatFilterCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/greatFilterCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why is pain important?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/28/why-is-pain-important.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why is pain important?" /><published>2021-01-28T16:00:01-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-28T16:00:01-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/28/why-is-pain-important</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/28/why-is-pain-important.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Why is pain important?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nadwa Atwi. 01/29/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/painOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;A child cries in pain after falling off his bike.
(Tampa General Hospital)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Avoiding pain and seeking pleasure are the two most basic principles humans pursue. But if we think about it, occasionally, people seek pleasure in order to evade pain. It’s fascinating to acknowledge that human nature amounts to something as simple as this. But what if someone can’t feel the pain to begin with? Imagine never having to experience the immense pain that comes along with breaking a bone. It could be described as every person’s dream come true, but it’s actually a curse in disguise.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Importance of Pain&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The sensation of pain protects humans from the damaging effects of dangerous stimuli and is therefore critical for the well-being of the organism. It’s important to point out, however, that pain shouldn’t be merely regarded as a form of perception, but rather a motivation to act.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20170426-the-people-who-never-feel-any-pain&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ingo Kurth&lt;/a&gt;, a doctor at the Institute of Human Genetics in Aachen, Germany, “We fear pain, but in developmental terms from being a child to being a young adult, pain is incredibly important to the process of learning how to modulate your physical activity without doing damage to your bodies, and in determining how much risk you take.”
According to psychologists, pain consists of three dimensions or components that work as a unit in order to deliver perceptual information that eventually affects the motor processes characterizing pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first dimension is the sensory-discriminative, which allows the individual to assess the intensity, location, duration and nature of the pain. A disruption to this dimension would lead to insensitivity to pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then comes the effective-motivational component. This component provides psychological responses like irritation, anxiety and fear that motivate people to get their bodies out of danger. A malfunction in this dimension would result in indifference to pain.
The final dimension is the cognitive-evaluative, which is the brain’s evaluation of the input in terms of past experiences and its appraisal regarding the probability of different response strategies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;How do healthy individuals sense pain?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/painTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This figure demonstrates the general pathway of the pain sensation.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.brainfacts.org/thinking-sensing-and-behaving/touch/2012/touch-and-pain&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(BrainFacts)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Tissue damage caused by a hot object, as an example, is detected by pain receptors (nociceptors) in the skin, each of which forms on one end of a neuron. When the nociceptor is activated, it sends an electrical signal to the spinal cord through the nerve fiber.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Within an area of the spinal cord called the dorsal horn, the electrical signals are transmitted to the brain from one neuron to another through synapses by releasing neurotransmitters, which are essentially chemical messengers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the brain, the signals reach the thalamus, which then conveys them to different parts of the brain. Signals are sent to the somatosensory cortex (responsible for physical sensation), the frontal cortex (in charge of thinking) and the limbic system (related to emotions).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point, a person would feel the sensation and respond emotionally to the pain by feeling irritated, for example.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, by this time, the individual would have most likely already reacted involuntarily through a reflex response that occurs within the spinal cord. They would have shifted their hand away from the heat source mere milliseconds before the brain actually became aware of the pain sensation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;What is Congenital insensitivity to pain (CIP)?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Congenital insensitivity to pain is an umbrella term used to describe hereditary sensory and autonomic neuropathies (HSANs), which are rare autosomal recessive disorders characterized by the absence of pain sensation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are caused by mutations in the SCN9A gene, responsible for encoding a voltage-gated sodium channel that plays a significant role in nociceptive signaling. Both gain and loss of function mutations have been reported. For example, mutations that amplify this gene’s function causes autosomal dominant disorders characterized by extreme pain, whereas mutations that diminish the SCN9A gene’s function cause congenital insensitivity to pain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although CIP has a long history, it was not until recently that reports of individuals who showed CIP actually attracted medical attention. Scientists realized that probing into this rare disorder may offer a new understanding of pain itself, which in turn could help them better treat patients subjected to chronic pain conditions.
Patients with CIP do not seem to notice sensations of pain; that is, they have a noticeably compromised ability to perceive the intensity and quality of painful stimuli. They can sense the difference between sharp and dull sensations but cannot discern temperatures, and thus won’t notice - for example - something as typical as a hot beverage burning their tongue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Young children with congenital insensitivity to pain typically have various wounds resulting from self-mutilation, like biting their lips and fingers, in addition to multiple burn-related injuries. The accumulation of these injuries usually results in a reduced life span in individuals with this condition.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is believed that the reason this condition is so rare is because of the fact that very few patients dealing with congenital insensitivity to pain actually reach adulthood.
Congenital insensitivity to pain is closely associated with congenital indifference to pain, in which painful stimuli are perceived but there is an absence of the effective response to pain, rather than a lack of signal transmission. While these individuals report experiencing sensations of pain, they display no inclination to evade the painful stimuli.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the absence of the body’s natural warning mechanism, many individuals with congenital insensitivity to pain display - albeit unintentionally - self-destructive behaviors as children. To put it simply, pain is indispensable for survival. By sensing it, a person is able to tell when and where their body needs further care and attention.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (NBC News)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Nadwa Atwi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Nadwa is a pharmacy student from Lebanon. She is a science enthusiast that loves to feed her curiosity by probing into the most unusual medical conditions. Through InterSTEM, Nadwa aspires to let people recognize just how fascinating science can be, and hopes to share her passion with them as well. In her free time, she enjoys reading novels and reviewing them on her blog, binge-watching anime and fangirling over her favorite Kpop groups.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Nadwa Atwi</name></author><summary type="html">Why is pain important? Nadwa Atwi. 01/29/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/painCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/painCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Overview of personality psychology</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/28/overview-of-personality-psychology.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Overview of personality psychology" /><published>2021-01-28T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-28T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/28/overview-of-personality-psychology</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/28/overview-of-personality-psychology.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Overview of personality psychology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Omar Dajani. 01/29/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/psychologyOne.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This illustration ties into the origins of the word ‘personality.’ The person alternating between two different masks is exactly what the actors did a long time ago to warrant the original Latin inspiration for the word. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?app=desktop&amp;amp;v=dcsc_EsJmsA&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Practical Psychology)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A person’s personality has a tremendous impact on their life. It affects their interests, aspirations, likes, dislikes and various other aspects of their being. Because of its large influence, it has an entire branch of psychology dedicated to learning more about it. This branch, known as personality psychology, aims to understand &lt;a href=&quot;https://mypages.unh.edu/jdmayer/personality-scientific-discipline&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a person’s psychological tendencies&lt;/a&gt; and how they are displayed in everyday life. This field has been growing ever since it was established back in Ancient Greece, and many discoveries relating to personality have been made due to its expansion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For a brief history, the word ‘personality’ comes from the Latin word ‘persona.’ A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.betterhelp.com/advice/psychologists/all-about-personality-psychology-definition-and-examples/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;persona&lt;/a&gt; was defined as a mask worn by actors when they were up on stage; those masks needed to be changed multiple times throughout a performance, as shown in the illustration above. This might be taken as someone changing how they present themselves to the world, which can also extend to the way people shift their personalities around certain people. Eventually, the word ‘persona’ gave way into ‘personality.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fascination with this subject gave way to several different theories of how personality came to be. One of these theories is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/the-big-five-personality-dimensions-2795422&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the Big Five theory&lt;/a&gt;, which states that everyone has five universal personality traits. These traits are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychologytoday.com/intl/basics/conscientiousness&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;conscientiousness&lt;/a&gt; (wanting to excel in everything), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychologytoday.com/intl/basics/agreeableness&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;agreeableness&lt;/a&gt; (appearing to be kind and friendly), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/how-openness-influences-your-behavior-4796351&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;openness&lt;/a&gt; (being aware of inner feelings and desires), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/what-is-extroversion-2795994&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;extraversion&lt;/a&gt; (getting enjoyment outside of things related to the individual directly) and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychologytoday.com/intl/basics/neuroticism&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;neuroticism&lt;/a&gt; (ability to be emotional, which correlates to feelings of anxiety, fears and anger among much more). These traits are on a spectrum for everyone, with certain traits being stronger than others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other theories include &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/personality-psychology-4157179&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Freud’s theory of sexual development and Erik Erikson’s eight psychosocial stages of life&lt;/a&gt;. Freud’s theory focuses on how different erogenous zones impact development until adulthood, and Erikson’s theory centers on the idea that each stage of life is plagued by a huge psychosocial event, with this event having either a positive or negative outcome on the individual. While the former can be seen as more ‘risqué’ compared to the latter, both are very similar as they both entail that people go through different stages of development throughout their lives. These two theories state that by the end of this long developmental period, people become fully developed and are ready to be an adult.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to mention the personality types that have been observed since the field’s inception. There are about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/personality-types&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;16 personality types in total&lt;/a&gt;, all of which are based on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/the-myers-briggs-type-indicator-2795583&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;variety of certain traits&lt;/a&gt;. Some of these include sensing, perceiving, feeling and extroversion. The traits dictate someone’s personality, and each type has its own set of strong traits. Each personality has an acronym, an example being &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/intj-personality&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;INTJ&lt;/a&gt;, which means the person has Introverted, Intuitive, Thinking and Judging personality traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another discovery pertains to the fact that these 16 personalities have two types. These types, Assertive and Turbulent, dictate how the person’s personality will be exhibited. For example, an Assertive INTJ will be more outspoken and commanding, while a Turbulent INTJ will be more laid back and quiet. They are still both INTJ, but they showcase their personalities and traits in different ways. Think of it as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.16personalities.com/articles/assertive-architect-intj-a-vs-turbulent-architect-intj-t&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Assertive types being more on the frontline, while Turbulent types are more to the side&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With these discoveries, it is easy to understand why some people get along with others so well. There are obviously a variety of other reasons, &lt;a href=&quot;https://onlinelearning.ucl.ac.uk/resources/personality-affects-work-behaviour-career-success/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;but their similar personalities definitely play a part in making it easy to bond and thrive with one another&lt;/a&gt;. When people with similar personalities are around each other, it is likely they will benefit each other as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/psychologyTwo.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This illustrates how each person has their own unique personality, as well as how they all have the ability to influence other similar or different personality types. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.dmitstudio.com/blog/key-factors-analyzing-mental-status-examination-career-counselling-adhd-cases/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(DMIT Studio)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Even with the positive ways that personalities can influence each other, they can also have a negative impact. Some of the problems are mild like simply not getting along with someone, while some others are more serious and involve a degree of pettiness and general annoyance. It all depends on whether or not the different types are compatible. Luckily, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.truity.com/page/personality-type-interactions-compatibility&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;there are various ways&lt;/a&gt; to figure out if a person with a certain personality might get along with someone else.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Other negative aspects of personality psychology include personality disorders. Characterized as mental disorders that can seriously impact a person’s functioning and wellbeing, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/personality-psychology-4157179&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;personality disorders&lt;/a&gt; are a broad field. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/personality-disorders-a2-425427&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Categorized into three clusters&lt;/a&gt;, the different personality disorders are grouped together depending on their similarities. The first cluster, Cluster A, has disorders that are known to be strange or eccentric. Examples of these can be paranoid personality disorder and schizoid personality disorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The personality disorders in the second cluster, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/the-cluster-b-personality-disorders-425429&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Cluster B&lt;/a&gt;, are grouped together due to their similar dramatic nature. Disorders in this cluster include antisocial personality disorder and narcissistic personality disorder. The last cluster, Cluster C, has disorders that are linked together by their emphasis on extreme anxiety. Some of these are avoidant personality disorder and dependent personality disorder.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Potentially not bonding with someone of a differing personality type is already bad on its own depending on how a person looks at it, but &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/personality-disorders-a2-425427&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;personality disorders cause a slew of additional issues&lt;/a&gt;. They can prevent people from bonding well with others at all, strain pre-existing relationships, make people extremely nervous all the time or in need of constant reassurance from those who care, among many more side effects.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A personality psychology professional can examine these symptoms and their longevity, eventually deciding whether or not to diagnose a person with a certain disorder. Before they can do that though, they need to decide on a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/provisional-diagnosis-vs-differential-diagnosis-1067284&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;differential diagnosis&lt;/a&gt;. This entails the professional determining if these symptoms are not the cause of other mental disorders or medical conditions. From there, sufficient treatment for the patient is decided on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personality psychology is an interesting and expanding field. It has come a long way since researchers first started examining it more closely, and it is now one of the most popular fields of psychology. It also happens to be one of the most complex as well. Numerous discoveries have been made, and the world understands how humans work a lot more due to these breakthroughs. As humans continue to evolve, so will personality psychology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.salesforce.com/ca/blog/2016/01/psychology-of-sales.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Salesforce)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Omar Dajani&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Omar Dajani is an international student from Jerusalem, Palestine. He is currently a sophomore at Fullerton College and is majoring in English with a minor in Computer Science. He enjoys gaming, blogging, journaling, meditating, and going on walks. He intends on transferring to UC Berkeley for Fall 2021.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Omar Dajani</name></author><summary type="html">Overview of personality psychology Omar Dajani. 01/29/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/psychologyCover.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/psychologyCover.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">COVID-19: A detailed vaccine timeline</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/21/covid-19-a-detailed-vaccine-timeline.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19: A detailed vaccine timeline" /><published>2021-01-21T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-21T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/21/covid-19-a-detailed-vaccine-timeline</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/21/covid-19-a-detailed-vaccine-timeline.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;COVID-19: A detailed vaccine timeline&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mehri Sadri. 01/22/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/vaccineOne.png&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://coronavirus.utah.gov/vaccine/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Utah.gov)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Normality. A concept that has been seemingly destroyed by a global pandemic for almost 10 months. With 21st-century science innovation and unlimited funding, many expected a quick solution to the problems that have pierced the lives of millions. However, science cannot be rushed, as safety and surrounding logistics still linger during the initial inoculation process of the mRNA COVID-19 vaccine. Many individuals wonder when they’ll get the vaccine, and this evidently depends on one’s surrounding resources, location, vocation and risk for contracting the virus. Below is a detailed, yet estimated timeline for when vaccines will be distributed throughout 2021, and when individuals can be expected to return back to emerging feelings of “normalcy”: slowly, but surely.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though COVID-19 vaccines are not accessible to everyone as of January 2021, mid-December marked the healthcare worker rollout. This makes sense, as healthcare workers have been risking their lives every day to care for firsthand COVID-19 patients. However, there is another group of early vaccinators that have been receiving backlash for their place within this timeline. Older Americans who reside in nursing homes have been another high-risk category that has received vaccine doses in large quantities. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/12/05/health/covid-vaccine-first.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The New York Times&lt;/a&gt;, choosing which group to prioritize has been a large issue, as it is often a debate of ‘human preservation’ versus ‘the slowing rate of spread.’ Though healthcare workers are an integral part of the essential work-force, there are also thousands of other Americans providing services in grocery stores and restaurants, sectors that are considered essential to keep American families in check. So far, there has been an increasing amount of support for placing essential workers before senior citizens and instead putting elder citizens at a subphase, known as phase 1b of the vaccination treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With numerous first-responders being vaccinated with either one or both doses today, there is a new phase, which started in late December and ends mid-January, that encompasses a larger population of individuals. Of course, essential healthcare workers who were not a part of this initial phase are included, but high-risk persons, K-12 teachers and nurses who work in long-term facilities have also been added into the mix. The teachers receiving the COVID-19 vaccine primarily contain those who are a part of districts that resumed in-person learning. Though most schools are in locations classified as red tiered, meaning a greater risk of infection, some schools have stayed open as early as October, thus qualifying teachers to &lt;a href=&quot;https://edsource.org/2021/some-california-teachers-and-staff-to-receive-covid-19-vaccines-beginning-this-week/646526&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;receive vaccinations during this beginning phase&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though most shipped vaccines will be put to use, there will always be a few outliers: vaccines that aren’t put to use. With these extras, California governor Gavin Newson plans to remain flexible, administering the extra doses to other essential works, such as food and agricultural workers, teachers or additional healthcare workers. No vaccine dosage will go to waste! Though a possibility, there will likely be few extra vaccines, considering that there are pandemic centers in California like Los Angeles that are in dire need of protection for their many healthcare workers forced to work longer shifts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After all healthcare and essential workers have received the vaccine, it would be time to distribute it to senior citizens, those over the age of 65. This would be known as phase 1c, likely encompassing one of the larger groups of qualified patients. Although this phase does encompass all senior citizens, the highest priority would go to those who are immunocompromised, meaning that going out every day and returning to normal life would be an even greater risk than before. Although there is no set time for this phase’s subsection, &lt;a href=&quot;https://whyy.org/articles/when-will-it-be-your-turn-to-get-the-coronavirus-vaccine-heres-a-guide/#&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;experts expect this wave to occur&lt;/a&gt; around March or April of 2021. However, with current inoculation backlogs, this could, unfortunately, be pushed back a bit further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Once these groups have all received the COVID-19 vaccine, it would be time to transition into stage 2: everyone else. Individuals who are not included in the priority groups mentioned in stage 1 would be included here, and this comprises most of the U.S. population. Though vaccinations do provide immense protection from suffering disastrous COVID-19 effects, masks and other protective measures will still be mandated in public places, assuring that individuals are treated as safely as possible. 2021’s holiday season will likely entail the beginnings of society’s return to normalcy, as experts predict that most families can finally come together in joy and relief.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (CDC)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/Mehri_Sadri.JPG&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Mehri Sadri&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Mehri is a senior at Scripps Ranch High School in San Diego, California. Although she has always been more inclined in humanities subjects, Mehri has found a love for combining science and art and their practicalities, and hopes to spread this same love to others with her articles.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Mehri Sadri</name></author><summary type="html">COVID-19: A detailed vaccine timeline Mehri Sadri. 01/22/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/detailedVaccineCover.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/detailedVaccineCover.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The half-baked adolescent brain</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/21/the-half-baked-adolescent-brain.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The half-baked adolescent brain" /><published>2021-01-21T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2021-01-21T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/01/21/the-half-baked-adolescent-brain</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/01/21/the-half-baked-adolescent-brain.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The half-baked adolescent brain&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joan Joe. 01/22/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/adolescentBrainOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This image shows the difference between an adult and a teenage brain.
&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.elegantbrain.com/edu4/classes/readings/depository/TNS_560/brain/teenage_brain.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Elegant Brain)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Adolescence is a phase of development marked by suboptimal decisions and behaviors. It’s associated with an increased rate of accidental injury, aggression, drug abuse, unintended pregnancy and sexually transmitted diseases. At times, it seems that teenagers do not think things through or thoroughly understand the implications of their actions. They differ from adults in the way they act, address conflicts and make choices.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are over 13,000 youth deaths in the United States per year, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/16760893/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the National Center for Health Statistics&lt;/a&gt;. Around 70% of these deaths are caused by motor vehicle collisions, accidental injury, murder and suicide. Results from &lt;a href=&quot;https://nam.edu/tracking-adolescent-health-behaviors-and-outcomes-strengths-and-weaknesses-of-the-youth-risk-behavior-surveillance-system/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the National Youth Risk Behavior Survey&lt;/a&gt; (YRBS) show that adolescents engage in behaviors that increase their chance of death or illness by driving after drinking, driving without a seat belt, using illegal substances, carrying weapons and/or engaging in unprotected sex that leads to unintended pregnancies and STDs, including HIV infections. The importance of recognizing risky decisions and actions in teenagers is underlined by these figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why do adolescents act without caution?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A biological explanation for this disparity is available. Studies have shown that during childhood and adolescence and well into early adulthood, brains continue to mature and develop. When they’re very young, children’s brains have a huge growth spurt. By the time they’re six, about 90 to 95% of the adult size is already in their minds. But before it can function as an adult brain, the brain also needs a lot of remodeling. Even though the brains of all teenagers evolve roughly at the same time, there are still variations between individuals.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The relationship between genetics and the environment (nature and nurture) parallels the growth and development of the brain, as the latter is modeled on the features of the various developmental phases of human development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The key change is that unused connections are ‘pruned’ away in the thought and processing section of the brain called the grey matter. White matter is a large, intertwining neural link system that joins all four brain lobes (frontal, temporal, parietal and occipital) and the limbic system’s emotional center of the brain. Other relations are improved at the same time. Based on the ‘use it or lose it’ concept, this is the brain’s way of being more successful. This phase of pruning begins in the back of the brain. The anterior portion, the prefrontal cortex, is remodeled last.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/adolescentBrainTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This diagram identifies both grey and white matter. &lt;a href=&quot;https://ib.bioninja.com.au/options/option-a-neurobiology-and/a2-the-human-brain/brain-matter.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(BioNinja)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A particular area of the brain called the amygdala has been identified by scientists to be responsible for immediate responses, including fear and violent behavior. This develops first. Since the prefrontal cortex is still maturing, adolescents rely more on the amygdala to solve problems than adults do.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The prefrontal cortex is the brain’s decision-making organ, responsible for the ability to prepare and think about the effects of actions, solve problems and control impulses. Changes continue into early adulthood in this section. The prefrontal cortex keeps on developing until the age of 25.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/adolescentBrainThree.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The prefrontal cortex and amygdala are identified in this diagram.
 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theoakleafnews.com/features/2020/10/07/the-california-stop-explained/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(The Oak Leaf)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Other brain changes during puberty involve a rapid increase in brain cell connections and making brain pathways more functional. Myelin, an insulating layer that lets cells communicate, is produced by nerve cells. For the production of organized thinking and actions, all these changes are necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To further confuse matters for the teenage brain, not all sections develop on the same schedule, and schedules differ between individuals as well. The first sections to mature are primitive functions, such as motion and sensory processing (with boys maturing faster than girls in these areas). What we think of as ‘greater’ roles are on a much slower maturation timeline, such as impulse management, long-term planning, cognitive control and risk evaluation (with girls maturing faster than boys in these areas).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/adolescentBrainFour.png&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The different stages of brain development of the brain from left to right.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychologytoday.com/intl/blog/vitality/201306/parenting-and-the-amazing-teen-brain-part-1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Psychology Today)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;How Teenagers React to Emotions&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The adolescent brain is somewhat different from that of an infant or adult when it comes to coping with emotion. For the very first time, the teenage brain experiences complex emotions (enhanced or damaged by hormones, depending on context); not only do teenagers lack the adult’s life experiences to control complex emotions, but the areas of the brain that manage one’s emotions are not yet completely formed.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When faced with intense or complicated feelings, teenagers are met with a double-whammy; they don’t know how to wield them, and even if they did, they wouldn’t have the brain systems in place to pull it off, as an adult brain might.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The Crucial Role of Parents and Peers&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the brain’s developmental stages, parents and peers play a vital role. The constantly accessed parts of the brain are improved, while the parts not used are pruned away. The teen brain is on a quest to build up what is needed and get rid of what isn’t, which is why a decline in grey matter in the early twenties is the final stage of brain maturation. With a good dollop of love, affection and support, bonds are formed and enhanced by repetitive exposure to new physical abilities, mental abilities and life experiences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These variations in the brain do not mean that young people are unable to make good choices or distinguish between right and wrong. That also doesn’t mean that teenagers should not be held accountable for their actions. A knowledge of these disparities, however, will assist parents, teachers, advocates and policymakers to consider and healthily support adolescent behavior.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.columbian.com/news/2014/mar/23/teen-brain-new-science-developmental-stage/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(The Columbian)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Joan Joe&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Joan is a freshman in St. Antony’s Public School, India. She is intrigued by psychology and neuroscience and aspires to join research in neuroscience and STEM-related works. She hopes to help others pursue their passion for STEM through her platform. In her free time, she plays the piano, sings, and loves to read Dan Brown’s books.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Joan Joe</name></author><summary type="html">The half-baked adolescent brain Joan Joe. 01/22/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/adolescentBrainCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/adolescentBrainCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>