<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-11-17T13:29:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">InterSTEM</title><entry><title type="html">Mapping the human genome</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/12/mapping-human-genome.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Mapping the human genome" /><published>2020-11-12T16:00:05-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-12T16:00:05-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/12/mapping-human-genome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/12/mapping-human-genome.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Mapping the human genome&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reagan Smith. 11/13/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/mappingHumanGenomeOne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Scientists undertook a massive project in the 90s: mapping the entire human genome.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.genome.gov/human-genome-project&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(National Human Genome Research Institute)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
On Oct. 1, 1990, scientists undertook one of the most significant explorations of the universe to this date. Instead of aiming upwards at the stars, researchers looked into our cells and began the arduous process of mapping the entire human genome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The project took a total of thirteen years to complete and was first outlined by the National Academy of Sciences. Later, the National Institutes of Health and the Department of Energy collaborated to create a detailed outline for the project, which was funded by Congress. With James Watson at the helm of the NIH branch, which was renamed the National Center for Human Genome Research, the project was soon underway. The seven areas the project looked into were Mapping and Sequencing the Genome, Mapping and Sequencing the Genomes of Model Organisms, Data Collection and Distribution, Ethical, Legal, and Social Considerations, Research Training, Technology Development and Technology Transfer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists looked at the genomes of both homo sapiens and a set of model organisms to compare the functions and purpose of the human genome, according to &amp;lt;a href=”https://www.genome.gov/human-genome-project/What” target=”_blank’&amp;gt;Understanding Our Genetic Inheritance, The First Five Years&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt;. The data they acquired would be used to treat genetic diseases, and the specific technology they developed could be applied to other fields of science in agriculture and environmental science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.genome.gov/human-genome-project/What&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The National Human Genome Research Institute&lt;/a&gt; (NHGRI) reports that researchers successfully determined the sequence of every single base of DNA in the human genome, made maps showing the locations of various genes in the chromosomes and created linkage maps (maps that track inherited traits over generations). Human genome researchers sequenced a total of 3 billion DNA letters, covering about 99% of the portion of the human genome that contains genes, with 99.99% accuracy. They also mapped the genomes of E. coli, S. cerevisiae, C. elegans, D. melanogaster, C. briggsae, D. pseudoobscura, mouse and rat organisms, putting their findings into context amongst other organisms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/mappingHumanGenomeTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This is a mapped sequence of the E. coli DNA. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/figure/Insertion-of-the-reporter-cassette-into-the-E-coli-K-12-MG1655-genome-The-chromosome_fig6_265558006&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(ResearchGate)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
According to an article on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/scitable/topicpage/dna-sequencing-technologies-key-to-the-human-828/#:~:text=The%20shotgun%20phase%20of%20the,and%20establish%20a%20contiguous%20sequence&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Scitable&lt;/a&gt;, the process of sequencing the DNA began with creating genetic clones of separate human chromosomes using ligated (individually cut) DNA segments bonded to chromosome vectors. The vector-segment combos were then placed into bacteria to reproduce and form colonies. The DNA fragments were separated from the bacterial organisms and placed into agarose (a sugar-based gel substance), in which the fragments’ size could be measured by gel electrophoresis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november//mappingHumanGenomeThree.png&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Gel electrophoresis of three separate DNA segments is visible in agarose gel.
(Wikipedia)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Francis Collins, the director of the NHGRI in February of 2001, stated that the genome is “a history book– a narrative of the journey of our species through time. It’s a shop manual, with an incredibly detailed blueprint for building every human cell. And it’s a transformative textbook of medicine, with insights that will give health care providers immense new powers to treat, prevent and cure disease.” His view of the project dictates its significance in today’s world of medicine and science, and having this large bank of data increases efficiency and progress in other related undertakings. Scientists have a better understanding of what makes humans look and act the way they do, and they are able to utilize this information to better treat and prevent diseases.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;http://sitn.hms.harvard.edu/flash/2019/lessons-from-the-human-genome-project/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Harvard University)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/Reagan_Smith.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Reagan Smith&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Reagan is a junior from Sage Hill School. She is passionate about all things related to science, especially biology and medicine. She also loves being able to use her talents and knowledge to help others and make a difference in the world.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Reagan Smith</name></author><summary type="html">Mapping the human genome Reagan Smith. 11/13/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/mappingHumanGenomeCover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/mappingHumanGenomeCover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Left and right-brained characteristics and striving for dominance</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/12/left-and-right-brain.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Left and right-brained characteristics and striving for dominance" /><published>2020-11-12T16:00:04-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-12T16:00:04-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/12/left-and-right-brain</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/12/left-and-right-brain.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Left and right-brained characteristics and striving for dominance&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joan Joe. 11/13/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/leftRightBrainOne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The graphic above depicts the left and right-brained characteristics.
(AliExpress)

&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you’re like me, you belong to 90 percent of the world’s population of right-handed people. This is often genetically determined, though it isn’t clear why our evolution has led to more righties than lefties. It’s a well-accepted belief that lefties and righties are right and left-brained respectively. However, in keeping with new research, the concept of individuals being either left or right-brained might not be as fixed as once thought.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is a widely acknowledged fact that most animals have an anatomically and functionally asymmetric brain. A number of the differences are learned and others are inherited. While the dominant side of the brain may be randomly assigned, a large spectrum of possibilities indicates that there could be something more than randomness at work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studies conducted on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2729063/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;zebrafish embryos&lt;/a&gt; about their developing brain suggest that there can be a fight for dominance between the hemispheres. Researchers have known that neurons migrate long distances in an exceedingly developing brain. This is often controlled by a gene called fibroblast protein 8 (FGF8), which creates a protein that acts as a magnet to draw in nerve cells to one hemisphere of the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is little difference within the number of cells on each side, but what does differ are the types of neurons on the left and right and their connections. Each side of the brain contains FGF8, resulting in a tug-of-war to draw in certain migrating nerve cells. But this can be an unfair fight. Only on the left side of the brain is another protein, called Nodal, present.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“The pair wins when it teams up with FGF8, causing a repetitive pattern of neuron links within the cerebral hemisphere that helps to clarify why in groups of people there is clear handedness,” Professor Stephen Wilson of University College London and Ph.D. student Jenny Regan explained to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.livescience.com/3261-left-battle-brain-discovered.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Live Science&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/leftRightBrainTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This is the structure of an FGF8 protein. (Emw / Wikipedia)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The process of becoming right-brained or left-brained is thanks to a contest between the two sides of the brain. If the rivalry was fair and equal, then half of the population would be left-brained and half would be right-brained. However, because of the signals on the left side of the brain that acts as an advantage, in most cases, it wins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most right-handed people process language within the left brain. At the same time, many left-handed people even have language proficiency localized to the left. Some individuals throw a right-handed pitch but write with the left hand. Others have a particular preference that the arm goes on top when folded. Others have a dominant eye. A number of these asymmetries can be genetically determined, reinforced by behavior or randomly assigned to support one or more tug-of-war battles between the two sides of the brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In theory, people being left or right-brained is simply a sign of which side of their brain is more dominant. This theory became known due to the psychobiologist and Nobel prize winner Roger W. Sperry within the 1960s. The left hemisphere is more analytical, verbal, logical and orderly than the right-brain. So the right-brained thinkers are known to be more creative free thinkers. The left-brained people may give more attention to details and rule by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.health.harvard.edu/blog/right-brainleft-brain-right-2017082512222&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;logic. There is a long-standing myth, associated with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.livescience.com/655-lefty-myths-mysteries-persist.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Rocky Balboa’s heroics&lt;/a&gt; within the ring, that left-handers (who have always made up 10 to 12 percent of the human population) are better fighters. True or not, handedness may well be tied to a war of sorts within the brain.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/leftRightBrainThree.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The image above shows that there is a functional asymmetry in the brain. This test was conducted with 1011 individuals between the ages of 7 and 29 at resting state under researchers from Beijing Normal University, China. &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0071275#abstract0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(PLOS)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A number of the functions indeed reside on one part of the brain over others. For example, damage to the front of the brain can be associated with reduced motivation, difficulty planning, and impaired creativity. Meanwhile, the rear of the brain, also known as the occipital cortex, integrates visual information from the attention. So damage to this cortex can cause partial or complete blindness. These are just some samples of how certain parts of the brain are responsible for specific functions. Much of our knowledge of this field of study comes from studying &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/science/split-brain-syndrome&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;split-brain&lt;/a&gt; patients. So, location does matter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, when it comes to individual creativity, there has been little to no evidence that the dominance of the brain plays a role. When comparing an &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id=10.1371/journal.pone.0071275&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;MRI&lt;/a&gt; or CT scan of a mathematician and an artist, there is often no observable differences. Math, for instance, requires logical thought so it is usually said to reside within the left-hemisphere, isolated from all the artsy right-brain abilities. But mathematics can be a profoundly creative endeavor, in addition to being logical.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So why is that this myth so popular? It should be because it gives us scientific thanks for speaking about our favorite subjects – ourselves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (MedicineNet)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Joan Joe&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Joan is a freshman in St. Antony’s Public School, India. She is intrigued by psychology and neuroscience and aspires to join research in neuroscience and STEM-related works. She hopes to help others pursue their passion for STEM through her platform. In her free time, she plays the piano, sings, and loves to read Dan Brown’s books.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Joan Joe</name></author><summary type="html">Left and right-brained characteristics and striving for dominance Joan Joe. 11/13/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/leftRightBrainCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/leftRightBrainCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Gene editing and the future of human evolution</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/gene-editing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Gene editing and the future of human evolution" /><published>2020-11-06T16:00:04-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-06T16:00:04-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/gene-editing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/gene-editing.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Gene editing and the future of human evolution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simone Rothaupt. 11/07/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/geneEditingOne.png&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Gene editing with CRISPR technology will revolutionize human evolution and cure countless diseases. (Adobe Stock / Andriano_cz)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Over the course of millions of years, homo sapiens have evolved into the dominant organism across the globe because humans are the only animals capable of working flexibly and creatively in large groups, according to bestselling author and doctoral graduate from the University of Oxford &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/transcripts/468882620&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Yuval Harari&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though we have developed such advanced cognitive function and physical abilities, scientists like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencealert.com/are-humans-still-evolving#:~:text=Evolution%20can't%20be%20stopped,natural%20selection%20is%20always%20happening.&amp;amp;text=Humans%20are%20still%20evolving%2C%20and,to%20change%20in%20the%20future.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dr. Alywyn Scally&lt;/a&gt; of the University of Cambridge assert humans are still evolving. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/05/humans-are-still-evolving-and-we-can-watch-it-happen&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Scientists from Stanford University&lt;/a&gt; revealed, using data from 3,000 genomes collected across the United Kingdom, that height, head circumference in infants and hip size in females (factors relevant to birth) have undergone selection in the past 2,000 years. In another study by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencemag.org/news/2016/05/humans-are-still-evolving-and-we-can-watch-it-happen&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Stanford University&lt;/a&gt;, researchers found that traits like lactose intolerance and blond hair and blue eyes have spread rapidly in the past 2,000 years. An &lt;a href=&quot;https://journals.plos.org/plosbiology/article?id=10.1371/journal.pbio.2002458&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;investigation&lt;/a&gt; by evolutionary geneticists Joseph Pickrell and others claims that the ApoE4 allele, which is connected to Alzheimer’s disease, has dropped in frequency over time as carriers die earlier on in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to the traditional methods of evolution, humans have now finally harnessed a technique known as gene editing, which controls life down to the genetic level void of natural influence. The most familiar version of gene editing, known as clustered regularly interspaced short palindromic repeats-associated protein 9 (CRISPR-Cas9), utilizes a naturally-occurring bacterial complex. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.genome.gov/about-genomics/policy-issues/Genome-Editing/How-genome-editing-works&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Human Genome Research Institute&lt;/a&gt; explains that bacteria creates CRISPR arrays, or DNA snippets, from segments of an invading virus’ DNA, allowing for the bacteria to form RNA segments to recognize the same virus if it returns. Once the virus is located, the Cas9 enzyme is used to cut the virus’ DNA apart to destroy it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For human application, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://medlineplus.gov/genetics/understanding/genomicresearch/genomeediting/#:~:text=Genome%20editing%20(also%20called%20gene,to%20change%20an%20organism's%20DNA.&amp;amp;text=The%20bacteria%20then%20use%20Cas9,works%20similarly%20in%20the%20lab.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;US National Library of Medicine&lt;/a&gt; states that scientists create, with CRISPR-Cas9, an RNA segment that can be used to recognize the part of DNA that needs to be edited. Once the correct DNA location is found, the Cas9 enzyme cuts the DNA, and the cell’s built-in methods for repairing damaged DNA, such as base repair excision, are manipulated to customize the sequence. The Cpf 1, CasX, Cas Y, and other enzymes are also used for cutting DNA as they can be more precise and accurate. Though other gene-editing methods exist such as homologous recombination and zinc-finger nucleases (ZFN), CRISPR-Cas9 has become the most popular as it is more accurate, efficient, cheaper and faster than most alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cancer.gov/news-events/cancer-currents-blog/2020/crispr-cancer-research-treatment&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Cancer Institute&lt;/a&gt;, gene editing has the potential to cure genetic diseases such as sickle cell, Huntington’s, and even cancer. &lt;a href=&quot;https://time.com/5642755/crispr-gene-editing-humans/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Time&lt;/a&gt; reported that Editas Medicine and Allergan, both prominent pharmaceutical companies, are working on testing CRISPR-Cas9 for congenital vision diseases, such as Leber congenital amaurosis 10. Similarly, Vertex Pharmaceuticals and CRISPR Therapeutics are attempting to utilize gene editing for curing blood diseases, such as beta thalassemia and sickle cell anemia. For the &lt;a href=&quot;https://ir.editasmedicine.com/news-releases/news-release-details/allergan-and-editas-medicine-announce-dosing-first-patient#:~:text=AGN%2D151587%20(EDIT%2D101)%20is%20an%20experimental%20medicine,protein%20290%20(CEP290)%20gene.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Allergan and Editas Medicine&lt;/a&gt; Leber congenital amaurosis 10 treatment study, a single mutation in the centrosomal protein 290 gene can be removed through CRISPR technology so that photoreceptor cells can detect light properly. For the &lt;a href=&quot;http://ir.crisprtx.com/news-releases/news-release-details/crispr-therapeutics-and-vertex-announce-progress-clinical&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CRISPR Therapeutics and Vertex&lt;/a&gt; beta thalassemia study, diseased bone marrow cells will be replaced with stem cells altered with CRISPR technology to turn on fetal hemoglobin production as the adult hemoglobin production genes for patients of this disease do not function properly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/commentisfree/2019/dec/08/gene-editing-will-let-us-control-our-very-evolution-we-must-use-it-wisely&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Guardian&lt;/a&gt; proposes that humans will now evolve more rapidly and in more ways than ever before. Changes to the human genome will no longer occur across thousands of years, but in a single lifetime. Previously, the selection of a single gene was considered a massive shift in evolution, but with gene editing, thousands of genes can quickly be altered.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though it appears that the potential for gene editing is limitless, debates loom large in this field. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-019-00673-1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nature Research&lt;/a&gt; warns that scientists must be extremely careful when choosing genes to alter as genes can have three to four unrelated functions. This means that removing a gene could have unintended and often unpredictable consequences, such as a weakened protection against lungs, liver and brain diseases. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.genome.gov/about-genomics/policy-issues/Genome-Editing/ethical-concerns&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Human Genome Research Institute&lt;/a&gt;, the field of gene manipulation is filled with controversy, such as fears that only the wealthy will have access to genome editing, as well as moral and religious objections to the testing of human embryos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though CRISPR-Cas9 can cure countless diseases, the threat of unethical misuse has prevented the rapid adoption of this novel technology. For the first time, an organism will be able to dictate its own evolution, and gene editing will hopefully be able to change the world for the better.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Simone Rothaupt&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Simone is a sophomore at Thousand Oaks High School in Ventura, California. She is interested in exploring STEM related topics, such as medicine, and she also hopes to spread this passion to others through writing.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Simone Rothaupt</name></author><summary type="html">Gene editing and the future of human evolution Simone Rothaupt. 11/07/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/geneEditingCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/geneEditingCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Fermi paradox: Possibilities of extraterrestrial life</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/fermi-paradox.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Fermi paradox: Possibilities of extraterrestrial life" /><published>2020-11-06T16:00:03-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-06T16:00:03-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/fermi-paradox</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/fermi-paradox.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The Fermi paradox: Possibilities of extraterrestrial life&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ana Monsalud. 11/07/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/fermiParadoxOne.png&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The Mars 2020 Mission will land in the Jezero Crater on Mars, which contains an ancient delta system where NASA scientists are hoping to find evidence of ancient life. &lt;a href=&quot;https://planetaria.ca/2018/12/15/high-res-view-of-mars-2020-landing-site-jezero-crater/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Planetaria)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There are &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.esa.int/Science_Exploration/Space_Science/Herschel/How_many_stars_are_there_in_the_Universe&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;tens of billions of galaxies&lt;/a&gt; in our observable universe, each containing millions of stars. Scientists estimate that each star has an average of about &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/startswithabang/2018/03/13/space-is-full-of-planets-and-most-of-them-dont-even-have-stars/?sh=4ce74893b2a1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ten planets&lt;/a&gt;, an approximation calculated just from the planets that have survived throughout the 4.5 billion years of our universe’s existence. With hundreds of billions of planets, is it really possible that humans are alone in the universe?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even before there was concrete evidence that could quantify the size of the universe, it was clear how vast it was. Scholars were already incredibly fascinated by the possibilities that lay beyond our planet prior to modern technology. In the 17th century, Galileo used the revolutionary development of the telescope to observe the characteristics of the Milky Way. And in 1923, Edwin Hubble discovered concrete evidence for the existence of galaxies other than the Milky Way. But even with these groundbreaking discoveries, many were left feeling like something was missing. One mystery surfaced above the rest: “Where is everybody?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This dilemma was the reason for Enrico Fermi’s lunchtime remark that sparked decades of research and speculation. Named after the famous physicist, the Fermi paradox is the contradiction between the high probability for extraterrestrial life and the lack of evidence supporting the existence of aliens. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.seti.org/press-release/how-many-habitable-planets-are-out-there&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;SETI Institute&lt;/a&gt;, as many as 300 million planets may be habitable in just the Milky Way. Billions of planets orbit within the habitable zones of stars and scientists have even discovered several planets that resemble Earth. The Fermi paradox perplexes even the most knowledgeable scientists today, and there is still no viable answer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Numerous theories debate this paradox, with a few of the most popular speculating that aliens see no reason to visit Earth, they have already visited Earth undetected, we don’t have the correct technology to contact aliens, or that life itself is unlikely, and the possibility of it developing into intellectual species is even more so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dozens of other theories exist, each with its own fair amount of counterarguments and doubt. For over 70 years, researchers and scientists have published papers and debated the viability of various theories. One method that scientists rely on when debating the Fermi paradox is the &lt;a href=&quot;https://exoplanets.nasa.gov/news/1350/are-we-alone-in-the-universe-revisiting-the-drake-equation/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Drake Equation&lt;/a&gt;. Developed in the 1960s, it calculates the number of civilizations in the Milky Way galaxy of which humans could theoretically communicate with. The Drake Equation multiples together evidential factors, like the number of planets per solar system that can support life, and hypothetical ones, such as the length of time that these civilizations actually release detectable signals into space. However, the indefinite nature of both the Fermi paradox and any attempts to supplement the issue means that any papers published can only be, at best, regarded as speculation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each new decade brings more and more uncertainty about the possibility of life outside of Earth. Even with new technologies capable of taking pictures of stars as far as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/feature/new-horizons-captures-record-breaking-images-in-the-kuiper-belt/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;3.79 billion miles away from Earth&lt;/a&gt;, humans are unable to find any evidence supporting the possibility of extraterrestrial life. Despite this discouraging amount of progress, many scientists stand by their belief that aliens do indeed exist. But whether or not scientists can find conclusive evidence of extraterrestrial civilizations, humanity will surely continue to explore deeper into space and uncover the mystery of our own existence.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Ana Monsalud&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Ana is a junior from Cambridge Virtual Academy who is a huge nerd for pretty much everything related to math and science. Through InterSTEM, she hopes to inspire others with her same love for learning and curiosity about the world. In the future, she hopes to pursue a career in healthcare and contribute to change in her community.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ana Monsalud</name></author><summary type="html">The Fermi paradox: Possibilities of extraterrestrial life Ana Monsalud. 11/07/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/fermiParadoxCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/fermiParadoxCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Creation of a New Arctic</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/new-artic.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Creation of a New Arctic" /><published>2020-11-06T16:00:02-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-06T16:00:02-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/new-artic</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/new-artic.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Creation of a New Arctic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carly Schinhofen. 11/07/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/newArticOne.png&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;As climate change continues to skyrocket and temperatures and carbon emissions show no signs of slowing, a separate Arctic climate system is forming. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vectorstock.com/royalty-free-vector/cartoon-winter-polar-arctic-or-antarctic-ice-vector-20923394&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.vectorstock.com/royalty-free-vector/cartoon-winter-polar-arctic-or-antarctic-ice-vector-20923394&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(VectorStock)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Climate change is pushing new boundaries as dangerously high temperatures suggest an entirely new climate system is emerging in the Northern pole. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41558-020-0892-z.epdf?sharing_token=FtYt7dQsxgKZ-glVzsT7U9RgN0jAjWel9jnR3ZoTv0MqVMypMyE7pAbPE1tu481cfXA0d4GjqhJeVhIB88dZZJi1abe22TQZDvIoxlpfXD-yndBKgUoVFuPC-jto2hvBoIFE8jjwIiZ62S7k2DdoXoqOS1Vpq2NwPIh2JOn443IgUz4QPzUEPSMrk-2XN17vWSCWzIJ1rf9GMd3roXQ0uhi9sUofO3q5QEPd7eL_HwcxBXWoHIR59wvGfVxwcaGGrUDfeXFxmChn9OWPZqDltCpS4CEduy2BNjiDAppQNmrl_Bbz1SaG8jeaNdvYBm9s&amp;amp;tracking_referrer=www.scientificamerican.com&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; from the National Center for Atmospheric Research (NCAR), this Arctic climate system is forming as the Northern Hemisphere sea-ice extents have “been lower in each of the past 13 years than any other years since 1980, as new research displays.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the next decade, scientists predict that climate change may reach a point where it is unstoppable. Laura Landrum and Marika Holland, researchers at the NCAR in Colorado, made their recent findings about Arctic conditions public in their journal, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/a-new-arctic-is-emerging-thanks-to-climate-change/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nature Climate Change&lt;/a&gt;. Due to such significant and rapid alterations in the climate patterns, a completely new climate best describes the current conditions of the Arctic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Various climate models depicted in Landrum and Holland’s report indicate that this new Arctic has already emerged. Due to the increasing rate of human-produced carbon emissions and other contributing biological factors, sea ice has already declined more than anyone would have believed 30 years ago. On its own, this crucial layer prevents the ocean from heating up quickly. When this ice layer thins or disappears, water temperature increases, thereby starting the cycle of melting ice again and continuing the positive feedback loop.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Climate change is upon us, and the actions taken in the next decade are crucial to slowing it down before it reaches a point where temperatures increase at an exponential rate. At that point— which draws nearer everyday— humanity’s survival is at stake, since increased sea levels can threaten people’s security and safety. Additionally, the fate of oceanic and land organisms is threatened, since higher ocean temperatures and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.whoi.edu/press-room/news-release/scientists-identify-how-ocean-acidification-weakens-coral-skeletons/#:~:text=The%20rising%20acidity%20of%20the,corals%20to%20build%20their%20skeletons.&amp;amp;text=Corals%20grow%20their%20skeletons%20upward,thicken%20them%20to%20reinforce%20them.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ocean acidification&lt;/a&gt; are deadly to various animals. Fish can become more sensitive to the increasing temperatures and lose available breeding grounds and overall habitat. Ocean acidification occurs as the ocean absorbs carbon dioxide from the atmosphere and is gradually shifting from a basic ph to a more neutral ph. For marine life, even fractions of a change in ph can be deadly. As the ocean absorbs CO2, there are fewer carbonate ions in the water, which makes it harder for coral’s calcium carbonate skeletons to develop. For ecosystems such as coral reefs, the absence or bleaching of coral can cause entire ecosystems to collapse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oceanic ecosystems will topple without the presence of key organisms. As climate change causes temperatures to rise and transform the global climate, ecosystems are suffering and dangerous new climates are emerging. It is crucial to reduce carbon emissions in a collective effort to lessen the future devastating effects of climate change.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.euronews.com/living/2020/10/10/world-s-biggest-arctic-expedition-brings-back-1000-ice-samples-to-predict-climate-change&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Alfred-Wegener Institut / Steffen Graupner)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Carly Schinhofen&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Carly is a junior at Woodbridge High School. She is intrigued by biology and geology, and aspires to hold a career in science. Through her platform, she hopes to help others pursue their love for STEM. In her free time, she enjoys playing volleyball and trips to the beach.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Carly Schinhofen</name></author><summary type="html">Creation of a New Arctic Carly Schinhofen. 11/07/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/newArticCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/newArticCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The discovery of a new Tetraquark in a nutshell</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/tetraquark.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The discovery of a new Tetraquark in a nutshell" /><published>2020-11-06T16:00:01-08:00</published><updated>2020-11-06T16:00:01-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/tetraquark</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/11/06/tetraquark.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The discovery of a new Tetraquark in a nutshell&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ayush Kumar. 11/07/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/tetraquarkOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt; These are the most popular types of ‘quarks’.
(Greatest Idea Ever)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Particle physics is such a unique and interesting topic, but first, let’s explore the fundamentals!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Quarks are the particles which constitute the protons and neutrons and were discovered after the invention of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/search?kgmid=/m/0d1hs&amp;amp;hl=en-IN&amp;amp;q=Particle+accelerator&amp;amp;kgs=ea26cdaf23844447&amp;amp;shndl=0&amp;amp;source=sh/x/kp&amp;amp;entrypoint=sh/x/kp&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;particle accelerators&lt;/a&gt;. They are always found in clusters bound to each other through means of strong nuclear force (one of the fundamental forces of the universe, which affects a very small region in the nuclei of atoms). For example, protons are made up of two up and one down quark, while neutrons are made up of two down and one up quark.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are six types of quarks, also referred to as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.livescience.com/18141-wacky-physics-particle-flavors.html#:~:text=For%20instance%2C%20quarks%20(which%20make,each%20with%20a%20different%20mass.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;flavors&lt;/a&gt;, which differ from each other in terms of mass and charge characteristics. These can be grouped into three pairs: up and down, strange and charm, and top and bottom. Quarks are also further divided into  antiquarks, or counterparts of quarks. When combined, quarks and antiquarks form &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hadron&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;hadrons&lt;/a&gt;. Quarks are also classified into colors, even though they do not possess any color in reality. Different colors indicate the source of their strong nuclear force which binds them together. Now let’s learn about tetra-quarks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The discovery&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, now to understand the importance and unusualness of this discovery, let’s learn about the usual characteristics associated with quarks. Simply put, quarks are the fundamental particles of the universe that constitute matter, mostly three-quark particles— protons, neutrons, mesons, etc. These particles do not contain more than two quarks of the same type, specifically not more than two heavy quarks (quarks with comparatively large masses).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/november/tetraquarkTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt; This is an image of a tetra-quark. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sci-news.com/physics/four-charm-quark-particle-08602.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(CERN)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
But this newly discovered particle actually has four quarks (which is rare to be found), two charms and two anti-charms. This means that all the quarks are of the heaviest type! This discovery baffles scientists and has made scientists realize that there is much more to learn about quarks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This four quark particle has been named X6900 and was discovered at Large Hadron Collider (LHC), near Geneva, Switzerland. The European Organization for Nuclear Research (CERN) scientists reported the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sci-news.com/physics/four-charm-quark-particle-08602.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;discovery&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sci-news.com/physics/four-charm-quark-particle-08602.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;on June 30, 2020&lt;/a&gt;. The first four-quark particle was discovered in &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.sci-news.com/physics/science-z4430-cern-exotic-hadrons-01843.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2014&lt;/a&gt; and a year later, penta-quarks (five-quark particles) were discovered by LHC beauty (LHCb) Collaboration. Outgoing spokesperson of the LHCb Collaboration Dr. Giovanni Passaleva states, “Particles made up of four quarks are already exotic, and the one we have just discovered is the first to be made up of four heavy quarks of the same type, specifically two charm quarks and two charm anti-quarks.” He also mentioned that the LHCb and other experiments had only observed tetra-quarks with two heavy quarks at most and not a single with more than two quarks of the same type or with four heavy quarks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The LHC data showed that this four-quark particle decayed into two &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/J/psi_meson&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;J/ψ&lt;/a&gt; particles each containing a charm and a charm anti-quark. X6900 can be a single entity with four quarks bundled together, or a pack of two-quark particles loosely bound to each other.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Impact of discovery on research&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It will be easier for scientists to track observations for X6900 over any other four-quark particle consisting of lighter quarks, as it is quite difficult to accurately predict the complex behavior of light quark particles. Thus, it will be easier for scientists to understand various unknown properties of quarks. This heavy quark particle will also answer some of the most important questions in particle-physics, such as how quarks constructed matter and how strong-nuclear forces interact with various quarks.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Ayush Kumar&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ayush Kumar</name></author><summary type="html">The discovery of a new Tetraquark in a nutshell Ayush Kumar. 11/07/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/tetraquarkCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/tetraquarkCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Wildfire smoke and COVID-19</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/24/wildfire-smoke.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Wildfire smoke and COVID-19" /><published>2020-10-24T06:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-24T06:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/10/24/wildfire-smoke</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/24/wildfire-smoke.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Wildfire smoke and COVID-19&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emily Richter. 10/24/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/october/wildfireSmokeOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Southern California is just one of the regions currently plagued by bad air quality thanks to wildfires.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.purpleair.com/map?opt=1/mAQI/a10/cC0#6.13/36.029/-118.975&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(PurpleAir)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Fires burning all across the western United States have caused millions of Americans to wake up to smoky air. Many of these people, especially those living in wildfire-prone California, have experienced poor air quality like this before. In recent years, poor air quality due to wildfire smoke has prompted school closures, event cancellations and even strict shelter-in-place orders. However, this year, an unprecedented number of wildfires combined with an unprecedented pandemic complicates matters even further.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wildfire smoke can harm a person’s respiratory and cardiovascular systems, both of which are also targeted by COVID-19. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/pm-pollution/how-smoke-fires-can-affect-your-health#:~:text=The%20biggest%20health%20threat%20from,even%20linked%20to%20premature%20death.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Environmental Protection Agency&lt;/a&gt; (EPA), wildfire smoke is “a complex mixture of gases and fine particles”. The fine particles are the cause for worry; when they come in contact with the lungs, they inhibit the lungs’ ability to function properly. As a result, the cardiovascular and respiratory systems are both threatened, and the lungs are also more susceptible to infection. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/disasters/covid-19/wildfire_smoke_covid-19.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Center for Disease Control&lt;/a&gt; (CDC), if COVID-19 comes in contact with weakened lungs, those lungs are more likely to be infected. The CDC also warns that if a person is already infected, the weakening of the respiratory and cardiovascular systems could allow the virus to permanently damage the heart or lungs. This creates a situation where the combination of wildfire smoke and COVID-19 has disastrous consequences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is worth noting that the masks required for protection against COVID-19 are not effective against wildfire smoke. The CDC recommends wearing an N95 mask but also mentions that at this time, healthcare workers desperately need N95 masks. In the likely event that one cannot acquire an N95 mask, the best thing to do would be to stay inside as much as possible. In fact, staying inside at home protects against both the COVID-19 infection and unhealthy air quality!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.llu.edu/health-wellness/wildfire-smoke-covid-19-how-you-can-protect-your-lungs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Loma Linda University Health Department)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Emily Richter&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Emily is a junior from Maria Carrillo High School in Sonoma County. She loves chemistry and the environmental sciences and plans to be an environmental chemist when she gets older. Through InterSTEM, she hopes to combine her experience in writing with her interest in STEM in order to help others enjoy and understand STEM. In her free time, she likes playing the flute, and baking and cooking.


&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Emily Richter</name></author><summary type="html">Wildfire smoke and COVID-19 Emily Richter. 10/24/2020 Southern California is just one of the regions currently plagued by bad air quality thanks to wildfires. (PurpleAir) Fires burning all across the western United States have caused millions of Americans to wake up to smoky air. Many of these people, especially those living in wildfire-prone California, have experienced poor air quality like this before. In recent years, poor air quality due to wildfire smoke has prompted school closures, event cancellations and even strict shelter-in-place orders. However, this year, an unprecedented number of wildfires combined with an unprecedented pandemic complicates matters even further.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/wildfireSmokeCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/wildfireSmokeCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Higgs boson giving mass</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/18/higgs-boson.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Higgs boson giving mass" /><published>2020-10-18T06:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-18T06:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/10/18/higgs-boson</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/18/higgs-boson.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Higgs boson giving mass&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teddy Rosenthal. 10/18/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/october/higgsBosonOne.png&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt; The Large Hadron Collider at the European Organization for Nuclear Research.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://science.sciencemag.org/content/361/6407/1054&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Science Magazine)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;What is the Higgs Boson?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Simply put, the Higgs boson is the most recent edition to the Standard Model of particle physics, and the field that produces it plays a big role in the properties of all matter in the universe. Its discovery played a big role in modern physics, as it helped people understand concepts ranging from misconceptions in the masses of certain particles to what the universe was like at its earliest stages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;History&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;In 2012, it was announced that the European Organization for Nuclear Research (CERN) had discovered a particle that was first theorized 48 years prior. This was a particularly elusive particle that was predicted to generate mass, which was significant because it could allude to a plethora of theoretical possibilities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1964, physicist Peter Higgs suggested the concept of a particle that caused mass. Later that same year, physicists Robert Brout and François Englert also theorized a mechanism that could produce mass and went on to win the Nobel prize for this discovery. This mechanism was named the Higgs Mechanism for Peter Higgs’ contribution to the discovery. Dick Hagen, Gerald Guralnik and Tom Kibble, who are all renowned physicists and professors, also received credit for independently publishing a similar theory not long after Higgs published his.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/october/higgsBosonTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt; Peter Higgs won the Nobel Prize in Physics in 2013.
(A. Mahmoud / Nobel Media)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In 1995, the top quark (a particle in the third generation of matter), was discovered by Fermilab in their pursuit to find the particle first theorized by Higgs 30 years prior. During this time, the  Higgs boson would gain more and more recognition from the media, and many speculations would arise, one being that the Large Hadron Collider (LHC) would create a black hole that would destroy the Earth. The Higgs boson is commonly referred to as the “God particle” because it is an integral part of the Standard Model of particle physics, which is a theory that describes the connections between three of the four fundamental forces.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That was, until 2008 when the LHC in Switzerland became operational. Following false rumors and debate over theories of the boson over the past few years, CERN finally announced on July 4, 2012, that &lt;a href=&quot;https://home.cern/science/physics/higgs-boson&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;they had found a particle&lt;/a&gt; with a mass of 125 GeV/c2, the predicted mass of the Higgs boson. After 48 years of hard work and dedication, this “God particle” had finally been found.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/october/higgsBosonThree.png&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt; (The Large Hadron Collider at CERN)
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.extremetech.com/extreme/283928-cern-reveals-plans-for-particle-collider-four-times-larger-than-lhc&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(ExtremeTech)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
That is the history of its discovery, but why does the Higgs boson matter?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does the Standard Model classify the Higgs boson?
A commonly asked question about the Higgs boson is: if the Higgs is a boson, why doesn’t it carry a force? This is asked frequently because the four gauge bosons are carriers of the four fundamental forces: gravity, electromagnetism, strong interaction and weak interaction. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.symmetrymagazine.org/article/where-the-higgs-belongs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Symmetry Magazine&lt;/a&gt;, the Higgs is classified as a boson due to its integer value spin, a property of all bosons. Right now it is labeled as a “scalar boson” due to its different nature compared to the gauge bosons. For instance, it is the only elementary particle with a spin of zero.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The electroweak symmetry
With the discovery of the Higgs boson, several other principle theories were proven true, namely the Higgs mechanism and the Higgs field. Certain particles, like the W and Z bosons (the particles that carry the weak nuclear force), will only acquire mass if the electroweak symmetry is broken. This is only possible if a “new” field exists in all places, and this field would have to have enough energy to break the electroweak symmetry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The electroweak interaction is a combination of the already manifested electromagnetic and weak nuclear forces that exist in the presence of a high energy system. It is predicted that the very early stages of the universe existed with this force present, as it took time for the four forces to separate. While this theory is proven, it requires the W and Z bosons to have no mass, which has been refuted through observation of these particles in accelerators.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Higgs Field
The energy caused by the Higgs Field’s interaction with the massless particles produced by the electroweak force allows the force to break into the electromagnetic and weak interaction. This can be explained by the fact that the Higgs boson exists in a low potential energy state, and will appear when there is an excitation of energy in the Higgs field. This scenario can be difficult to recreate, hence the extended period of time it took to discover this particle, but the connection between the Higgs boson and the electroweak interaction exists in the role that the Higgs plays in giving mass to the W and Z bosons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The electroweak force produces 4 massless bosons which are completely different from the particles carrying the two separated forces. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.quantumdiaries.org/2011/11/21/why-do-we-expect-a-higgs-boson-part-i-electroweak-symmetry-breaking/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Quantum Diaries&lt;/a&gt;, the W and Z bosons use the Higgs boson to gain mass by “absorbing” it. This action breaks electroweak symmetry and provides a reasonable explanation for why the W and Z bosons have mass and for why the Higgs field exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Higgs Mechanism
A simple analogy used to describe the Higgs mechanism is the difference between pushing a large cube across the ground and pushing a large ball on the same surface. The shape of the object represents the resistance caused by the field, and the friction experienced by the objects as they are pushed represents the mass gained from the field’s resistance. You will notice that a large cube is harder to push around than a ball due to the shapes of the objects. The same applies to particles in the Higgs field, where a particle like a photon would be the ball and a particle like a lepton would be the cube. This can be observed, as a photon moving in a vacuum will travel at “c,” (the speed of light), due to its low resistance to the field, which makes it massless. A lepton, however, will move slower and take longer than a photon to reach an equally distanced endpoint due to the lepton having a stronger interaction with the field. To put it simply, certain particles are resisted more than other particles by this field, which is how they “acquire” mass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Conclusion
After almost 50 years of digging and experiments, a powerful factor in modern physics was discovered, helping to pave the way for discoveries in modern theoretical physics. The Higgs field and the Higgs boson seemed to have wrapped a neat little bow around our current understanding of particle physics, strengthening humanity’s knowledge of the physical world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Teddy Rosenthal&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Teddy is a sophomore at Westlake High School who enjoys learning about math and science related topics. Through InterSTEM, Teddy's goal is to spread knowledge of the most interesting STEM topics in hopes to popularize science. He also enjoys music, wrestling, and hiking.


&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Teddy Rosenthal</name></author><summary type="html">Higgs boson giving mass Teddy Rosenthal. 10/18/2020 The Large Hadron Collider at the European Organization for Nuclear Research. (Science Magazine) What is the Higgs Boson? Simply put, the Higgs boson is the most recent edition to the Standard Model of particle physics, and the field that produces it plays a big role in the properties of all matter in the universe. Its discovery played a big role in modern physics, as it helped people understand concepts ranging from misconceptions in the masses of certain particles to what the universe was like at its earliest stages.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/higgsBosonCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/higgsBosonCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The mother of physics: Marie Curie</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/07/marie-curie.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The mother of physics: Marie Curie" /><published>2020-10-07T06:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-07T06:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/10/07/marie-curie</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/07/marie-curie.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The mother of physics: Marie Curie&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ramizah Tayiba. 10/07/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/october/marieCurieOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt; Marie Curie works in her laboratory.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biography.com/news/marie-curie-biography-facts&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(AFP / Getty Images)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Throughout history, female scientists have been undermined and pushed aside. But there is one woman with a scientific legacy so strong she is considered the “Mother of Modern Physics,” despite the misogyny during her time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maria Skłodowska, who later became Marie Curie after marrying Pierre Curie, was the first woman to win a Nobel Prize in Physics. She later became one of only four people to win two Nobel prizes, the second being in Chemistry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She scientifically excelled at a time where opportunities for women were rare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Childhood and Education&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marie Curie was born in Warsaw, Poland on Nov. 7, 1867. Her father was a teacher who gave her some scientific training. In 1891, she moved to Paris to continue her career in science and later obtained &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/physics/1903/marie-curie/biographical/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Licenciateships&lt;/a&gt; in Physics and the Mathematical Sciences at the Sorbonne. In 1894, she met a professor in the School of Physics named Pierre Curie, who she married the next year. In 1903, she became the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/physics/1903/marie-curie/biographical/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Head of Physics&lt;/a&gt;at the Sorbonne and earned her Doctorate of Science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was later the first woman to be appointed as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/physics/1903/marie-curie/biographical/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Professor of General Physics in the Faculty of Sciences&lt;/a&gt;, when she replaced her husband after his death in 1906.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Contribution to Science&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Henri Becquerel’s discovery of radiation emitting from uranium, Marie began her research to find other elements that emit radiation and eventually coined the term radioactivity. She and her husband quickly discovered that the existing element thorium emitted radiation as well. They also discovered that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/physics/1903/marie-curie/biographical/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;radiation originates within an atom itself&lt;/a&gt;. For this discovery, she and her husband, as well as Henri Becquerel, were awarded the Nobel Prize in Physics in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atomicheritage.org/profile/marie-curie1903&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1903&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atomicheritage.org/profile/marie-curie&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;In 1898&lt;/a&gt;, the Curies discovered two new radioactive elements, radium and polonium. The latter of the two was named after Poland, Marie’s birth place. When Pierre died in 1906, Marie continued their research and later won the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atomicheritage.org/profile/marie-curie&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1911 Nobel Prize for Chemistry&lt;/a&gt; for isolating pure radium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marie later served as the director of the Red Cross Radiology Service during the first World War, where she treated soldiers with her X-ray units. She later opened the Radium Institute in Poland with her sister in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atomicheritage.org/profile/marie-curie&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1932&lt;/a&gt;. She died in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atomicheritage.org/profile/marie-curie&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1934&lt;/a&gt; due to leukemia that was induced from her work in radiation since at the time, people weren’t aware of its dangers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet Marie Curie was a pioneer in the field of physics and a trailblazer for women in science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/womenwhochangedscience/stories/marie-curie?keyword=x-ray&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Association Curie Joliot-Curie)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Ramizah Tayiba&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ramizah Tayiba</name></author><summary type="html">The mother of physics: Marie Curie Ramizah Tayiba. 10/07/2020 Marie Curie works in her laboratory. (AFP / Getty Images) Throughout history, female scientists have been undermined and pushed aside. But there is one woman with a scientific legacy so strong she is considered the “Mother of Modern Physics,” despite the misogyny during her time.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/marieCurieCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/marieCurieCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The dangers of sitting and how to counter them</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/06/dangers-of-sitting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The dangers of sitting and how to counter them" /><published>2020-10-06T06:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-06T06:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/10/06/dangers-of-sitting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/06/dangers-of-sitting.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The dangers of sitting and how to counter them&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Angela Zhang. 10/05/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/october/dangersOfSittingOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt; One of the most prevalent effects of long-term sitting is back pain. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webmd.com/fitness-exercise/ss/slideshow-sitting-health&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;(Thinkstock)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
One of the most defining differences about life during this pandemic is that for everyone, working or learning from home nowadays entails sitting in place, eyes glued to a computer screen for hours on end. All this sitting takes a significant toll on your body, and it’s imperative that everyone who spends extensive hours seated realizes this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking a seated position at first may not seem particularly harmful to your body. But once you don’t budge from it for hours upon hours, day after day, it can easily become an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webmd.com/fitness-exercise/ss/slideshow-sitting-health&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;alarming issue&lt;/a&gt;. For one, you could develop muscle atrophy, where your lower-body muscles will weaken over time and you could end up not being able to balance or even stand properly. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2015/06/150626095520.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Research&lt;/a&gt; shows that young people could lose a third of their muscle strength in just two weeks of inactivity, while older people could lose a fourth of their strength and likely suffer worse implications on their general health and wellbeing. In addition, when there comes a time for you to move about, you will likely cramp up or strain a muscle because you’re not used to such a sudden stretch. Furthermore, you are prone to developing hip and back pain, since sitting shortens your hip flexors and compresses the discs in your spine, increasing the likelihood of premature degradation in these areas. Degradation of these spinal discs may cause pain and weakness in the back that may spread to neighboring areas such as the neck and shoulders or buttocks and upper thighs. Poor posture and a chair with insufficient support will exacerbate these issues as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, this gradual deterioration in health can be halted before it’s too late. With adequate physical activity per day, health risks brought on by sitting can be strategically avoided. However, busy working days and demanding academic schedules make it exceptionally difficult for most to squeeze in time to work out regularly. That is why stretching— even if you’re not planning on exercising vigorously— is the golden solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.healthline.com/health/benefits-of-stretching#benefits&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Stretching&lt;/a&gt;, as we all know, increases flexibility. Your muscles, stiff from being stationary all day, need this movement to both reduce tension and alleviate pain. &lt;a href=&quot;https://shcs.ucdavis.edu/blog/archive/healthy-habits/why-stretching-extremely-important&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Stretching&lt;/a&gt; also promotes blood circulation, which increases the supply of nutrients that travels through your veins and restores much-needed blood flow to your muscles. This allows for your whole body to feel refreshed and rejuvenated, releasing pent-up stress and raising energy levels. In addition, it encourages proper musculoskeletal alignment, which improves poor posture and all the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.backfithealth.com/7-detrimental-effects-of-bad-posture#:~:text=Poor%20posture%20or%20slouching%20can,cause%20muscle%20tension%20and%20stiffness.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;issues&lt;/a&gt; surrounding it, such as back, neck and shoulder pain, as well as poor circulation and digestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, stretching should never be done on cold muscles, or muscles that haven’t been warmed up beforehand. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/fitness/in-depth/art-20047931&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Stretching&lt;/a&gt; is most effective and least likely to lead to an injury when done after completing a short bout of physical activity, like jogging in place or jumping jacks. Putting on your favorite jam and dancing your heart out for two or three minutes could work too. While stretching, it is important to give both sides of your body symmetrical treatment to reduce the risk of injury. It’s also recommended to hold the position for about 30 seconds and not overdo it to the point of pain. You should aim to release stress, not cause more to your body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take five to ten minutes out of your day to give your hunched self a time to unfurl and relax. A well-stretched body will be able to counteract the dangers of sitting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.popsci.com/improve-posture/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Deposit Photos)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/Angela_Zhang.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Angela Zhang &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Angela Zhang is a junior at Beckman High School. She is an aspiring storyteller who hopes to make a profound impression on her audience with her writing. She is also a passionate cactus enthusiast and has a soft spot for cheesy puns.



&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Angela Zhang</name></author><summary type="html">The dangers of sitting and how to counter them Angela Zhang. 10/05/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/dangersOfSittingCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/dangersOfSittingCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>