<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2020-10-27T16:30:25-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">InterSTEM</title><entry><title type="html">How space fosters an interest in science</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/07/marie-curie.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How space fosters an interest in science" /><published>2020-10-07T06:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-07T06:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/10/07/marie-curie</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/07/marie-curie.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The mother of physics: Marie Curie&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Angela Zhang. 10/07/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/october/marieCurieOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt; Marie Curie works in her laboratory.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.biography.com/news/marie-curie-biography-facts&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(AFP / Getty Images)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Throughout history, female scientists have been undermined and pushed aside. But there is one woman with a scientific legacy so strong she is considered the “Mother of Modern Physics,” despite the misogyny during her time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Maria Skłodowska, who later became Marie Curie after marrying Pierre Curie, was the first woman to win a Nobel Prize in Physics. She later became one of only four people to win two Nobel prizes, the second being in Chemistry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She scientifically excelled at a time where opportunities for women were rare.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Childhood and Education&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marie Curie was born in Warsaw, Poland on Nov. 7, 1867. Her father was a teacher who gave her some scientific training. In 1891, she moved to Paris to continue her career in science and later obtained &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/physics/1903/marie-curie/biographical/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Licenciateships&lt;/a&gt; in Physics and the Mathematical Sciences at the Sorbonne. In 1894, she met a professor in the School of Physics named Pierre Curie, who she married the next year. In 1903, she became the
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/physics/1903/marie-curie/biographical/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Head of Physics&lt;/a&gt;at the Sorbonne and earned her Doctorate of Science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;She was later the first woman to be appointed as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/physics/1903/marie-curie/biographical/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Professor of General Physics in the Faculty of Sciences&lt;/a&gt;, when she replaced her husband after his death in 1906.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Contribution to Science&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After Henri Becquerel’s discovery of radiation emitting from uranium, Marie began her research to find other elements that emit radiation and eventually coined the term radioactivity. She and her husband quickly discovered that the existing element thorium emitted radiation as well. They also discovered that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/prizes/physics/1903/marie-curie/biographical/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;radiation originates within an atom itself&lt;/a&gt;. For this discovery, she and her husband, as well as Henri Becquerel, were awarded the Nobel Prize in Physics in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atomicheritage.org/profile/marie-curie1903&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1903&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atomicheritage.org/profile/marie-curie&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;In 1898&lt;/a&gt;, the Curies discovered two new radioactive elements, radium and polonium. The latter of the two was named after Poland, Marie’s birth place. When Pierre died in 1906, Marie continued their research and later won the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atomicheritage.org/profile/marie-curie&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1911 Nobel Prize for Chemistry&lt;/a&gt; for isolating pure radium.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Marie later served as the director of the Red Cross Radiology Service during the first World War, where she treated soldiers with her X-ray units. She later opened the Radium Institute in Poland with her sister in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atomicheritage.org/profile/marie-curie&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1932&lt;/a&gt;. She died in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.atomicheritage.org/profile/marie-curie&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;1934&lt;/a&gt; due to leukemia that was induced from her work in radiation since at the time, people weren’t aware of its dangers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Yet Marie Curie was a pioneer in the field of physics and a trailblazer for women in science.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nobelprize.org/womenwhochangedscience/stories/marie-curie?keyword=x-ray&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Association Curie Joliot-Curie)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Ramizah Tayiba&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ramizah Tayiba</name></author><summary type="html">The mother of physics: Marie Curie Angela Zhang. 10/07/2020 Marie Curie works in her laboratory. (AFP / Getty Images) Throughout history, female scientists have been undermined and pushed aside. But there is one woman with a scientific legacy so strong she is considered the “Mother of Modern Physics,” despite the misogyny during her time.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/marieCurieCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/marieCurieCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The dangers of sitting and how to counter them</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/06/dangers-of-sitting.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The dangers of sitting and how to counter them" /><published>2020-10-06T06:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-06T06:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/10/06/dangers-of-sitting</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/06/dangers-of-sitting.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The dangers of sitting and how to counter them&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Angela Zhang. 10/05/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/october/dangersOfSittingOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt; One of the most prevalent effects of long-term sitting is back pain. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webmd.com/fitness-exercise/ss/slideshow-sitting-health&quot; target=&quot;blank&quot;&gt;(Thinkstock)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
One of the most defining differences about life during this pandemic is that for everyone, working or learning from home nowadays entails sitting in place, eyes glued to a computer screen for hours on end. All this sitting takes a significant toll on your body, and it’s imperative that everyone who spends extensive hours seated realizes this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking a seated position at first may not seem particularly harmful to your body. But once you don’t budge from it for hours upon hours, day after day, it can easily become an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webmd.com/fitness-exercise/ss/slideshow-sitting-health&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;alarming issue&lt;/a&gt;. For one, you could develop muscle atrophy, where your lower-body muscles will weaken over time and you could end up not being able to balance or even stand properly. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2015/06/150626095520.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Research&lt;/a&gt; shows that young people could lose a third of their muscle strength in just two weeks of inactivity, while older people could lose a fourth of their strength and likely suffer worse implications on their general health and wellbeing. In addition, when there comes a time for you to move about, you will likely cramp up or strain a muscle because you’re not used to such a sudden stretch. Furthermore, you are prone to developing hip and back pain, since sitting shortens your hip flexors and compresses the discs in your spine, increasing the likelihood of premature degradation in these areas. Degradation of these spinal discs may cause pain and weakness in the back that may spread to neighboring areas such as the neck and shoulders or buttocks and upper thighs. Poor posture and a chair with insufficient support will exacerbate these issues as well.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thankfully, this gradual deterioration in health can be halted before it’s too late. With adequate physical activity per day, health risks brought on by sitting can be strategically avoided. However, busy working days and demanding academic schedules make it exceptionally difficult for most to squeeze in time to work out regularly. That is why stretching— even if you’re not planning on exercising vigorously— is the golden solution.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.healthline.com/health/benefits-of-stretching#benefits&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Stretching&lt;/a&gt;, as we all know, increases flexibility. Your muscles, stiff from being stationary all day, need this movement to both reduce tension and alleviate pain. &lt;a href=&quot;https://shcs.ucdavis.edu/blog/archive/healthy-habits/why-stretching-extremely-important&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Stretching&lt;/a&gt; also promotes blood circulation, which increases the supply of nutrients that travels through your veins and restores much-needed blood flow to your muscles. This allows for your whole body to feel refreshed and rejuvenated, releasing pent-up stress and raising energy levels. In addition, it encourages proper musculoskeletal alignment, which improves poor posture and all the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.backfithealth.com/7-detrimental-effects-of-bad-posture#:~:text=Poor%20posture%20or%20slouching%20can,cause%20muscle%20tension%20and%20stiffness.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;issues&lt;/a&gt; surrounding it, such as back, neck and shoulder pain, as well as poor circulation and digestion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That being said, stretching should never be done on cold muscles, or muscles that haven’t been warmed up beforehand. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/fitness/in-depth/art-20047931&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Stretching&lt;/a&gt; is most effective and least likely to lead to an injury when done after completing a short bout of physical activity, like jogging in place or jumping jacks. Putting on your favorite jam and dancing your heart out for two or three minutes could work too. While stretching, it is important to give both sides of your body symmetrical treatment to reduce the risk of injury. It’s also recommended to hold the position for about 30 seconds and not overdo it to the point of pain. You should aim to release stress, not cause more to your body.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Take five to ten minutes out of your day to give your hunched self a time to unfurl and relax. A well-stretched body will be able to counteract the dangers of sitting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.popsci.com/improve-posture/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Deposit Photos)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/Angela_Zhang.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Angela Zhang &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Angela Zhang is a rising junior at Beckman High School. She is an aspiring storyteller who hopes to make a profound impression on her audience with her writing. She is also a passionate cactus enthusiast and has a soft spot for cheesy puns.



&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Angela Zhang</name></author><summary type="html">The dangers of sitting and how to counter them Angela Zhang. 10/05/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/dangersOfSittingCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/dangersOfSittingCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How space fosters an interest in science</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/06/space-fosters.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How space fosters an interest in science" /><published>2020-10-06T06:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-06T06:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/10/06/space-fosters</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/06/space-fosters.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;How space fosters an interest in science&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reagan Smith. 10/06/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/october/spaceFosterOne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt; Ad Astra Academy students from Bangladesh
(Ad Astra)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.adastra.world&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Ad Astra Academy&lt;/a&gt; is a non-profit organization that visits underserved communities in various countries around the globe and works with students to foster an interest in science.  Launched in January 2015 in Northeastern England, their philosophy is based on utilizing humans’ innate creativity and curiosity to develop STEM skills and a desire to pursue a career in science. The Academy’s workshops can be anywhere from three hours to three months, and they provide participating schools with books, technology and resources to continue the program.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To test the efficacy of this program, a study was conducted in 2015 and in 2018 in a disadvantaged area of Rio de Janeiro, according to an article about the program from &lt;a href=&quot;https://sciworthy.com/can-space-exploration-motivate-students-to-learn-science/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;SciWorthy&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The three traits the researchers from the academy tested were competency, independence and relatedness. Competency was measured by the students’ ability to recall the steps of the scientific method and facts about Mars exploration, while independence and relatedness were measured using the students’ perceptions of their new skills and confidence in their scientific abilities. Overall, both metrics showed growth, and students finished the program with a new passion for science and a desire to learn more in the STEM field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So far, the organization has worked with the aforementioned groups in Rio de Janeiro as well as Bangladesh to capture twelve new images of the surface of Mars. The teams partnered with the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mars.nasa.gov/mro/mission/instruments/hirise/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;HiRISE camera&lt;/a&gt;, an instrument on the spacecraft currently looking down at Mars, and with Dr. Paul Hayne, the chief scientist at Ad Astra, to interpret the images and their meaning in
the study of Mars.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/october/spaceFosterTwo.jpg&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;An image of the HiRISE camera students were able to use to gain access to the newest images of Mars’s surface.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://mars.nasa.gov/mro/mission/instruments/hirise/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(NASA)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The groups of students were able to participate in the newest discoveries and stand at the forefront of space exploration, something previously unknown to them. In addition, students were introduced to many STEM-related careers and the opportunities available to those who show passion for the field.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s so amazing about Ad Astra Academy is that the program is able to successfully change students’ futures through short interventional steps. It doesn’t take endless time and energy to forever change someone’s path in life and make a difference, and you don’t need to attend a prestigious university or take on a rigorous class schedule to find a passion in STEM.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is so much untapped potential in the world that we never get to witness because of the environment people may live in, and the Ad Astra Academy provides a way to reach those children and bring their minds and skills to light.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.adastra.world/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Ad Astra)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/Reagan_Smith.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Reagan Smith&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Reagan is a junior from Sage Hill School. She is passionate about all things related to science, especially biology and medicine. She also loves being able to use her talents and knowledge to help others and make a difference in the world.


&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Reagan Smith</name></author><summary type="html">How space fosters an interest in science Reagan Smith. 10/06/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/spaceFosterCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/spaceFosterCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Venus and Uranus: Two Planets with Distinct Orbital Characteristics</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/05/two-planets.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Venus and Uranus: Two Planets with Distinct Orbital Characteristics" /><published>2020-10-05T06:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-05T06:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/10/05/two-planets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/05/two-planets.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Venus and Uranus: Two Planets with Distinct Orbital Characteristics&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Eric Bebenov. 10/05/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/october/twoPlanetsOne.png&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Planets Venus and Uranus spin distinctly compared to other planets in the Solar System. &lt;a href=&quot;https://elements.envato.com/the-planet-venus-is-spinning-in-space-DQXBGAU&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(elements.envato)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Our Solar System has many interesting phenomena that require a wide range of scientific research. An interesting discovery features our neighbouring planet Venus and how it spins in the opposite direction compared to other planets. This unusual rotation that causes Venus to spin westward and clockwise has prompted much debate about the scientific reasoning behind it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One common &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/why-venus-spins-the-wrong/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;theory&lt;/a&gt; states that Venus has never actually changed the way it spins. Instead, at one point it could have flipped over 180 degrees because of a strong atmospheric tide caused by the Sun’s gravitational pull on Venus’ atmosphere. Another common theory proposes Venus gradually slowed down until it reversed its direction, due to a combination of the pull of the Sun’s magnetic forces and the impact of atmospheric tides. Initially, it would have been Venus’ atmosphere spinning in retrograde that would provide the rest of the force necessary to move the entire planet in a backwards direction. Neither one of these two theories dominate over the other and thus urges researchers to investigate Venus’ past in search for answers. Tracking the rotation rate and axial tilt, two important dynamics of the planet, can provide support for each of these hypotheses. If the initial rotation rate of Venus was rapid, this would explain the axis-flip mechanism that could have caused the planet to turn 180 degrees. However, if the planet had a relatively small tilt and rotated slower than once every four Earth days, then the other hypothesis of the planet slowing down and reversing can be validated. There are still many models that need to be developed to assist researchers in finding the most probable cause.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the recent decade, a previously disregarded &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=vEiSZaRnfIg&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;hypothesis&lt;/a&gt; made a comeback. The altered spin of Venus could be attributed to the far beginning of when it was a planetesimal, which is an object formed by rock and dust, in addition to other materials. An object of an almost identical size could have collided with the planet many years ago, causing it to spin in a backwards fashion. Rather than destroying the small size of Venus, they both collided and formed a larger planet.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Venus is not the only planet that has a distinct clockwise spin. Far out into the Solar System, another planet not only has a similar retrograde spin, but also a tilt unlike others. Along its orbital path, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=rVYP36Mj6vU&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Uranus &lt;/a&gt;lays 98 degrees on its side when its direction of rotation is taken into account, unlike other planets, which tilt no more than 30 degrees along their axes. Due to this trend, season patterns vary extremely, with each season lasting 21 Earth years. This means that one hemisphere has constant sunlight, while the other has constant darkness during the span of these years. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=sEQMqpj4rbQ&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;hypothesis&lt;/a&gt; includes a collision between Uranus and another object within the Solar System. What is interesting is how the moons of the planet orbit at the same tilt as its axis, further contributing to the reality of this hypothesis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Venus and Uranus are two very interesting planets to study, and there is a lot more information that is waiting to be uncovered to solidify any theories regarding these planets. Not only will we be able to learn more about these planets, but new information might allow us to take a look at the Solar System as a whole and explore novel trends.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Awarenergy)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Eric Bebenov&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Eric Bebenov</name></author><summary type="html">Venus and Uranus: Two Planets with Distinct Orbital Characteristics Eric Bebenov. 10/05/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/twoPlanetsCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/twoPlanetsCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The miracle drug: A look into Accutane and its mechanism</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/03/miracle-drug.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The miracle drug: A look into Accutane and its mechanism" /><published>2020-10-03T06:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2020-10-03T06:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/10/03/miracle-drug</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/10/03/miracle-drug.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The miracle drug: A look into Accutane and its mechanism&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Patrick Nguyen. 10/05/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/october/miracleDrugOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This is a box of Accutane capsules for patients with severe cases of acne vulgaris. &lt;a href=&quot;https://medshadow.org/a-short-history-of-accutane/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Medshadow)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
It all starts with a pimple at the age of 13. You brush it off hoping for it to go away in a few days but then another comes up. Now at the age of 16, your face has fully broken out and after spending hundreds of dollars on skincare products and antibiotics, nothing seems to work. You head to the dermatologist in desperation and they recommend the oral use of Isotretinoin, also known as Accutane. This is a common occurrence in many teens who face self-esteem issues and anxiety regarding acne.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accutane is known for its miraculous effect of curing severe forms of acne. However, this oral drug is infamous for the intense regulation and monitoring that your local dermatologist has to conduct when taken. Although there are minor side effects such as dryness and sensitivity in the skin, Accutane has been linked to depression and mental issues Additionally, there are monthly checkups and multiple forms that you have to fill out specific to Accutane. Why does a drug that cures something as non-threatening as acne require so much regulation? Let’s analyze the pharmacology and mechanism of the miracle drug to see what’s going on here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/october/miracleDrugTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This is the chemical structure of Isotretinoin.(PubChem)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
To start, your sebaceous glands, located in the dermis (region below the outermost layer of your skin), naturally produce an oil called sebum made up of lipids such as triglycerides and fatty acids. This keeps your face hydrated and maintains a barrier from the outside world. However, many patients with acne overproduce sebum, therefore clogging their pores. That’s when Propionibacterium acnes (P. acnes), a naturally occurring bacteria that live on your skin, come in. These bacteria love to live in sebum, so with more sebum, there come more P. acnes. As a result, your skin induces an immune response as a result of the excessive amount of P. acnes, which leads to acne. Accutane then comes in to reduce sebum production by shrinking the oil glands. When the oil glands do not produce sebum, P. acnes cannot colonize, and therefore, there is a reduction in skin inflammation. However, let’s dive into this more deeply from a biochemical point of view.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Accutane (13-cis-retinoic acid) is a derivative of Vitamin A which has been proven to be beneficial for the skin in many ways. Forms of Vitamin A are called retinoids and they include other medications such as Tretinoin, which is also used in acne treatment. Although the exact mechanism of Accutane is unknown, there are key chemicals that have been noted to contribute to the efficacy of Accutane. Once Accutane is introduced into the body, it increases the levels of neutrophil gelatinase-associated lipocalin (NGAL). NGAL has been observed to increase the apoptosis (programmed cell death) of sebocytes. Sebocytes are the cells involved in the sebaceous glands and the production of sebum. Because NGAL leads to apoptosis in the sebaceous gland, there is less sebum produced in the skin. According to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://aac.asm.org/content/54/4/1580&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;research paper by Marcus Miethke and Arne Skerra&lt;/a&gt;, NGAL also interferes with the colonization of P. acnes by interfering with a certain mechanism regarding iron acquisition. This gives Accutane its antimicrobial properties against the gram-positive bacteria. Although there are many other factors that come into play, NGAL is key. There is still a lot of gray area concerning the exact processes, which has led to multiple studies being conducted today.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/october/miracleDrugThree.jpg&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This is a diagram of Sebaceous Gland with Sebocytes. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/abs/pii/S1357272509003471&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(ScienceDirect)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
So why does Accutane have a connection with mental problems in patients? According to a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2637283/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;study on mice and rats regarding the psychopathology of Isotretinoin&lt;/a&gt;, researchers have come to the conclusion that retinoids (derivatives of Vitamin A) bind to dopaminergic receptors in the central nervous system (CNS). This disrupts the structure of the receptors and neurotransmission in the brain leading to a decrease in dopamine levels. Dopamine is known as the chemical linked with happiness and excitement. Although there are other mechanisms that occur in the brain due to Isotretinoin, it is safe to assume that it does indeed affect the nervous system, explaining why there are many regulations regarding this drug.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The next time you go to the dermatologist for a solution to your acne, remember to take the time to consider the potency of this drug and its drawbacks. Accutane is a very powerful drug and can affect the body as a whole. If you are on Accutane and have experienced depression, headaches or suicidal thoughts, it is urged to stop taking the medication immediately. Although the drawbacks are daunting, it is not a common occurrence in all patients. Speaking from my personal experience, there have only been events of dryness on the skin and nosebleeds. The miracle drug has the ability to permanently cure your acne after several months of dosage and monitoring, leading to a happier, more confident individual.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Hospital &amp;amp; Healthcare Management)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Patrick Nguyen&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Patrick is a rising junior at Sage Hill School who enjoys studying cosmetic science and playing tennis. Through InterSTEM, Patrick aspires to help underrepresented communities have access to STEM education and stimulate their curiosity for science.


&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Patrick Nguyen</name></author><summary type="html">The miracle drug: A look into Accutane and its mechanism Patrick Nguyen. 10/05/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/miracleDrugCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/miracleDrugCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">COVID-19’s educational impacts back to school</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/28/educational-impact.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="COVID-19’s educational impacts back to school" /><published>2020-09-28T06:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-28T06:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/28/educational-impact</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/28/educational-impact.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;COVID-19’s educational impacts back to school&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ari Rednour. 10/25/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/september/educationalImpactOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The debate regarding whether facial masks should be mandatory to slow COVID-19’s spread has been a controversial issue across the United States. (Freepik)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In early March, schools were presented with the tough task of completing their academic terms without face-to-face learning, as 50 million students were left with a compromised form of education. Online school renders a less-rigorous schedule for most students, which is concerning for many parents who strive for their kids to be academically challenged in the classroom. With schools opening up in the late summer, school districts are scrambling to figure out what type of learning would offer both safe and quality education for these students— all with different standards and wants. Unfortunately, with many districts making adverse choices to one another, disagreement has struck between not only them but also with the parents’ and students’ opinions regarding this issue.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One side of the argument consists of individuals who believe in the importance of face-to-face learning and would choose to send themselves or their children back to school despite COVID-19. They express concern regarding the anxiety, depression and overall regression of students who need school to gauge success in academia.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;President Donald Trump has supported the reopening of schools since summer break ended. He argues that scientific evidence pledges that the transition back into the classroom will be beneficial, as the immunity of children from COVID-19 should be done before adult immunity. However, immunity to the virus for an individual is indicative of whether they have previously contracted it or not. Therefore, the idea of infecting students and putting them at risk of contracting side effects potentially worse than expected does not sit well with some. Gokul Prasad, freshman at UCSD, contends how “school boards are far too optimistic of how quickly they can reopen. Despite varying levels of COVID-19 presence around the nation, it is still far too high to think about reopening.” Although Prasad has graduated from high school, he worries that his younger siblings may get sent back to school too early, and may be at risk to contract the potentially deadly virus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Those who believe that schools should not reopen in the fall are faced with another debate: the quality of online academia. Prasad believes that online learning in the previous school year was insufficient, as the “sudden transition from in-person to online classes was the main root of issues.” He believes that with the summer to plan out class schedules via an online platform, students should be better prepared to handle an online atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Whether separate school districts choose to go completely online, completely in person, or both is a decision which will not be fully agreed on among the guardians’ of the attendees; however, as Olsen depicts, “the quality of education will be the most crucial factor for however the schools choose to operate.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/Mehri_Sadri.JPG&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Mehri Sadri
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Mehri is a rising senior at Scripps Ranch High School in San Diego, California. Although she has always been more inclined in humanities subjects, Mehri has found a love for combining science and art and their practicalities, and hopes to spread this same love to others with her articles.

&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Mehri Sadri</name></author><summary type="html">COVID-19’s educational impacts back to school Ari Rednour. 10/25/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/educationalImpactCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/educationalImpactCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Sweden’s Controversial Approach to COVID-19</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/26/sweden-covid.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sweden’s Controversial Approach to COVID-19" /><published>2020-09-26T06:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-26T06:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/26/sweden-covid</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/26/sweden-covid.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Sweden’s Controversial Approach to COVID-19&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reagan Smith. 09/26/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/september/swedenOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Anders Tegnell, the leader of Sweden’s response to the pandemic, is a controversial figure for his unusual policies and stubborn beliefs. &lt;a href=&quot;https://nypost.com/2020/09/23/swedish-fauci-blames-covid-19-deaths-on-mild-flu-season/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Pontus Lundahl / TT NEWS AGENCY / AFP via Getty Images)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Throughout this global pandemic, countries have utilized different response strategies to combat the virus and stop the spread. Sweden’s approach has by far been the most unique, as the middle-aged epidemiologist Anders Tegnell refused to shut Sweden down and insisted that a lockdown is “using a hammer to kill a fly”  For a while, the world looked at Sweden as a primary example of what not to do when combating COVID-19; however, Tegnell’s approach may still prove to be correct in the end.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tegnell sought to keep schools, restaurants, gyms and borders open, and he stood resolute in his decision to not put his country in a formal lockdown, which some Swedes appreciated. Many of his employees looked up to him as an example of logic and reason while the rest of the world fell into emotional decisions and panic. In fact, Richard Milne, a reporter and writer,  notes in an article for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Financial Times&lt;/a&gt; that most Swedes supported him fully— some even going as far as tattooing his face on their bodies— because life has remained mostly normal for them. In a &amp;lt;a href=”“https://globalizationandhealth.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12992-020-00588-x#Tab1 target=”_blank”&amp;gt;bebate&amp;lt;/a&amp;gt; on the media’s report of Sweden during COVID-19, Rachel Irwin, a professor at Lund University, says the economy has been doing well and the hospitality industry increased by 1400%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to a chart from &lt;a href=&quot;https://globalizationandhealth.biomedcentral.com/articles/10.1186/s12992-020-00588-x/tables/1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Globalization and Health&lt;/a&gt; detailing the public health measures taken in the first month (March 11 to April 16) of the pandemic response, Swedish people were advised to stay home if they felt sick, travel only if necessary, limit contacts and gatherings if over 70 years of age and avoid large public gatherings. The Public Health Agency recommended working from home as of March 16th and closing high schools and higher education as of March 17th.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Only on March 19th did they begin to put bans in place, including a ban on travel entry, crowding in public dining areas and events with more than 50 people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Swedes have been able to maintain their freedom and sense of normalcy, Tegnell’s strategy has meant that thousands of elderly people in care homes have died due to the disease. Sweden has the fifth-highest death rate per capita and has had far more deaths than its neighboring countries of Denmark, Norway and Finland. A chart from &lt;a href=&quot;https://ig.ft.com/coronavirus-chart/?areas=usa&amp;amp;areas=gbr&amp;amp;areas=swe&amp;amp;areas=dnk&amp;amp;areasRegional=usny&amp;amp;areasRegional=usca&amp;amp;areasRegional=usfl&amp;amp;areasRegional=ustx&amp;amp;byDate=1&amp;amp;cumulative=0&amp;amp;logScale=1&amp;amp;perMillion=1&amp;amp;values=deaths&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Financial Times&lt;/a&gt; explains that Sweden was right alongside the United States and the United Kingdom in death per capita in March to June, with all three countries hitting their peak in mid-April. Denmark, along with Norway, did hit its peak at the same time, but with a third of the average deaths per a million people.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, in September, there is a huge, consistent rise in the number of deaths in the United States, United Kingdom and Denmark, while that of Sweden continues to decline. This is the “second wave” mentioned often in context with COVID-19, and Sweden seems to be avoiding it, despite Tegnell’s primary intention. He sought to avoid drastic closures and reopenings because it was “going to be a disaster”, he sums up in an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ft.com/content/5cc92d45-fbdb-43b7-9c66-26501693a371&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;interview&lt;/a&gt;. Overall, his goal was to utilize Sweden’s healthcare system and view the problem from all sides, rather than focusing on lowering COVID-19 deaths.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, Sweden’s approach, while putting elderly at risk and causing controversy, is an interesting parallel to the quick-acting, decisive measures put in place by other countries. Its number of cases spiked drastically over other countries, but the country’s number of deaths remained in line with those of the United States, United Kingdom, Denmark and Norway. Now, heading into October, scientists have predicted a second wave that has already hit the United States, and other countries appear to be nearing that second peak as well. For Sweden, their numbers are decreasing, so Tegnell’s methods may prove to be successful. Although we must wait to know what the correct response to COVID-19 should have been, it is important to take note of the different strategies each country has decided to use in case of another pandemic in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/world/2020/sep/21/dont-ignore-sweden-in-covid-19-lessons&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(AFP / Getty)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/Reagan_Smith.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Reagan Smith&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Reagan is a junior from Sage Hill School. She is passionate about all things related to science, especially biology and medicine. She also loves being able to use her talents and knowledge to help others and make a difference in the world.


&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Reagan Smith</name></author><summary type="html">Sweden’s Controversial Approach to COVID-19 Reagan Smith. 09/26/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/swedenCover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/swedenCover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Why do cats sleep so much?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/26/cats-sleep.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why do cats sleep so much?" /><published>2020-09-26T06:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-26T06:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/26/cats-sleep</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/26/cats-sleep.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Why do cats sleep so much?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ari Rednour. 10/25/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/september/catCover.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;An orange tabby household cat taking a nap. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.catster.com/cat-behavior/why-do-cats-sleep-so-much-sleeping-cats-facts&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Getty Images / Ryhor Bruyeu)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For anyone who has owned or taken care of a household cat, it is well known that unless a cat is eating or playing in one of their brief moments of energy, they are most likely sleeping. From cardboard boxes and sunny spots on the tile to comfy beds or mini plush homes, cats can be found sleeping just about anywhere. Now, why do cats sleep so much? How are they able to sleep for more hours of the day than they are awake? Let’s look at their biology and natural instincts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.petmd.com/cat/behavior/evr_ct_why_do_cats_sleep_so_much&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PetMD&lt;/a&gt;, cats are natural born predators. They are engineered to chase their prey and hunt for their next meal. Lions, for example, sleep primarily in the day and use their restored energy to hunt at night. Similarly, house cats have the hunting and sleep habits of their ancestors and larger relatives. Have you ever played with a cat with a string or laser pointer? Even in what one may call simple games, cats exhibit their natural hunting instincts through their gentle stalking, readying of the paws and their pouncing on a moving object. When a cat “hunts”, whether it is a mouse in a field or a catnip toy in the house, they use an immense amount of energy. The amount of sleep they get during the day is to recharge the battery for their moments of being in an excited state of running, stalking, pouncing and climbing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, cats are known to sleep anywhere from fifteen to twenty hours in one day, but their quality of sleep changes in cycles. Similar to a human’s cycle of on-and-off REM sleep, cats shift from moments of deep sleep to periods of normal or light sleep. Deep sleep tends to only last for about five minutes at a time, while light sleep, or dozing, lasts anywhere from fifteen to thirty minutes. In the periods of light sleep, a cat is resting, but in a position ready to launch into action at any moment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The age of a cat also affects the amount of sleep they need. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aecmemphis.com/site/vet-blog-memphis/2020/02/13/my-cat-sleeps-constantly-when-should-i-worry&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Animal Emergency Center at Memphis&lt;/a&gt;, cats are very similar to humans in that the amount of sleep they need is dependent on their age. For example, kittens, like babies, need large amounts of sleep; therefore, they will sleep for most of the day, except for short moments of energy between eating. Adolescents, like teenagers, have inconsistent sleep patterns and tend to be more active than when they were kittens. At the adult stage, cats by this point have somewhat of a regular sleep schedule that consists of anywhere from twelve to twenty hours of sleep per day. Finally, senior cats have limited energy and activity levels, and they tend to sleep for long periods of time, most likely more than they did as a kitten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to their own set sleep patterns, cats also have the natural ability to tailor their sleep schedule to match those of their human owners. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ovrs.com/blog/cats-sleep/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Oakland Veterinary Referral Services&lt;/a&gt; writes that cats will typically adjust their schedules to spend time with their humans or favorite people in the household. Similarly, cats also can adjust their nap schedule to important events of the day, such as feeding times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While cats may be animals of unconventional sleeping habits, they demonstrate many similarities to humans, but simply in larger quantities. Their natural instincts of hunting remain a part of a house cat’s chemistry, even with their evolution through time. Their larger relatives, such as lions and tigers, share these traits of sleeping as well. But of course, they are in their natural habitats on defense and survival mode. Domestic cats may not need to worry about what may be outside of their house life, but their natural instincts remain ingrained in their blood to continue on for generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/Reagan_Smith.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Reagan Smith&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Reagan is a junior from Sage Hill School. She is passionate about all things related to science, especially biology and medicine. She also loves being able to use her talents and knowledge to help others and make a difference in the world.


&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ari Rednour</name></author><summary type="html">Why do cats sleep so much? Ari Rednour. 10/25/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/catCover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/catCover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Climate TRACE: A revolution in climate tracking</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/25/climate-tracking.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Climate TRACE: A revolution in climate tracking" /><published>2020-09-25T06:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-25T06:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/25/climate-tracking</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/25/climate-tracking.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Climate TRACE: A revolution in climate tracking&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ari Rednour. 10/25/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/september/climateTrackingOne.png&quot; width=&quot;80%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Climate change represents the greatest challenge our generation faces with serious consequences already influencing millions of people. (Mortgage Finance Gazette).&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In 1950, the blue skies of our native home planet had roughly 300 carbon dioxide (CO₂) molecules per one million regular air molecules (PPM), a number that had never been exceeded in the past 800,000 years. But, this relatively constant carbon dioxide level did not last much longer. Mankind exited an era where nature was still in power, and the tides shifted as humans began to dictate their environment and even the climate. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://research.noaa.gov/article/ArtMID/587/ArticleID/2636/Rise-of-carbon-dioxide-unabated&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration&lt;/a&gt;, a Cavity Ring-Down Spectroscopy (CRDS), which calculates particles of CO₂ by measuring the exponential rate of absorption of light in the detector, registered an atmospheric carbon dioxide reading of 417.1 PPM at Mauna Loa in Hawaii, an all-time peak, in May 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The impacts of climate change are being felt worldwide, as the National Aeronautics and Space Administration (NASA) reports that &lt;a href=&quot;https://climate.nasa.gov/news/2817/with-thick-ice-gone-arctic-sea-ice-changes-more-slowly/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;two-thirds of all sea ice has melted&lt;/a&gt; and that &lt;a href=&quot;https://climate.nasa.gov/vital-signs/global-temperature/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;global temperatures have increased significantly since the 1880s&lt;/a&gt;. Priya Krishnakumar and Swetha Kannan of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.latimes.com/projects/california-fires-damage-climate-change-analysis/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Los Angeles Times&lt;/a&gt; describe how eight of the ten worst fires in California’s history have occurred in 2020, and Jonathan Erdman of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://weather.com/storms/hurricane/news/2020-09-21-nine-us-landfalls-2020-hurricane-season-ties-record&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Weather Channel&lt;/a&gt; reveals that the number of tropical storms in 2020 has tied the previous record held in 1918. With time running out, humans are trying to amend our past mistakes. Organizations and people, such as former Vice President Al Gore, Blue Sky Analytics and CarbonPlan have partnered to unveil a first of its kind real-time carbon emissions tracker called Climate Tracking Real-time Atmospheric Carbon Emissions, or Climate TRACE.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although volcanic eruptions and respirations release carbon dioxide, researchers John Cook and others found a &lt;a href=&quot;https://iopscience.iop.org/article/10.1088/1748-9326/11/4/048002&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“97 [percent] consensus”&lt;/a&gt; among all scientists that human activities are the main cause of rising CO₂ levels. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.epa.gov/ghgemissions/sources-greenhouse-gas-emissions&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Environmental Protection Agency&lt;/a&gt; reports that deforestation, the burning of fossil fuels for industrial and transportation uses and agriculture cause the majority of carbon emissions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, the United States and Taiwan are two of the few countries that announce plant emissions and power generation for every hour whereas European nations and Australia only report on how much power is generated, not emissions. There is such limited information on emissions as most countries do not have government policies in place or enough money. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.powermag.com/air-emissions-tampering-leads-to-felony-charges-at-power-plant/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Aaron Larson&lt;/a&gt; also reported that all countries, regardless of wealth, can tamper their data and release unreliable information.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Present methods for obtaining atmospheric data include using CRDS and satellites that measure infrared absorption, but both of these methods utilize outdated technology. The observatories using CRDS are unable to monitor air quality high in the atmosphere, and according to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://atmosphere.copernicus.eu/flawed-estimates-effects-lockdown-measures-air-quality-derived-satellite-observations&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Atmosphere Monitoring Service&lt;/a&gt;, the satellites are prone to poor resolution imaging quality with weather skewing absorption data.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Carbon emissions can only be controlled if they are measured properly, and the current carbon tracking system depends on infrequent, unreliable, and often outdated self-reporting without independent third-party verification. To obtain better data, new technology is required to address these issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Climate TRACE, these problems are solved. According to Climate TRACE software engineer &lt;a href=&quot;https://spectrum.ieee.org/energywise/energy/fossil-fuels/how-to-track-the-emissions-of-every-power-plant-on-the-planet-from-space&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt; Heather D. Couture&lt;/a&gt;, both visible light and thermal infrared will be detected from three Earth satellite networks and radars such as the European Space Agency’s Sentinel 2 mission; so the prototype system can collect 5,000 heat signatures and images without clouds in them per day. As this is a large amount of data covering various wavelengths and angles, no team of human analysts would be capable of evaluating this information quickly and accurately. So, artificial intelligence and deep learning technology, the same kind used in speech recognition and machine translation, are utilized to rapidly spot patterns concealed in the large mass of facts and figures.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers used historical images combined with plant-reported data to teach the algorithm to identify those patterns. For instance, the AI could predict emissions when it is given an entirely new image of a known plant. To identify the power plants in the first place, the AI searches for visual and thermal signatures, such as a hot flue stack which is a smoke plume released by power plants, a large water vapor plume released by cooling towers nearby generators or hot water released by cooling towers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now that technology exists where greenhouse gas emissions can be tracked down to individual ships across the globe quickly and reliably, the world can be held to a higher standard so that climate change can be slowed. With this AI, falsified reporting will be limited, and people will be empowered to do what is right. Although Climate TRACE is not yet perfected, we are within the grasp of, as former Vice President Al Gore said, a “new era of transparency”.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.istockphoto.com/photo/detail-of-white-smoke-polluted-sky-gm167231386-23735966&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(iStockphoto)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Simone Rothaupt&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;


&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Simone Rothaupt</name></author><summary type="html">Climate TRACE: A revolution in climate tracking Ari Rednour. 10/25/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/climateTrackingCover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/climateTrackingCover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">New Australian study shows low COVID-19 transmission rates in schools</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/18/transmission-rates.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="New Australian study shows low COVID-19 transmission rates in schools" /><published>2020-09-18T06:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2020-09-18T06:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/09/18/transmission-rates</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/09/18/transmission-rates.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;New Australian study shows low COVID-19 transmission rates in schools&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reagan Smith. 9/18/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/september/transmissionOne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;100%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;African American citizens of Harlem, New York, are waiting in line to receive food and masks in order to protect themselves and their families against COVID-19. &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.apimages.com/metadata/Index/APTOPIX-Virus-Outbreak-Uruguay/f51b789442b54e789666b36e87ffed29/1/0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(AP Photo / Matilde Campodonico)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As of Aug. 4, 2020, a study from the University of Sydney found that COVID-19 transmission rates between children and children to adults were low in New South Wales schools and early educational settings, such as preschools and pre-kindergarten.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Researchers from the National Centre for Immunization Research and Surveillance (NCIRS) worked with the University of Sydney to examine data from January to April of 2020. The group, led by Professor Kristine Macartney, looked at twenty-five various locations, including fifteen schools and ten childcare/daycare centers. According to Macartney, “COVID-19 transmission in schools appears to be considerably less than that seen for other respiratory viruses, such as influenza.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This is good news for Americans as schools reopen, because it means that— when done properly— children can return to school safely. Macartney cites contact tracing, routine cleaning, and temporary closures if a member of the school contract COVID-19 as effective procedures to keep transmission rates low. Other data concerning COVID-19 shows that overall, the disease has a lower transmission and milder effect overall in the younger population. This is seen in the fact that out of 1333 primary and high schools the University and NCIRS studied, only five secondary infections were recorded, meaning COVID-19 had a .04 percent transmission rate in the settings, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2020/08/200804100225.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Science Daily&lt;/a&gt;. The study is ongoing, and researchers are still collecting transmission data for the July to September block.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Australia’s response to COVID-19 after learning of the case in Wuhan, China on Jan. 25, 2020 was different from the US’s. The country surveyed incoming travelers and communities, tested frequently and aggressively, isolated cases, and performed contact tracing. They also closed their borders and put an immediate quarantine in place. However, Australia has kept their schools open throughout the pandemic, with measures in place to help prevent the spread, closing finally on March 23, 2020, at the peak of the pandemic. They did keep early child education and care open for children ages six weeks to five years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even before the outbreak, Australia “has done a fair amount of preparation and had the mechanisms in place,” says Dr. Lesley Russel, an Associate Professor at the Menzies Centre for Health Policy, in an interview for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/expert-explains-4-key-differences-between-us-australia-coronavirus-strategy-2020-5#1-preparation-australian-leadership-empowered-its-health-agencies-while-the-trump-administration-has-taken-a-just-in-time-approach-1&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Business Insider&lt;/a&gt; on Australia’s pandemic response. They have a well-funded infection monitoring system, and the state and federal government has cooperated during this time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By comparison, the US has, in recent years, cut funding for the CDC, which is lacking resources and money. Russel says the Trump administration has utilized a “just in time” response, which may be an attempt to help prevent the economy from falling apart.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Australia’s response to the pandemic has not been politicized, and politicians have let the scientists gauge the situation and appropriate responses. The U.S. government did hold daily briefings on updates about the pandemic, but they fell into disarray as facts were skewed, reporters were berated, and past actions were called into question.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We need to look at Australia as an example of what is possible in these times, and to know that, with proper safety measures, children can go back to schools. While America cannot change its actions in the past in terms of how we have handled the pandemic, moving forward, we need unified, confident, and effective methods to maintain safety while reopening. This study done by the University of Sydney can give us a look into the long-term effectiveness of quarantining compared to keeping certain settings open, and it can give us security as the school year starts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As schools reopen, studies show the transmission rates of COVID-19 are low, with proper distancing and safety requirements.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/07/01/opinion/coronavirus-schools.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Kyle Grillot / Reuters)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/Reagan_Smith.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Reagan Smith&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Reagan is a junior from Sage Hill School. She is passionate about all things related to science, especially biology and medicine. She also loves being able to use her talents and knowledge to help others and make a difference in the world.


&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Reagan Smith</name></author><summary type="html">New Australian study shows low COVID-19 transmission rates in schools Reagan Smith. 9/18/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/transmissionCover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/transmissionCover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>