<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.2">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-07-15T22:46:44-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">InterSTEM</title><entry><title type="html">Benefits of Coffee</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/06/18/coffee.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Benefits of Coffee" /><published>2022-06-18T10:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-18T10:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/06/18/coffee</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/06/18/coffee.html"><![CDATA[<h2 style="font-family: Ergonomique Bold">Benefits of Coffee</h2>
<p>Peter Bui. 06/18/2022</p>
<hr />

<p><img src="/images/blogs/2022/june/brown_coffee.png" width="60%" style="display: block; margin: 0 auto" /></p>
<center> <i>
<a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/better/lifestyle/how-tap-health-benefits-coffee-ncna1096031" target="_blank">(NBC)</a>
</i></center>
<p><br /></p>

<p>Coffee is a miracle beverage enjoyed by millions of people worldwide on a daily basis. However, the caffeine in coffee that makes a person more alert does more than just that, and that cup of coffee overall does justice to the drinker. Coffee, along with the taste and energy, comes with many benefits!</p>

<p><br /><span style="font-weight: 900">What is coffee?</span></p>

<p>Coffee is a brewed drink prepared from roasted coffee beans, the seeds of berries from certain flowering plants in the Coffea genus. From the coffee fruit, the seeds are separated to produce a stable, raw product: unroasted green coffee. The seeds are then roasted, a process which transforms them into a consumable product, roasted coffee, which is ground into fine particles typically steeped in hot water before being filtered out. This is what produces a cup of coffee.</p>

<p>Coffee is darkly colored, bitter, slightly acidic and has a stimulating effect in humans, primarily due to its caffeine content. It is one of the most popular drinks in the world and can be prepared and presented in a variety of ways (such as espresso French press, caffè latte, or already-brewed canned coffee). It is usually served hot, although chilled or iced coffee is also common.</p>

<p><br /><span style="font-weight: 900">What benefits does drinking coffee have?</span></p>

<p>To name a few, coffee boosts your energy level. Coffee contains caffeine, a central nervous system stimulant that is known for its ability to fight fatigue and increase energy levels. This is because caffeine blocks the receptors of a neurotransmitter called adenosine, which increases levels of other neurotransmitters that regulate energy levels, one being dopamine. In addition, coffee is often used as an ergogenic aid by athletes looking to improve performance and increase energy levels. An ergogenic aid is also called a performance enhancer. One review of nine studies reported that drinking coffee before exercise improved people’s endurance and decreased their perceived exertion when compared with a control group. Additionally, a large review reported that moderate caffeine consumption could slightly improve power output and time-trial completion time. However, results varied, so the researchers also noted that caffeine may affect people differently.</p>

<p>While drinking coffee is enjoyed by many and comes with plenty of pros, there’s some downsides to it. First of all, bad coffee can be toxic. Bad quality coffee could have impurities, which can cause sickness and headaches. Even one ruined bean could ruin your coffee. In addition, coffee can cause insomnia and restlessness. This is due to the caffeine in the coffee. Your recommended maximum amount of caffeine is 400 milligrams, roughly the amount that you’ll get from 4 cups of coffee. If you’re caffeine-sensitive, be careful with coffee. You are probably already aware what amount and what kind of coffee suits, or doesn’t suit you. The amount of caffeine that is safe for human consumption is actually written in our DNA.</p>

<p>In conclusion, coffee is loved by millions of people around the world and will likely continue to be for years to come. Drinking coffee can provide plenty of benefits such as keeping us energized and supplying plenty of energy, although there’s some negative aspects of coffee, such as causing insomnia and restlessness. However, everything has its ups and downs and if coffee is what you’re into then go for it!</p>

<p>Cover Photo: <a href="https://www.kidney.org/newsletter/coffee-and-kidney-disease" target="_blank">(kidney.org)</a></p>
<hr />

<p><img src="/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg" width="170" style="float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;" /></p>
<div style="margin-bottom: 5%;">
<span style="font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;">Peter Bui</span>
<br />
</div>]]></content><author><name>Peter Bui</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Coffee. A refreshing beverage enjoyed by millions around the world among almost every age group. While in the past coffee has not been on the side of science, newer research shows that in moderation coffee can actually be pretty beneficial!]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2022/june/steamed_coffee.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2022/june/steamed_coffee.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How does electricity work?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/06/11/how-does-electricity-work.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How does electricity work?" /><published>2022-06-11T10:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-11T10:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/06/11/how%20does%20electricity%20work</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/06/11/how-does-electricity-work.html"><![CDATA[<h2 style="font-family: Ergonomique Bold">How does electricity work?</h2>
<p>Vova Prylepa. 06/11/2022</p>
<hr />

<p><img src="/images/blogs/2022/june/electrical_distribution.png" width="60%" style="display: block; margin: 0 auto" /></p>
<center> A small magnet is used to manipulate ferrofluid into unique modifications.<i>
<a href="https://www.instituteforenergyresearch.org/electricity-distribution/" target="_blank">(Institue for Energy Research)</a>
</i></center>
<p><br /></p>

<p>Any electrical device, be it the phone in your hand, a toaster, or the television is powered by electricity. However, even though electricity is such an important factor in our well-being and every day comfort, very few people truly understand the way humans interact with electrons by the medium of various machines in order to exploit the energy carried by these small particles. In this article, we will explore what electricity is and some tools in our everyday life that help us control it.</p>

<p>To determine how electricity works, we first have to acknowledge that everything in this world is made up of various different types of atoms. All atoms are made of protons, neutrons, and electrons. These parts are indistinguishable from element to element, meaning that the protons observed in any element will be identical in all of their properties, differing only by quantity (in some cases). Protons have a positive charge, while neutrons are neutral, and electrons are negatively charged. The number of these subatomic particles and their proportions inside, and outside the nucleus determine the type of atom and its properties. In fact, all atoms contain a nucleus, which is a collection of the aforementioned protons and neutrons, which are surrounded by a cloud of electrons in constant, and to a certain degree, orderly movement around it. Atoms contain the same number of electrons as they do protons, which is scientifically called a balance of charges.</p>

<p>The number of electrons is restricted to the number of orbits around an atom. The quantity of electrons on a given orbit path stays the same across atoms (for instance 2 for the first orbit and 8 for all of the following), but the number of orbits varies in relation to the number of electrons needed to balance out the positively charged protons. The more protons there are, the bigger the positive charge, the more electrons are needed and thus the more orbits available. It’s also possible that the outer orbit containing electrons only needs one or two additional electrons to balance the atom, even though it isn’t at its maximum electron capacity, having the potential to hold more electrons.</p>

<p><br /><span style="font-weight: 900">Insulators vs Conductors</span></p>

<p>Atoms want to create an electrical charge balance and be stable by filling in their orbits with electrons. Depending on the type of atom or element, if it has an incomplete orbit, it will steal electrons from atoms nearby just to complete its outermost orbit. This back and forth exchange of electrons created when incomplete atoms take electrons from other atoms to create a charge balance in a continuous chain reaction is what we call electricity.</p>

<p>Atoms with the tendency to temporarily steal electrons from each other (primarily metal atoms), are called conductors, while those that do not are called insulators. Rubber is the most well-known and used insulator, utilized to cover wires with a protective layer that blocks the current of electrons from flowing through the wires, and electrocuting us.</p>

<p><br /><span style="font-weight: 900">Resistance - Resistors</span></p>

<p>Not all conductors have the same degree of conductivity, with some better and some worse than others. Resistance is the speed of the electrons in the current flow at which a conductor moves electricity. Resistance increases the slower the conductor is and decreases the faster the conductor is. If the resistance is too insignificant and we put a lot of electricity in a circuit, the object you try to power up may be damaged from all the energy flowing through it at high speeds, <a href="https://theengineeringmindset.com/how-electricity-works/" target="_blank">hitting nearby atoms</a> and breaking bonds between them.</p>

<p>Resistors are tools that regulate the amount of electricity flowing through a circuit. A resistor is an object made of conductive material that has a higher resistance than the wires in the circuit. It slows down the electricity so objects such as light bulbs don’t become damaged.</p>

<p><br /><span style="font-weight: 900">Current</span></p>

<p>The two types of currents are the alternating current (AC) and the direct current (DC). A direct current is when electricity leaves one end of the battery, travels along a path that travels throughout the phone, and then ends up returning back into the battery.</p>

<p>An alternating current is when the direction of the flow of electrons rapidly changes, allowing electricity to charge numerous devices at a time. The outlets in houses are wired so that they can charge any device simultaneously without it having to wait for its turn.</p>

<p><br /><span style="font-weight: 900">Conclusion:</span></p>

<p>Electricity is the chain reaction of atoms taking electrons from each other to fill their incomplete outermost orbitals. Resistance is the speed of the electrons in the current flow at which a conductor moves electricity, increasing in a slow conductor and decreasing in a fast conductor. Resistors are tools that regulate the amount of electricity flowing through a circuit, slowing down the flow to prevent damage. The direct current is a one directional current linked with a battery, while the ac is a current that can change directions, and allows us to charge devices simultaneously, without them having to wait for their turn.</p>

<p>Cover Photo: <a href="https://www.vox.com/2016/9/19/12938086/electrify-everything" target="_blank">(Vox)</a></p>
<hr />

<p><img src="/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg" width="170" style="float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;" /></p>
<div style="margin-bottom: 5%;">
<span style="font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;">Vova Prylepa</span>
<br />
</div>]]></content><author><name>Vova Prylepa</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Learn about the production of electricity, as well as some key components of circuits to understand one of the most essential resources of our time.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2022/june/electricity.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2022/june/electricity.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Liquid magnetic telescopes</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/06/01/liquid-magnetic-telescopes.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Liquid magnetic telescopes" /><published>2022-06-01T10:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2022-06-01T10:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/06/01/liquid-magnetic-telescopes</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/06/01/liquid-magnetic-telescopes.html"><![CDATA[<h2 style="font-family: Ergonomique Bold">Liquid magnetic telescopes</h2>
<p>Jessica Chung. 06/01/2022</p>
<hr />

<p><img src="/images/blogs/2022/june/magnet.png" width="60%" style="display: block; margin: 0 auto" /></p>
<center> A small magnet is used to manipulate ferrofluid into unique modifications.<i>
<a href="https://spinoff.nasa.gov/Spinoff2018/cg_3.html" target="_blank">(NASA)</a>
</i></center>
<p><br /></p>

<p>Space research is constantly developing and expanding, and from Earth, the main source of our data is the telescopes that we’re able to use. While we’ve been able to acquire some amazing data with everything from radio to ultraviolet telescopes, there’s always room for improvement.</p>

<p>When it comes to telescopes, the bigger the better - the wider the lens, the more light you’ll be able to collect. Thus, your images will be higher resolution and your data will be clearer. Unfortunately, though, this means that one day we’ll approach some limit to what size telescope we’re able to build, cast into metal, how much weight a telescope will be able to support on its own, or how much money we’re willing to invest into solving all of these problems.</p>

<p>Another issue with a few telescopes is that Earth’s atmosphere often <a href="https://www.photonics.com/Articles/Adaptive_Optics_Taming_Atmospheric_Turbulence/a25129#:~:text=For%20more%20than%20three%20centuries,limit%20set%20by%20their%20optics." target="_blank">distorts telescope images that astronomers take</a>. Recognized as early as Newton’s time, this is because as the atmosphere consists of a variety of temperatures, trying to take a photo through all of these layers often results in the light collected from the telescope going in slightly different directions depending on where in the atmosphere it passed through. The photo ends up distorted in ways that are hard to fix, especially because it’s not a consistent discrepancy over the entire thing.</p>

<p>There’s a solution that answers both of these problems: <a href="https://adsabs.harvard.edu/full/1996A%26AS..115..175R" target="_blank">liquid magnetic telescopes</a>. The concept behind these telescopes is, in essence, simple: it uses the idea of liquid mirrors, often made out of mercury, to create a telescope surface that can be manipulated as the user pleases. This idea can be expanded upon by making the liquid mirror out of something called ferrofluid, a magnetic liquid made of tiny particles that allow it to act as a liquid in the presence of magnets and as a solid otherwise. This power is perfect for these types of applications: it would allow the surface of telescopes to be specially adjusted to offset the distortion from the atmosphere while also being affordable.</p>

<p>In general, liquid mirror telescopes work by spinning the liquid fast enough that it creates a parabolic shape, which happens to be exactly what you need for a telescope - an idea first developed by Isaac Newton. This kind of stable rotation requires something like an electric motor in order to work, and means that they can only work if placed directly vertically, unlike conventional telescopes, which can orient themselves to look across the sky. However, this isn’t actually as inhibiting as you might think since if we’re looking for faraway objects like distant galaxies, you can find those no matter what part of the sky you look at - so for collecting general data, having these kinds of telescopes will be just fine.</p>

<p>In 2005, <a href="https://www.americanscientist.org/article/liquid-mirror-telescopes" target="_blank">Paul Hickson</a> worked with a few other scientists to develop the Large Zenith Telescope, or LZT, with the goal of developing liquid mirror technology that could rival the telescopes that had already existed at that time. It cost about a million dollars, significantly less than traditional telescopes of the same size (only about 1% of the cost). So, if resources were dedicated to building more instruments with this type of technology, astronomers would be able to benefit from significantly more observing time.</p>

<p>The LZT is the third largest optical telescope in the North America. In it, a rotating steel truss and 30 adjustable pads support a 6 centimeter thick dish of hexagonal segments that form a shell to hold a thin layer of liquid mercury. There are walls on the edge of the dish so that the mercury doesn’t spill over the sides. Pressurized air is used between the truss and its bearings in order to minimize friction and allow the telescope to spin as fast as possible.</p>

<p>In liquid mirror telescopes made with ferrofluid, the ferrofluid consists of extremely small particles of magnetite (Fe3O4), each about 10 nm in diameter, which can be magnetized. The ferrofluid sits above several magnetic coils, so by controlling the current and magnetic field of each of these coils, the shape of the surface can be altered. <a href="https://physicsworld.com/a/liquid-mirror-shows-promise-for-adaptive-optics/" target="_blank">A few researchers</a> investigated this hypothesis through testing if the mirror could account for misaligned lenses (based on incoming light), as well as creating aberrations by placing Petri dishes in front of the mirror. The liquid mirror succeeded in correcting the distortion in both of these cases.</p>

<p>We’ve been trying to learn more about the sky and the stars ever since early civilizations, myths about the stars that humans have written since the beginning of time. Especially with the threat of climate change looming over us, the prospect of finding more about outer space is ever appealing, and we’ll need a viable way to learn more about it. While it’s possible to keep investing resources to build bigger and bigger telescopes that require more and more resources, it’s also quite possible that liquid magnetic telescopes are a cheaper and more reasonable alternative to keep sweeping the skies.</p>

<p>According to <a href="https://www.atlasobscura.com/places/large-zenith-telescope" target="_blank">Atlas Obscura</a>, NASA hopes to develop extracurricular liquid telescopes that could be placed on the moon. Besides that, there are plenty of other applications including cosmology, the structure of the universe, the evolution of galaxies, and supernovas. It’s a worthwhile investment to consider as the study of astronomy continues to expand.</p>

<p>Cover Photo: <a href="https://www.nbcnews.com/id/wbna19337520" target="_blank">(NBC News)</a></p>
<hr />

<p><img src="/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg" width="170" style="float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;" /></p>
<div style="margin-bottom: 5%;">
<span style="font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;">Jessica Chung</span>
<br />
</div>]]></content><author><name>Jessica Chung</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[As the field of astrophysics continues to expand and we attempt to peer into the far reaches of the universe, one new technology is starting to prove its worth —— liquid magnetic telescopes, whose surfaces can be altered in real time. When we can manipulate the physical technology in our hands, a universe of possibilities opens up.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2022/june/liquid_magnetic_telescopes.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2022/june/liquid_magnetic_telescopes.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Zombies exist… careful, you might have one inside of you!</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/22/zombie-exist.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Zombies exist… careful, you might have one inside of you!" /><published>2022-05-22T10:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-22T10:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/05/22/zombie-exist</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/22/zombie-exist.html"><![CDATA[<h2 style="font-family: Ergonomique Bold">Zombies exist… careful, you might have one inside of you!</h2>
<p>Vova Prylepa. 05/22/2022</p>
<hr />

<p><img src="/images/blogs/2022/may/virus_list.png" width="60%" style="display: block; margin: 0 auto" /></p>
<center> Some of the most common and dangerous types of viruses.<i>
<a href="https://www.istockphoto.com/illustrations/hepatitis-b" target="_blank">(iStockphoto)</a>
</i></center>
<p><br /></p>

<p>Viruses, half-dead half-living molecular parasites, have terrorized humans for over millennia. Let’s delve deep into the biology of our biological foe, the main causes of the danger it represents, and how to fight it.</p>

<p>Viruses are much smaller than cells and are simple containers of genetic material. They invade the cells in our bodies to procreate and mess up the processes responsible for the healthily functioning of the cell. The cells in question are destroyed in the process. They can’t create copies of themselves without being inside of a cell. In fact, on their own, they aren’t able to engage in processes we associate with life, which qualifies them as zombies. However, they do contain the necessary instructions without being able to translate them into useful biochemical components, a function for which they rely on their host cells. Once produced, these components become part of the virion (the virus particle) that will carry these instructions from cell to cell. Interestingly enough, most viruses contain only a few genes, the minimum being two to three.</p>

<p>Viruses mutate and evolve in order to survive better against the organisms’ attempts to suppress it (for instance, antibiotics that work on bacteria do not work on viruses). As the viral genome is being read to create new copies, the wrong base, and thus the wrong nucleotide is occasionally inserted in the gene, similar to a typo on a computer. Even though such typos happen seldom on an individual gene, because of the frequency of the replication of the virus, they accumulate with time and aid the virus with completely new dangerous properties.</p>

<p>For instance, HIV becomes very genetically diverse during infection because it can make the cells read and create copies of itself several times a day in an individual for years. It means that these typos build up and add mutations to the virus, <a href="https://www.livescience.com/56598-deadliest-viruses-on-earth.html" target="_blank">allowing damage to a wider range of bodily functions</a> than previously available, and making it harder to kill due to the number of copies. That’s why HIV is resistant to specific drugs; the genome of the virus differs with every hour from the one that was replicated before. Therefore, treating HIV with a single drug won’t affect the virus because its genes mutate very quickly and the drug won’t be adapted to stop the cells from replicating a specific HIV gene with a particular number of typos.</p>

<p><br /><span style="font-weight: 900">Why do only some of the millions of viruses cause illness?</span></p>

<p>Over long periods of evolution, a virus can either die out, kill its host (sometimes an entire species), or it can <a href="https://www.livescience.com/56598-deadliest-viruses-on-earth.html" target="_blank">co-evolve so it can no longer cause the damage</a> to kill the host, but can still replicate inside of it. It’ll cause a mild sickness, but the host will recover so the virus can survive.</p>

<p>But when the virus finds itself in a new species, it might be very dangerous for that host because the host hasn’t adapted to the disease to be able to negate its dangerous effects. That’s why a virus that doesn’t do much to animals can harm humans (such as HIV or COVID-19) and a virus that does not do much to humans can harm animals.</p>

<p>Some viruses are dormant in our bodies. They live within us but don’t cause any harm because they are suppressed by our immune system. They can be awoken if the immune system is damaged though, and some of them can cause serious harm, such as CMV. A person with HIV has a very weak immune system, which means it can’t suppress CMV anymore and the cytomegalovirus can destroy the retina, completely blinding its host.</p>

<p><br /><span style="font-weight: 900">Are there harmless viruses that just live in us?</span></p>

<p>Some viruses are stable outside of cells, like the coronavirus (which can be transmitted through droplets of saliva) or polio (transmitted through contaminated water), while others, like HIV, have low environmental stability and can only be transmitted through sex or blood transfusion.</p>

<p><br /><span style="font-weight: 900">Methods of prevention/ treatment</span></p>

<p>We can prevent viruses with vaccines and treat them with <a href="https://www.mayoclinic.org/diseases-conditions/infectious-diseases/in-depth/germs/art-20045289" target="_blank">antiviral drugs</a>. A vaccine is usually a component of the virus or a weakened version of the virus in some cases. It induces a response from the body to make antibodies. It is done so when the organism is confronted to an actual virus again, this time in its full strength, the antibodies will remember how to kill it off before it has a chance to cause disease. The vaccine is thus similar to a practice exercise for the antibodies.</p>

<p>An antiviral is a small molecule component of viral RNA or DNA. It is then modified to have the ability to disrupt the replication of the virus in question. Although the virus will not leave the body, antivirals can help treat viral infections such as influenza or Ebola.</p>

<p><br /><span style="font-weight: 900">Conclusion </span></p>

<p>Viruses can be fragile or strong, varying in lethality per virus based on the species. Copying errors during DNA transfer can give viruses the potential to cause more harm since their genetic makeup may change before a vaccine with a weakened version of the virus is made. Some well-known and dangerous viruses include HIV, polio, the common cold, and COVID-19, and while these can be very harmful, anti-viral treatment or vaccination can serve as a remedy against its effects.</p>

<p>Cover Photo: <a href="https://www.nhlbi.nih.gov/sites/default/files/styles/16x9_crop/public/2021-12/iStock-1268214384.jpg?h=99d60463&amp;itok=AbrAPV9D" target="_blank">(NHLBI)</a></p>
<hr />

<p><img src="/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg" width="170" style="float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;" /></p>
<div style="margin-bottom: 5%;">
<span style="font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;">Vova Prylepa</span>
<br />
</div>]]></content><author><name>Vova Prylepa</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Learn about why viruses are so dangerous for us, as well as about the key characteristics of the most dangerous viruses out there and different types of treatment.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2022/may/virus.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2022/may/virus.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Social Skills and Mental Health</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/15/social-skills-and-mental-health-Copy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Social Skills and Mental Health" /><published>2022-05-15T10:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2022-05-15T10:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/05/15/social-skills-and-mental-health%20-%20Copy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/05/15/social-skills-and-mental-health-Copy.html"><![CDATA[<h2 style="font-family: Ergonomique Bold">Social Skills and Mental Health</h2>
<p>Peter Bui. 05/15/2022</p>
<hr />

<p><img src="/images/blogs/2022/may/social_skills.png" width="60%" style="display: block; margin: 0 auto" /></p>
<center><i>
<a href="https://www.emotivebrand.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/08/Business-Imperative-Socializing-Strategy.jpg" target="_blank">(Emotive Brand)</a>
</i></center>
<p><br /></p>

<p>In modern society, it’s of utmost importance to have a positive attitude and good mental health. Depression and anxiety are very real, affecting millions of people worldwide everyday. A possible contributor to poor mental health is not being able to talk to people or lack of  social skills. In relation, a possible solution for maintaining a good mental health is by developing social skills.</p>

<p><br /><span style="font-weight: 900">What is mental health and why is it important to have a positive outlook? </span></p>

<p>The <a href="https://www.mentalhealth.gov/basics/what-is-mental-health" target="_blank">definition</a> of mental health is “a state of well-being in which the individual realizes his or her own abilities can cope with the normal stresses of life, can work productively and fruitfully, and is able to make a contribution to his or her community”. Having  good mental health indicates emotional, psychological, and social well-being. Mental health is crucial in many different <a href="https://www.cdc.gov/mentalhealth/learn/index.htm#:~:text=It%20affects%20how%20we%20think,others%2C%20and%20make%20healthy%20choices.&amp;text=Mental%20health%20is%20important%20at,childhood%20and%20adolescence%20through%20adulthood." target="_blank">aspects</a>. It affects how we deal with stress, think, feel, and act. Poor mental health can lead to depression, which can even result in suicide or drug abuse. According to research, social skills may play a key role in preventing it.</p>

<p><br /><span style="font-weight: 900">What exactly are social skills and what role do they play? </span></p>

<p><a href="https://www.skillsyouneed.com/ips/social-skills.html" target="_blank">Social skills</a>
 are skills we use to communicate and interact with each other, both verbally and non-verbally, through gestures, body language and our personal appearance. According to skillsyouneed.com, social skills can help build better relationships, which, in the long run, helps reduce stress and boost self esteem. In addition, it also increases overall happiness.
Indirectly, social skills have an impact on health through stress and loneliness. In fact, a leading cause of depression is long term loneliness or isolation. People with poor social skills often experience stress and loneliness which potentially develops a risk for compromised mental and physical health. The increasing loneliness and stress can escalate into mental disorders. Talking to more people and socializing ultimately leads to better mental health rather than isolating yourself or not talking to as many people. In fact, a <a href="https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2017/11/171106090116.htm" target="_blank">study</a> surveying 775 people with ages ranging from 18 to 91 showed that poor social skills can actually be harmful to health in general.</p>

<p>In addition, the more friends or time spent with other people is a huge contributing factor to a positive mental health. Having someone to talk to about how you feel is very important. It helps you let out how you feel and also helps you relate to people. Building social skills and making friends is important throughout life. A quote that highlights this can be “Our mental health depends on us being able to verbalize our feelings and emotions without the use of violence.” One of the most important parts of being human is “having the ability to communicate your feelings and emotions”. Based on <a href="https://ourworldindata.org/happiness-and-friends" target="_blank">research</a>, people who actively decide to improve their social relations often report becoming happier. A good social circle is a key to overall happiness. According to another <a href="https://happyproject.in/friend/" target="_blank">study</a> made in 2008, knowing someone who is happy makes you 15.3 percent more likely to be happy yourself. When a friend of yours has a happy friend, it increases your own chances of happiness by 9.8%. If a friend of yours has become happy in the past 6 months, you are 45% more likely to be happy. In conclusion, not only is having friends around you an important factor, but also having happy friends, or ones that can at least cheer you up.</p>

<p>There’s a difference between extroverts and introverts in the sense of socializing. While an extrovert is an outgoing, overtly expressive person, introverts are more shy and quiet. While being introverted is usually not a problem, or can even <a href="https://www.inc.com/glenn-leibowitz/yale-psychologists-introverts-are-better-than-extroverts-at-performing-this-essential-leadership-skill.html#:~:text=Extroverts%20may%20be%20known%20for,how%20to%20effectively%20lead%20others." target="_blank">be better than being extroverted</a>
 in the sense that they tend to be more observant and understand social behavior, they are also more likely to have depression and even anxiety. This can be because they tend to have a greater sensitivity to feelings and emotions and also may not have people to communicate with. Overall, introverts are <a href="https://scholarworks.uni.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1312&amp;context=grp" target="_blank">more vulnerable</a> than extroverts.</p>

<p>There are many different approaches to improving social skills, but mainly, it is simply talking to people. Finding people who have common interests for topics as simple as games can lead to friendships, which can also lead to overall happiness. Joining clubs with people who have shared interests can be a way to meet new people. Replace negative thoughts with positive thoughts and let people know how you feel.</p>

<p>In conclusion, social skills and mental health have a correlation in the sense that poor social skills can be related with poor mental health. It’s important to learn to socialize and make friends for your mental health.</p>

<p>Cover Photo: <a href="https://www.cmuse.org/" target="_blank">(cmuse)</a></p>
<hr />

<p><img src="/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg" width="170" style="float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;" /></p>
<div style="margin-bottom: 5%;">
<span style="font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;">Peter Bui</span>
<br />
</div>]]></content><author><name>Peter Bui</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[In this day and age, it’s important to maintain good mental health. Are social skills a primary factor in achieving good mental health?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2022/may/people.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2022/may/people.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The basic concepts of quantum computers</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/22/basics-of_quantum-computing.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The basic concepts of quantum computers" /><published>2022-04-22T10:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2022-04-22T10:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2022/04/22/basics-of_quantum-computing</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2022/04/22/basics-of_quantum-computing.html"><![CDATA[<h2 style="font-family: Ergonomique Bold">The Basic Concepts of Quantum Computers</h2>
<p>Emma Ylagan. 04/22/2022</p>
<hr />

<p>When most people hear the term “quantum computing” they probably think of complex theories, with futuristic-looking computers. Although it is inherently a higher-end subject, utilizing concepts of advanced calculus and physics, the core ideas can be broken down into simple, easy-to-visualize components.</p>

<p><br /><span style="font-weight: 900">A Look at a Quantum Computer</span></p>

<p>Although the core ideas of quantum computing can be explained quite simply, quantum computers themselves are quite complex. When hearing the term “quantum computer”, if you thought of something futuristic, you aren’t wrong, but it probably looks a little different than you would expect. This is a quantum computer.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blogs/2022/april/quantum_computing.png" width="60%" style="display: block; margin: 0 auto" /></p>
<center><i>IBM’S Quantum Computer
<a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/ibm/2020/01/16/the-quantum-computing-era-is-here-why-it-mattersand-how-it-may-change-our-world/?sh=3f5b4cea5c2b" target="_blank">(Forbes)</a>
</i></center>
<p><br />
It’s suspended in this chamber-like contraption for several reasons, including temperature regulation and noise reduction, and the computer itself looks quite complex with lots of parts, but again, this can all be broken  down into the fundamental ideas behind quantum computing. But first, the focus lies on what this device is, and how it compares to the Dells and Macs we typically use.</p>

<p><br /><span style="font-weight: 900">Classical vs Quantum</span></p>

<p>First off, we call these more traditional computers “classical computers’’. Classical computers utilize bits to store data and information; everything you see and do on a computer can be broken down into 0s and 1s. Quantum computers, on the other hand, use quantum bits, not classical bits. A common abbreviation for this term is “qubit”. A qubit is essentially able to store more information than a classical bit ever could. But how? That brings us to our first quantum concept: superposition.</p>

<p><br /><span style="font-weight: 900">Superposition</span></p>

<p>Superposition is the phenomenon where something is considered to be two things at once. This mind-bending concept can be simplified using a famous analogy called Schrodinger’s cat. The analogy goes like this: You put a cat in a bag with some poison that could be released at any moment. Assuming you can’t receive any tells of the cat’s well-being from looking at the bag itself, at any moment in time, the cat can be considered both dead and alive. That is, until you actually open the bag.</p>

<p>This is the exact concept used in qubits. Qubits are found in a state of superposition, as was the cat, in which it can be considered both a 0 and 1. Of course, this is only until it is measured, in which it collapses into either-or.</p>

<p><img src="/images/blogs/2022/april/superposition.png" width="60%" style="display: block; margin: 0 auto" /></p>
<center><i>Visual representation of a qubit 
<a href="https://medium.com/@kareldumon/the-computational-power-of-quantum-computers-an-intuitive-guide-9f788d1492b6" target="_blank">(Medium)</a>
</i></center>
<p><br /></p>

<p>This is what gives qubits the upper hand when compared to classical bits. Consider a computer with 4 bits, each one being definitively 0 or 1. There are 16 different combinations you can make with them. That means you would need 64 bits (16 combinations x 4 bits per combination) to cover all of the possible combinations. However, when we look at qubits and take into account the fact that they are both 0 and 1 simultaneously, you only need four qubits to “cover” all combinations. This creates a high level of efficiency, especially when dealing with large amounts of data.</p>

<p><br /><span style="font-weight: 900">Entanglement</span></p>

<p>The next concept of focus is quantum entanglement. When two qubits become “entangled”, they are considered permanently linked. This means that no matter how far apart they are, they will always mirror each other’s state (either 0 or 1). Measuring one will always yield information in knowing the state of the other, and vice versa.</p>

<p>Thinking about this visually, if you have a qubit right in front of you with its entangled partner halfway across the universe, and you measured the one in front of you, collapsing its state of superposition, its partner would also collapse, and you’d know this information instantaneously. Within a quantum computer, this means that you can take measurements of many qubits at the same time, dramatically increasing its computing power.</p>

<p><br /><span style="font-weight: 900">Applications</span></p>

<p>There are many different applications to the concepts of quantum computing, as well as quantum computers themselves. For example, when we look at the neuroscience and psychology field, there are many challenges posed by the lack of computer data storage when doing something like mapping out the human brain. A quantum computer, given its high levels of efficiency and power, could help with this data storage issue.</p>

<p>Something to keep in mind, however, is that quantum computers aren’t the definitive future of the computer itself. As opposed to some initial thought, quantum computers aren’t always better than classical computers. They are, without a doubt, extremely helpful in specific situations that involve heavy calculations or require an immense amount of data, but <a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/will-quantum-computing-ever-live-up-to-its-hype/" target="_blank">generalizing that they are always “better” would be inaccurate</a>. Some tasks simply work better on classical computers, so the “hype” around the quantum computer is more about being able to have this new tool that we can use, an option when the need for it arises.</p>

<p>Cover Photo: <a href="https://www.wilsoncenter.org/sites/default/files/styles/embed_text_block/public/media/uploads/images/shutterstock_1571766802.jpg" target="_blank">(Wilson Center)</a></p>
<hr />

<p><img src="/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg" width="170" style="float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;" /></p>
<div style="margin-bottom: 5%;">
<span style="font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;">Emma Ylagan</span>
<br />
</div>]]></content><author><name>Emma Ylagan</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This article breaks down the fundamental ideas behind quantum computing, including what a qubit is, superposition, and quantum entanglement.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2022/april/quantum_computer.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2022/april/quantum_computer.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The environmental impacts of fast fashion</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/10/01/the-environmental-impacts-of-fast-fasion.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The environmental impacts of fast fashion" /><published>2021-10-01T17:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2021-10-01T17:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/10/01/the-environmental-impacts-of-fast-fasion</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/10/01/the-environmental-impacts-of-fast-fasion.html"><![CDATA[<h2 style="font-family: Ergonomique Bold">The environmental impacts of fast fashion</h2>
<p>Denzel Galang. 10/26/2021</p>
<hr />

<p><img src="/images/blogs/2021/october/fashionOne.jpg" width="70%" style="display: block; margin: 0 auto" /></p>
<center><i>
The mass production of fast fashion, as shown here, can negatively affect the environment with its extreme use of nature’s resources. <a href="https://thinksustainabilityblog.com/2020/04/14/the-unsustainable-growth-of-fast-fashion/" target="_blank">(Think Sustainability)</a>
</i></center>

<p>Our planet is already carrying a heavy burden ever since we started industrializing. Power plants burn fossil fuels, which have greatly contributed to the increase in greenhouse gas emissions along with mass deforestation to clear the way for buildings. Another great example would be the clothing industry, which has also played a role in destructing the environment by producing fast fashion clothing. Fast fashion is a practice used by some clothing retailers in an attempt to capitalize off the latest trends in fashion. They make a profit by mass-producing trendy outfits for a low price, but these clothes are made of low-quality materials such as polyester.</p>

<p>They are deliberately designed to be made of cheap fabrics so that they would wear out easily, making consumers return later on to buy more fast fashion clothes. The clothing’s ability to deteriorate quickly means consumers are throwing them out frequently, resulting in a massive increase in waste production. According to <a href="https://thinksustainabilityblog.com/2020/04/14/the-unsustainable-growth-of-fast-fashion/" target="_blank">Think Sustainably</a>, more than 100 billion garments are produced every year, and around $450 billion worth of textiles are thrown away. This is why fast fashion is such a harmful business to the environment. The excessive amount of resources that are put into producing fast fashion ultimately end up being thrown away, as fashion trends inevitably come and go. This is a quick and convenient way for large companies to make tons of money while simultaneously disregarding any concerns for what they have done to the environment.</p>

<p>Shortcuts in the clothing industry not only create ludicrous amounts of waste but also lead to widespread water pollution due to cheap, toxic, textile dyes used to produce fast fashion clothing. Textile dyeing is the second largest cause of water pollution, with the fashion industry being responsible for approximately 20 percent of industrial water pollution worldwide, according to <a href="https://www.businessinsider.com/fast-fashion-environmental-impact-pollution-emissions-waste-water-2019-10#all-in-all-the-fashion-industry-is-responsible-for-20-of-all-industrial-water-pollution-worldwide-21" target="_blank">Business Insider</a>. This is another problem that could have been easily resolved if clothing retailers were not so greedy and instead spent a little more to make sure that their products were safe for both the consumers and the environment. Unfortunately, profit remains a top priority in these companies.</p>

<p>Fast fashion industries also dump these toxic textile dyes, along with microfibers, into waterways where they make their way into the wild, potentially harming entire ecosystems. Additionally, fashion that involves animal fur puts the well-being of these animals on the line. According to <a href="https://www.theage.com.au/national/victoria/real-fur-from-tortured-dogs-being-sold-as-fake-in-melbourne-s-markets-20191121-p53cw2.html" target="_blank">The Age</a>, markets were caught selling beanies that claimed to be made from rabbits. However, when the beanies were sent for testing, it was discovered that the fur was from raccoons. As if the results were not shocking enough, undercover investigations were conducted that revealed that these raccoons were caged and treated poorly. The raccoons were killed through torturous methods, including skinning them alive, electrocuting them, or repeatedly striking them with a club until death. These practices are unacceptable (they amount to animal abuse) and are being perpetrated by the fast fashion industry. Inhumane treatment and killing of animals to gain some type of profit are downright disgusting. It is very saddening because many consumers do not know that some clothes that they purchase from fast fashion brands could be fur from abused animals. So, some of these brands are essentially scamming people by telling their consumers that they are selling products that have fur from one type of animal, when in reality it is from a completely different one, for the same reason as before: because it is cheaper and requires less effort to raise raccoons instead of rabbits, thus it is another example of a shortcut.</p>

<p>The fast fashion industry further tries to hide its wrongdoings to the environment by claiming to go green. According to <a href="https://goodonyou.eco/what-is-fast-fashion/" target="_blank">good on you</a>, some stores place bins where their customers can drop off unwanted items. Unfortunately, according to <a href="https://www.newsweek.com/2016/09/09/old-clothes-fashion-waste-crisis-494824.html" target="_blank">Newsweek</a>, only 0.1 percent of all clothing collected by charities and take-back programs is recycled into new textile fiber. This shows how brands that produce fast fashion clothing make it seem like they want to do good when, in actuality, they do not care at all. These brands would have had more success converting donated clothes back into recycled textile fiber if they put more effort into it. Unfortunately, recycling clothes to help the environment is not a top priority, but money is.
All in all, fast fashion has played a detrimental role when it comes to the environment, so it is best to avoid clothes that come from fast fashion brands. Clothes made from polyester are good indicators of fast fashion, as polyester is a relatively cheap material. While it may be hard to refrain from buying from fast fashion brands, it is important to note that these companies are destroying the environment. We only have one planet to live on, so it is vital that we take care of it.</p>

<p>Cover Photo: <a href="https://www.ecowatch.com/fast-fashion-riverblue-2318389169.html" target="_blank">(RiverBlue)</a></p>

<hr />

<p><img src="/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg" width="170" style="float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;" /></p>
<div style="margin-bottom: 5%;">
<span style="font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;">Denzel Galang</span>
<br />
</div>]]></content><author><name>Denzel Galang</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Fast fashion, despite being such a big part of the clothing industry, is a lose-lose situation for both the environment and its consumers due to its cheap methods and shortcuts.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/october/fashionCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/october/fashionCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Efficient Studying</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/10/01/efficient-studying.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Efficient Studying" /><published>2021-10-01T17:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2021-10-01T17:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/10/01/efficient-studying</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/10/01/efficient-studying.html"><![CDATA[<h2 style="font-family: Ergonomique Bold">Efficient Studying</h2>
<p>Peter Bui. 10/26/2021</p>
<hr />

<p><img src="/images/blogs/2021/october/studyingOne.png" width="70%" style="display: block; margin: 0 auto" /></p>
<center><i>
<a href="https://chilledcow.com/" target="_blank">(ChilledCow)</a>
</i></center>

<p>Studying for hours for little results, cramming at the last minute the night before a test, or forgetting everything you just studied. These methods are deemed inefficient for obvious reasons, but what exactly is efficient studying? What form of studying helps recall the most information in a timely manner?</p>

<p>First of all, notes. Notes are an effective studying method because they help us learn both in school and out of school. Taking notes in class “<a href="https://www.umassd.edu/dss/resources/students/classroom-strategies/why-take-notes/#:~:text=Note%20taking%20forces%20you%20to,and%20remember%20the%20information%20later." target="_blank">forces you to pay attention and helps you focus in class</a>”. It’s more efficient than solely listening to the teacher, regardless how much you focus. Notes constantly keep you active and learning. There are many different types of notes, each appealing to different people. The first is summarizing (typically in a notebook or on scratch paper). With this method, an individual would write down the key points they hear in a lecture and use it for studying purposes later on. This is efficient because it keeps the person engaged in the class, but excludes minor, “less important” details, which may or may not contribute to the subject overall. Another method can be flashcards. Flashcards are typically helpful for learning definitions, so their use is more restricted/limited  than typical paper notes. They are still efficient, however, because one can study the material and quiz themselves  with ease. Last but not least, Cornell notes. Cornell Notes are infamous for being assigned  by teachers, and they <a href="" target="_blank">serve their purpose incredibly well</a>. This format is structured so that an individual   takes notes by using bullet points to highlight important information, as well as summarization at the end of the notes. Some honorable mentions, though more uncommon, can be The Outline Method, the Mind Mapping Method, and <a href="https://www.lifehack.org/856826/note-taking" target="_blank">more</a>. Notes are meant for studying in a productive manner, so it’s important that the user feels comfortable and the method is helpful for them.</p>

<p>A study habit can be focusing on a specific topic. This study method is based on <a href="https://gradepowerlearning.com/effects-of-multitasking-on-learning/#:~:text=Multitasking%20while%20doing%20homework%20(or,social%20media%20while%20doing%20homework." target="_blank">research</a> and proves that putting all your focus into one subject or assignment can result in more effective studying. When multitasking (checking phones, studying multiple subjects at once, watching a show, etc.), the productivity of the student <a href="https://gradepowerlearning.com/effects-of-multitasking-on-learning/#:~:text=Multitasking%20while%20doing%20homework%20(or,social%20media%20while%20doing%20homework." target="_blank">decreases to no more than 40%</a> than without it. A way to avoid distractions and increase productivity is to remove anything that can serve as a distraction. A phone call from an unknown number, a spam Email, anything that can suddenly shift the attention from what is being done, should be removed or silenced. Another source/study proves that music is good for studying because it improves the mood, keeps the person alert, and increases <a href="https://study.com/academy/popular/is-it-good-to-listen-to-music-while-studying.html#:~:text=Music%20that%20is%20soothing%20and,stress%20or%20anxiety%20while%20studying.&amp;text=During%20long%20study%20sessions%2C%20music,which%20indirectly%20boosts%20memory%20formation." target="_blank">endurance</a>. However, another study shows that listening to music can serve as a <a href="https://themusicuniverse.com/disadvantages-listening-music-while-studying/" target="_blank">distraction</a> by making it more difficult to remember notes and diminishing the brain’s cognitive abilities. The changing words and tunes, as well as the changing songs and volumes can throw a person off their stream of study. A solution to this can be to listen to a type of music that maintains a consistent atmosphere  and has little to no words. Lo-Fi (Low Fidelity) Music, a combination of jazz and other instrumentals, is proven to aid study. It also increases the amount of dopamine and serotonin and improves focus.</p>

<p>Last but not least, studying in groups can be an effective strategy. <a href="https://source.wustl.edu/2006/07/discovering-why-study-groups-are-more-effective/#:~:text=Studying%20in%20groups%20helps%20students,has%20consistently%20demonstrated%20that%20fact.&amp;text=%E2%80%9CA%20large%20number%20of%20college,their%20professor%2C%E2%80%9D%20says%20R." target="_blank">Research</a> shows that studying in groups usually results in  efficient study sessions. When students working together have a question, they can ask a peer in the study group and have access to help and tutoring, if needed. They can get an explanation for a question they have, or for something they don’t understand. It also pushes the students to be more committed and not fall behind the rest of the group.  Discussing topics and communicating amongst each other results in productivity. Notes can be compared and different perspectives can be displayed. Skeptical feelings towards a subject can be changed, and naivety on a subject can turn to full understanding. Test anxiety and stress is reduced, and is a fun learning experience.</p>

<p>Remember, it’s always important to study smarter, not harder. Whatever method works best and is reflected in performance should be a to-do. If cramming helps, that works too. At most times, it’s important to do what’s comfortable to you and helps you do things better, especially studying.</p>

<p>Cover Photo: <a href="https://unsplash.com/" target="_blank">(Unsplash)</a></p>

<hr />

<p><img src="/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg" width="170" style="float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;" /></p>
<div style="margin-bottom: 5%;">
<span style="font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;">Peter Bui</span>
<br />
</div>]]></content><author><name>Peter Bui</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Studying for hours on end for little to no results can be distressing. What studying methods and habits can result in more meaningful study? Research shows that certain methods and habits can be more effective and efficient in studying.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/october/studyingCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/october/studyingCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">What is bubble tea and how is it made?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/10/01/what-is-bubble-tea-and-how-is-it-made.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is bubble tea and how is it made?" /><published>2021-10-01T17:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2021-10-01T17:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/10/01/what-is-bubble-tea-and-how-is-it-made</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/10/01/what-is-bubble-tea-and-how-is-it-made.html"><![CDATA[<h2 style="font-family: Ergonomique Bold">What is bubble tea and how is it made?</h2>
<p>Catherine Todd. 08/28/2021</p>
<hr />

<p><img src="/images/blogs/2021/october/bobaOne.png" width="70%" style="display: block; margin: 0 auto" /></p>
<center><i>
Bubble tea: a delightful mix of refreshing tea and chewy boba <a href="https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.foodunfolded.com/article/what-is-bubble-tea-insider-secrets-on-bubble-tea&amp;sa=D&amp;source=editors&amp;ust=1633235420216000&amp;usg=AOvVaw2ez-2TUdcD4bil2N-iL7-b" target="_blank">(FoodUnfolded)</a>
</i></center>

<p>Bubble tea has quickly become a global phenomenon since its invention in Taichung, Taiwan in the 1980s. A refreshing mix of cool tea and sweet spheres of chewy boba, bubble tea comes in many flavors and forms. Drinks range from the traditional milk tea topped with boba to extravagant fruit-flavored teas or smoothies filled with chunks of pudding, jellies, and popping bubbles.</p>

<p>There are many different flavors of tea, but all tea leaves come from the <a href="https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.sciencelearn.org.nz/resources/1661-the-science-of-tea&amp;sa=D&amp;source=editors&amp;ust=1633235444527000&amp;usg=AOvVaw1iDVQk5AMHQ5Ua1So0NHMP" target="_blank">Camellia sinensis</a> plant. Classic bubble tea uses <a href="https://www.teatulia.com/tea-varieties/what-is-black-tea.htm" target="_blank">black tea</a>, which has a malty taste that is created by rolling and bruising Camellia sinensis assamica leaves. This maximizes the amount of oxidation, a chemical process where oxygen reacts with the natural flavoring compounds in the leaves that the leaves go through. On the other hand, milder teas such as green tea are created by heating and drying Camellia sinensis assamica leaves as soon as they are harvested to prevent oxidation and preserve their fresh taste. Hence, tea-making follows this general concept: smaller leaves and less oxidation result in lighter-flavored teas, while larger leaves and more oxidation create stronger-flavored teas.</p>

<p><a href="https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/make-boba-for-bubble-tea/" target="_blank">Boba</a> is the special ingredient that distinguishes bubble tea from others. The chewy morsels are made from a combination of tapioca flour, water, and brown sugar. The tapioca flour consists solely of starch, and when mixed with hot water, it swells and breaks apart, forming a water-retaining network that forms the solid gel-like texture of boba. This process is called starch gelatinization. Modern chefs have created a new type of boba with molecular gastronomy, called <a href="https://fanaledrinks.com/blogs/blog/18322291-how-is-popping-boba-made" target="_blank">popping boba</a>. This topping is exactly what it sounds like: chewy spheres that pop in your mouth, releasing a small burst of fruit juice. To create this popping effect, a small quantity of powdered sodium alginate is mixed with the fruit juice and then dripped into a bowl that contains a solution of calcium chloride. This forms small bubbles in the liquid that have a layer of thin skin composed primarily of seaweed extract. However, boba and its siblings are not the only <a href="https://www.kungfutea.com/our-toppings" target="_blank">toppings</a> available today - chunks of pudding, jelly, red beans, and cream caps are available as well</p>

<p>To tie it all together, flavoring is needed. The first bubble tea used <a href="https://www.healthline.com/nutrition/brown-sugar-vs-white-sugar" target="_blank">brown sugar</a>, but now white sugar is also used. All sugar comes from the sugarcane plant: Saccharum officinarum. Sugarcane juice is extracted from the stalk of the plant, then purified and heated, forming a brown, concentrated syrup called molasses. Next, the molasses is centrifuged to produce brown sugar crystals, which are then ready for packaging. If white sugar is desired, the brown sugar is further processed to remove all remnants of molasses. Because brown sugar contains more molasses, it is denser, less sweet, and more expensive than white sugar. While homemade bubble teas usually use brown sugar to pertain to tradition, most bubble teas sold in stores use white sugar. As such, though a properly created cup of bubble tea may seem flawless and simple, there is actually a lot of work that goes into making it, i.e. processing the tea, making the boba, and flavoring and customizing it all to each person’s desires.</p>

<p>What began as a Taiwanese street vendor product has now blossomed into one of the most well-known drinks in the world. It has even become a popular staple in America with the help of chain stores such as Kung Fu Tea and Kokee Tea. These modern stores continue to innovate, creating new flavors of tea and types of toppings, all while sticking to the essence of Taiwanese culture that made it all possible. Sample a region’s bubble tea, and you will be able to glimpse the culture of the people living there. One sip of the traditional milk bubble tea will transport you to a Taiwanese night market, teeming with bubble tea vendors and hundreds of other food stands waiting for you to explore them. One sip of a milk cap deluxe bubble tea featuring brown sugar syrup streaks and thick, frothy cream, will drop you into one of Taiwan’s deluxe malls, bustling with energy and class. Whether you favor heartwarming, homemade bubble teas or lavish remixes, you will find yourself taking sip after sip of the wonderful drink called bubble tea.</p>

<p>Cover Photo: <a href="https://www.thespruceeats.com/different-flavors-of-bubble-tea-766444" target="_blank">(The Spruce Eats)</a></p>

<hr />

<p><img src="/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg" width="170" style="float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;" /></p>
<div style="margin-bottom: 5%;">
<span style="font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;">Rachel Huang</span>
<br />
</div>]]></content><author><name>Rachel Huang</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Bubble tea was invented in Taiwan and has become one of the most popular drinks in the world. It consists of a refreshing mix of tea, boba, and toppings including chunks of pudding, jelly, and popping boba. One sip of bubble tea, and you will feel as if you’ve been transported to a Taiwanese night market where dozens of food vendors are waiting for you to explore.]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/october/bobaCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/october/bobaCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How has the pandemic influenced sleep?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/09/03/how-has-the-pandemic-influenced-sleep.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How has the pandemic influenced sleep?" /><published>2021-09-03T17:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-03T17:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/09/03/how-has-the-pandemic-influenced-sleep</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/09/03/how-has-the-pandemic-influenced-sleep.html"><![CDATA[<h2 style="font-family: Ergonomique Bold">How has the pandemic influenced sleep?</h2>
<p>Audrey Lee. 09/04/2021</p>
<hr />

<p><br />
<img src="/images/blogs/2021/september/sleepOne.png" width="50%" style="display: block; margin: 0 auto" /></p>
<center><i>An exhausted woman struggles to fall asleep despite the late hour. <a href="https://www.utoimage.com/?m=goods.photo_view&amp;pm=goods.search&amp;catg=CILL&amp;sf=local&amp;mk=%EB%B6%88%EB%A9%B4%EC%A6%9D&amp;page=1&amp;idx=20924827" target="_blank">(Utoimage)</a>
</i></center>

<p><br />
Over a year ago, the world found itself facing a pandemic that forced several countries into lockdown and chaos. Many might believe that staying at home would have helped people to finally solve the all-too-familiar problem of sleep deprivation. So has it helped the world to catch up on lost sleep? Or did the pandemic make everything worse?</p>

<p><b>Revenge bedtime procrastination</b>
<br />Back in 2014, <a href="https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpsyg.2014.00611/full" target="_blank">a study from the Netherlands</a> revealed how procrastination can be found in sleeping and was not limited to the academic sector. Coining it bedtime procrastination (later renamed <a href="https://www.bbc.com/worklife/article/20201123-the-psychology-behind-revenge-bedtime-procrastination" target="_blank">revenge bedtime procrastination</a> in 2018), the collaborators of the study defined it as the tendency to push back on sleep for no reasonable explanation. Procrastination is an <a href="https://www.nationalgeographic.com/science/article/are-you-procrastinating-more-blame-the-pandemic" target="_blank">emotional coping strategy</a> that is used when faced with high levels of stress. Thus, the heightened levels of stress brought by the pandemic have made it more difficult for people to resist the urge of staying up at night. Despite being aware of its consequences, the desire for a temporary escape from the never-ending demands during the daytime makes people fall into an unhealthy cycle that evidently takes a toll on <a href="https://news.gallup.com/poll/327311/americans-mental-health-ratings-sink-new-low.aspx" target="_blank">mental health</a>. Adults worldwide have expressed dissatisfaction with how long they sleep and more than half of the Americans surveyed by the <a href="https://j2vjt3dnbra3ps7ll1clb4q2-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/sleep-prioritization-survey-2021-covid-somnia.pdf" target="_blank">American Academy of Sleep Medicine (AASM)</a> have reported new sleep problems post-pandemic. But the problem is yet to be solved.</p>

<p><b>Coronasomnia</b>
<br />On top of throwing the world into a <a href="https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34006330/#:~:text=Most%20patients%20with%20COVID%2D19,septic%20shock%2C%20and%20cardiovascular%20manifestations." target="_blank">health crisis</a>, insomnia became an even larger problem. It was already the <a href="https://openstax.org/books/psychology-2e/pages/4-4-sleep-problems-and-disorders" target="_blank">most common sleeping disorder</a> before the pandemic but has increased so much so that a new term called “Coronasomnia” is being used. Coronasomnia, a portmanteau (i.e., blend) of the words “coronavirus” and “insomnia”, has been used to describe the recently surging cases of insomnia as a result of the pandemic. In short, those with insomnia struggle to fall asleep and stay asleep even if they manage to. <a href="https://www.verywellmind.com/what-is-revenge-bedtime-procrastination-5189591" target="_blank">Stress, anxiety, and depression</a> are all common side effects of sleep deprivation, and in turn, can lead to both insomnia and revenge bedtime procrastination. But if staying at home means easy access to beds, why has this reduced levels of sleep as opposed to increasing them?</p>

<p><b>Boundaries between work, school and home</b>
<br />Forcing adults and students to stay home has <a href="https://www.medicalnewstoday.com/articles/revenge-bedtime-procrastination-a-plight-of-our-times#What-is-it,-and-why-does-it-happen?" target="_blank">“blurred the line”</a> between academic or work life and personal life. Though it may seem unimportant at first glance, keeping a distinct separation between the two is an important factor toward reducing work or school-related stress and maintaining mental health. When they become so closely intertwined to the point that it is hard to tell where one starts and the other ends, it makes it increasingly difficult to <a href="https://www.charityjob.co.uk/careeradvice/keep-work-and-home-life-separate/" target="_blank">“switch off”</a> from one and focus on the other, which can thus influence productivity. It also leads to an increased risk of <a href="https://www.healthassured.org/blog/risk-burnout-everyone-needs-break-work/" target="_blank">burning out</a> if overworked.</p>

<p><b>Escalated technology use</b>
<br />Aside from meetings and classes being replaced with virtual alternatives, people have become increasingly reliant on technology to communicate with friends or take a break from the turmoil. Since many areas have been on lockdown for over a year and counting, the restrictions make it difficult for people to meet up in person. And although people have already been reliant on devices before the virus, people cannot help but use more of them now since there aren’t many options open.</p>

<p>Social media and streaming services are more accessible than ever before and everything is only a click away. So when exhausted and stressed individuals have had a long day, it is far more likely for them to whip out their phone or turn on their TV than take a jog outside. Students who used to meet their friends outside have now turned to social media or other chatting platforms to make up for the loss of social interaction. And having a smartphone readily available just before bed makes people even more susceptible to revenge bedtime procrastination and coronasomnia. According to <a href="https://openstax.org/books/psychology-2e/pages/4-1-what-is-consciousness" target="_blank">OpenStax</a>, melatonin, a hormone that helps to regulate sleep, is “stimulated by darkness and inhibited by light”. So staying up late at night staring at a bright computer screen will signal the brain to stop producing melatonin and is counterproductive toward a better night’s sleep. The pandemic seems to be far from drawing to a close, so how can people improve their sleeping habits?</p>

<p><b>Adjustments to improve sleep</b>
<br />Due to the sudden changes in lifestyle, it is only natural that individuals’ circadian rhythms have been thrown out of balance. One way to slowly return to a normalized sleep schedule is to keep screens off in the bedroom. As mentioned above, stopping the production of melatonin will only keep the brain more alert. Instead, read a book or engage in an alternative activity that does not require a device. Avoid taking naps longer than 20 to 30 minutes to allow adenosine (a chemical that promotes sleep at night) to <a href="https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-couch/202101/7-ways-get-sleep-stay-asleep-and-get-back-sleep" target="_blank">build up</a> throughout the day. And although it may be tempting to do everything in bed, marking it as the “sleeping place” can help the <a href="https://health.ucdavis.edu/health-news/newsroom/covid-19-is-wrecking-our-sleep-with-coronasomnia--tips-to-fight-back-/2020/09" target="_blank">brain associate it with only sleep</a> and not productivity. In addition to maintaining a regular daily sleeping and working schedule, <a href="https://www.healthline.com/health-news/coronasomnia-how-the-pandemic-may-be-affecting-your-sleep#How-to-get-the-rest-you-need" target="_blank">setting aside</a> an hour or two specifically for relaxation can help to prevent revenge bedtime procrastination and thus improve sleep cycles. And finally, keep in mind that an individual suspecting they may be suffering from insomnia or any other health issue should always consult or reach out to a medical professional instead of self-diagnosing. Even if it turns out to be nothing, it is always better to be safe instead of risking further consequences in the future.</p>

<p>Cover Photo: <a href="https://www.everydayhealth.com/sleep/how-put-racing-mind-bed-sleep-now/" target="_blank">(Everyday Health)</a></p>

<hr />

<p><img src="/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg" width="170" style="float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;" /></p>
<div style="margin-bottom: 5%;">
<span style="font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;">Audrey Lee</span>
<br />
</div>]]></content><author><name>Audrey Lee</name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[It’s no news to anyone that a large portion of the population is sleep-deprived. So how did this change when the pandemic forced the world into a global lockdown? Has staying at home helped the world finally catch up on lost sleep?]]></summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/september/sleepCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/september/sleepCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>