<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-05-09T17:24:45-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">InterSTEM</title><entry><title type="html">The potential of brain-computer interfaces</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/08/the-potential-of-brain-computer-interfaces.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The potential of brain-computer interfaces" /><published>2021-05-08T17:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-08T17:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/05/08/the-potential-of-brain-computer-interfaces</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/08/the-potential-of-brain-computer-interfaces.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The potential of brain-computer interfaces&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rachel Ding. 05/09/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/may/computerOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Bill Kochevar becomes the first person with quadriplegia to receive a neural implant.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2017/03/28/521665654/paralyzed-man-uses-thoughts-to-control-his-own-arm-and-hand&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(NPR)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Bill Kochevar never thought he would be able to feed himself again. After a tragic biking incident, Kochevar was paralyzed from his neck down. For many years, he couldn’t even scratch an itch himself: he depended totally on caregivers. But in 2017, researchers at &lt;a href=&quot;https://engineering.case.edu/groups/BrainGate2/node/11&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Case Western University&lt;/a&gt; developed an electromechanical system that mimicked Kochevar’s spinal cord. At the end of the study, he was able to grab a mug of water, drink through a straw and scratch his nose with a sponge. Through two arrays of sensors in his brain and electrodes in his right arm, Kochevar saw the impossible happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kochevar is one of only 24 people around the world who have received sensors implanted into their brain to aid with paralysis. But given that up to 500,000 people suffer from spinal cord injuries each year according to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/spinal-cord-injury&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;World Health Organization&lt;/a&gt; (WHO), and even more suffer from neurological diseases and mental illnesses, brain-computer interfaces (BCIs) bear incredible healing potential. They may even make our daily lives far more convenient, both for the patients and those who interact with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many varieties of BCIs, from the electrode system that helped Kochevar regain function in his arm to circuits that help the user control technology with their brain, all the way to AI-equipped super brains currently under development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A research paper conducted by &lt;a href=&quot;https://med.stanford.edu/news/all-news/2017/02/brain-computer-interface-allows-fast-accurate-typing-by-people-with-paralysis.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Stanford University&lt;/a&gt; showed the progress of neural interfaces that are able to allow people to type on a screen using brain signals. In the study, three participants with limb weakness were able to type at a rate of eight words per minute through one to two arrays of electrodes that were inserted into their brains. The electrodes were able to receive signals from the participants’ motor cortex and transmitted them to a nearby computer. The computer then translated the data into point-and-click commands, enabling the participants to move the cursor to click on keys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another study by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/news/pioneering-brain-implant-restores-paralysed-man-s-sense-of-touch-1.20804&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Pittsburgh University&lt;/a&gt; aimed to give Nathan Copeland’s sense of touch back in his arm. Copeland was 18 years old when he was in a car accident that rendered him paralyzed and unable to feel his lower half. Copeland had two electrode arrays implanted into his somatosensory cortex (which embeds sensation) and two other electrodes positioned in the motor cortex (which controls hand and arm movement). They linked a robotic arm to the neural interface and programmed it such that Copeland could feel anything that touched the robotic arm on his own arm. The research team electrically stimulated these regions, and as a result, Copeland was able to feel the sensations, including which fingers were being touched and the regions of those fingers. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/08/28/opinion/sunday/brain-machine-artificial-intelligence.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mr. Copeland&lt;/a&gt; described them as “weird,” “electrical tingly” but also “amazing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Broadly speaking, BCIs use brain signals to enhance the brain’s functions. How does this technology work? The human brain has over 86 billion neurons. Neurons have three main parts: the dendrite, the soma and the axon. The dendrite receives signals, the somas are the processing units and axons send out the information. When the total input arriving in the soma exceeds a certain threshold, the axon generates a short electrical pulse. Neural interfaces work through a series of electrodes that gather data from these pulses. A chip on the scalp analyzes the data and can even communicate with other technologies using Bluetooth and artificial intelligence, software that allows machines to mimic human functions. AI is now able to detect the important signals and analyze them, then execute different motions accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a BCI, people can control home appliances, activate car brakes and type and control cursors just by thinking. BCIs can also deliver targeted electromagnetic pulses to improve memory, attention and consciousness for cognitively impaired patients and alleviate symptoms for chronic pain, substance abuse and depression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this all may seem like something out of a science fiction novel, BCIs are arriving at the forefront of society sooner than you think. Once this technology is popularized, it may be accessible not just to patients with spinal cord injuries, but to everyone. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://venturebeat.com/2019/11/20/ctrl-labs-ceo-well-have-neural-interfaces-in-less-than-5-years/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;VentureBeat&lt;/a&gt;, CTRL-labs CEO Thomas Reardon believes neural interfaces will be commercially available in the mid-2020s. Back in 2017, &lt;a href=&quot;https://med.stanford.edu/news/all-news/2017/02/brain-computer-interface-allows-fast-accurate-typing-by-people-with-paralysis.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dr. Krishna Shenoy&lt;/a&gt;, a professor of electrical engineering at Stanford, predicted that “the day will come — closer to five than 10 years from now… when a self-calibrating, fully implanted wireless [BCI] can be used without caregiver assistance, has no cosmetic impact and can be used around the clock.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In just a few short years, it could be perfectly normal to drive without touching a steering wheel, receive the weather forecast in your head and direct your thermostat to warm up or cool down while you’re nowhere near it. BCIs still can’t read brain signals with perfect accuracy, but they are rapidly improving. The better they become, the more they will continue making the impossible, possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://theconversation.com/deep-brain-stimulation-a-fix-when-the-drugs-dont-work-14097&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1620609408459000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw1bj__Oif5fF3qEq3W9J0qB&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Theconversation)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Rachel Ding&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Rachel Ding</name></author><summary type="html">The potential of brain-computer interfaces Rachel Ding. 05/09/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/may/computerCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/may/computerCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Artificial intelligence morals and ethics: Could the capabilities of machine learning be its demise?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/08/artificial-intelligence-morals-and-ethics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Artificial intelligence morals and ethics: Could the capabilities of machine learning be its demise?" /><published>2021-05-08T17:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-08T17:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/05/08/artificial-intelligence-morals-and-ethics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/08/artificial-intelligence-morals-and-ethics.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Artificial intelligence morals and ethics: Could the capabilities of machine learning be its demise?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aryav Nagar. 05/09/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/may/aiOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The image above depicts the painting Edmond de Belamy. (Christies)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Some computer systems are even capable of developing abstract forms of creativity similar to individual thought in the form of meaningful literature and paintings. An example of computer-minded artwork is “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edmond_de_Belamy&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1620609012096000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw2HLL-SXOXuUBHDT85hEuf8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Edmond de Belamy&lt;/a&gt;”, a fully AI-generated “painting.” Through deep learning, AI is able to imitate a creative mind based on previous human work, as seen in the paint strokes and the prominent human figure wearing a suit and collared shirt.  Apart from the visual aspect of art, AI is well capable of creating forms of analytical literature. An open-source artificial intelligence, GPT-2, has created multiple excerpts of poetry and fictional writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example-
And, ere the cloud of the tempest blew,
His soul was with the world at play.
He looked to the stars, and the stars smiled,
And the moon in the heaven looked;
And, as he looked, he beheld her light,
And all the heaven smiled with him.
When winds and tempests fly,
When floods and fires fail,
As their wake doth meadow and fen,
Tis the man-child’s heart that craves.
And I — I shall be bound,
With the hoary-headed, strong, old,
To earth, and the graves of the dead,
Whose feet are mowed down, as they lie;
And I shall rest my weary head,
In the silence of Eternity,
In the peaceful arms of God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outstandingly, GPT-2 not only generated a meaningful poem with the possibility of thoughtful creative analysis, but it has also expressed human emotion, religion and curiosity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The moral argument against AI&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI has constantly proven itself to imitate and exceed human behavior, but this raises concerns within the public opinion: Will AI take away jobs? What will happen to targeted workers? Can AI take over the world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reality, these are valid arguments. As this technology advances further in complexity, it can very well branch out and perform tasks related to other fields of work. This seems highly plausible in the coming years as AI has been appealing to most companies since machine learning and neural networking is proven to be much more accurate and sustainable than manual labor. Some are already adopting this fully automated system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Yangshan Deep-Water Port is the biggest fully automated container port in Shanghai. “It’s all controlled by artificial intelligence,” Yang Jiemin, who is in charge of technological support, said to &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.cgtn.com/news/3d637a4e31677a4d/share_p.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CGTN&lt;/a&gt;, as he describes the 24/7 fully automated workforce. If this trend of adopting AI-powered machines grows, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.usnews.com/news/economy/articles/2019-06-26/report-robots-will-replace-20-million-manufacturing-jobs-by-2030&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1620609000911000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw34zLkFfkEoxLL170XjX7ii&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;by 2030, over 20 million jobs could be replaced by machine learning robots&lt;/a&gt;. The fact of the matter is, the complexity and sheer capabilities of machine learning could result in public opinion that sides against the growth of artificial intelligence. The reason being? Robots can replace manual workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from the possibility of AI taking over the workforce, many believe it is on its path to take over the world. Although it may seem that AI could develop into an evil army of robotic human beings, most probably due to sci-fi films, AI computing is unable to understand the world through a moral aspect. Partaking in a war against humanity is far beyond machine learning’s algorithmic capabilities. And while it may seem as if AI has this abstract understanding through its literary and visual art forms, it is unable to fully comprehend what exactly it is generating. After all, a computer system, even as advanced as complex deep learning systems, is unconscious. Algorithms dictate AI capabilities, and a basic understanding of morality is a concept that cannot be written out in an algorithmic form. Translating emotion into binary values for the computer to understand does not seem plausible to achieve anytime soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Should AI continue to develop?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consequences of AI are definitely apparent, but the possibilities this field could create are not something our technologically dependent society should overlook. AlphaGo is a Google DeepMind computer program specified to perform tasks in the abstract strategy board game, Go. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smithsonianmag.com/smart-news/latest-ai-teaches-itself-play-games-no-human-help-180965322/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;AlphaGo trained for only a staggering 40 days&lt;/a&gt;. After this short training period, it was able to defeat 18-time world champion Lee Se-dol. To put this into perspective, Go is speculated to be a 2,500-year-old board game that originated in China. AlphaGo was self-trained during the 40 days by repeatedly playing over 40 million games against itself. Within this time period, AlphaGo was able to learn and test strategies that have been developing for the past 25 centuries at the highest possible level. If this deep mind software was able to defeat some of the greatest Go minds in history through new strategies and quick decision making, similar deep learning programs could be implemented to assist human practice throughout a multitude of fields of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In modern-day technology, this is how AI is currently being used. Some of the most common forms of computer intelligence are actually present in everyday tasks, such as virtual assistants on your mobile phone or self-driving cars seen around roads. All these are used to assist human tasks and speed up daily processes. They are not replacing human appearance. If we are able to use AI as a tool to refine human lives, the fear of robots replacing human work would become non-existent and technological advancements would become much more rapid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Vox)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Aryav Nagar&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Aryav Nagar</name></author><summary type="html">Artificial intelligence morals and ethics: Could the capabilities of machine learning be its demise? Aryav Nagar. 05/09/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/may/aiCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/may/aiCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The latest innovations of Apple, Huawei and Samsung</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/29/the-latest-inventions-of-apple-huawei-and-samsung.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The latest innovations of Apple, Huawei and Samsung" /><published>2021-04-29T17:00:03-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-29T17:00:03-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/29/the-latest-inventions-of-apple-huawei-and-samsung</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/29/the-latest-inventions-of-apple-huawei-and-samsung.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The latest innovations of Apple, Huawei and Samsung&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rachel Huang. 04/30/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/innovationOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
Apple’s iPhones are currently competing with mobile phones from other countries, such as Huawei from China and Samsung from South Korea.&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=aeQnQ-vjtuY&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(YouTube)&lt;/a&gt;

&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Apple&lt;/a&gt; is the top mobile phone brand in the United States, with approximately 65% of the national market share. However, this statistic is not necessarily representative of the global market, as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasdaq.com/articles/top-five-smartphone-companies-in-the-world-2020-09-03&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;records&lt;/a&gt; from 2020 show that Apple ranked third in the global smartphone market with 13% of the market share. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.samsung.com/us/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Samsung&lt;/a&gt;, placing second, claimed 19%, while the leading company, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.huawei.com/us/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Huawei&lt;/a&gt;, held 20%. These rankings still stand in 2021, and as Apple, Huawei and Samsung continue to compete for consumers, the spotlight falls on a product that they all have in common: the smartphone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arguably the most iconic smartphone brand in the world, Apple released its newest iPhone, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/iphone-12-pro/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;iPhone 12 Pro Max&lt;/a&gt;, on Nov. 13, 2020. The iPhone 12 Pro is powered by Apple’s newest chip, the A14 Bionic, which is the first 5-nanometer chip in the microchip industry featuring a grand total of 11.8 billion transistors. The camera sensors (named the Pro camera system) are also 47% larger than the ones of the previous iPhone. In addition to its larger size, the featured cameras include a new 65 mm telephoto lens and 5X optical zoom range that uses Deep Fusion and Neural Engine to analyze multiple exposures pixel by pixel to bring out unprecedented detail in the photos it takes. Artificial intelligence and machine learning are also used - machine learning helps separate the subject from the background in photos.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/innovationTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
A snapshot of Apple’s new and improved Pro camera system.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apple.com/newsroom/2020/10/apple-introduces-iphone-12-pro-and-iphone-12-pro-max-with-5g/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Apple)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The 12 Pro utilizes a LiDAR Scanner that is basically portable Augmented Reality. The LiDAR Scanner is able to measure how long it takes light to reflect back from objects, creating a depth map of any space the user is in and transforming a room into any realistic scene of the user’s choice in a matter of seconds. These features, and more, are displayed across 3.4 million pixels, the most ever in an iPhone. To complete Apple’s signature bold and simple look, the iPhone 12 Pro comes in four crisp colors: Pacific Blue, Gold, Silver and Graphite.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;China has been rapidly reinventing its global image over the last decade, doubling its number of software companies with a recent count of over 37,800 active Chinese software companies as of year-end 2018, with at least a dozen of these companies reaching valuations of greater than $1 billion. One of these companies, Huawei, is best known for its rapid progress in mobile development and 5G networks, putting it in first place in the global phone manufacturing market as of Q2 2020. Huawei’s newest mobile phone, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://consumer.huawei.com/en/phones/mate-x2/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;HUAWEI Mate X2&lt;/a&gt;, was released on Feb. 25, 2021, and features the signature Huawei ability to seamlessly fold in half, offering users the option of using it as a “folded, 6.45-inch flagship smartphone, or unfolded as an 8-inch FullView Display.” To better enable this folding option, the Mate X2 utilizes a new and improved multi-dimensional hinge that is made using innovative materials and forging techniques, making the hinge discreetly concealed and giving the Mate X2 a virtually invisible seam.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/innovationThree.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
Huawei’s Mate X2 offers a new and improved multi-dimensional hinge to create a flawless seam.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://consumer.huawei.com/en/phones/mate-x2/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Huawei)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The ability to fold in half offers new uses for smartphone screens; unfolded, the 8-inch screen’s Smart Multi-Window feature allows users to split their screen into four windows at the same time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Huawei’s 5 nanometer Kirin 9000 5G SoC chip is used to power the Mate X2. This chip is packed with over 15 billion transistors and an NPU (Neural Processing Unit) that pushes AI processing to a new level. The Huawei Mate X2 also uses 5G networks, in addition to Huawei’s 5G super Uplink that allows users to upload, send, and share anything at optimal speed and quality. As for cameras, each Huawei Mate X2 features a 16 MP Ultra Wide Camera lens that takes pixel-perfect photos bursting with sharpness and dynamic range. This lens is coupled with a 2.5 cm Macro Lens that can take pictures from as little as 2.5 cm away. To tie it all together, the Huawei Mate X2 boasts an “Edge of Gravity” feature where the phone’s folded shape is slightly wedged, with the thinnest part having a width of only 4.4 millimeters wide. This design not only looks slim and feels light, but keeps the center of gravity closer to where you hold it, giving you an easier grip. The Huawei Mate X2 can be found in a new color palette featuring refreshing Crystal Blue, dreamy Crystal Pink, classic Black and classic White.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Located in Seoul, South Korea, Samsung is one of the top mobile phone manufacturing companies in the world. Its newest release on Jan. 29, 2021, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.samsung.com/us/smartphones/galaxy-s21-5g/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Samsung Galaxy S21 5G&lt;/a&gt;, features an industry-leading 5G chipset that boasts 8GB of RAM (Random Access Memory) and 256 GB of built-in memory. In addition, the 5-nm processor is the fastest processor that Samsung Galaxy has released so far, supporting the phone’s powerful features, such as the four cameras located on its exterior. The strongest camera of these four is a 64 MP camera; this 64-megapixel camera takes photos with a corresponding 64MP resolution, which means that 64 million pixels can be found in every single photo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/innovationFour.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
The Galaxy S21 5G features two 12MP cameras and a 64 MP camera on its outward-facing exterior.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.samsung.com/us/smartphones/galaxy-s21-5g/ &quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Samsung)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In addition to its high resolution, the Galaxy S21 5G can also zoom in up to 30x on a subject with Space Zoom, enabling users to capture distant details with stunning clarity while Zoom Lock helps keep the subject centered. The Galaxy S21 5G’s cameras are enhanced by artificial intelligence that allows photos to be analyzed for the best lighting, angles, and color possible. There is even a special AI assistant for content creators; the Single Take (AI). Single Take selects the best from a collection of photos that the user has taken, and automatically edits them for the user. As for video, the Galaxy S21 5G flaunts the highest resolution video in a smartphone, 8K, with a variety of abilities. One of these, the 8K Video Snap, lets users “snip” an album of photos that are up to 33 MP in resolution, straight out of every 8K video. Samsung captures this ground-breaking ability with the catchy quote: “record now, snap later.” To complete this high-quality, high-function, mobile device, the Samsung Galaxy S21 5G is protected by Corning Gorilla Glass Victus, the toughest glass available on a Samsung smartphone. The Galaxy S21 5G can be found as part of a Phantom color series: Phantom violet, Phantom silver and Phantom black, sure to wow consumers and solidify Samsung’s position in the smartphone market worldwide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each of these three companies, Apple, Huawei and Samsung, are innovative in their own way, whether it be specificities in hardware, application of AI, or overall presentation. However, they all share more similarities in their smartphones than the average consumer may think. For example, all three of these brand’s flagship smartphones, the iPhone 12 Pro Max, the Huawei Mate X2 and the Samsung Galaxy S21 Max, all utilize 5-nanometer processor chips, 5G networks, and artificial intelligence and machine learning. This stands as a significant piece of evidence that although different countries around the world are rapidly developing and becoming more technology-oriented and competitive, the whole world actually shares more in common than presumed differences.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Rachel Huang&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Rachel Huang</name></author><summary type="html">The latest innovations of Apple, Huawei and Samsung Rachel Huang. 04/30/2021 Apple’s iPhones are currently competing with mobile phones from other countries, such as Huawei from China and Samsung from South Korea.(YouTube)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/innovationCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/innovationCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The bee loss epidemic in the shadows</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/29/the-bee-loss-epidemic-in-the-shadows.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The bee loss epidemic in the shadows" /><published>2021-04-29T17:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-29T17:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/29/the-bee-loss-epidemic-in-the-shadows</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/29/the-bee-loss-epidemic-in-the-shadows.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The bee loss epidemic in the shadows&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emily Richter. 04/30/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/beeOne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Native bees like this one are at risk, but honey bees continue to steal the spotlight when it comes to bee conservation. (Credit: Emily Richter)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Honey bees have become the subjects of worldwide attention. A simple google search for “save the bees” yields a tidal wave of honey bee-oriented websites. Many websites sell shirts, jewelry and posters encouraging honey bee-focused conservation. Other websites host webinars and programs aimed at teaching people about honey bees, bee keeping and bee gardens. While honeybees play important roles in keeping ecosystems in balance, they are an introduced species everywhere but in Europe. In those places, native bees have been successfully playing the role of chief pollinator for millions of years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Honey bee numbers have certainly been declining. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nrdc.org/save-bees&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Natural Resources Defense Council&lt;/a&gt; reports that, in the United States, honey bee populations declined 40% between 2017 and 2018. While these statistics are alarming, honey bees are in no real danger of extinction. Farmers and beekeepers worldwide are dedicated to managing and maintaining the population of honey bees. Native bees do not have this luxury. As a result, many species are in danger of extinction; &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.discovermagazine.com/environment/while-we-worry-about-honeybees-other-pollinators-are-disappearing&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Discover Magazine&lt;/a&gt; notes that some native bees have lost “as much as 96% of their population” in recent years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to Discover Magazine, when native bees and honey bees find themselves in the same garden, the results lead to drastic declines. Honey bees typically prefer pollinating the types of plants found in household gardens or yards. When humans move into an area, the resulting landscape benefits honey bees. The introduced species outcompetes native bee species, resulting in a dangerous drop in native bee populations. These population declines can have adverse effects on the native producers of an area, putting the health of ecosystems in danger.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thousands of species of native bees can be found in North America alone, and nearly a quarter of a million species can be found in the world. &lt;a href=&quot;https://blog.nature.org/science/2019/08/19/focus-on-native-bees-not-honey-bees/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Nature Conservatory&lt;/a&gt; reports that the diversity of native bee species results in pollination support for an “incredible diversity of flowering plants”. On the other hand, honey bees only pollinate between 25% and 40% of flower species. The diversity of ecosystems can be threatened by this selective pollination. Maintaining the diversity seen in nature depends upon the well-being of native bees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Native bees also pollinate flowers more efficiently than honey bees. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.cornell.edu/stories/2011/10/native-bees-are-better-pollinators-honeybees&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2011 Cornell University study&lt;/a&gt; revealed that native bees pollinate flowers two or three times better than honey bees. The Cornell University team says this is because “native bees are mostly pollen collectors”, while honey bees mostly focus on drinking the nectar of flowers. As a result, native bees take a higher amount of pollen from flowers and deposit a higher amount on the next flower they visit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;If native bees are the superior pollinators, why do honey bees get so much attention? While native bees are a part of nature, honey bees participate in commercial agriculture. Humans place a higher monetary value on honey bees because of their ability to be cultivated and manipulated. For example, the California almond crop depends entirely on staggering numbers of honey bees, transported by beekeepers from all over North America. Without these honey bees, there would be a severe shortage of almonds and almond products. The Natural Resources Defense Council estimates that 15 billion dollars of crops would be lost if honey bees suddenly disappeared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these estimates could be very wrong. A spokesperson for the groundbreaking 2011 Cornell University study argues that “the role of native bees in crop pollination has been largely unappreciated”. He says that, if honey bee populations decline, native bee populations may be able to pick up the agricultural slack. Since native bees are more effective pollinators than honey bees, this could potentially be advantageous to the agricultural industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The best way to ensure that the future has healthy ecosystems and an abundant variety of agriculture is to focus on conserving native bees. Unfortunately, the public does not recognize the decline of native bees as a pressing issue. A 2019 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nrpa.org/About-National-Recreation-and-Park-Association/press-room/new-survey-shows-americans-agree-communities-should-support-pollinators-respondents-are-unsure-how-they-can-help/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Parks and Recreation Society survey&lt;/a&gt; revealed that 95% of people in the United States believe that honey bee protection is an issue of high concern. If honey bees continue to bask in the conservation spotlight, hundreds of native bee species will likely go extinct.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 2016, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pbs.org/newshour/nation/bees-endangered-list&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PBS&lt;/a&gt; announced to the public that, for the first time, seven different native bee species had been added to the endangered species list. This caused the seven species, all native Hawaiian yellow-faced wasp-like bees, to receive federal protection. Since then, more bee species have been added to the list as well, allowing them a fighting chance for survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another positive sign for native bee populations is the skyrocketing popularity of native plant gardens. In the last decade, many homeowners and gardeners have taken part in the trend, which adds some native flair to urban areas. Native plant gardens provide native bees with their favorite host plants. Since honey bee populations often decimate native bee populations due to the availability of gardens, native plant gardens help to level the playing field between native bees and honey bees.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The native bee crisis gets very little attention, but if extinction begins to spread across native bee populations, it could quickly cause an environmental crisis, and possibly an agricultural crisis. Protecting bees does not only ensure that future generations have over twenty thousand native bee species to marvel at; it also ensures humanity’s continued survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: Emily Richter&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Emily Richter&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Emily Richter</name></author><summary type="html">The bee loss epidemic in the shadows Emily Richter. 04/30/2021 Native bees like this one are at risk, but honey bees continue to steal the spotlight when it comes to bee conservation. (Credit: Emily Richter) Honey bees have become the subjects of worldwide attention. A simple google search for “save the bees” yields a tidal wave of honey bee-oriented websites. Many websites sell shirts, jewelry and posters encouraging honey bee-focused conservation. Other websites host webinars and programs aimed at teaching people about honey bees, bee keeping and bee gardens. While honeybees play important roles in keeping ecosystems in balance, they are an introduced species everywhere but in Europe. In those places, native bees have been successfully playing the role of chief pollinator for millions of years.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/beeCover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/beeCover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Sci-Fi reverse human aging is now a reality</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/29/sci-fi-reverse-human-aging-is-now-a-reality.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sci-Fi reverse human aging is now a reality" /><published>2021-04-29T17:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-29T17:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/29/sci-fi-reverse-human-aging-is-now-a-reality</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/29/sci-fi-reverse-human-aging-is-now-a-reality.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Sci-Fi reverse human aging is now a reality&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;André Lombardi. 04/30/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A common, loose-ended icebreaker question: What is your greatest fear in life? Some might mention earthquakes, spiders or heights. But for me, I’d say death. However, with a recent discovery on reverse human aging, scientists are getting even closer to elongating the lives of humans and making that ultimate fearless prominent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In Ancient Egypt, the average lifetime was about 19 years due to the immense risks that children faced. Even for those who survived childhood, life expectancies, at most, were 30 years for women and 34 years for men. Fast-forward to 1920, and the life expectancy reached 53.6 years for men and 54.6 years for women. Yet, in just a century, it has soared to an average of 78.9 years in the United States. This increase in life expectancy in the past has been attributed to substantial scientific understanding in which public health measures have been adopted by the vast majority of populations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally, as the human body ages, the protective tips of chromosomes known as telomeres begin shrinking, and along with it, the body produces an increase of malfunctioning senescent cells. Senescent cells are, in short, vital in their role of tumor suppression and wound healing. Thus, an expanded malfunctioning of senescent cells can contribute to age-related diseases. In order to increase life expectancy beyond its limits and essentially rewind the process of human aging, researchers and scientists have been targeting these two integral components of the aging process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedaily.com/releases/2020/11/201120150728.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A clinical trial&lt;/a&gt;, involving 34 adults over the ages of 65, put a method known as hyperbaric oxygen therapy to the test, to determine if aging could in fact be reversed. The trial placed subjects in a pressurized chamber where they were supplied with pure oxygen for 90 minutes a day, five days a week over the course of three months. Data concludes that telomeres increased by about 20% average in length, and that useless cells were reduced by up to 37%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“Today telomere shortening is considered the ‘Holy Grail’ of the biology of aging,” Professor Efrati of Tel Aviv University, who led the clinical trial, said. “Our HBOT protocol was able to achieve this, proving that the aging process can in fact be reversed at the basic cellular-molecular level.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In other words, this trial and its results are providing a path forward for the future of research and are emulating how scientists can continue delving into unknown realms of science. Hyperbaric oxygen therapy (HBOT) can also be used for various other applications, such as treating carbon monoxide poisoning and infections or wounds where tissue is depleted or starved for oxygen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There have been other attempts recently, some of which have been proven successful; others unsuccessful. In 2015, an unverified biotech company claimed that permanent changes could be made to one’s DNA that could combat muscle loss and other age-related conditions. In fact, attempts to alter life expectancy go as far back as hunter-gatherers, or approximately 30,000 years ago, with efforts to keep a tribe healthy and stable enough to survive in the long term. These days, there are significantly more technologically advanced ways we must look to increase life expectancy, such as what this trial has investigated. However, there are also numerous non-technological methods that we as a species can adapt further to increase life expectancy. Consuming a more plant-based diet, limiting exposure to cigarettes and second-hand smoking and simply getting health screenings and exams on a regular basis can all add years to the average life expectancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As technologically interconnected and advanced, wealthy nations continue to pave the way in new technological methods, we should simultaneously exponentially increase our efforts in third world countries. Not only should we expand technological research in third world societies, such as has already been done in countries like Rwanda and Kazakhstan, but we should improve access to health screenings in these countries. Thousands of organizations, companies and initiatives have already jumpstarted the future of healthcare in these countries, but every citizen can further contribute to humanity’s attempts to increase life expectancy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, none of these studies, such as the one conducted by Tel Aviv University, can fully verify the impacts of this treatment due to the small sample size. However, time will tell, literally, how this trial will age and how humans in the future may adopt both sci-fi-like reverse aging and simple yet effective public health measures in the near future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Healogics)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Andre Lombardi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Andre Lombardi</name></author><summary type="html">Sci-Fi reverse human aging is now a reality André Lombardi. 04/30/2021 A common, loose-ended icebreaker question: What is your greatest fear in life? Some might mention earthquakes, spiders or heights. But for me, I’d say death. However, with a recent discovery on reverse human aging, scientists are getting even closer to elongating the lives of humans and making that ultimate fearless prominent.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/humanAgingCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/humanAgingCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Handwriting vs. typing notes, and does font color matter?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/22/the-science-behind-note-taking.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Handwriting vs. typing notes, and does font color matter?" /><published>2021-04-22T17:00:03-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-22T17:00:03-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/22/the-science-behind-note-taking</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/22/the-science-behind-note-taking.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Handwriting vs. typing notes, and does font color matter?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nadwa Atwi. 04/23/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Taking notes is one of the most important parts of the learning process. Students often spend a lot of time considering how to take notes, only to end up choosing a technique unfit for the material they’re tackling. So here we’ll be covering the pros and cons of each and discussing the right font-color combination for ideal note-taking.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Comparison&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. Accuracy&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When it comes to accuracy, typing certainly wins out as it’s much faster to type than to write something down. However, this definitely depends on the material one is taking notes on. If it demands that notes be taken down verbatim then transcribing the lecturer’s speech, this would call for a laptop. But it’s very important to note that taking down notes in the form of a transcript isn’t effective for all subjects. A study was conducted by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychologicalscience.org/news/releases/take-notes-by-hand-for-better-long-term-comprehension.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;psychology scientists Pam Mueller and Daniel Oppenheimer&lt;/a&gt; in which students were asked to write down notes on a number of TED talks using the method that they normally used to take notes. The results showed that although the two types of note-takers did equally well on questions that required facts-citation, laptop note-takers performed particularly worse on the conceptual questions. That made the scientists suggest that students who took down handwritten notes were involved in more information processing than laptop users. As a result, they sorted through the information and opted for the more relevant ones to add to their notes. Additionally, the study suggests that writing by hand improves memory retention and understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The conclusion was that students who took more notes scored higher on the test, but that also applied to those who had less verbatim overlap. This proposes that unconscious transcription nullifies the advantage of having more content.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. Legibility, organization and accessibility&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Typing notes on a laptop offers a more aesthetic structure, easier editing and instant spelling check. So laptop users have the advantage of not having to worry about bad handwriting or making a mess of their notes when they make a mistake. While sharing handwritten notes could be a hassle, sharing digital notes is a piece of cake. Not to mention syncing them across devices makes them accessible anytime and anywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3. Distractions&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The ease and simplicity laptops offer come at a price. Although the extra tools and resources they provide save the note-taker the inconveniences that other note-takers face, that also means more distractions. For example, many people cannot resist checking social media while they’re in a lecture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studies also show that the laptop user is not the only one affected by those distractions. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gse.harvard.edu/news/uk/17/08/note-taking-low-tech-often-best&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Harvard University&lt;/a&gt;, researchers at York and McMaster conducted an experiment in which they had students watch a lecture and then take a comprehension test. Some students were randomly asked to carry out a couple of short tasks on their laptops during the lecture, like looking up movie times. The rest of the students were allowed to focus on the lecture. All seats were randomly assigned.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unsurprisingly, the multitasking students scored about 11% lower on the test than those who focused on the lecture. But interestingly, the students sitting near the multitaskers also got affected. Students who weren’t multitasking but could view the screen of a multitasker’s laptop scored 17% lower on comprehension than those who had no distracting view. So it’s important to note that by choosing typing as a method of note-taking, one could potentially distract those around them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Factors to consider when deciding which method to use when taking notes:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1. The type of learning that is called for&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://effectiviology.com/handwriting-vs-typing-how-to-take-notes/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Effectiviology&lt;/a&gt;, note-taking through typing works better when the material requires factual learning, which involves memorizing specific details and merely entails a shallow understanding of the material. However, conceptual learning, which involves securing a rigorous understanding of the fundamental concepts in the material, calls for taking notes manually by hand.
On that account, the student must first determine the kind of material they’re dealing with and choose the note-taking method accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2. The length and type of notes&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another aspect a student should take into consideration is the length of the text they’ll eventually end up with. Writing notes down by hand proves to be a physically exhausting method when there’s a lot to write down, and of course, there’s a certain limit to how fast a person can write. Consequently, this method demands the note-taker to be more concise, which can be convenient since it means that only the more relevant aspects of the material are included in the notes. But the student could also end up leaving out significant details in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On the other hand, typing notes allows the student to write more details, as typing is a faster process than writing. This definitely comes in handy when there are lots of points to cover. However, it’s crucial to note that there’s the disadvantage of writing too much that the unnecessary details end up overriding the important ones. That makes it more difficult to study the notes at a later time.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, this depends on the type of learning that we previously discussed.
Another point worth mentioning is the type of notes the student is taking. For example, mathematical formulas are definitely faster to write down than to type. The same thing applies to sketching and labeling figures, as handwritten notes allow more freedom with the graphics and thus are more flexible in that aspect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Font color&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Something that applies to both handwritten and typed notes is the font color. Color is a form of visible light, essentially a portion of the electromagnetic spectrum. Each color has its own wavelength that can affect neurological pathways in the brain, creating a biochemical response. Consequently, using the right color, along with the right selection and arrangement, can have a significant impact on feelings, concentration and behavior when learning. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.shiftelearning.com/blog/how-do-colors-influence-learning&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Shift Learning&lt;/a&gt;, although it isn’t definite science, each color can elicit its own unique biological response.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Green promotes tranquility and calm and improves concentration, as it’s a low-frequency color. In a study led by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smh.com.au/technology/seeing-green-boosts-your-concentration-research-shows-20150525-gh8udh.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dr. Kate Lee&lt;/a&gt;, 150 university students were given a tedious task, which involved pressing a key as a series of numbers repeatedly flashed on a computer screen. They were asked not to press the key when the number three popped up on the screen. The students were given a short break halfway through the task to look at a city rooftop scene. Half of the students looked at a green roof whereas the other half viewed a bare concrete roof. After the break, students who looked at the greener scenery made considerably fewer errors and showed better concentration than those who viewed the concrete roof.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Orange is a mood lifter and a stimulator, as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scienceofpeople.com/color-psychology/#:~:text=Orange%20is%20a%20color%20of,effect,%20and%20stimulates%20brain%20activity.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;it has been found&lt;/a&gt; to increase oxygen supply to the brain, producing an energizing effect. It is best used for highlighting and accentuating certain parts in notes.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blue promotes productivity. Some research suggests that people with particularly intellectual work like programmers and academics are more productive in the presence of blue surroundings. Blue is best used for learning situations that are challenging and ones that require substantial comprehension.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/notetakingOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;A student highlights words in different colors. &lt;a href=&quot;https://study.com/blog/5-tips-for-color-coding-your-notes.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Study)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;The verdict&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When it comes to the learning method, it all comes down to preference! And the type of material one is dealing with. Both techniques have their pros and cons, but if the material equally allows for either method to be used, then writing by hand is surely the way to go because it allows learners to comprehend and retain information better than typing does.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What’s also worth mentioning is the fact that recently, tablets have become the go-to device for students, as it bears some of the best aspects of both methods: handwritten notes that can be easily organized and shared.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Regarding the font color, notes shouldn’t be kept too monochrome, so it is best to use blue along with one or two other colors. In any case, trial and error is key so remember to stay open-minded and try out different techniques with different materials.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://sites.psu.edu/siowfa16/2016/10/18/notes-by-hand-or-laptop/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Penn State)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Nadwa Atwi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Nadwa Atwi</name></author><summary type="html">Handwriting vs. typing notes, and does font color matter? Nadwa Atwi. 04/23/2021 Taking notes is one of the most important parts of the learning process. Students often spend a lot of time considering how to take notes, only to end up choosing a technique unfit for the material they’re tackling. So here we’ll be covering the pros and cons of each and discussing the right font-color combination for ideal note-taking.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/notetakingCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/notetakingCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dopamine: The molecule that drives addiction</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/22/dopamine-the-molecule-that-drives-addiction.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dopamine: The molecule that drives addiction" /><published>2021-04-22T17:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-22T17:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/22/dopamine-the-molecule-that-drives-addiction</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/22/dopamine-the-molecule-that-drives-addiction.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Dopamine: The molecule that drives addiction
&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Arul Loomba . 04/23/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/dopamineOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Dopamine is a neurotransmitter that is released into the brain’s reward system (right) and is released into cells (left) initiating a response. Often, an increase in the release of dopamine creates a feeling of pleasure.
(Getty Images / Verywell Health)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The brain craves pleasure. Going on a vacation, jumping out of a plane or even taking a bite of ice cream stimulates the action of billions of neurons - the cells in our brains that send signals throughout our body to do everything from helping us walk to reading a book. There is one chemical that does consistent and important signaling using the brain’s neurons, especially when it comes to sending information about pleasure: the neurotransmitter &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencenewsforstudents.org/article/explainer-what-dopamine&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;dopamine&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencedirect.com/topics/neuroscience/nucleus-accumbens&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Neurotransmitters&lt;/a&gt; are small molecules that neurons use to communicate with one another, and they help elicit certain responses like happiness from opening a gift. They also play a substantial role in our everyday actions, including moving, running and most importantly, thinking. Dopamine, a significant neurotransmitter in the brain, influences emotional activity and response. For example, it stimulates the brain so people can concentrate on certain enjoyable actions and ignore those that don’t provide the same feeling. The molecule acts on the brain’s reward system, a neuronal pathway in the brain used for transmitting emotions; when doing an activity that brings pleasure, the reward system creates feelings of joy and craving. After the consistent release of these emotions, a person’s attention span will change: “You can’t pay attention to everything, but you want to be adept as an organism at recognizing things that are novel,” Director of the National Institute of Drug Abuse &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/4001507&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Nora D. Volkow&lt;/a&gt; said. Dopamine is a chemical that allows a person to concentrate on novel and attractive things - ones that we hope to receive pleasure from.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Overall, dopamine plays a significant role in motivating a person to participate in pleasurable activities. This can range from exercising to watching a movie - anything that prolongs the release of dopamine. While many times this prolongation can be healthy (as a source of motivation and effort), too much of anything can have a dark side: uncontrolled amounts of dopamine are the primary cause of drug addiction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A recent study by Dr. Volkow illustrates that drug abuse is associated with the increased “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2009/10/27/science/27angier.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;intensity and duration&lt;/a&gt;” of dopamine release. Street drugs like opiates and cocaine are major drivers of addiction because they increase the concentration of dopamine that cells put out. These drugs inhibit the natural mechanisms the body has to maintain balance, which in this case regulates dopamine concentration, providing the users with a burst of satisfaction or “high.” The mechanisms that keep the levels of dopamine under control involve proteins that take excess dopamine out of circulation. By imitating the shape of the molecular repressors that inhibit reuptake proteins, drugs can have a significant effect. Long-term consequences of inhibition, include the brain growing accustomed to greater concentrations of dopamine. Moreover, in many cases, this environmental change can result in the brain stopping the natural release of dopamine, creating a reliance on drugs to maintain its concentration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The discovery that drug addiction stems from the increased presence of dopamine in the brain also has significant treatment implications. Frequent drug users often rely on the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC5171207/%23:~:text%3DThe%2520incentive%252Dsensitization%2520theory%2520posits,an%2520amplification%2520of%2520%27liking%27.&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1619249325183000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw3msOfZe9-ITtTf6UVBcdt3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;euphoric feeling&lt;/a&gt; that dopamine provides to fuel their addiction - it gives them “motivation” to abuse certain substances. Volkow’s research opens up new treatment options for these addicts. For example, creating new medications that limit the dopamine “reward” that addicts feel from abused drugs can effectively eliminate the cause of addiction. Once available frequently, these treatments could be combined with rehab and therapy to encourage addicts to seek rewards from alternative sources like exercise or positive social interactions. Dopamine is naturally released at times of excitement, so gaining this in other ways would stimulate the normal neuronal pathways, and not ones related to drugs. These simple, yet important solutions, are key to fixing a problem present in many developing communities around the world. The safest, most effective way to address the issue would be changing its source: availability and composition drugs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Volkow is optimistic about the implications of her research: “Our findings suggest that interventions designed to enhance [dopamine] brain function in drug abusers,” noting that none of this will be successful unless treatment can “provide them with non-drug alternatives” with the ultimate goal to “help the addicted subject overcome the strong drive to take the drug.” With new treatments, the brain’s craving can be overcome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Getty Images / Stock Photo)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Arul Loomba&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Arul is currently a sophomore at Rancho Cucamonga High School in California. He has a deep passion for biomedicine and is looking to pursue regenerative medicine in the future. Currently, he is trying to research articles and data collected by many professors to formulate his theories and ideas! Arul is also a fan of cooking, playing tennis, and writing.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Arul Loomba</name></author><summary type="html">Dopamine: The molecule that drives addiction Arul Loomba . 04/23/2021 Dopamine is a neurotransmitter that is released into the brain’s reward system (right) and is released into cells (left) initiating a response. Often, an increase in the release of dopamine creates a feeling of pleasure. (Getty Images / Verywell Health) The brain craves pleasure. Going on a vacation, jumping out of a plane or even taking a bite of ice cream stimulates the action of billions of neurons - the cells in our brains that send signals throughout our body to do everything from helping us walk to reading a book. There is one chemical that does consistent and important signaling using the brain’s neurons, especially when it comes to sending information about pleasure: the neurotransmitter dopamine.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/dopamineCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/dopamineCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Social media and its effects on mental health</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/22/social-media-and-its-effects-on-mental-health.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Social media and its effects on mental health" /><published>2021-04-22T17:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-22T17:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/22/social-media-and-its-effects-on-mental-health</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/22/social-media-and-its-effects-on-mental-health.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Social media and its effects on mental health&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rheigina Quijote. 04/23/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/socialMediaOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;In this age of social networking, there are many platforms that lead to the decline of mental health for adolescents and adults.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.statista.com/chart/19262/impact-of-social-media-on-mental-health/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Statista)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In today’s world, social media plays an active role in the mental health of an individual. Throughout our lives, humans seek interaction with others since being social can foster positivity in a person. But during this era of technology and growing digital interaction, social media has made its way into everyone’s daily lives. Social media brings exposure to all users, as a craving for attention is now an active figure in the lives of many. What is regarded as a source of entertainment and a form of efficient communication for humans is also the source of increasing mental illness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A research article by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/profile/Shabir-Bhat/publication/323018957_Effects_of_Social_Media_on_Mental_Health_A_Review/links/5a7c9e97aca272341aeb7472/Effects-of-Social-Media-on-Mental-Health-A-Review.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the International journal of Indian Psychology&lt;/a&gt; states that similarly to the human body, which seeks nutrition, the human mind seeks to be nurtured by thoughts. As social media life separates a person from others in the real world, it affects their mental health and social interaction. The journal found that the younger generation is more susceptible at an embryonic stage of their life. This indicates that because the youth is more easily swayed and most active on social media, they are at a larger risk of serious mental health effects. By being easily influenced by social media, they’re exposed to situations of bullying and comparing themselves with others online. Online activity has become an essential part of daily life, and while it does contain its benefits like an increase in communication, it can strongly impact the well-being of its users.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media is known to cause an increase in anxiety and depression as stated by the International Journal of Indian Psychology. About 45% of British adults have felt restlessness because of a lack of accessing social media sites. The same was found with adolescents. Adolescents are unable to decipher the difference between a notification they receive and one someone else does, a condition known as phantom vibration syndrome. There is a positive correlation between social media and mental health: the longer you spend on social media the more likely you are at risk of depression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another look at the topic at hand is the current global situation of COVID-19. Because of the virus outbreak, people are forced to live in isolated circumstances, which leads to a rise in technological use. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://journals.plos.org/plosone/article?id%3D10.1371/journal.pone.0231924&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1619248925761000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw0-TYccMD_hzv4rzkOYRw4S&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Plos One&lt;/a&gt; brings an insight into mental health problems and their association with social media exposure during COVID-19. By conducting their experiment and surveying the results, it is shown that because of  COVID-19, a rise in misinformation through social media has been an underlying effect of increasing mental illness.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In their investigation, they examined 4,872 Chinese citizens under 18 through online surveys. It was found that about 48% were depressed, 22% had anxiety and 19% had a combination of the two. Shown from the data, it’s believed social media exposure was associated with high anxiety within individuals, and the increase of social media exposure, in general, was due to the COVID outbreak. From this extended use of social media, it was concluded that misinformation that was fueled by social media was an indirect cause of anxiety.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study had the participants report any experience of positivity in the last two weeks and those that scored less than 13 on their 6-point scale represented depression. Similarly, their study over anxiety had initially the same rating scale where they reported signs of anxiousness during the last two weeks. Those with scores greater than one were assumed to have an anxiety disorder. They determined social media uses by how often the respondents had seen news or information regarding COVID-19 on social media. In the results, the increase of social media exposure corresponded to increased odds of depression as was with anxiety and the combination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To conclude, the two main reasons to describe the association of social media exposure and mental health is the misinformation in social media, not only the COVID outbreak but in this generation overall. This is likely because of the lack of privacy and expectancy of attention of users that the increase of self unimportance or anxiousness. As a way to prevent such problems and help those who have felt as such, both research articles and studies encourage seeking professional counseling and user age restrictions. In hopes of enlightening others on the harms that social media may cause to one’s health and for your benefit and growth, monitor and limit your time around the screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (The Digital Age)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Rheigina Quijote&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Rheigina Quijote</name></author><summary type="html">Social media and its effects on mental health Rheigina Quijote. 04/23/2021 In this age of social networking, there are many platforms that lead to the decline of mental health for adolescents and adults. (Statista) In today’s world, social media plays an active role in the mental health of an individual. Throughout our lives, humans seek interaction with others since being social can foster positivity in a person. But during this era of technology and growing digital interaction, social media has made its way into everyone’s daily lives. Social media brings exposure to all users, as a craving for attention is now an active figure in the lives of many. What is regarded as a source of entertainment and a form of efficient communication for humans is also the source of increasing mental illness.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/socialMediaCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/socialMediaCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Kepler-452b: An Earth-like planet light-years away from us</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/15/kepler-452b-an-earth-like-planet-light-years-away-from-us.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Kepler-452b: An Earth-like planet light-years away from us" /><published>2021-04-15T17:00:03-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-15T17:00:03-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/15/kepler-452b-an-earth-like%20planet-light-years-away-from-us</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/15/kepler-452b-an-earth-like-planet-light-years-away-from-us.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Kepler-452b: An Earth-like planet light-years away from us&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Bui. 04/16/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/keplerOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Above is an image of Kepler-452b.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.gettyimages.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Getty Images)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://exoplanets.nasa.gov/exoplanet-catalog/5471/kepler-452-b/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Kepler-452b&lt;/a&gt; is a planet that exists light-years away from us. The planet can and most likely once did support life. But what exactly does this planet have to offer? Are there any downsides that may disrupt the possibility of the planet supporting life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To begin with, Kepler-452b is an &lt;a href=&quot;https://exoplanets.nasa.gov/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;exoplanet&lt;/a&gt; located 1,402 light-years away from Earth. Its appearance is similar to Earth, having an atmosphere, water and land. And similar to how the Earth has the sun, Kepler-452b orbits around Kepler-452, a star 6 billion years old, which is pretty old in comparison to the solar system’s sun, aged 4.5 billion years. But Kepler-452 has around the same temperature as the sun, which can support the idea that Kepler-452b can still harbor life. Whether or not it has a moon is unknown as of now.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While it may sound bizarre that Kepler-452b and Earth are similar, it’s true. Other than the facts stated previously, what other aspects do both planets have? First off, water. Last year, water was discovered on &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/d41586-020-02751-1#:~:text=The%20discovery%2C%20reported%20on%2028,orbiting%20spacecraft%2C%20called%20Mars%20Express.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mars&lt;/a&gt;. This was a huge discovery because it hints that Mars once supported life. But Kepler-452b is an especially unique case because it has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.space.com/30034-earth-cousin-exoplanet-kepler-452b-life.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;lakes&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.space.com/30034-earth-cousin-exoplanet-kepler-452b-life.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;rivers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.space.com/30034-earth-cousin-exoplanet-kepler-452b-life.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;pools&lt;/a&gt;. There were once oceans, but unfortunately, all of them have dried up. Unlike &lt;a href=&quot;https://coolcosmos.ipac.caltech.edu/ask/80-Can-we-breathe-on-Mars-#:~:text=Mars%20does%20have%20an%20atmosphere,with%20oxygen%20to%20work%20outdoors.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mars&lt;/a&gt;, the atmosphere might be actually breathable. The air on Mars is 100 times thinner than that of Earth, compared to Kepler-452b where the air is pretty similar to that of Earth. However, this topic is still in &lt;a href=&quot;https://education.abc.net.au/newsandarticles/blog/-/b/3345118/curious-kids-could-humans-live-on-kepler-452-b&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;debate&lt;/a&gt; because we do not know what is in the air, especially if there is something more dangerous in it than Earth’s nitrogen and oxygen. The temperature on Kepler-452b is slightly &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kepler-452b#:~:text=The%20planet%20takes%20385%20Earth,a%20little%20warmer%20than%20Earth.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;warmer&lt;/a&gt; than Earth but is still as livable as a warm day on Earth. The appearance, as mentioned, is almost exactly the same. The majority of the outside view is blue, indicating water, with patches of land. Both orbit around a star that is roughly the same temperature and have clouds. But just because they are similar in a handful of aspects doesn’t mean Kepler-452b is Earth. In fact, they are pretty different in quite a few ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First off, the sun of Kepler-452b or Kepler-452contrasts with our sun. Kepler-452 is also 20% brighter than the sun, as well as 11% larger. The terrain of Kepler-452b is rocky, which is different from Earth’s variety of landforms. Not only are the landforms bigger, Kepler-452b is actually &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/press-release/nasa-kepler-mission-discovers-bigger-older-cousin-to-earth/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;60%&lt;/a&gt; larger in diameter, meaning it is 1.6 times bigger than Earth. The gigantic size difference between both planet and exoplanet is what gives Kepler-452b the title of a &lt;a href=&quot;https://exoplanets.nasa.gov/what-is-an-exoplanet/planet-types/super-earth/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Super-Earth&lt;/a&gt;. The exoplanet is also rather massive, having &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kepler-452b#:~:text=Kepler%2D452b%20has%20a%20probable,exoplanets%20are%20only%20rough%20estimates.&amp;amp;text=Its%20radius%20is%2050%25%20bigger,zone%20of%20its%20parent%20star.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;5 times&lt;/a&gt; as much mass as the Earth. The surface gravity is about 2 times as much as the gravity on Earth, resulting in jumping being twice as hard. A complete revolution on the Earth, 365 days, is considered a year. For Kepler-452b however, it takes &lt;a href=&quot;https://exoplanets.nasa.gov/resources/282/comparison-between-earth-and-kepler-452b-and-their-host-stars/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;385&lt;/a&gt; days to complete a full revolution around its star, resulting in a 385 day year. Earth has “only” existed for &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalgeographic.org/topics/resource-library-age-earth/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;4.54&lt;/a&gt; billion years, but Kepler-452b is estimated to have the age of &lt;a href=&quot;https://exoplanets.nasa.gov/exoplanet-catalog/5471/kepler-452-b/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;6&lt;/a&gt; billion!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kepler-452b is by no means Earth. Earth has all of our needs: natural fruits and vegetables, food sources such as meat, oceans for trade— the full bundle. Kepler-452b has a handful of that. Whether or not Kepler-452b has life or had life is not known yet. The question of whether humans can live on this planet, even if they did bring their own supply, is in debate. The temperature is nice, sure, but is the environment habitable? Will the air have any metals that are potentially lethal or just not safe? Can it really harbor human life? The short answer for this is yes, no, maybe so. We do not know if the planet has everything we need, but one thing can be sure: it comes really close to that point, with water, land, weather and all. Maybe someday in the future, we’ll know for sure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, Kepler-452b is more or less similar to Earth. In fact, there are dozens upon dozens of Kepler planets! Kepler is a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/kepler/overview/index.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;NASA mission&lt;/a&gt; to discover hundreds of Earth-like planets, and to this point up to 24 potential exoplanets may be even better than the conditions of Earth, but of all of them Kepler-452b will always be one of the likeliest candidates, and for good reason too! However, although all these amazing planets have been found, remember that they are not in our solar system, and by no means within reach. Being thousands of light-years is too far for human travel, and all purposes of looking for them are merely to answer the question “Are we alone in this universe?” or “Are there others like us?”. So even though planets as amazing as Kepler-452b and all of the other exoplanets are out there, the chance of actually inhabiting one of the candidates is near impossible. However, it is important to know that somewhere out there, such an amazing planet actually exists.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (NASA / Ames / JPL-Caltech)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Peter Bui&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Peter Bui</name></author><summary type="html">Kepler-452b: An Earth-like planet light-years away from us Peter Bui. 04/16/2021 Above is an image of Kepler-452b. (Getty Images) Kepler-452b is a planet that exists light-years away from us. The planet can and most likely once did support life. But what exactly does this planet have to offer? Are there any downsides that may disrupt the possibility of the planet supporting life?</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/keplerCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/keplerCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The genius of Bitcoin, a revolutionary currency</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/08/the-genius-of-bitcoin-a-revolutionary-currency.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The genius of Bitcoin, a revolutionary currency" /><published>2021-04-08T17:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2021-04-08T17:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/04/08/the-genius-of-bitcoin-a-revolutionary-currency</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/04/08/the-genius-of-bitcoin-a-revolutionary-currency.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The genius of Bitcoin, a revolutionary currency&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rachel Huang. 04/09/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/btcOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The high stakes involved with Bitcoin have only made its value soar higher than ever before. &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/four-factors-driving-the-price-of-bitcoin-87244&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(The Conversation)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Launched in 2009 from the anonymous Satoshi Nakamoto’s whitepaper, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/terms/b/bitcoin.asp&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bitcoin&lt;/a&gt; (BTC) was created to be an electronic payment system “based on cryptographic proof instead of trust.” Bitcoin is now the world’s largest cryptocurrency (digital currency) with an astonishing value of over $55,000 for a single coin and is also the first application of blockchain technology, an innovative creation that allows it to be distributed, traded and stored. A blockchain is essentially a collection of “blocks,” files that record all of the transactions that occur, making them transparent and visible to all of the computers that run Bitcoin’s code and store its blockchain. The creation of Bitcoin has united thousands of people around the world over a common goal: obtaining bitcoin and turning a profit.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are currently 12,000 computers connected to Bitcoin’s blockchain; these computers are called nodes, while the owners of the computers are called miners - the miners control Bitcoin’s release into circulation via a process called Bitcoin mining and are rewarded with coins adding blocks to the blockchain. Bitcoin mining requires the solving of complex computational puzzles in order to discover a new block, and expensive mining rigs (elaborate mining processors and hardware) increase a miner’s ability to earn more rewards. Mining rigs are available for purchase in the form of computer chips like Application-Specific Integrated Circuits (ASIC) and Graphic Processing Units (GPUs). All of these Bitcoin transactions are verified by cryptographic proof, making the system very secure. For example, a person with malicious intent would need to operate 51% of the total computing power that makes up Bitcoin to cheat the system. With miners acting as Bitcoin’s decentralized authority, miners are motivated to add to the growing blockchain because of the prospect of reward, and the blockchain benefits by growing and developing even more.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While David Zeiler, cryptocurrency expert for Money Morning, describes Bitcoin as “the best-known crypto and a secure, decentralized currency that has become a store of value like gold,” there may be more exaggeration than truth in his statement. The long-term security that Zeiler describes only refers to Bitcoin’s official certification and verifiability, not Bitcoin’s prices. Cryptocurrency is a highly speculative investment, with the potential for intense price swings, or as described in the words of CEO of Digital Currency Group Barry Silbert, “It is pretty much the highest-risk, highest-return investment that you can possibly make.” As a safeguard against these risks, it is highly recommended that &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/advisor/investing/what-is-cryptocurrency/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;investors&lt;/a&gt; trade on official cryptocurrency exchanges, such as Coin base and Bitfinex. Potential investors and traders are enticed by Bitcoin’s high exchange rate, lower transaction fees and instant payments that are a result of its “peer-to-peer” technology that grants instant rewards. In addition, Bitcoin can also be exchanged for traditional currencies and act as an alternative to national fiat money and traditional commodities like gold. The overall success of Bitcoin has triggered the release of a slew of other cryptocurrencies, amounting to over 5,000 different types released into circulation, collectively referred to as altcoins.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As another facet of its multipurpose nature, Bitcoin can also be used to buy things! Bitcoin can be split into smaller units to make transactions easier - the common unit of Bitcoin used in everyday transactions is called the Satoshi, which is 100 millionths of a Bitcoin, currently worth approximately 0.02 cents. In response to the growing Bitcoin community, many retailers have begun to accept bitcoin with the proper hardware terminal and/or wallet address through QR codes and touch screen apps. Keys are the main form of hardware terminal through which Bitcoin can be transferred: there are public and private keys, both of which are long strings of numbers and letters linked through the mathematical encryption algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/btcTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;An example of Bitcoin’s private and public keys.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://coinsource.net/private-keys-public-keys-addresses-and-wallets/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Coinsource)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
A &lt;a href=&quot;https://coinsource.net/private-keys-public-keys-addresses-and-wallets/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;public&lt;/a&gt; key’s address is published to the world and others may send bitcoins to it as necessary. On the other hand, private keys are a guarded secret and only used to authorize personal bitcoin transmissions. Keys increase Bitcoin’s liquidity by making Bitcoins less like stocks and more like cash because the private keys needed to authorize spending can be printed out and stored physically. Stores may also accept Bitcoin wallets, a physical or digital device that facilitates the trading of bitcoin and allows users to track ownership of coins with a software program that interacts with the blockchain, allowing users to exchange the currency.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin’s appeal has been greatly increasing in recent years, especially because Bitcoin quickly approaches its approvable max of 21 million bitcoin. With a current count of about 18,614,806 in &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.investopedia.com/tech/what-happens-bitcoin-after-21-million-mined/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;circulation&lt;/a&gt;, there are only about 3 million Bitcoins left to be mined. This makes it seem like Bitcoin will run out soon, sending miners and investors into a frenzy. However, this is not the case because rewards are halved for every 210,000 blocks added to Bitcoin’s blockchain; the current reward for each block discovery has become a meager 6.25 bitcoins (of course, if you take into account the value of a single Bitcoin, then the overall value of the reward is greater than ever). If you think about how a store of 3 million Bitcoins gets depleted by withdrawals of 6.25 bitcoins, you will understand how, in reality, Bitcoin will actually “run out” in around 2140.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bitcoin continues to be the leader and definer of the cryptocurrency value cycle; the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/investor/2021/02/12/bitcoin-price-prediction-2021-where-is-the-top/?sh=31480e9c3ed0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;prices&lt;/a&gt; of bitcoin and Ethereum (another cryptocurrency) are currently riding a FOMO-driven high, going almost vertical. The direction and stability of these high prices are very unpredictable, or, in the words of Clem Chambers, “a week is now a long time in crypto” due to its extreme volatility. Investors can monitor transaction fees as a sign of Bitcoin’s upcoming value - transaction fees are now exorbitant; when transaction fees start to fall it will be a signal that the FOMO is falling, and the prices will drop. For now though, the fees continue to rapidly increase.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/april/btcThree.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Google Trends shows interest in bitcoin, Ethereum, DeFi (decentralized finance) and stocks.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/investor/2021/02/12/bitcoin-price-prediction-2021-where-is-the-top/?sh=31480e9c3ed0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Forbes)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As a child of the 21st century, Bitcoin is, and will no doubt continue to be at the forefront of the digital currency revolution. Versatile and secure, investable and ever-expanding, Satoshi Nakamoto’s application of blockchain technology has blossomed into proportions that must have been unimaginable before its creation. Microsoft, Home Depot, Burger King, Starbucks: all of these major retailers have started the movement of accepting Bitcoin and other forms of cryptocurrency as a form of payment. Who knows? One day, Bitcoin may become the new dollar bill - as liquid as cash, and accepted anywhere and everywhere. Only time will tell how the wonders of Bitcoin and its siblings will transform the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://coingeek.com/bitcoin-sv-rallies-as-world-record-638mb-block-is-mined/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Coingeek)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Rachel Huang&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Rachel Huang</name></author><summary type="html">The genius of Bitcoin, a revolutionary currency Rachel Huang. 04/09/2021 The high stakes involved with Bitcoin have only made its value soar higher than ever before. (The Conversation) Launched in 2009 from the anonymous Satoshi Nakamoto’s whitepaper, Bitcoin (BTC) was created to be an electronic payment system “based on cryptographic proof instead of trust.” Bitcoin is now the world’s largest cryptocurrency (digital currency) with an astonishing value of over $55,000 for a single coin and is also the first application of blockchain technology, an innovative creation that allows it to be distributed, traded and stored. A blockchain is essentially a collection of “blocks,” files that record all of the transactions that occur, making them transparent and visible to all of the computers that run Bitcoin’s code and store its blockchain. The creation of Bitcoin has united thousands of people around the world over a common goal: obtaining bitcoin and turning a profit.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/btcCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/april/btcCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>