<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-01-03T21:37:22-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">InterSTEM</title><entry><title type="html">Why can’t we perfectly predict weather on Earth?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/why-can't-we-perfectly-predict-weather-on-earth.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why can’t we perfectly predict weather on Earth?" /><published>2020-12-31T16:00:04-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-31T16:00:04-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/why-can't-we-perfectly-predict-weather-on-earth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/why-can't-we-perfectly-predict-weather-on-earth.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Why can't we perfectly predict weather on Earth?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ana Monsalud. 01/01/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/weatherOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;We often overlook the role that weather plays in our lives. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theverge.com/2020/1/14/21065095/google-ai-weather-forecast-predictions-rainfall-research&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(The Verge)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Have you ever wondered why weather reports don’t show the weather more than a week into the future? And sometimes, predictions are wildly inaccurate for even just three days from when they’re announced. With the technology we have today, why is this the case?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Modern Weather Forecasting&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Weather forecasting today is possible due to a mix of technology, observation and educated guessing. The educated guesses, however, aren’t made by humans: they’re made by computers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In a process called &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.discovermagazine.com/planet-earth/how-weather-forecasts-are-made&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;numerical weather prediction&lt;/a&gt;, meteorologists input current weather conditions into a computer model. These conditions are measured through various weather instruments such as thermometers, weather balloons, weather satellites and more to evaluate the conditions of factors like current temperature, air pressure, humidity, rainfall and wind. The computer model will then be able to simulate the current atmosphere and allow meteorologists to predict the weather for the next few hours or days. Weather models use a complex process that can track weather on a larger scale, like in the case of a large storm, or with more accuracy for a smaller area. Models for a smaller region are more expensive to compute, however, and can only predict up to one or two days.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different weather models also use different factors. This could mean that two models form two different predictions because of slight differences between provided data, the way the model simulates the atmosphere, or the difference in which factors are prioritized. So even when provided the same exact data, different models might have different predictions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although it may seem like there’s no place for humans in this process anymore, meteorologists still play a part in weather prediction. Human judgment is still an important factor for various reasons. If a meteorologist is familiar with an area and knows about common weather irregularities that don’t appear on a model, then they could use their own judgment to provide a possibly more accurate forecast. Certain factors could be early signs of intense weather and not be picked up on by the computer, but be easily noticed by a meteorologist. Even though modern weather prediction is effective, the human touch is still extremely helpful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;But why are models unable to predict future weather with complete certainty?&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Despite their accuracy and reliability, weather models aren’t able to perfectly simulate the environment. This is because it’s difficult enough to measure every aspect of the current atmosphere. But even if we were able to make observations of all the factors in the atmosphere, those observations would most likely not be perfect. So with the imperfect and limited observations that can be made today, we’re able to create an accurate, but not flawless, model.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;So how accurate are weather forecasts?&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;The farther into the future a prediction is made, the less of a chance that it’s accurate. However, weather forecasts are still reliable for predicting about a week into the future. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://scijinks.gov/forecast-reliability/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration (NOAA) Scijinks website&lt;/a&gt;, a five-day forecast is accurate about 90% of the time. That accuracy drops to 80% for a seven-day forecast. Yet, a 10-day forecast falls to an accuracy of around 50%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This happens due to a phenomenon known as the butterfly effect. The most famous example of this effect is per its namesake: where a butterfly flapping its wings causes a typhoon. The butterfly effect refers to when a small action causes a large effect. And with the weather, it means that it isn’t possible to know whether a tiny updraft might have bigger effects after a week. Observing the average temperature to be even just one degree higher than the actual average, or if the average recorded wind speed in the frame of an hour is one or two mph under what it was throughout most of the day, might change the long term model significantly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Then how technically accurate is modern weather prediction?&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;All factors considered, modern weather prediction is actually an impressively accurate feat of science. By combining new technology and science, it’s possible to predict the weather at a very reliable rate. Even though it isn’t possible today, and probably ever, to perfectly predict the weather to an exact degree, it’s still extremely helpful to have predictions that are normally less than a few degrees off.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Modern weather prediction allows us to do more than just have a better idea of what we should wear for the day, though. These models allow meteorologists to predict the patterns of large storms, intense weather and more. The accuracy of these models means that people can be safer in the case of severe weather and that scientists are able to study changes to climate and hypothesize possible causes. Even though we aren’t able to have weather forecasts perfectly accurate to the degree, modern technology has come a long way in allowing us to understand our complex earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencenewsforstudents.org/article/explainer-weather-and-weather-prediction&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Science News for Students)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Ana Monsalud&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Ana is a junior from Cambridge Virtual Academy who is a huge nerd for pretty much everything related to math and science. Through InterSTEM, she hopes to inspire others with her same love for learning and curiosity about the world. In the future, she hopes to pursue a career in healthcare and contribute to change in her community.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Ana Monsalud</name></author><summary type="html">Why can't we perfectly predict weather on Earth? Ana Monsalud. 01/01/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/weatherCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/weatherCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The history of vaccines</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/the-history-of-vaccines.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The history of vaccines" /><published>2020-12-31T16:00:03-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-31T16:00:03-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/the-history-of-vaccines</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/the-history-of-vaccines.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The history of vaccines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sydney Hollingsworth. 01/01/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/vaccinesOne.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Edward Jenner vaccinates eight-year-old James Phipps in 1796.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.history.com/news/the-rise-and-fall-of-smallpox&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(DEA Picture Library / Getty Images)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As news of the COVID-19 vaccine floods headlines, the spread of myths and misconceptions surrounding vaccines is at an all time high. Many cringe at the thought of introducing foreign substances into their bodies, and wordy lists of molecules used in vaccines circulate the internet to elicit angry responses from the masses. The bases of these fears are simple: we are afraid of what we do not understand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The science behind vaccines is complicated, and resistance against advancements in medicine is certainly not a new phenomenon. To many, vaccines seem like a magic, ‘too-good-to-be-true’ fix to deadly diseases, and the decision to take them boils down to a question of trust. Perhaps, to combat hesitancy, a quick trip through history will remind us of what vaccines have done and help us understand the necessity of them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The concept of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nlm.nih.gov/exhibition/smallpox/sp_variolation.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;inoculation&lt;/a&gt;, or creating immunity by introducing the immune system to a disease, is far from new; evidence of a similar procedure has been traced all the way back to ancient China. A method called variolation involved the drying and powdering of smallpox scabs which were then inhaled through the nose. Patients contracted a mild form of smallpox and were left immune once they recovered. By the 18th century, the procedure had spread to India, Africa and the Ottoman Empire.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Variolation came to Europe in the early 1700s when the wife of a British ambassador observed the procedure in Constantinople. Soon after, the royal family was vaccinated against smallpox and variolation became popular among the upper class.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although resulting in similar effects, vaccination and its predecessor, variolation, are quite different. Variolation had a much higher mortality rate because the patient had to have been able to recover from the infection, and the procedure was often done without proper sterilization. Variolation also used the actual disease rather than a weakened or similar form and is no longer used in modern medicine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The invention of modern vaccination is often credited to Edward Jenner in 1796, but could more accurately be attributed to &lt;a href=&quot;https://pediatrics.aappublications.org/content/pediatrics/139/4/e20162833.full.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Benjamin Jesty&lt;/a&gt;, a farmer from Dorset, England. At the time, milkmaids were known for their smooth skin, which was not covered by the smallpox scars that many adults had, and they were able to care for relatives who were sick with smallpox without contracting the disease themselves. Jesty hypothesized that the immunity had something to do with the cowpox that milkmaids were prone to, a mild disease similar to smallpox that came from touching the udders of affected cows.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1774, 22 years before Jenner conducted his famous experiment, Jesty vaccinated his family with cowpox in response to a smallpox outbreak in Dorset. Unfortunately, his wife’s arm became infected at the site of the puncture wound. Although she recovered quickly, the news of Jesty’s experiment had spread through the community like wildfire. He and his family were run out of town by a mob who believed Jesty wanted to turn them all into half-human, half-cow monsters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1805, after Jenner’s findings had been published, Jesty was invited to London by the Original Vaccine Pock Institution where he proved that his vaccine worked by infecting his oldest son, who had been vaccinated 31 years earlier with smallpox. The Institution declared Jesty’s success in September of 1805 in the Edinburgh Medical and Surgical Journal and rewarded him with a portrait, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thelancet.com/journals/lancet/article/PIIS0140-6736(06)69878-4/fulltext&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;rediscovered in 2004&lt;/a&gt; by the U.K.’s Wellcome Trust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://www.bbc.co.uk/history/historic_figures/jenner_edward.shtml&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Edward Jenner&lt;/a&gt; conducted his famous experiment in 1796 when he came to a similar conclusion as Jesty and tested the idea on his gardener’s eight-year-old son. After continued experimentation, Jenner’s findings were published in 1798 but were met with the same backlash Jesty received. Uneasiness at the idea of introducing material from a sick animal into one’s body overwhelmed the potential of his discovery. Newspaper cartoons in 1802 even depicted people with cow heads but as the vaccine was proven effective, ridicule declined.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.historyofvaccines.org/timeline/all&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Vaccines were brought to the U.S.&lt;/a&gt; in 1800 by Benjamin Waterhouse with President Thomas Jefferson’s support. As vaccination was proven effective, laws were proposed to require children attending school to be vaccinated against smallpox, inspired by similar laws in Europe and efforts towards eradication of the disease. However, these laws were met with protests. Parents, in particular, were opposed to the procedure as it involved an incision in their child’s arm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By the 1890s, as cases of smallpox became increasingly rare and vaccines were made more effective and safe, the occasional adverse reactions became much more obvious. Even in the wake of multiple deadly outbreaks, growing opposition to vaccines would resurface amongst government efforts to require them. This trend would continue through the next century, with measles, diphtheria, tuberculosis, polio and others.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Meanwhile, as public opinion rose and fell, advancements in vaccination technology continued. In 1879, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/biography/Louis-Pasteur/Vaccine-development&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Louis Pasteur&lt;/a&gt;, best known for his invention of pasteurization, used live, weakened cultures of chicken cholera to vaccinate chickens against the infection. This was the first use of a weakened microbe as a vaccine. He later extended this principle to anthrax and discovered a vaccine with the help of funding from local farmers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1882, Pasteur once again extended this principle of milder vaccines to rabies. At first, he incorrectly assumed the disease was caused by a microbe rather than a virus and began preserving the spinal cords of infected rabbits to better observe it. Instead, he found that his preservation method had actually neutralized the virus, creating the first neutralizing antibody and paving the way for a new type of vaccine called inactivated vaccines. The first use of Pasteur’s rabies vaccine was on a nine-year-old boy who had been bitten by a dog. His success marked the beginning of preventative medicine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Through the years, it seems as if there were two sides to the history of vaccines. On one hand, the scientific advancement of vaccines has been clearly, steadily improving. On the other hand, responses to vaccines have been varied, as the fear of deadly diseases and interference wrestle for control over public opinions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is important to understand that science does not exist in a vacuum; whether or not the public accepts a scientific advancement is just as important as the advancement itself. The natural reaction to avoid what we do not understand has become more apparent in recent history as science has quickly surpassed the awareness of the average person. Understanding how far vaccines have come and all the good they’ve done is imperative if one wishes to manage the science behind them. It helps to remember that the discoveries of today were not made overnight; they have been built on years of hard work by people attempting to understand the world around them in order to help the people they care for most.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.historyofvaccines.org/content/1920s-immunization&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Metropolitan Life Insurance Co.)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Sydney Hollingsworth&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sydney Hollingsworth</name></author><summary type="html">The history of vaccines Sydney Hollingsworth. 01/01/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/vaccinesCover.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/vaccinesCover.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Can science and religion coexist?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/can-science-and-religion-coexist.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can science and religion coexist?" /><published>2020-12-31T16:00:01-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-31T16:00:01-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/can-science-and-religion-coexist</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/can-science-and-religion-coexist.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Can science and religion coexist?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Emily Richter. 01/01/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/scienceAndReligionOne.png&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Many scientists believe that it is possible for religion and science to harmoniously coexist. (Emily Richter)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Science and religion seem to always be at odds. In the 1500s, when Nicolaus Copernicus announced that his observations about other planets supported the idea that Earth is a round planet revolving around the sun, the Catholic Church strongly objected to his findings because they contradicted the words of the Bible. Even today, some people doubt the roundness of Earth, pointing to the Bible as evidence against the proven idea. Throughout history, scientists and religious leaders have clashed as both point to different types of evidence to support their ideas about the world. History repeats itself today. Many religious people do not believe in human-caused climate change, while most scientists do. The conflict between science and religion has created deep fissures in society. Is it possible for the two subjects to peacefully coexist?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The most common point of contention between scientists and theologists is likely evolution. When naturalist and biologist Charles Darwin introduced the theory of evolution in the nineteenth century, religious leaders everywhere panicked. Darwin’s theory of evolution, which states that all living things evolved from a common ancestor, seemed to disprove many religious texts. As many religions preach that humans were created by a god as unique and superior beings, the idea that humans, animals, bacteria and every other living thing come from the same ancestor does not sit well with many religious people. However, &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.harvard.edu/gazette/story/2007/03/can-science-religion-coexist-in-peace/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Harvard professor Martin A. Nowa&lt;/a&gt; believes that evolution poses “as little problem for religion as [the concept of] gravity.” Nowak notes the evolution of what he calls “human cooperation” is evidence for the theological belief of human superiority.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nowak’s concept of human cooperation starts with the most obvious thing that sets humans apart from other living things. As of now, scientists have not discovered any other species that communicates using a language with specific grammatical rules. Nowak also notes the widespread human belief that “close relations have the highest social importance” and the fact that humans are “hopeful, generous, and forgiving” set humanity apart in the realm of communication. Since scientific evidence suggests that humanity carries these three unique communication traits due to evolution, Nowak suggests that evolution does not refute human superiority. Instead, he believes that the concept of evolution actually supports religious belief and provides an explanation for it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many theologists believe that religious texts are best understood as metaphors that aid humanity in its understanding of higher powers. While science and religion can clash when religious texts are taken as fact, science peacefully coexists with metaphorical understandings of religious texts. If the creation of humanity is understood not as a fact but as a metaphor, evolution and religion can both easily find a place in the universe’s timeline. Nowak says that “to say science disproves God goes beyond what science really says.” As both a scientist and a religious man, he believes that relying solely on either science or religion to explain the world makes a person insatiable in their understanding of the world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.huffpost.com/entry/religion-and-science-can-coexist_n_974116&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2011 study&lt;/a&gt; at Rice University led by sociologist Elaine Ecklund revealed that about 70% of faculty members associated with science at research universities believed that science and religion are sometimes in conflict. In addition to polling research university faculty, Ecklund polled and interviewed hundreds of scientists. Her 5,000 pages of transcribed interviews reveal that overall, scientists believe that while some specific strains of religions and some specific religious people often clash with science, religion as a whole is usually able to successfully coexist with science. Scientists who did not believe religion and science could coexist usually had “a narrow view of religion, identifying it most with conservative strains of American evangelical Christianity” and not with other religions, or even other branches of Christianity. Scientists whose views of religion included other religions and “non-institutionalized spiritual practices, such as meditation” were likely to identify science and religion as compatible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As part of the interview process, scientists were asked to review their religious colleagues. Many scientists reviewed their religious colleagues favorably, and some even cited scientists like Christian geneticist Francis Collins as examples that religious people can make good scientists. Ecklund’s findings agree with Nowak’s belief that science and religion both strive to make sense of the world in different ways and that both are “valid avenues of knowledge”. While the divisions in society created by conflict and religion cannot be completely fixed in the near future, the fact that many scientists believe that religion and science should be able to peacefully coexist is comforting and hopeful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Emily Richter)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Emily Richter&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Emily is a junior from Maria Carrillo High School in Sonoma County. She loves chemistry and the environmental sciences and plans to be an environmental chemist when she gets older. Through InterSTEM, she hopes to combine her experience in writing with her interest in STEM in order to help others enjoy and understand STEM. In her free time, she likes playing the flute, and baking and cooking.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Emily Richter</name></author><summary type="html">Can science and religion coexist? Emily Richter. 01/01/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/scienceAndReligionCover.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/scienceAndReligionCover.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Holidays and mental health</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/holidays-and-mental-health.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Holidays and mental health" /><published>2020-12-31T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-31T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/holidays-and-mental-health</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/31/holidays-and-mental-health.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Holidays and mental health&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Omar Dajani. 01/01/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/mentalHealthOne.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This infographic shows how many people are impacted by the ‘holidays blues’ yearly. &lt;a href=&quot;https://churchandmentalhealth.com/holiday-blues-infographic/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Church and Mental Health)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
This holiday season, many of us were having fun celebrating and being safe around family. Many of us were likely enamored by the ‘holiday spirit,’ but some may have not felt very strongly towards this holiday. Part of the reason can be attributed to the ongoing COVID-19, but there are other causes that may contribute to this as well. One cause seems to be what is called the ‘&lt;a href=&quot;https://ct.counseling.org/2019/12/positive-actions-to-prevent-the-holiday-blues/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;holiday blues&lt;/a&gt;,’ which are feelings of anxiety and depression that occur during the holidays. These feelings impact a person’s enjoyment of a holiday in a variety of negative ways, which may make them feel even worse. How does someone get these feelings, though? Is there a way to get rid of them? How is the current pandemic impacting the holiday blues, if at all?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People may experience the holiday blues for a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mayoclinic.org/healthy-lifestyle/stress-management/in-depth/stress/art-20047544&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;variety of reasons&lt;/a&gt;, some of which include cooking that needs to be done, decorations that need to be bought, outfits that need to be coordinated, people that need to be seen, among many more. A person also may not be able to celebrate with family, and thus may &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.healthline.com/health/depression/holidays&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;compare themselves to others&lt;/a&gt; and feel as if they barely have anyone to be festive with as a result. All of these factors can cause a person to feel bad during the holiday season, which, as mentioned before, may lead to guilt for not enjoying a holiday. This only causes the holiday blues to become stronger. It is, effectively, a never-ending cycle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/january/mentalHealthTwo.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This picture illustrates some of the most common feelings of someone going through the ‘holiday blues.’ &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.thefamuanonline.com/2020/12/05/how-to-cope-with-a-mental-illness-during-the-holidays/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(The Flinn Foundation)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
As the picture at the top of this article illustrates, quite a large number of people experience holiday blues. This makes it so this issue has a sense of universality to it, as it seems like people from all walks of life can get the holiday blues. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.mcleanhospital.org/essential/mcleans-guide-managing-mental-health-around-holidays&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;American Psychological Association&lt;/a&gt; conducted a survey asking people about how they feel during the holiday season. Around 38% of people surveyed said their stress increased during the holiday seasons, which shows how prominent this issue really is. In a strange way, remembering you are not alone in feeling this way may actually be very encouraging and helpful when it comes to not letting these feelings get to you. Knowing that there are others experiencing the same things you are can be reaffirming and comforting, even if the context behind why you are getting these emotional boosts can feel upsetting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It is obvious that holiday blues is a problem, so how can you go about handling it? What else can you do besides remembering you are not alone? There are a &lt;a href=&quot;https://churchandmentalhealth.com/holiday-blues-infographic/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;variety of ways&lt;/a&gt;, including getting light exercise, trying to stick to your normal schedule as much as possible, eating in moderation, trying to set reasonable goals and making a budget when it comes to buying presents. It also helps to remind yourself how holidays are only temporary and that they will be over soon enough. The way you are feeling right now is not here to stay! Just because you experienced the holiday blues before does not necessarily mean you will experience them again later.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, COVID-19 is its own problem when it comes to the holiday blues. Usually, people seem to get the holiday blues because they might feel as if &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.huffpost.com/entry/therapist-predict-holidays-mental-health_l_5fca573ec5b6787f2a977639&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;they are not doing enough&lt;/a&gt; to celebrate the holidays, or they are comparing themselves to other families and seeing how happy those families are. With the pandemic, people might get the holiday blues because they cannot see their families at all in the first place. They may want participate in the holiday festivities, but sadly cannot due to what is going on in the world. This puts a spin on how the holiday blues usually occur, and there is sadly no real solution to combat this specific problem. All people can do is remain safe and hope that next year’s holidays will not be like 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with the mindset that holidays blues is only temporary, it seems like the issue itself often repeats. It certainly helps that it only happens during holidays, but there is no proper way to get rid of the holiday blues once and for all. Every person is different, and a person who was unhappy during Christmas one year can be over the moon the next year. It seems to be based on context, which is why it is important for someone experiencing these types of feelings to do whatever they can to not let their holiday experience be ruined. If it does become very difficult to deal with, the option of calling a mental health professional is always available. There are ways to combat your holiday blues, as long as you try to be as proactive as possible and not let these feelings overwhelm you before you get the chance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sacmag.com/health/curing-the-holiday-blues/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Sacramento Magazine)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Omar Dajani&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Omar Dajani, an international student from Palestine, is currently a sophomore at Fullerton College. He used to be an English major but changed into a Computer Science major not too long ago. He enjoys gaming, blogging, journaling, meditating, and going on walks. He intends on transferring to UC Berkeley for Fall 2021. Currently learning Python, HTML, and CSS.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Omar Dajani</name></author><summary type="html">Holidays and mental health Omar Dajani. 01/01/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/mentalHealthCover.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/january/mentalHealthCover.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Boyan Slat and the ocean cleanup</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/24/boyan-slat-and-the-ocean-dump.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Boyan Slat and the ocean cleanup" /><published>2020-12-24T16:00:01-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-24T16:00:01-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/24/boyan-slat-and-the-ocean-dump</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/24/boyan-slat-and-the-ocean-dump.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Boyan Slat and the ocean cleanup&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sydney Hollingsworth. 12/25/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/boyanSlatOne.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Boyan Slat addresses the media in Vancouver on Dec. 12, 2019.
(Jason Payne)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Covering 70% of the Earth’s surface and containing 50 to 80% of life as we know it, the ocean is our most valuable resource, but it is in danger. Although the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencehistory.org/the-history-and-future-of-plastics&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Science History Institute&lt;/a&gt; reports observations of plastic pollution as early as the 1960s, the threat of irreversible damage due to pollution has become increasingly obvious in the past decade.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Every year, over eight million tons of plastics enter the ocean and wreak havoc on marine life. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.noaa.gov/education/resource-collections/ocean-coasts/ocean-pollution&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration&lt;/a&gt; (NOAA), plastics of all sizes can be deadly. Large, floating tangles of netting and trash can trap sea creatures or provide transportation for invasive species across the ocean. Smaller pieces can wrap around animals or be confused for food. Over time, plastics may seem to break down, but in reality, they only break apart into tiny pieces. These microplastics absorb harmful chemicals and are often mistaken for plankton by predators and make their way up the food chain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eventually, the ocean plastics accumulate in one of the world’s five massive rotating current systems called gyres. Once they’ve reached the gyres, the plastics form patches of concentrated debris. The most famous is the Great Pacific Garbage Patch which covers nearly 1.6 million square kilometers, or three times the size of France.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how can we remove these mini-continent-sized garbage patches? This question is being asked by scientists everywhere and is especially important to young people, who believe if a solution is not found soon, the damages will haunt them for the rest of their lives and generations to come.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most notable young people in ocean conservation is 26-year-old Boyan Slat from the Netherlands. His non-profit, &lt;a href=&quot;https://theoceancleanup.com/about/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Ocean Cleanup&lt;/a&gt;, aims to remove 50% of the Great Pacific Garbage Patch over the course of five years and nearly all ocean plastics by 2050, much sooner than previously predicted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slat’s plan is unique in that it cleans the ocean directly by removing trash from the garbage patches rather than focusing on prevention or coastal cleanups. In a 2012 &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ROW9F-c0kIQ&amp;amp;list=WL&amp;amp;index=3&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;TED Talk&lt;/a&gt;, Slat, just 18 years old at the time, explained his plan.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He attributed his inspiration for his plan to a scuba diving trip in Greece two years earlier when he noticed more plastic in the water than fish. Later, as a school project, he and a friend pulled fine, mesh netting through ocean water and spun the nets’ contents in a centrifuge to separate plankton from microplastics. In doing this, Slat found a simple, efficient way to safely remove tiny pieces of plastic from the ocean without harming the smallest of marine life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slat’s new discoveries turned his attention to the ocean’s five polluted gyres; with the help of professors from the University of Delft, Utrecht and Hawaii, he estimated there would be 7.25 million tons of plastics in the surface layers of the gyres alone by 2020.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Previous removal plans required boats with nets to capture floating trash and were far too expensive to be practical. Slat proposed a design with several strategically placed, floating platforms, anchored to the seafloor, with nets suspended between them. The design would use the gyres’ own currents to push the plastic into the nets, removing an estimated 55 shipping containers of trash a day.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In an interview with &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=qQQffhWdihs&amp;amp;list=WL&amp;amp;index=4&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;NowThis News&lt;/a&gt;, Slat shared how he executed his plan. In 2013, he left the University of Delft, to start The Ocean Cleanup. With only 300 euros and no sponsors, his plan seemed impossible, but with the help of crowdfunding, Slat was able to launch the largest scale plastic cleanup ever attempted.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first challenge Slat and his team faced was the complex design of the anchor lines needed to attach the platforms to the seafloor, five kilometers below. The proposed systems were complicated and required too many lines to be cost effective. The team was ready to quit when two interns suggested a drifting design. The new plan was drastically different and involved several smaller systems scattered throughout the patch that would use wind and waves to move towards larger concentrations of plastics.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Ocean Cleanup released their first system (001) into the Pacific in September of 2018, and after extensive durability testing, released System 001/B in June of 2019. Slat hopes to have System 002 ready by 2021 and would like to refine the design further before launching a total of 60 systems to tackle the Great Pacific Garbage Patch.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The organization has since started a new line of sunglasses made from the collected plastics and sells them on their website to fund the continuation of the cleanup.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slat and his team’s newest project focuses on removing plastics before they can reach the ocean in the first place. Appropriately named the Interceptor, this system intercepts trash in rivers before they enter the ocean. The Ocean Cleanup has identified a total of 1,000 rivers responsible for 80% of ocean plastics. The system is positioned on the side of the river that the current pushes towards, collecting floating debris while still allowing boats to pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Slat’s discoveries and inventions have opened a world of possibilities to save the ocean from permanent plastic pollution. What started as an idea of a 16-year-old high school student has grown into a global project. Slat continues to push the boundaries of ocean cleaning technology while inspiring young scientists everywhere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (USA Today)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Sydney Hollingsworth&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sydney Hollingsworth</name></author><summary type="html">Boyan Slat and the ocean cleanup Sydney Hollingsworth. 12/25/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/boyanSlatCover.jpeg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/boyanSlatCover.jpeg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The secret to learning a language</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/24/secret-to-learning-a-language.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The secret to learning a language" /><published>2020-12-24T16:00:01-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-24T16:00:01-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/24/secret-to-learning-a-language</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/24/secret-to-learning-a-language.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The secret to learning a language&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Reagan Smith. 12/25/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/learningLanguageOne.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Languages can all be connected to one another utilizing a “tree” as a visual representation. From here, we can see how the Romance languages, Spanish, Portuguese, Italian, French, and Catalan, as well as other minor ones, stem from the same branch. &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/swlh/towards-a-larger-view-of-information-architecture-2a7bd6ebafb7&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Medium)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
There’s no doubt that in today’s fast paced, multicultural, connected world, it’s beneficial to know more than one language. Over half the world– estimated to be between 60 and 75%– speak at least two languages, according to Gaia Vince from BBC’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/future/article/20160811-the-amazing-benefits-of-being-bilingual&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Future&lt;/a&gt;. In fact, our brains have evolved to understand multiple languages, to look for clues and to decipher foreign words we have seldom encountered. Language is a complex combination of sounds and symbols that all come together to represent a group of people connected by culture, and, if one follows the signs, they can unlock a world of understanding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Latin is a unique language to learn because it is no longer spoken, only written and read. We can trace thousands of our words back to their Latin roots and witness the long-lasting presence of the Romans in our governmental structure, art and literature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This brings me to today, where I sat down with Latin teacher Dr. Jeffrey Feland, a faculty member of Sage Hill School in Newport, CA. He works with students in Latin classes one through four, runs the Junior Classical League, a club that participates in annual challenges and competitions and is a favorite amongst the students. A common theme that emerged from our interview was how important patterns are to a language, and he explained how seeing them helped him excel in his learning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Reagan Smith&lt;/b&gt;: So starting off, how many languages do you know, and what are they?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Jeffrey Feland&lt;/b&gt;: Well, I would say I know Latin and Ancient Greek, but I’ve never had to speak to others in them. Then, I can understand, read and speak Spanish and know basic conversational Italian, French and German. I feel fairly fluent in modern Greek– but then of course that brings up the question of how to define “fluency.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;RS&lt;/b&gt;: Of course. So in total, that’s eight languages, including English, obviously. Wow, that’s a lot. How did you begin learning your first foreign language, and what pushed you to become fluent?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;JF&lt;/b&gt;: At the end of your 7th-grade year, your teacher can recommend you to take high-school classes during the summer before 8th grade, and there was the option for Algebra 1 and Spanish 1. Now I only got the recommendation to do Algebra 1, and I went to my language arts teacher in 7th grade, being the precocious 12 year old I was, and asked why I didn’t get a recommendation to do Spanish 1, even though I had A’s in her class. She told me to my face that she didn’t feel that my English skills were strong enough and that I would never be good at a foreign language, in her opinion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;RS&lt;/b&gt;: That’s shocking, considering you now know eight languages.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;JF&lt;/b&gt;: Yes, I was stunned, and I didn’t know how to respond, so I just assumed that she was right, coming from a place of authority. Eventually, during freshman year I was in my Spanish 1 class. I remember feeling pretty disoriented the first month in that class, but then one day I looked at everything on the page and thought, “This is just patterns. I can just repeat patterns and rules again and again.” Spanish is a pretty straightforward language, so if you learn the rules for it and how the sounds change, you can predict words you’ve never heard before. I started teaching myself all fourteen verb tenses, and on the back of my tests, I would take a random verb and conjugate it into a chart that would take up the whole piece of paper. My teacher finally asked me, “who taught you this; why are you in Spanish 1– this is, like, everything.” I said to her, “I just figured it was patterns.” They moved me up to Spanish 2, where I had the highest grade in the class, and I decided I had one thing left to do freshman year, which was to revisit my 7th grade language teacher. I told her, “Remember how you told me Spanish 1 would be really hard for me and I would struggle? Well, that first month was pretty hard, but then something clicked, they moved me up to Spanish 2, and I’m acing every test. I wanted to tell you to never tell another student they would be bad at a foreign language because that is not how to encourage a student.” Everybody can do a foreign language, you just have to have the right teacher.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;RS&lt;/b&gt;: Where did you go from there, a freshman in Spanish 2?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;JF&lt;/b&gt;: I did Spanish 3 and 4 sophomore year, and because my school didn’t offer AP Spanish, I taught it to myself in the library with a tape recorder and got a four on the AP test. I then taught myself French, since it’s related to Spanish and there’s some overlap, and senior year I was helping French 4 students with their homework because they just couldn’t see the patterns. Still, somehow I graduated as a math-science person and planned on majoring in biochemical engineering at UC Davis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;RS&lt;/b&gt;: So how did you get into the linguistic route in life?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;JF&lt;/b&gt;: I took a class in Latin and Greek roots in medical vocabulary, to help me become a doctor. I loved the course and the teacher, I could recognize the roots, and I saw how the words changed. Then, I decided to switch to a classics major and double in English, with a focus on creative writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;RS&lt;/b&gt;: Have you come up with some patterns that help you organize the various Romance languages you’ve learned over the years?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;JF&lt;/b&gt;: So, I enjoy following the etymology of words and seeing how they change from Latin to French to English, because of course, French was the official language of England when they conquered the land. The hard c in Latin turns into a soft c in French and then turns into a “ch” in English. One of my favorites is the words “carus” and “ergos” in Latin, which mean “hand” and “work” respectively. They come together to mean “work of the hand.” French takes this and has the word “chirurgie,” and this translates to “surgery” in English. It blew my mind that you could still see it in a way if you took the patterns and identified them. There’s sound, places where things have softened or simplified, and, of course, dealing with word families, where you can take a root word and learn all related words and paths to learn a huge section of words.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;RS&lt;/b&gt;: Do you have any guidelines or a general process for learning a language? What has been the most helpful?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;JF&lt;/b&gt;: I always say to learn the verbs first, because those are the words of action. You can identify the patterns, see when the action is happening, see who’s doing the action. That’s essential, especially with Romance languages. Once you’ve mastered the verbs, it’s really a matter of some grammatical constructions, the subjunctive mood and vocabulary. Verbs are just so central to a language because if you can understand the action of the sentence, you can understand what other words are coming into play and can add on and play with it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;RS&lt;/b&gt;: As a teacher, you teach new students Latin every year.  What is the difference between learning a language and teaching a language?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;JF&lt;/b&gt;: When you start teaching to someone else, you really learn it. The two [learning and teaching] are aligned. When you learn a language, you sometimes become your own teacher; you learn what your strengths and challenges are.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a teacher, I try to demystify the language and be as straightforward and honest, now that I’m on the far end of the spectrum of knowing the language. It’s a language: it’s complicated and there are lots of moving pieces. This is where my scientific brain comes into play, where I try to make it “x plus y equals z” and find rules and patterns to follow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;RS&lt;/b&gt;: What do you think has been the most helpful language to know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;JF&lt;/b&gt;: Latin- it gives us two-thirds of our English vocabulary, and about 90% of our technical vocabulary (science, math, medicine, legal system and government). It is so foundational and so important to English, so knowing those greatly opens up your English ability. English is a weird and important juncture of languages– heavily influenced by French and taking vocabulary from the Latin family– which is what makes it so difficult but also what gives it huge flexibility and creativity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://culturesconnection.com/translating-history-why-you-should-learn-latin/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Cultures Connection)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/Reagan_Smith.jpeg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Reagan Smith&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Reagan is a junior from Sage Hill School. She is passionate about all things related to science, especially biology and medicine. She also loves being able to use her talents and knowledge to help others and make a difference in the world.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Reagan Smith</name></author><summary type="html">The secret to learning a language Reagan Smith. 12/25/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/learningLanguageCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/learningLanguageCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Dark energy: Summarized</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/24/dark-energy-summarized.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Dark energy: Summarized" /><published>2020-12-24T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-24T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/24/dark-energy-summarized</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/24/dark-energy-summarized.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Dark energy: Summarized&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Teddy Rosenthal. 12/25/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/darkEnergyOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This image depicts the cosmic microwave background. (Wikipedia)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Intergalactic Repulsion&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
First, let’s take a look at how we know that the universe is expanding. In 1925, American astronomer Edwin Hubble saw that galaxies that were farther away from Earth emitted light with spectral lines that had shifted towards the red end of the electromagnetic spectrum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This phenomenon is now known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.space.com/25732-redshift-blueshift.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;redshift&lt;/a&gt;, where light waves experience the &lt;a href=&quot;https://imagine.gsfc.nasa.gov/features/yba/M31_velocity/spectrum/doppler_more.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Doppler effect&lt;/a&gt;. Light takes longer to reach the Earth when the object emitting the light is moving away from the Earth. Since the light takes a longer time to reach a certain point, the waves appear longer because they are stretched out. If these galaxies appeared to be redshifted from Earth, that meant that they were moving away from Earth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In 1929, Hubble was able to study the rate at which galaxies travel by observing a direct proportionality between a galaxy’s distance and the velocity at which it travels away from us (as shown in the image down below). This is summarized in &lt;a href=&quot;https://courses.lumenlearning.com/astronomy/chapter/the-expanding-universe/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Hubble’s Law&lt;/a&gt;, v=Hd, where ‘v’ is velocity, ‘H’ is the Hubble constant and ‘d’ is the distance of a galaxy. This law is used to calculate the velocity of any galaxy given its distance, or vice versa.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/darkEnergyTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;http://hosting.astro.cornell.edu/academics/courses/astro201/hubbles_law.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Cornell)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;An Expanding Universe&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
A similar pattern to the repulse between galaxies is shown in atoms or molecules filling a vacuum. The law that governs this principle is known as entropy and it causes particles to fill in a space until the system is homogeneous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It can then be deduced that galaxies are moving away from each other to fill some sort of empty space. The fact that galaxies are moving away from one another must mean there is a background force acting as some repulsive form of gravity that causes space itself to expand.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The term ‘dark energy’ was conceived in 1998, as a way to refer to this phenomenon. In 1915, Albert Einstein published his paper on his general theory of relativity, and with it, his field equations. His equations were supposed to find a link between the geometry of spacetime and the mass density of the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/darkEnergyThree.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The diagrams show the expansion rate in relation to time for each possible shape of space. &lt;a href=&quot;https://heasarc.gsfc.nasa.gov/docs/cgro/epo/brochures/new_win/nw3.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(NASA)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
In 1917, Einstein decided to add a value known as the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.scholarpedia.org/article/Cosmological_constant&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;cosmological constant&lt;/a&gt;, ‘Λ,’ to his equation. It would assume that the universe is static and not expanding. Its value was set to 0 by Einstein but later repurposed with a new value that would represent the newly observed expansion and acceleration of the universe. A simple rearrangement of the constant (moving it from one side of the equation to the other) turned it from a geometric value to a contribution to the total mass density of the universe. This means that the cosmological constant represents something that exists and is now understood as the simplest and most coherent realization of dark energy. It is used in Einstein’s field equation to predict its own effect on the universe.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Energy in Empty Space&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How does dark energy affect our understanding of the universe?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since it is understood that there is energy residing in empty space between particles and in outer space, the cosmological constant has a positive value. The energy in empty space is also recognized by quantum theory as vacuum energy and is represented by the cosmological constant.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Vacuum or dark energy takes up 70% of the composition of the universe, meaning that its value is significant alongside the density of the matter, dark matter and radiation in the universe. Since it is also used in Einstein’s field equation (which is used to predict the geometry of the universe given the total energy density and the cosmological constant), there must have been dramatic changes in the accepted geometry as the cosmological constant gained positive value.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this is true, predictions were made involving the needed mass and energy for the universe to be flat (in 3-dimensions where space can be understood as vast amounts of adjacent cubes of space and where parallel lines never cross), which requires the total energy to equate to the integer ‘1,’ and the predicted energy constant of dark energy allows it to equal one.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, many predictions have been made to explain the shape of the universe, and the existence of dark energy presently supports the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=7ImvlS8PLIo&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;theory of a flat universe&lt;/a&gt;, though nothing is certain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Substantial mysteries involving dark energy are still yet to be answered. One such example is the density of dark energy in any given region remaining constant over time, even though its density should be decreasing similar to matter and radiation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite scientists working day and night to solve the obscurity of this “anti-gravity,” all that is known is the existence of dark energy, which will determine the future of the universe and humanity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/darkEnergyFour.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The pie chart shows the composition of the universe. &lt;a href=&quot;https://wmap.gsfc.nasa.gov/universe/uni_matter.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(NASA)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nbcnews.com/mach/science/what-dark-energy-ncna1061206&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(NBC News)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Teddy Rosenthal&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Teddy is a sophomore at Westlake High School who enjoys learning about math and science related topics. Through InterSTEM, Teddy's goal is to spread knowledge of the most interesting STEM topics in hopes to popularize science. He also enjoys music, wrestling, and hiking.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Teddy Rosenthal</name></author><summary type="html">Dark energy: Summarized Teddy Rosenthal. 12/25/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/darkEnergyCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/darkEnergyCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Science behind cryptids</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/17/science-behind-cryptids.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Science behind cryptids" /><published>2020-12-17T16:00:00-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-17T16:00:00-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/17/science-behind-cryptids</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/17/science-behind-cryptids.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Science behind cryptids&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Omar Dajani. 12/18/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/cryptidsOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This image displays a variety of cryptids, some of which you may be familiar with. (Edge of Orion)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
If you are an American, you likely have heard the name “Bigfoot” here and there in addition  to the names “Yeti” and “Loch-ness Monster.” All three of these names correspond to “cryptids,”  which are monsters that apparently roam our world. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalgeographic.com/news/2013/9/130907-cryptid-crytozoology-bigfoot-loch-yeti-monster-abominable-science/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Geographic&lt;/a&gt;, science has had a long battle with the existence of these monsters, due to the circumstantial evidence documenting their existence. Such evidence, which includes blurry pictures, strange footprints and eyewitness reports, is not enough for scientists to confirm their existence. While both factions are at war with each other, it is safe to say that science is the clear winner. Even so, the lore behind these cryptids and how they tie into the human psyche is interesting.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some examples of cryptids were listed above, but it is important to know exactly what they are. Donald R. Prothero, a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalgeographic.com/news/2013/9/130907-cryptid-crytozoology-bigfoot-loch-yeti-monster-abominable-science/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;paleontologist&lt;/a&gt; who has written over 250 scientific reports, including a  book discussing cryptids, defined them as “any animal that has never been described by science,  usually something very unusual along the lines of a Loch Ness monster or Bigfoot, something that  stretches the limits of what is scientifically plausible.” Prothero’s definition helps us understand that these cryptids cannot exist, as they seem to stretch what is scientifically possible within our world.  Daniel Loxton, Prothero’s partner who helped him write the aforementioned book, added on to his definition, stating “It’s based on the word cryptozoology, which means hidden life or animals. It  implies a creature that’s been recorded through folklore, something that we have reason to suspect  exists.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All that being said, how can science help us understand the world of cryptozoology more?  First, for cryptids to exist, there cannot only be one cryptid of that species. Basically, Bigfoot is an offspring of other Bigfoot. The “monster” did not come into existence out of nowhere. The same goes for the other variety of cryptids. Speaking of which, the second way science can help us understand cryptids more is by their size. Many cryptids, such as giant squids and giant okapi, are abnormally large in size, so how is it possible that they have not been recently sighted at all? How would it be possible for them to avoid the public eye for as long as they have? Technology has been rapidly improving each year, making it so that finding these types of creatures should be no problem as of this point in time. The third and final way science can help us understand cryptids is not actually directly related to science itself, but rather the folklore and myths of old. In these stories, a lot of animals, such as bears, would exhibit human-like characteristics. People who know of these folklore stories and myths, upon seeing a weird looking bear, might not realize it is just a bear and think it is something more mystical as a result of these old stories. This is a solid example of the complexities of the human psyche and is also why it is important to take people’s eye-witness reports with a  grain of salt. Our senses (especially that of sight) can sometimes fool us into thinking we saw something mysterious when it was but a mere shadow of some normal animal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/cryptidsTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;An image displaying a variety of information on cryptids, with the standout info being that of how
big some of the cryptids are. This ties directly into the previous point of them being too large to not notice. (Paranormal Encounters)&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
With all the above, it is quite obvious that cryptids are not actually real. Why then do some people still practice cryptozoology? Well, some think that by studying the stories and urban legends behind monsters like the Flat-Woods Monster, &lt;a href=&quot;https://cosmosmagazine.com/society/science-history-the-weird-world-of-cryptozoology/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;they are conserving parts of Earth’s history&lt;/a&gt;.  Regardless of whether or not these monsters are real, the tales behind them and their sightings are definitely quite interesting, which is why these cryptozoologists want to make sure the legends never die out and are always available for people to be fascinated by and ponder about.  Cryptozoology is also important as it might highlight humanity’s curiosity about the natural world.  Even then, it is important to note that some monsters who were labeled as cryptids at one point turned out to be actual real-life animals. Animals such as the platypus, manatee, okapi, and even
gorillas were all thought to be, at one point or another, mythological beasts. Might be hard to believe or imagine, but it is the truth. People disregarded their existence until it was made clear that the stories were not mere fiction, which led to the animals being scientifically recognized as real species with due time. The platypus especially has had a long and rough history with whether or not it was actually a real animal, with it finally being confirmed and scientifically recognized in the year 1799. With this piece of information, maybe creatures like the Yeti, Ningen, and even mermaids do actually exist after-all. It just might be that their discovery is around the corner and that they too will soon be scientifically recognized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Storenvy)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Omar Dajani&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Omar Dajani, an international student from Palestine, is currently a sophomore at Fullerton College. He used to be an English major but changed into a Computer Science major not too long ago. He enjoys gaming, blogging, journaling, meditating, and going on walks. He intends on transferring to UC Berkeley for Fall 2021. Currently learning Python, HTML, and CSS.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Omar Dajani</name></author><summary type="html">Science behind cryptids Omar Dajani. 12/18/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/cryptidsCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/cryptidsCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Cravings and connections</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/10/cravings-and-connections.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Cravings and connections" /><published>2020-12-10T16:00:05-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-10T16:00:05-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/10/cravings-and-connections</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/10/cravings-and-connections.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Cravings and connections&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Carly Schinhofen. 12/11/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/cravingsOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Groundbreaking research shows humans’ innate desire for connections with others is surprisingly similar to hunger cravings.  
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.uri.edu/features/neuroscience/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(The University of Rhode Island)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Just as hungry brains crave food, lonely brains crave people, new research suggests. This interesting connection between the two types of deprivation is increasingly important as COVID-19 isolates us all, demonstrating how social distancing can have detrimental effects on our lonely brains.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Livia Tomova and her team at MIT created an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41593-020-00742-z&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;experiment&lt;/a&gt; to test the cognitive response to cravings. Participants volunteered to go without food for 10 hours so Tomova could determine which nerve cells responded to the need for food. Certain neurotransmitters became excited at the sight of junk food, and the neurons subsequently released dopamine as a positive reaction. This happy chemical is released frequently as a type of reward for the human brain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Based on this initial segment of the experiment, Tomova wanted to test exactly how the brain responds to social deprivation, and how it differed from food deprivation. The same subjects were placed in a room entirely alone for 10 hours. After the isolation time ended, Tomova exposed the subjects to pictures of people and social gatherings. The subjects’ brains were immediately activated and produced dopamine, the same chemical that indicates a reward. In other words, they responded almost identically to the need for food as to the need for human contacts, indicating a fundamental connection between the two necessities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For some subjects, the loneliness was more difficult, and this was reflected in their neural response to the hours of isolation. Others reported that the experience was not nearly as challenging for them, as it reflected their daily lifestyle. Therefore, environmental impacts such as general isolation or loneliness throughout life can make a human brain more accustomed to the feeling, thus not feeling much of a reward when exposed to social situations. Similarly, people tolerate hunger differently, since some generally have a greater tolerance for pain, which can come from a lack of food. They may feel the hunger on varying degrees, in the same way they experience loneliness, so people should remember that everyone’s circumstances in COVID-19 are inconsistent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A thought to keep in mind, however, is that those who have stronger wills to combat suffering may still be in pain, although it may not be obvious to others. During COVID-19, all people should still receive empathy for the loneliness they may be feeling, since they can still be hurting at the same degree as those that express their feelings more. It is important to remember that a coping mechanism for many is to push their struggles deep inside and ignore that something is missing in their lives, which may give others the illusion that they are unaffected by these times.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The physiological connection between the need for food and social interactions demonstrates how humans’ brains react similarly when we are deprived of certain needs that our bodies require. Tomova’s experiment reflects how people’s brains are different from those of other individuals and therefore have varying responses to isolation. But overall, the deprivation of social connections can have an adverse effect on the brain as dopamine is an essential chemical to positive mental health.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Tomova stressed the importance of being understanding in our current time, as isolation can put mental and physical health at stake, so everyone should respect the situations of others, as isolation impacts everyone in various ways.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Denison)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Carly Schinhofen&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Carly is a junior at Woodbridge High School. She is intrigued by biology and geology, and aspires to hold a career in science. Through her platform, she hopes to help others pursue their love for STEM. In her free time, she enjoys playing volleyball and trips to the beach.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Carly Schinhofen</name></author><summary type="html">Cravings and connections Carly Schinhofen. 12/11/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/cravingsCover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/cravingsCover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Invisible bruises: PTSD</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/10/invisible-bruises-ptsd.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Invisible bruises: PTSD" /><published>2020-12-10T16:00:04-08:00</published><updated>2020-12-10T16:00:04-08:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2020/12/10/invisible-bruises-ptsd</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2020/12/10/invisible-bruises-ptsd.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Invisible bruises: PTSD&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Joan Joe. 12/11/2020&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/ptsdOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The graphic above depicts several symptoms of PTSD.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newstartrecoverysolutions.com/what-is-ptsd/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(New Start Recovery Solutions)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Introduction&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Post-traumatic stress disorder (PTSD) is an anxiety disorder that develops after a traumatic experience. A certain trigger after the incident may cause a person to recall the horrifying event, which in turn may cause them to become distant with those they once were close to. Everything from a mugging, threats, scarring incidents, robbery, and natural catastrophes can be a traumatic experience. Depression and drug misuse also exacerbate the condition. Different individuals encounter novel experiences that are more traumatic than others. This makes it difficult to precisely determine what particular event is traumatic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the period from just after the traumatic incident to six months later, acute stress disorder occurs. PTSD begins at the six-month mark and persists thereafter. However, not all trauma patients develop PTSD immediately following exposure. Some individuals respond rapidly to traumatic exposure, while others remain unscathed only to experience the sudden onset of PTSD symptoms months or years later. Flashbacks, extreme anxiety and uncontrollable thoughts about the incident can all be symptoms.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;PTSD Amongst Veterans&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We have seen a dramatic rise in the &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/25077185/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;number of Iraq and Afghanistan war veterans&lt;/a&gt; seeking help for PTSD over the past few years, shining a spotlight on this chronic condition and posing crucial questions about adequate treatment services and care barriers. At any given point, the disorder affects millions: about 8% of individuals in the United States will experience it at some point in their lives. Military veterans are extremely vulnerable: 20% of those who served in Iraq and Afghanistan returned home with PTSD or depression. And since the year 2000, over 350,000 service members have been diagnosed with traumatic brain injury, many of whom have cognitive or behavioral disabilities. The alarming suicide rate among veterans is a testament to psychic wounds that linger long after the war ends: 20 end their lives every day.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/ptsdTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This graph shows the percent of war veterans suffering from mental disorders.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/figure/Prevalence-of-veterans-self-reported-postdeployment-driving-difficulties-by-clinical_fig1_51784252&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Research Gate)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;b&gt;Impacts of Mental Trauma on Memory and the Brain&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Abuse of children and other causes of severe stress may have permanent effects on the areas of the brain involved in memory and emotion. In particular, the hippocampus appears to be very stress-sensitive. Not only will stress damage to the hippocampus cause difficulty in coping with memories and other consequences of prior traumatic events, but it can also hinder new learning. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK3874/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Research&lt;/a&gt; has shown that as part of its regular function, the hippocampus can regenerate nerve cells, but stress impairs the process by preventing or slowing down the regeneration of neurons.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/ptsdThree.png&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The hippocampus (in blue) is shown within the context of the brain.
(Wikipedia)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/253494116_The_Invisible_Epidemic_Post-Traumatic_Stress_Disorder_Memory_and_the_Brain&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A study&lt;/a&gt; was carried out to see whether the symptoms of PTSD matched the observable loss of neurons in the hippocampus. Vietnam war veterans with declaratory memory issues caused by PTSD were first tested. These war veterans were found to have an 8% decrease in right hippocampal volume, assessed with magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) and brain imaging. However, there were no changes in other areas of the brain.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/ptsdFour.png&quot; width=&quot;40%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The MRI scans are of the Vietnam war veterans who have declaratory memory issues.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.researchgate.net/publication/253494116_The_Invisible_Epidemic_Post-Traumatic_Stress_Disorder_Memory_and_the_Brain&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Research gate)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The study found that reduced right hippocampal volume was associated with short-term memory loss in patients with PTSD. When looking at PTSD patients who were victims of physical or sexual assault during their childhood, similar findings were observed. According to more recent studies that have reported hippocampal volume reduction in PTSD, these studies also indicate that the reduction in hippocampal volume is unique to PTSD and is not correlated with conditions such as anxiety or panic disorders.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Damage to the hippocampus, following exposure to the strain brought on by childhood abuse, results in distortion and fragmentation of memories. In linking and arranging various aspects of memory, the hippocampus plays an important role and is assumed to be responsible for locating the memory of an occurrence in its proper time, place and context.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For example, if a person was a victim of childhood abuse due to alcohol and was locked away in a closet of old clothes, he or she may only remember the smell of alcohol or that of the old clothes, but not the part about having been locked in the closet. He or she may experience a sudden flashback or have a panic attack when the smell of alcohol hits them. Psychotherapy (talk therapy) or an experience that causes similar feelings will help the patient rebuild memories in these situations.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another significant area is the amygdala, a region of the brain involved in associative learning, value encoding and emotional responses. PTSD symptom intensity can be independently predicted by both smaller amygdala volume and less reliable monitoring of the negative value of face stimuli (negative surprises in the environment) in the amygdala.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nimh.nih.gov/news/science-news/2019/brain-biomarkers-could-help-identify-those-at-risk-of-severe-ptsd.shtml&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;A study&lt;/a&gt; conducted by Daniela Schiller, Ph.D. and Ilan Harpaz-Rotem, Ph.D. on combat veterans offered the conclusion that the severity of PTSD symptoms is mirrored in how combat veterans react to negative external shocks when the anticipated results are not as planned, and how the way the brain is tuned to these stimuli is different.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/ptsdFive.png&quot; width=&quot;20%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The regions of interest (functionally defined amygdala) used in the study of computational imaging are shown in red.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nimh.nih.gov/news/science-news/2019/brain-biomarkers-could-help-identify-those-at-risk-of-severe-ptsd.shtml&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(NCBI)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Variations between those with or without PTSD were also shown in other brain regions involved that are related to danger learning, such as the striatum (a part that coordinates multiple aspects of cognition) and the dorsal anterior cingulate cortex (a brain region that subserves cognition and motor control).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Treatments&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To minimize symptoms and improve function, having appropriate care after the development of PTSD symptoms may be crucial. The ideal PTSD treatment, which is secure, safe, fast-acting and has minimal side effects, has been elusive. And, as with many mental health conditions, patients often have difficulty embracing or adhering to any of the available solutions. For years, the military department and healthcare experts have sought a range of options for effective treatment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rti.org/impact/stellate-ganglion-block-new-treatment-ptsd#:~:text=SGB%20is%20a%20true%20breakthrough,a%20deterrent%20to%20seeking%20treatment&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;One of the recent procedures&lt;/a&gt; is the stellate ganglion block (SGB) procedure, which was discovered to be effective in the fall of 2019. The operation involves injecting the stellate ganglion with a local anesthetic. This community of neck nerve cells helps control the “fight or flight” function of the body. Some military medical facilities started offering this treatment to PTSD patients in the early 2010s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As the SGB procedure was studied by more researchers and patients, the results appeared positive. But the proof of its efficacy was still required by the medical community. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rti.org/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;RTI International&lt;/a&gt;, a nonprofit research institution, launched a randomized, controlled SGB trial in 2014, and gave an official report by the end of 2019. A suggested reason for the sustained efficacy of SGB on PTSD, as well as the effects of hot flashes and complex regional pain syndrome, is that local anesthetic application to the stellate ganglion contributes to a decrease in the growth factor of the nerve and subsequently, a decrease in the amount of sympathetic nerve sprouting and norepinephrine.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2020/december/ptsdSix.png&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The diagram above illustrates the stellate ganglion.
(Anatomy of the Human Body)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Psychotherapy and drugs that are short- and long-term will also treat PTSD well. Sometimes, the two types of treatment are more successful together.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another way of treating PTSD is by using &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cognitive_processing_therapy&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Cognitive Processing Therapy (CPT)&lt;/a&gt;. It is a particular method of cognitive-behavioral therapy that has been effective in minimizing PTSD symptoms. Over 12 hours, CPT is administered; the process helps patients learn how to question and change harmful trauma-related assumptions. In doing so, the patient develops a new perception and conceptualization of the traumatic incident so that its ongoing detrimental effects on current life are minimized.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exposure to a traumatic stimulus is another method of intervention widely used to help people confront fears in cognitive-behavioral therapy. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.apa.org/ptsd-guideline/treatments/prolonged-exposure&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Prolonged exposure (PE)&lt;/a&gt; is a special form of cognitive-behavioral therapy that helps people gradually handle memories, emotions and circumstances relevant to their trauma. Most individuals try to stop something that reminds them of the trauma they have endured, but their anxiety is intensified by doing so. An individual may minimize PTSD symptoms by consciously learning that the memories and signs related to trauma are not dangerous and do not need to be prevented by confronting what has been avoided.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Concerning physical treatment, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webmd.com/drugs/2/drug-6969-9095/paroxetine-oral/paroxetine-oral/details&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;paroxetine&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webmd.com/drugs/2/drug-1/sertraline-oral/details&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;sertraline&lt;/a&gt; are the only drugs to have been approved by the FDA for treating PTSD. Since different people react to drugs differently, and not everyone’s PTSD is the same, the doctor can also prescribe other “off label” medicines, meaning that the manufacturers of those medicines have not requested the FDA to review drug trials proving the drug is specifically effective for PTSD. These may include &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.webmd.com/depression/guide/depression-medications-antidepressants&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;antidepressants&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monoamine_oxidase_inhibitor&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;monoamine oxidase inhibitors&lt;/a&gt; (MAOIs), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/books/NBK519503/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;antipsychotics or second-generation antipsychotics&lt;/a&gt; (SGAs), &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medicalnewstoday.com/articles/173068&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;beta-blockers&lt;/a&gt; or &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medicinenet.com/benzodiazepines_sleep-inducing-oral/article.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;benzodiazepines&lt;/a&gt;. Medications do not remove the symptoms, but they may make them more manageable by decreasing their severity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The National PTSD Center provides self-help resources, including the PTSD Coach Online app and the &lt;a href=&quot;https://mobile.va.gov/app/ptsd-coach&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;PTSD Coach app&lt;/a&gt;. These provide therapy to deal with depression, anxiety and other symptoms that can be formed by people who have been through trauma. When PTSD patients feel depressed, the apps can help them relax, boost their mood, teach them how to solve tough issues and help change their thought patterns.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Taking Action&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;An individual who is subjected to a traumatic event may feel powerless, causing a concerned partner to take action to assist them. Perhaps the most effective approach is being there for the person, showing acceptance and concern, and listening without being judgmental or providing advice. It is necessary to promote healthy living, such as adherence to the diet, exercise and refraining from smoking and excessive alcohol use. Arranging fun recreational activities is another way to help those with PTSD live a happier and more relaxed life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.health.harvard.edu/mind-and-mood/how-to-recover-from-post-traumatic-stress-disorder&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Harvard Health Publishing)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Joan Joe&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Joan is a freshman in St. Antony’s Public School, India. She is intrigued by psychology and neuroscience and aspires to join research in neuroscience and STEM-related works. She hopes to help others pursue their passion for STEM through her platform. In her free time, she plays the piano, sings, and loves to read Dan Brown’s books.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Joan Joe</name></author><summary type="html">Invisible bruises: PTSD Joan Joe. 12/11/2020</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/ptsdCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/ptsdCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>