<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-06-25T01:05:51-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">InterSTEM</title><entry><title type="html">Can carbon recapture technology be a realistic solution to the climate crisis?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/12/can-carbon-recapture-technology-be-a-realistic-solution-to-the-climate-crisis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can carbon recapture technology be a realistic solution to the climate crisis?" /><published>2021-06-12T17:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2021-06-12T17:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/06/12/can-carbon-recapture-technology-be-a-realistic-solution-to-the-climate-crisis</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/12/can-carbon-recapture-technology-be-a-realistic-solution-to-the-climate-crisis.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Can carbon recapture technology be a realistic solution to the climate crisis?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catherine Todd. 06/13/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might not think about it often, but the original carbon capturers were trees and plants. For millennia, the world was kept in balance by the emittance of carbon dioxide by humans and the absorption of it by plants. Only during the Industrial Revolution did we stray from this model. Burning coal, natural gas and petroleum put unprecedented levels of toxins and greenhouse gases, like carbon dioxide, into the air. For a long time, people did not understand the huge impact emissions would have on the world. Even after they did, it was ignored for decades and some still ignore it. Even if we reach net-zero Earth, there will still a long period of time before plants can absorb all of this carbon dioxide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here comes the idea for carbon recapture technology. If we are able to “grab” the carbon dioxide from the air and redeposit it into the ground where it was stored for years in the form of fossil fuels, then we will be able to save the Earth from the climate crisis. Unfortunately, it is not that simple. The technology has been around since the 1970s, but it has not really taken off. These days we hear about solar, hydro, wind and other forms of clean energy, but carbon recapture is often not in the conversation. However, to be fair, Elon Musk recently tweeted about giving 100 million dollars to carbon recapture technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, the financial problem of carbon recapture technology persists. The financial incentive for a company to fund an expensive process to remove carbon dioxide from the atmosphere and place it back into the ground does not exist. Why fund a company that removes carbon from the air in an expensive way rather than one that releases it with no immediate consequence? Maybe with more regulation and costs associated with releasing carbon dioxide, the financial incentive to support carbon recapture technology will grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime though, carbon recapture technology continues to get better. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2021/01/31/carbon-capture-technology.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Berend Smit on CNBC&lt;/a&gt; says he is trying a new technology that involves carbon dioxide flowing through a sponge with chemicals that latch onto the carbon dioxide in the air and when it is heated Carbon Dioxide can be separated from the sponge and sent to storage underground. With this technology, carbon recapture will be able to be more freestanding and mobile, so it will require less machinery. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2021/01/31/carbon-capture-technology.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;According to Paitoon Tontiwachwuthikul&lt;/a&gt;, this new innovation could cost up to 70%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/june/carbonOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This infographic displays how many carbon recapture technologies aim to make a profit. They capture CO2 but then synthesize it into more fuel. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/science-environment-47638586&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Carbon Engineering)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Another factor to consider is how necessary recapture technology really is. Many people argue that trees are the only recapture technology we need and that we should plant more trees anyway. However, trees require a lot of resources, including water, which is in short supply in many places in the world. They also take time to grow, as well as a lot of land. Additionally, trees are already being cut down at a large rate in places such as the Amazon rainforest. There is no way to replenish trees at the rate they are killed and also plant enough to make a meaningful difference concerning the amount of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When speaking about these solutions, it is always imperative to mention that reducing fossil fuel consumption is still necessary to reduce greenhouse gas levels. Carbon recapture technology cannot be another ‘save the turtles by not using a plastic straw’ movement. Companies should not feel that they have no obligation to use green energy even if they employ carbon recapture tactics. It is too easy for someone to say that we can continue to use fossil fuels at our current levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, we have been polluting the Earth for some time now, and in order to make a positive impact on the environment, we need negative emissions, not zero emissions. Carbon recapture technology is certainly part of that, but definitely not all. This negative emission world would require the usage of solar energy, hydroelectricity, wind power and many more types of renewable energy. Maybe if this climate threat was taken more seriously earlier on, a more mild solution, such as removing carbon dioxide from the atmosphere, could be possible. Alas, we currently have 415 ppm of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere, versus the 280 ppm before the Industrial Revolution. We must recognize that no one thing can fix the problem that we have. Even though carbon recapture technology is great, it must be accompanied by appropriate policy, social change and renewable energy solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (IEEE Spectrum)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Catherine Todd&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Catherine Todd</name></author><summary type="html">Can carbon recapture technology be a realistic solution to the climate crisis? Catherine Todd. 06/13/2021 You might not think about it often, but the original carbon capturers were trees and plants. For millennia, the world was kept in balance by the emittance of carbon dioxide by humans and the absorption of it by plants. Only during the Industrial Revolution did we stray from this model. Burning coal, natural gas and petroleum put unprecedented levels of toxins and greenhouse gases, like carbon dioxide, into the air. For a long time, people did not understand the huge impact emissions would have on the world. Even after they did, it was ignored for decades and some still ignore it. Even if we reach net-zero Earth, there will still a long period of time before plants can absorb all of this carbon dioxide.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/june/carbonCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/june/carbonCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The neurochemistry behind school failure or how to stop procrastinating 101</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/12/the-neurochemistry-behind-school-failure-or-how-to-stop-procrastinating.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The neurochemistry behind school failure or how to stop procrastinating 101" /><published>2021-06-12T17:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2021-06-12T17:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/06/12/the-neurochemistry-behind-school-failure-or-how-to-stop-procrastinating</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/12/the-neurochemistry-behind-school-failure-or-how-to-stop-procrastinating.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The neurochemistry behind school failure or how to stop procrastinating 101&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vova Prylepa. 06/13/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/june/neurochemOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
This image taken explains how our brain interprets long-term tasks and the cognitive process that initiates procrastination. &lt;a href=&quot;https://thenextweb.com/news/brain-freeze-science-procrastination-smart-brains&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(The Next Web)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
First comes your homework, then your project, then the test and even the final exam— nothing and no one can escape the all-powerful, all-engulfing black hole of procrastination. Many people whose school performance is affected by procrastination tend to believe that they procrastinate for a variety of reasons: they believe they’re not good enough to complete or understand a specific task, they’re too lazy, or they think there’s a subconscious mechanism that maximizes their productivity under pressure. However, all of these statements are but a mere illusion— you are capable enough to finish that history project on time or to ace that biology test. Sometimes, the fact that you procrastinate isn’t even your fault, but one of the very deceptive neurotransmitters that control your impulsive decision-making: dopamine. By understanding the neurochemistry that reigns over the parts of the brain that makes us make these bad decisions, the ones that bring bitter, long-term consequences but so, so sweet short-term rewards, we can better understand procrastination, to eventually battle it and win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a start, we will divide our brain into many parts, but we’ll concentrate on the ones that are the most relevant to the neurochemistry of procrastination: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://nesslabs.com/neuroscience-of-procrastination&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;prefrontal system and the limbic system&lt;/a&gt;. The prefrontal system is the little brother of the limbic system. It is far weaker when it comes to its influence on our decision-making skills when being compared to the limbic system. The prefrontal system is responsible for the various ways in which we express our identity and our personality, for the planning of multiplex behaviors, reason and logic, while the limbic system is responsible for automatic, impulsive decisions in situations that are considered life-threatening or dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/age-of-awareness/from-procrastination-to-motivation-manipulating-dopamine-9c1a345b9bda&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dopamine’s&lt;/a&gt; role is (and has always been) to make us repeat certain behavior patterns that are likely to guarantee our survival or reproduction, dating back to the times where we ran after animals with sharp sticks. When we did a certain thing that resulted in us getting a better chance at survival or reproduction, a certain dose of dopamine would be delivered to our brain which would make us feel rewarded, relaxed and pleasured. For instance, when we eat, our brain rewards us with dopamine as consuming food is equivalent to survival. Therefore, since our brain is addicted to dopamine, it will automatically— almost unnoticeably—  make us do the thing that will give us the higher dosage of dopamine, based on the predicted or experienced plausibility of an activity delivering dopamine to the brain, and thus to make us survive and reproduce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, when it comes to our complex human society, this dopamine dosage technique also applies to the satisfaction of other social needs (money, status, public perception, etc) and other human needs (i.e. entertainment) rather than our primal needs. In order to make us procrastinate, our brains make the decision (mostly using our limbic system) to choose an activity that would maximize the dopamine, or the immediate reward, as opposed to the activity that has better long-term consequences, as the quantity of dopamine that’s received by the brain from the said activity is uncertain. More precisely, the limbic system contains the amygdala, which is a part of our brain that produces a powerful &lt;a href=&quot;https://thenextweb.com/news/brain-freeze-science-procrastination-smart-brains&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;emotional response&lt;/a&gt;: a fight (resistance) or flight (ignorance) reaction to a difficult/long-term task. That effect is created by the production of norepinephrine (causing fear and anxiety) and even adrenaline, similarly to a reaction produced to a life-threatening situation except that now, the only thing threatened is your comfort zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amygdala plays a more important part in our rationale, as it takes 1/32 of a second to send its chemical signal, as opposed to the three seconds take by the prefrontal system to generate a well-evaluated, rational thought. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://thenextweb.com/news/brain-freeze-science-procrastination-smart-brains&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;amygdala is simply faster&lt;/a&gt;, so we listen to it more when making a decision. Essentially, this reaction with norepinephrine is simply a way for our brain to avoid a task low in immediate dopamine to take part in an activity that guarantees a dopamine release in the shortest delays. This explains the fact that you are more drawn to play Angry Birds than to do your chemistry homework— although your prefrontal system knows that in the long run, the chemistry homework will benefit you more and might bring you dopamine (pleasure) if you do it right, the limbic system, the more dominant one, will make you strive for the more immediate and certain reward, the one that requires less effort and time to get that desired dopamine dosage. That dreaded homework, on the other hand, will get postponed to a later date, and then an even later one until it sinks into oblivion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To combat this, we need to rewire our brains into thinking of long-term tasks as the ones that bring the most dopamine (pleasure), and not the most norepinephrine/adrenaline (fight-flight response) for the victory in the fight against procrastination. Here are a few mental techniques that would allow you to do that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1: &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.neurogistics.com/index.php/dopamine/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Create an environment that’s conducive to focus and work&lt;/a&gt;. By eliminating all kinds of distractions around you, such as putting your phone away, cleaning your work desk from useless items and closing all kinds of unimportant tabs on your computer, you take away all kinds of short-term sources of dopamine, leaving only long-term sources of dopamine (like working on a project or studying for a test) to your brain. This way, by leaving it no choice, your brain is obliged to choose the only potential source of dopamine available, even though the amygdala is telling it that the levels of dopamine brought by this activity are uncertain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inc.com/kevin-daum/this-is-why-you-procrastinate-heres-what-to-do-about-it.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Set small goals and divide a big assignment into a series of smaller ones and set up a reward structure&lt;/a&gt;. The brain cannot tolerate any activities that don’t bring dopamine any soon, the amygdala making our focus shift to more rewarding activities. However, if we divide a task into smaller parts, which we do during set periods of time and get rewarded after that certain period of time, the amygdala considers each small part of that big task as a short-term source of dopamine. Thus our limbic and prefrontal cortex work in conjunction to guarantee the completion of the said long-term task, bit by bit. One method to use is the Pomodoro method, where one has to work for 25 minutes and take a short break after each work period, rewarding him or herself with a snack, a walk or simply a series of stretching exercises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3: Don’t be afraid to start and ask questions. People often procrastinate because they are too intimidated by a specific task or are too afraid to ask their teachers, supervisor, colleagues or friends about something they don’t understand, so they just never start. Just blindly starting a task without overthinking it would allow you to procrastinate far less. In fact, if you don’t know how to approach a specific activity, you can use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inc.com/jeff-haden/neuroscience-says-your-brain-is-wired-to-procrastinate-4-simple-ways-to-stop-putting-off-important-things-willpower-not-required.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the five minutes rule:&lt;/a&gt; you’ll have to invest yourself into something for only five minutes, but you’ll have to do it thoroughly. It would allow your cognitive muscles to warm up and after five minutes, you’ll lose your fear of the task and keep doing it almost automatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, don’t forget that when you procrastinate, you exchange potential big future rewards for smaller, futile pleasures. Some things just can’t be done tomorrow, and the best time to start them is today and now. Don’t be your dopamine’s slave— you can seek help for procrastination issues and no one will judge you for it. It is by disciplining your brain that you will be able to reach anything you want in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Tiny Buddha)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Vova Prylepa&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Vova Prylepa</name></author><summary type="html">The neurochemistry behind school failure or how to stop procrastinating 101 Vova Prylepa. 06/13/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/june/neurochemCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/june/neurochemCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">“Mixing and matching” COVID-19 vaccines</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/28/mixing-and-matching-covid-19-vaccines.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Mixing and matching” COVID-19 vaccines" /><published>2021-05-28T17:00:03-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-28T17:00:03-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/05/28/mixing-and-matching-covid-19-vaccines</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/28/mixing-and-matching-covid-19-vaccines.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;&quot;Mixing and matching&quot; COVID-19 vaccines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rachel Huang. 05/29/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/may/vaccineOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
“Mixing” vaccines may boost our immunity against COVID-19. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.clinicaltrialsarena.com/analysis/covid-19-vaccine-mixing-the-good-the-bad-and-the-uncertain/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Clinical Trials Arena)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The COVID-19 pandemic has lasted for over a year now, and many different brands of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/vaccines/different-vaccines.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;vaccines&lt;/a&gt; have been created in response to the coronavirus, such as the Pfizer-BioNTech, Moderna, Oxford-AstraZeneca and Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson vaccines. Even though not federally approved yet, the idea of mixing and matching these vaccines is gaining popularity as there is significant evidence that doing so strengthens the immune system. This “mix and match” method of administering vaccines can also be referred to as heterologous vaccination, which means that an individual receives one type of vaccine for their first shot and then another type for their second shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To better understand how this mixing approach utilizes different “types” of shots to strengthen the immune system, a brief overview of the human immune system is necessary. The human immune system has two main lines of defense: antibodies and T cells. Antibodies are proteins made by the immune system that bind to virus particles and “deactivate” them before they can infect any cells. T cells get rid of cells that have already been infected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most vaccines currently focus on the antibody line of the immune system and something on the coronavirus’ surface called a spike protein. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.technologyreview.com/2021/05/06/1024640/why-mixing-vaccines-could-help-boost-immunity/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;spike protein&lt;/a&gt; is what defines the coronavirus, so if your body is able to recognize the spike protein, it is able to recognize the coronavirus. The Pfizer and Moderna vaccines deliver &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/vaccines/different-vaccines/mrna.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;mRNA&lt;/a&gt;, a set of instructions for the cell, to the ribosomes, where the cells can then recreate the spike protein. After the spike protein is completed, the body is able to recognize that the spike protein is a foreign object and starts building up a memory-like response to it with antibodies. On the other hand, Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson and Oxford-AstraZeneca notify the cell about the coronavirus’ spike protein by delivering another virus (an adenovirus) that has the spike protein “hidden” on it. The problem with using this Trojan horse-like contraption is that the immune system builds up immunity to the delivery molecule, in this case the adenovirus, which means that subsequent vaccinations will be less effective. Regardless of how they transfer the spike protein to our immune systems and the relative efficacy of their methods, the Pfizer, Moderna, Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson and Astra-Zeneca vaccines all protect our immune systems from their coronavirus by focusing on getting our cells to recognize the coronavirus’ spike protein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/may/vaccineTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
The coronavirus’ spike protein is located on the exterior of the cell like a nametag that lets other cells recognize it. The instructions for the spike protein are found in the RNA in the coronavirus’ nucleus.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sfchronicle.com/projects/2021/coronavirus-vaccines-explainer/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(SF Chronicle)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with focusing on the spike protein is that viruses are constantly changing through mutation, and there are at least five &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/variants/variant.html?CDC_AA_refVal=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.cdc.gov%2Fcoronavirus%2F2019-ncov%2Ftransmission%2Fvariant.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;variants&lt;/a&gt; of the coronavirus in the United States right now with modified spike proteins that may be unrecognizable to current vaccines. Here, the “mix and match” approach to administering vaccines comes into play, where Professor Shan Lu, the pioneer of this strategy, says that the mechanism of combining shots is where the first shot a person receives addresses the spike protein via antibodies, while the second shot rallies your T cells. Current plans to get the T cells’ “attention” center around adding another protein to the coronavirus, or using one that is already present like a nucleoprotein to boost T cell response. This additional protein will act as a name tag that T cells will be better able to recognize and respond to, increasing the number of T cells and antibodies in the cell due to the increased number of targets on the coronavirus. Together, T cells and antibodies will double the efficacy of our immune systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States, China, the United Kingdom, Spain and Russia have already begun human trials testing this mix and match method where participants receive the first dose of say, Pfizer, and then the second shot of Moderna. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2021/05/05/993882203/giving-2-doses-of-different-covid-19-vaccine-could-boost-immune-response&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gritstone&lt;/a&gt;, a company in California, has made it its mission to design two different vaccines that are made to be given together, instead of using two different brands of vaccines. Gritstone’s CEO, &lt;a href=&quot;https://abc13.com/covid-vaccine-pfizer-moderna-astrazeneca/10591350/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Andrew Allen&lt;/a&gt;, says that their approach may be able to “give recipients the best of both worlds [antibodies and T cells]!” and Phase 1 human clinical trials have also recently begun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This mix and match method of administering vaccines is especially appealing from a scientific standpoint, especially for lower income countries that have less accessibility to vaccines. With heterologous vaccination, these countries will be able to continue administering vaccines even if one vaccine’s supply runs low or health concerns about a brand of vaccine arise. For people who worry about the safety of combining shots, “there is no danger in mixing vaccines,” Professor of Immunology at London School of Hygiene and Tropical medicine Helen Fletcher said. In fact, it may be more beneficial for patients with other diseases like MS and cancer whose antibody aspect of their immune systems have been weakened by their treatments. With bountiful scientific evidence proving that “mixing and matching” vaccines is beneficial for our immune systems, we can only hope that global and national authorities will quickly approve this strategy in order to strengthen us in our united fight against COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nbcnews.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(NBC)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Rachel Huang&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Rachel Huang</name></author><summary type="html">&quot;Mixing and matching&quot; COVID-19 vaccines Rachel Huang. 05/29/2021 “Mixing” vaccines may boost our immunity against COVID-19. (Clinical Trials Arena)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/may/vaccineCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/may/vaccineCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Artificial intelligence: Approach with caution</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/28/artificial-intelligence-approach-with-caution.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Artificial intelligence: Approach with caution" /><published>2021-05-28T17:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-28T17:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/05/28/artificial-intelligence-approach-with-caution</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/28/artificial-intelligence-approach-with-caution.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Artificial intelligence: Approach with caution&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yana Karapetyan. 05/29/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/may/artificialOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
This image depicts a futuristic autonomous vehicle. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.istockphoto.com/search/2/image?phrase=autonomous+car&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(iStock)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Tesla, Waymo and Zoox have all become household names in the market of driverless cars. These companies claim that &lt;a href=&quot;http://cyberlaw.stanford.edu/blog/2013/12/human-error-cause-vehicle-crashes&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;inattention and human error&lt;/a&gt; are responsible for the majority of automobile accidents. By removing the possibility of driver mistakes, they hope that their use of artificial intelligence technologies will improve road conditions and help save lives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, these intentions alone are not enough to introduce self-driving cars into the automotive market. First, companies must perform extensive testing across a variety of road conditions. Multiple cities across the United States have become testing sites for autonomous vehicles, including the fifth most populous city in the nation, Phoenix.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While there is general curiosity and enthusiasm surrounding driverless car technologies, not everyone shares the excitement. Many autonomous cars and their testers have become the subject of attacks. Some residents in testing cities have slashed tires, threatened self-driving car passengers with violence and even tried to run the cars off of the road.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Arizona has particularly been impacted by these attacks. In March of 2018, an Uber autonomous vehicle struck and killed a pedestrian in Tempe. In response to this incident, Uber’s driverless cars were banned from testing in the entire state. Since then, many residents have continued to hold even more cautious attitudes toward self-driving vehicles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While Uber no longer tests its autonomous vehicles in Phoenix, Waymo has rushed in to fill the gap. Similarly, Waymo vehicle supervisors have faced &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2018/12/31/us/waymo-self-driving-cars-arizona-attacks.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;violent threats&lt;/a&gt;, such as a local man waving a .22-caliber revolver at a Waymo vehicle and the emergency backup driver at the wheel. When questioned by police, the man said that he “despises” driverless cars, citing the incident of a pedestrian being killed by a self-driving car Uber car in 2018.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Companies with a vested interest in the use of artificial intelligence for the automotive industry often use their desire to make the road a safer place as their driving force behind developing this technology. Tesla, for instance, asserts that its technologies, such as a forward-facing radar with enhanced processing, provides the ability to see through difficult road conditions such as heavy rain, fog and dust.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, the self-driving car project is an ambitious one. Self-driving cars and their inability to process information the way that humans do concerns many who could potentially be sharing much more of the road with them. Additionally, the reluctance to welcome autonomous vehicles is not solely based on fear and past negative experiences. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.fleetowner.com/industry-perspectives/trucks-at-work/article/21702198/americans-remain-reluctant-regarding-autonomous-vehicles#:~:text=Conducted%20as%20part%20of%20its,car%20they%20drive%20reflects%20their&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;survey conducted by Ipsos&lt;/a&gt; that polled 21,000 adults across 28 countries about the acceptance of autonomous vehicles found that nearly one in four Americans reported that they would never use a self-driving vehicle.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ipsos noted that part of this reluctance is linked to the identity of classic car culture in the United States; six in ten surveyed identified themselves as “car people”. Ipsos had also found hints of a coming car-culture clash, coupled with disagreements on whether the government should regulate this niche market.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A full introduction of fully autonomous vehicles onto American roadways will trigger a litany of legal questions. Dean Kamen, an American engineer best known for his invention of the Segway, once said “Every once in a while, a new technology, an old problem and a big idea turn into an innovation.” Applying Kamen’s argument to this legal conundrum leaves us with two legal arguments: the old problem here is human error in driving causing casualties and the innovative solution is using artificial intelligence to reduce casualties in driving. However, our innovative solution begs the question of how this freshly emerging technology, with little legal precedent to compare to, will be regulated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.istockphoto.com/search/2/image?phrase=autonomous+car&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(iStock)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Yana Karapetyan&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Yana Karapetyan</name></author><summary type="html">Artificial intelligence: Approach with caution Yana Karapetyan. 05/29/2021 This image depicts a futuristic autonomous vehicle. (iStock)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/may/artificialCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/may/artificialCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Does infinity exist?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/28/does-infinity-exist.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Does infinity exist?" /><published>2021-05-28T17:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-28T17:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/05/28/does-infinity-exist</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/28/does-infinity-exist.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Does infinity exist?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dhruvi Shukla. 05/29/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/may/infinityOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
Georg Cantor created many theorems relating to the mathematical infinity.  (OpenMind BBVA)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Infinity. A value without limit. This concept created the law of continuity and allowed people to understand black holes, land rovers to mars, create new mathematical theorems and study the moon. Each discovery mentioned above comes from a different field in STEM. This is because there are three different types of infinities - the mathematical, the physical and the metaphysical. It is because of this that answering this question becomes more complicated. In this article, we’ll take an in-depth look into the mathematical infinities and see whether they exist or not.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;During the late 19th century, the question of mathematical infinity arose in mathematician Georg Cantor’s mind, and he began investigating this idea. Through his extensive research, he discovered that there are many kinds of infinities in math, some larger than others. If all infinities were to be separated into groups, they would be &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=elvOZm0d4H0&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;countable infinities and uncountable infinities&lt;/a&gt;. He started by writing a sequence of numbers; let’s say, for example, that the even numbers are in one-to-one correspondence with another sequence within the real number system. By doing this, he found that the countable infinities are actually smaller than the uncountable infinities (also known as the continuum). This finding led to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/science/continuum-hypothesis&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;continuum theory&lt;/a&gt;, which mathematicians are unable to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ias.edu/ideas/2011/kennedy-continuum-hypothesis&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;disprove or solve&lt;/a&gt; even now. You may be asking how there could be infinities smaller than other infinities? So, to understand this, let’s take some whole numbers and even numbers in one-to-one correspondence; in other words, we are pairing up one whole number with an even. It should look something like this.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1→2
2→4
3→6
4→8
5→10&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For simplicity’s sake, we will use numbers in chronological order. Cantor states that if we were to continue doing this infinitely, every whole number being paired up with an even number. This is strange to think about since there should be half as many even numbers as the whole, but when we are counting both numbers up to infinity, that stops being the case. Cantor continued using this method to research infinities and found various countable infinities until he started using irrational numbers. Even if he paired irrational numbers with another sequence of real numbers, he would still not be able to include every irrational number. In the exercise (above), it is safe to assume that if we went until infinity, we would be able to have all whole numbers paired with all even numbers. But this is not the case for irrational numbers. Repeating the exercise with irrational numbers will look something like this (remember this doesn’t need to be in chronological order):&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1→3.14159265…
2→0.70710678…
3→1.41421356…
4→2.44989743…
5→2.13417805…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now let’s imagine that we continue the pattern until infinity; we have all the whole and irrational values possible. Cantor states that there will still be irrational numbers which we will not find in our infinite list. To find this number for our list, circle all the numbers in your list in diagonals like so:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/may/infinityTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;20%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now write all these numbers down as a new irrational number like so:
0.10487…
Now, add one to all these numbers like this:
0.21598…
If we had an infinite list and used the method explained above for all the numbers in the list, we would have created a number that could not be found in the infinite list since one number from every number was changed. We see here what Cantor saw before concluding that there are infinities that are larger and smaller than one another; however, both infinities are still just ∞, and if we are to differentiate them, new axioms or equations that express the difference in these infinities must be created. It was Cantor’s theorem of the set theory, the continuum and the countable infinities that separated mathematical and physical infinities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When news of these infinities came to Galileo Galileo and Kurt Gödel, they began playing around with Cantor’s Theorem themselves. Galileo later founded &lt;a href=&quot;https://decodedscience.org/the-paradox-of-the-infinite-series-of-square-numbers-by-galileo/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Galileo’s Paradox&lt;/a&gt; and Gödel later created &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=la6BK5X2LI8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gödel’s incompleteness theorem&lt;/a&gt;. Galileo believed that having a less, greater or equal value only applies to number sets that are finite and not infinite. So using his paradox, we would state that “whether there are more irrational numbers than whole numbers, both infinite sets are neither greater, equal or less than each other”. However, Cantor believed this paradox was flawed and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.britannica.com/science/Cantors-theorem&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;constructed a framework&lt;/a&gt; in which it is possible to compare countable infinities with one another and uncountable infinities with one another.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Infinities do exist, but in the mathematical system, there is not just one type of infinity but more than one with different sizes. However, it is important to remember that mathematical infinities are completely different from physical and metaphysical infinities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (OpenMind BBVA)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Dhruvi Shukla&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Dhruvi Shukla</name></author><summary type="html">Does infinity exist? Dhruvi Shukla. 05/29/2021 Georg Cantor created many theorems relating to the mathematical infinity. (OpenMind BBVA)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/may/infinityCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/may/infinityCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The discovery of exoplanets</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/24/the-discovery-of-exoplanets.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The discovery of exoplanets" /><published>2021-05-24T17:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-24T17:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/05/24/the-discovery-of-exoplanets</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/24/the-discovery-of-exoplanets.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The discovery of exoplanets&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tania Firouzabady. 05/25/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/may/exoplanetsOne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
Above is an illustration of an exoplanet.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://exoplanets.nasa.gov/news/1418/nasa-to-host-news-conference-on-discovery-beyond-our-solar-system/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(NASA)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
On Jan. 9, 1992, scientists discovered the first exoplanet, or rather, two exoplanets orbiting the pulsar PSR 1257+12. The finding paved the path for the discovery of over 4,000 new exoplanets in the next few decades.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Exoplanets are planets that orbit stars outside the solar system. While the majority orbit other stars, some are free-floating, or rogue, planets. Measuring their size and mass allows astronomers to determine their compositions, which range from solid rock to gas. These properties are remarkably similar to those of regular planets.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The elements that make up exoplanets are also much like those that comprise planets in our solar system, though current technology is not yet advanced enough to directly determine the specific compositions. Instead, scientists rely on the elemental abundance in nearby stars. Specifically, they use a method called stellar spectroscopy, where they observe the interactions between light and the elements contained within a star’s upper layers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After the initial discovery of exoplanets by radio astronomers Aleksander Wolszczan and Dale Frail, NASA has used the Kepler Space Telescope and various techniques to discover thousands more. One such method is the wobble, or radial velocity, method, which, according to NASA, “measures changes in a star’s ‘radial velocity.’ The wavelengths of starlight are alternatively squeezed and stretched as a star moves slightly closer, then slightly farther away.” This method was used to discover an exoplanet about half the size of Jupiter in 1995. The gas giant moved in a very fast four-day orbit around its parent star. This irregular wobbling movement was detected by telescopes on Earth, prompting the development of the wobble method.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the process of exoplanet hunting may have been slow at first, the Kepler telescope made it much faster. &lt;a href=&quot;https://exoplanets.nasa.gov/discovery/how-we-find-and-characterize/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;NASA&lt;/a&gt; describes how “Kepler settled into an Earth-trailing orbit, then fixed its gaze on a small patch of sky… Within that small patch were 150,000 stars.” This discovery was vital for the development of the transit method, which allows astronomers to determine a planet’s orbital size and the star’s mass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, there are four classifications for exoplanets: Gas giant, super-Earth, Neptunian and Terrestrial. Gas giants are large planets primarily composed of gas, much like the name suggests. Super-Earths are mainly composed of rock but are much larger than Earth. Neptunian exoplanets are about the size of the planet Neptune and are also mostly composed of gas. Lastly, Terrestrial exoplanets are rocky planets similar to Earth, Mars, Mercury and Venus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One of the most promising features of exoplanets is that some may contain water or ice. As water is a key aspect of life, its presence could support the ability for life to exist on exoplanets. To better understand this, it’s important to discuss the concept of habitability, the quality of supporting life. In order to be habitable, a planet must have specific features, including temperature, chemical makeup, radiation level, oxygen and water (or an equivalent life-supporting substance).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/may/exoplanetsTwo.jpg&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
In the image above, there are planets outside and within the habitable zone based on their distance from the star.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/nasa-tess-telescope-finds-nearby-super-earth-sub-neptunes-2019-7&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Business Insider)&lt;/a&gt;  
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The search for habitable planets is an important one, and recent developments are helping scientists move a step closer. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.americanscientist.org/article/big-data-on-exoplanet-composition&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;American Scientist&lt;/a&gt;, astrophysicist Natalie Hinkel built “a publicly available database, called the Hypatia Catalog, to help researchers explore this deeper aspect of habitability.” Hinkel and her colleagues have recently modeled the TRAPPIST-1 system. Within the system, three of the planets are located in what is called a “habitable zone”, or region around a star that is the right temperature to allow liquid water to exist. Hinkel explains, “as the Hypatia Catalogue grows, it should become an increasingly valuable scientific resource.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One recent exoplanet development includes the discovery of a potentially habitable planet resembling Earth. This was announced on April 15, 2020, by NASA and the SETI Institute. Called Kepler-1649c, the planet is 300 light-years away from Earth and almost the same size. Not only does it orbit in the habitable zone of its star, but its temperatures are hypothesized to be very similar to Earth’s, further supporting its potential to support life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another crucial development was announced on the same day: Proxima Centauri b, an even larger exoplanet, was spotted orbiting a star nearest to the sun. As stated by &lt;a href=&quot;https://earthsky.org/space/exoplanets-kepler-1649c-proxima-centauri-c-nasa-seti-institute-sphere-vlt/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;EarthSky&lt;/a&gt;, “What’s puzzling is that the possible planet appears significantly brighter than it should. If the brightness was entirely from the light reflected off the planet itself, then the planet would be about five times larger than Jupiter. But its estimated mass is more similar to Neptune’s.” This unexpected finding has led scientists to postulate that Proxima Centauri b has a ring system, which would greatly increase its size but have a negligible effect on its mass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Both Kepler-1649c and Proxima Centauri b are evidence that there is still much to discover in the universe, and exoplanets may be a key piece to the puzzle. While a lot of progress has been made with regards to exoplanet discovery, there are still infinitely many questions left unanswered. Perhaps scientists will even discover an exoplanet harboring life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://exoplanets.nasa.gov/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(NASA)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Tania Firouzabady&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Tania Firouzabady </name></author><summary type="html">The discovery of exoplanets Tania Firouzabady. 05/25/2021 Above is an illustration of an exoplanet. (NASA)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/may/exoplanetsCover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/may/exoplanetsCover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Discrimination in STEM fields: Current racial and ethnic issues in the STEM work industry</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/14/discrimination-in-stem-fields.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Discrimination in STEM fields: Current racial and ethnic issues in the STEM work industry" /><published>2021-05-14T17:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-14T17:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/05/14/discrimination-in-stem-fields</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/14/discrimination-in-stem-fields.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Discrimination in STEM fields: Current racial and ethnic issues in the STEM work industry&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Caleb Izaguirre. 05/15/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Race and gender disparities remain a significant challenge in STEM industries and the future of the American workforce. Among STEM workers, African Americans are centerpoint for concerns that there is too little attention paid to increasing racial and ethnic diversity; their high experience with issues with diversity in the workforce is constantly met with failure.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this regard, blacks working in STEM jobs share a lot in common with Asian Americans, and to a lesser extent with Hispanic residents who are all less likely than whites in such jobs to believe that members of their own communities can achieve promotions and awards.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most blacks in these positions believe major underlying factors prevent involvement in STEM fields such as limited access to high-quality education, recruitment discrimination and a lack of encouragement to pursue these careers from an early age.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Most Americans see racial and ethnic diversity in the workplace as important&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Americans not only place a level of importance on diversity in the workplace, but these views extend to race and ethnicity as well. Eight-in-ten Americans say it is important to have diversity in all workplaces, recognizing that it is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewresearch.org/social-trends/2018/01/09/blacks-in-stem-jobs-are-especially-concerned-about-diversity-and-discrimination-in-the-workplace/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“extremely” or “very important.”&lt;/a&gt; In comparison, less than 10% find racial and ethnic diversity to be “not too” or “not at all important.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When asked which are valid reasons for increasing racial and ethnic diversity in the workplace, 45% of adults say it provides unique perspectives that contribute to overall business goals, while the same number says it gives many the equal opportunity to succeed. A smaller share believes that it creates a larger American workforce which in turn helps the national economy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Large public support for racial and ethnic diversity in the workplace is relevant with recent polls which emphasize traditional value reform. For example, a 2017 Pew Research Center report found that most Americans believe an increasing number of different worker racial groups, ethnic groups and nationalities in the U.S. makes the nation a safer and better place to live in.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;African Americans in the STEM workforce stress workplace diversity&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The majority of white, black, Hispanic and Asian STEM employees see racial and ethnic diversity in the workplace as somewhat critical, but there are wide differences in their areas of importance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Blacks are more likely to say racial and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.blackenterprise.com/64-of-blacks-say-racism-and-discrimination-are-issues-at-their-workplace/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;ethnic diversity in the workplace is extremely or very important&lt;/a&gt; than their white co-workers. Sentiments on this particular topic among Hispanic and Asian employees typically sway the unique culture of a company. This has come under heavy scrutiny by the public.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this forecast, STEM employees look similar to other job positions. Blacks and Hispanics in non-STEM careers similarly believe that they are more likely than whites in such jobs to believe that these ideals are very important in their careers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Racial, ethnic and gender pay gaps are still large&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Black and Hispanic workers remain widely underrepresented while representation varies for women according to new reports, efforts to promote equity and equality still have a long way to go.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/may/discriminationOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.insidehighered.com/news/2019/06/07/new-study-finds-discrimination-against-women-and-racial-minorities-hiring-sciences&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Inside Higher Ed)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pewresearch.org/social-trends/2018/01/09/blacks-in-stem-jobs-are-especially-concerned-about-diversity-and-discrimination-in-the-workplace/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Pew Research&lt;/a&gt;, the typical woman’s salary from 2017 to 2019 in STEM was about 75% of a man’s salary. That gap narrowed from 70% in 2016, but it was still wider than the pay gap in the overall workforce with women earning 80% of male salary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Racial and ethnic disparities in STEM salaries have also widened in recent years. Black STEM professionals typically earned, at most, 80% of white workers’ earnings from 2017 to 2019 — down from 82% in 2016. And average pay for Hispanic professionals in STEM was 83% of white earnings — down from 85% in that very year. Meanwhile, Asian professionals rose by 2%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Looking Ahead&lt;b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Pew findings are not surprising, but understanding why the numbers are where they are is even more important.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The barriers to entering STEM are very different for each group, but many underprivileged groups have to work through the adversity of the gamut of limited education and lack of STEM role models in local communities.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Early-career, student-led nonprofit movements like InterSTEM are not backing down and are instead empowering young students. These actions are aimed to help underprivileged children achieve their potential and will help create a more diverse and accepting workforce of the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newscientist.com/article/mg25033331-400-discrimination-is-still-a-problem-in-stem/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(New Scientist)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Caleb Izaguirre&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Caleb Izaguirre</name></author><summary type="html">Discrimination in STEM fields: Current racial and ethnic issues in the STEM work industry Caleb Izaguirre. 05/15/2021 Race and gender disparities remain a significant challenge in STEM industries and the future of the American workforce. Among STEM workers, African Americans are centerpoint for concerns that there is too little attention paid to increasing racial and ethnic diversity; their high experience with issues with diversity in the workforce is constantly met with failure.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/may/discriminationCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/may/discriminationCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Atmospheric escape: Why Earth will eventually resemble Mars</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/14/atmospheric-escape.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Atmospheric escape: Why Earth will eventually resemble Mars" /><published>2021-05-14T17:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-14T17:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/05/14/atmospheric-escape</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/14/atmospheric-escape.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Atmospheric escape: Why Earth will eventually resemble Mars&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Julia Nwokedi. 05/15/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/may/atmosphericOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The image above shows the surface of Mars.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://mars.nasa.gov/resources/25870/perseverances-hazard-cameras-view-ingenuitys-fourth-flight/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(NASA)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For as long as humans have studied astronomy, Mars has been defined by its reddish-orange hue. However, recent scientific discovery has noted that Mars closely resembled Earth billions of years ago, with lakes, rivers, seas, oceans and perhaps even life. And due to gradual processes that are taking place right now, Earth will closely resemble Mars in the distant future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hue on Mars is a product of natural chemical processes. Mars is a terrestrial planet, composed of silicate rocks and metals. All metals are susceptible to a chemical process known as &lt;a href=&quot;https://chem.libretexts.org/Ancillary_Materials/Exemplars_and_Case_Studies/Exemplars/Physics_and_Astronomy/Astronomy%3A_The_Earth_and_Corrosion&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;corrosion&lt;/a&gt;, which happens through oxidation. In chemistry, oxidation is the loss of electrons during a chemical reaction, and reduction is the complementary gain of electrons. When metals are oxidized, they corrode and become a reddish-orange hue. For example, iron is oxidized by water and oxygen, creating rust:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;4Fe + 3O2 + 6H2O → 4Fe(OH)3&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;All metals are electropositive and are disposed to losing electrons in a chemical reaction. Therefore, corrosion puts metals in their most natural and chemically stable state, and all metals—including stainless steel or silver—are susceptible to a type of corrosion at some point. This also means that terrestrial planets, composed of metal, are susceptible to corrosion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;On a much larger scale, atmospheric escape plays a major role in Mars’ hue. Atmospheric escape is a natural planetary process in which atmospheric gases are lost to outer space. The driving factor of atmospheric escape is heat; as gases are heated, they expand. Atmospheres are bound only by gravity, and at 5,778 K (9,941°F), the Sun provides more than enough heat to lift an atmosphere away from its planet. Through deep analysis of the Martian surface, planetary scientists have come to a consensus that &lt;a href=&quot;https://astrobiology.nasa.gov/news/water-on-mars-the-story-so-far/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mars used to be full of water&lt;/a&gt;, which explains how it dried out and corroded. At high enough temperatures, water can break down into hydrogen and oxygen. Hydrogen has the lowest atomic weight of all elements and can therefore easily escape into the atmosphere and then into space. Oxygen, almost 16 times heavier, expands into space at a much slower rate. Therefore, while hydrogen was escaping from Mars, oxygen remained on the surface for a bit and oxidized the surface of Mars. The data correspond—the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.universetoday.com/14702/what-is-mars-made-of/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Martian crust&lt;/a&gt;, corroded from oxidization, is composed of iron, magnesium, aluminum, calcium and potassium, along with oxygen and silicon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/may/atmosphericTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;A CGI interpretation of an ancient ocean on Mars, billions of years ago.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/press/2015/march/nasa-research-suggests-mars-once-had-more-water-than-earth-s-arctic-ocean/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(NASA)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite also being a terrestrial planet with an abundance of water, Earth has not corroded. Two major factors that explain this are gravity and magnetism. The gravity of an object is determined by its mass, and the magnetism is determined by its electric currents. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nasa.gov/press-release/goddard/2020/mars-electric-currents/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mars lacks a global magnetic field&lt;/a&gt;, and due to its mass, only has 38% of Earth’s gravitational pull, so it can’t grip onto its atmosphere quite as effectively as Earth can. Still, Earth’s atmosphere is constantly being pulled away from its surface. In a few billion years, however, external factors will create the ideal environment for Earth’s corrosion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each star, including our Sun, is powered through nuclear fusion of hydrogen and helium gas in its core. Nuclear fusion releases substantial amounts of energy, which causes a star to expand, but due to expanding, it loses density, cools down and compresses, causing it to release more energy again. These complementary and spontaneous reactions help stars remain in equilibrium, with a persistent size and shape, until they eventually &lt;a href=&quot;https://imagine.gsfc.nasa.gov/educators/lifecycles/LC_main3.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;run out of hydrogen and die&lt;/a&gt;. However, stars are not in an equilibrium of heat. According to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://usm.maine.edu/planet/sun-getting-hotter-if-so-why-will-earth-eventually-become-too-hot-life#:~:text=Astronomers%20estimate%20that%20the%20Sun's,too%20hot%20to%20support%20life.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;University of Southern Maine&lt;/a&gt;, “As the Sun ages, it slowly grows hotter due to the accumulation of residual energy emitted by these core reactions.” When the Sun’s heat becomes more intense, the rate of atmospheric escape will increase, and atmospheric escape on Earth will finally be rapid enough to create another dry, corroded planet. The intense heat, absence of water and thin atmosphere will cause life on Earth to come to a halt. Fortunately, this process will only occur in a few billion years.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the impacts of atmospheric escape will only be seen on Earth in the distant future, atmospheric escape itself is actively occurring. It is actively occurring on Mars, on exoplanets, but most relevantly, on planet Earth. Wherever there’s a planet in a solar system, there’s atmospheric escape, and that includes Earth with all its uniqueness and vitality. Outer space is not distant from Earth, but rather it encompasses Earth, and so do its laws. Earth, a planet set apart by its unique ability to contain life, will eventually become another dry, lifeless, corroded planet. And Mars, a dry, lifeless, corroded planet, possibly contained ancient life. Once the Sun becomes a gas giant, Earth will become engulfed. So, while Earth is extraordinary, it isn’t quite extraordinary enough to resist the forces of outer space.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://mars.nasa.gov/all-about-mars/facts/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(NASA)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Julia Nwokedi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Julia Nwokedi</name></author><summary type="html">Atmospheric escape: Why Earth will eventually resemble Mars Julia Nwokedi. 05/15/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/may/atmosphericCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/may/atmosphericCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The potential of brain-computer interfaces</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/08/the-potential-of-brain-computer-interfaces.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The potential of brain-computer interfaces" /><published>2021-05-08T17:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-08T17:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/05/08/the-potential-of-brain-computer-interfaces</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/08/the-potential-of-brain-computer-interfaces.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The potential of brain-computer interfaces&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rachel Ding. 05/09/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/may/computerOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Bill Kochevar becomes the first person with quadriplegia to receive a neural implant.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2017/03/28/521665654/paralyzed-man-uses-thoughts-to-control-his-own-arm-and-hand&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(NPR)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Bill Kochevar never thought he would be able to feed himself again. After a tragic biking incident, Kochevar was paralyzed from his neck down. For many years, he couldn’t even scratch an itch himself: he depended totally on caregivers. But in 2017, researchers at &lt;a href=&quot;https://engineering.case.edu/groups/BrainGate2/node/11&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Case Western University&lt;/a&gt; developed an electromechanical system that mimicked Kochevar’s spinal cord. At the end of the study, he was able to grab a mug of water, drink through a straw and scratch his nose with a sponge. Through two arrays of sensors in his brain and electrodes in his right arm, Kochevar saw the impossible happen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kochevar is one of only 24 people around the world who have received sensors implanted into their brain to aid with paralysis. But given that up to 500,000 people suffer from spinal cord injuries each year according to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.who.int/news-room/fact-sheets/detail/spinal-cord-injury&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;World Health Organization&lt;/a&gt; (WHO), and even more suffer from neurological diseases and mental illnesses, brain-computer interfaces (BCIs) bear incredible healing potential. They may even make our daily lives far more convenient, both for the patients and those who interact with them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many varieties of BCIs, from the electrode system that helped Kochevar regain function in his arm to circuits that help the user control technology with their brain, all the way to AI-equipped super brains currently under development.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A research paper conducted by &lt;a href=&quot;https://med.stanford.edu/news/all-news/2017/02/brain-computer-interface-allows-fast-accurate-typing-by-people-with-paralysis.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Stanford University&lt;/a&gt; showed the progress of neural interfaces that are able to allow people to type on a screen using brain signals. In the study, three participants with limb weakness were able to type at a rate of eight words per minute through one to two arrays of electrodes that were inserted into their brains. The electrodes were able to receive signals from the participants’ motor cortex and transmitted them to a nearby computer. The computer then translated the data into point-and-click commands, enabling the participants to move the cursor to click on keys.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another study by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/news/pioneering-brain-implant-restores-paralysed-man-s-sense-of-touch-1.20804&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Pittsburgh University&lt;/a&gt; aimed to give Nathan Copeland’s sense of touch back in his arm. Copeland was 18 years old when he was in a car accident that rendered him paralyzed and unable to feel his lower half. Copeland had two electrode arrays implanted into his somatosensory cortex (which embeds sensation) and two other electrodes positioned in the motor cortex (which controls hand and arm movement). They linked a robotic arm to the neural interface and programmed it such that Copeland could feel anything that touched the robotic arm on his own arm. The research team electrically stimulated these regions, and as a result, Copeland was able to feel the sensations, including which fingers were being touched and the regions of those fingers. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nytimes.com/2020/08/28/opinion/sunday/brain-machine-artificial-intelligence.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Mr. Copeland&lt;/a&gt; described them as “weird,” “electrical tingly” but also “amazing.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Broadly speaking, BCIs use brain signals to enhance the brain’s functions. How does this technology work? The human brain has over 86 billion neurons. Neurons have three main parts: the dendrite, the soma and the axon. The dendrite receives signals, the somas are the processing units and axons send out the information. When the total input arriving in the soma exceeds a certain threshold, the axon generates a short electrical pulse. Neural interfaces work through a series of electrodes that gather data from these pulses. A chip on the scalp analyzes the data and can even communicate with other technologies using Bluetooth and artificial intelligence, software that allows machines to mimic human functions. AI is now able to detect the important signals and analyze them, then execute different motions accordingly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With a BCI, people can control home appliances, activate car brakes and type and control cursors just by thinking. BCIs can also deliver targeted electromagnetic pulses to improve memory, attention and consciousness for cognitively impaired patients and alleviate symptoms for chronic pain, substance abuse and depression.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While this all may seem like something out of a science fiction novel, BCIs are arriving at the forefront of society sooner than you think. Once this technology is popularized, it may be accessible not just to patients with spinal cord injuries, but to everyone. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://venturebeat.com/2019/11/20/ctrl-labs-ceo-well-have-neural-interfaces-in-less-than-5-years/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;VentureBeat&lt;/a&gt;, CTRL-labs CEO Thomas Reardon believes neural interfaces will be commercially available in the mid-2020s. Back in 2017, &lt;a href=&quot;https://med.stanford.edu/news/all-news/2017/02/brain-computer-interface-allows-fast-accurate-typing-by-people-with-paralysis.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dr. Krishna Shenoy&lt;/a&gt;, a professor of electrical engineering at Stanford, predicted that “the day will come — closer to five than 10 years from now… when a self-calibrating, fully implanted wireless [BCI] can be used without caregiver assistance, has no cosmetic impact and can be used around the clock.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In just a few short years, it could be perfectly normal to drive without touching a steering wheel, receive the weather forecast in your head and direct your thermostat to warm up or cool down while you’re nowhere near it. BCIs still can’t read brain signals with perfect accuracy, but they are rapidly improving. The better they become, the more they will continue making the impossible, possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://theconversation.com/deep-brain-stimulation-a-fix-when-the-drugs-dont-work-14097&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1620609408459000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw1bj__Oif5fF3qEq3W9J0qB&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Theconversation)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Rachel Ding&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Rachel Ding</name></author><summary type="html">The potential of brain-computer interfaces Rachel Ding. 05/09/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/may/computerCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/may/computerCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Artificial intelligence morals and ethics: Could the capabilities of machine learning be its demise?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/08/artificial-intelligence-morals-and-ethics.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Artificial intelligence morals and ethics: Could the capabilities of machine learning be its demise?" /><published>2021-05-08T17:00:00-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-08T17:00:00-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/05/08/artificial-intelligence-morals-and-ethics</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/08/artificial-intelligence-morals-and-ethics.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Artificial intelligence morals and ethics: Could the capabilities of machine learning be its demise?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aryav Nagar. 05/09/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/may/aiOne.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;The image above depicts the painting Edmond de Belamy. (Christies)
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Some computer systems are even capable of developing abstract forms of creativity similar to individual thought in the form of meaningful literature and paintings. An example of computer-minded artwork is “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edmond_de_Belamy&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1620609012096000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw2HLL-SXOXuUBHDT85hEuf8&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Edmond de Belamy&lt;/a&gt;”, a fully AI-generated “painting.” Through deep learning, AI is able to imitate a creative mind based on previous human work, as seen in the paint strokes and the prominent human figure wearing a suit and collared shirt.  Apart from the visual aspect of art, AI is well capable of creating forms of analytical literature. An open-source artificial intelligence, &lt;a href=&quot;https://openai.com/blog/gpt-2-1-5b-release/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;GPT-2&lt;/a&gt;, has created multiple excerpts of poetry and fictional writing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is an example-
And, ere the cloud of the tempest blew,
His soul was with the world at play.
He looked to the stars, and the stars smiled,
And the moon in the heaven looked;
And, as he looked, he beheld her light,
And all the heaven smiled with him.
When winds and tempests fly,
When floods and fires fail,
As their wake doth meadow and fen,
Tis the man-child’s heart that craves.
And I — I shall be bound,
With the hoary-headed, strong, old,
To earth, and the graves of the dead,
Whose feet are mowed down, as they lie;
And I shall rest my weary head,
In the silence of Eternity,
In the peaceful arms of God.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Outstandingly, GPT-2 not only generated a meaningful poem with the possibility of thoughtful creative analysis, but it has also expressed human emotion, religion and curiosity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;The moral argument against AI&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;AI has constantly proven itself to imitate and exceed human behavior, but this raises concerns within the public opinion: Will AI take away jobs? What will happen to targeted workers? Can AI take over the world?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In reality, these are valid arguments. As this technology advances further in complexity, it can very well branch out and perform tasks related to other fields of work. This seems highly plausible in the coming years as AI has been appealing to most companies since machine learning and neural networking is proven to be much more accurate and sustainable than manual labor. Some are already adopting this fully automated system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Yangshan Deep-Water Port is the biggest fully automated container port in Shanghai. “It’s all controlled by artificial intelligence,” Yang Jiemin, who is in charge of technological support, said to &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.cgtn.com/news/3d637a4e31677a4d/share_p.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;CGTN&lt;/a&gt;, as he describes the 24/7 fully automated workforce. If this trend of adopting AI-powered machines grows, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.usnews.com/news/economy/articles/2019-06-26/report-robots-will-replace-20-million-manufacturing-jobs-by-2030&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1620609000911000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw34zLkFfkEoxLL170XjX7ii&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;by 2030, over 20 million jobs could be replaced by machine learning robots&lt;/a&gt;. The fact of the matter is, the complexity and sheer capabilities of machine learning could result in public opinion that sides against the growth of artificial intelligence. The reason being? Robots can replace manual workers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Apart from the possibility of AI taking over the workforce, many believe it is on its path to take over the world. Although it may seem that AI could develop into an evil army of robotic human beings, most probably due to sci-fi films, AI computing is unable to understand the world through a moral aspect. Partaking in a war against humanity is far beyond machine learning’s algorithmic capabilities. And while it may seem as if AI has this abstract understanding through its literary and visual art forms, it is unable to fully comprehend what exactly it is generating. After all, a computer system, even as advanced as complex deep learning systems, is unconscious. Algorithms dictate AI capabilities, and a basic understanding of morality is a concept that cannot be written out in an algorithmic form. Translating emotion into binary values for the computer to understand does not seem plausible to achieve anytime soon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Should AI continue to develop?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The consequences of AI are definitely apparent, but the possibilities this field could create are not something our technologically dependent society should overlook. AlphaGo is a Google DeepMind computer program specified to perform tasks in the abstract strategy board game, Go. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.smithsonianmag.com/smart-news/latest-ai-teaches-itself-play-games-no-human-help-180965322/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;AlphaGo trained for only a staggering 40 days&lt;/a&gt;. After this short training period, it was able to defeat 18-time world champion Lee Se-dol. To put this into perspective, Go is speculated to be a 2,500-year-old board game that originated in China. AlphaGo was self-trained during the 40 days by repeatedly playing over 40 million games against itself. Within this time period, AlphaGo was able to learn and test strategies that have been developing for the past 25 centuries at the highest possible level. If this deep mind software was able to defeat some of the greatest Go minds in history through new strategies and quick decision making, similar deep learning programs could be implemented to assist human practice throughout a multitude of fields of work.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In modern-day technology, this is how AI is currently being used. Some of the most common forms of computer intelligence are actually present in everyday tasks, such as virtual assistants on your mobile phone or self-driving cars seen around roads. All these are used to assist human tasks and speed up daily processes. They are not replacing human appearance. If we are able to use AI as a tool to refine human lives, the fear of robots replacing human work would become non-existent and technological advancements would become much more rapid.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Vox)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Aryav Nagar&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Aryav Nagar</name></author><summary type="html">Artificial intelligence morals and ethics: Could the capabilities of machine learning be its demise? Aryav Nagar. 05/09/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/may/aiCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/may/aiCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>