<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-07-18T00:05:27-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">InterSTEM</title><entry><title type="html">The Future of Coral Reefs</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/16/coral-reefs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Future of Coral Reefs" /><published>2021-07-16T17:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-16T17:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/07/16/coral-reefs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/16/coral-reefs.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The Future of Coral Reefs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daniel Wang. 07/17/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/july/coralOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Coral bleaching is the phenomenon in which coral reefs turn white while algae living inside the coral perish. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nbcnews.com/science/environment/great-barrier-reef-hit-third-major-bleaching-event-five-years-n1166676&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(NBC News)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each year, billions of tourists are drawn to the beauty of tropical shores and flock to places such as the Caribbean for vacation. In this age of information, a simple internet search of coral reefs will result in mesmerizing images of sparkling water filled with patches of multiple shades of green. While most may only associate the words “coral reef” with these images, coral reefs aren’t just natural sights, but they are more importantly, ecosystems that humans depend on. At the InterSTEM Speaker Series presentation, Dr. Garen Baghdasarian, a professor of marine biology at Santa Monica College, explained humanity’s dependence on coral reefs as well as the threats to their survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his presentation, Dr. Baghdasarian first established that coral reefs are indeed organisms. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.livescience.com/40276-coral-reefs.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LiveScience&lt;/a&gt;, coral reefs are structures formed from the skeletons of hermatypic coral, a marine invertebrate. Corals have exoskeletons that provide natural protection from underwater threats. In addition, Dr. Baghdasarian mentioned that coral reefs are the building blocks of clear, shallow water ecosystems as they are an energy source that many aquatic organisms depend on for survival. The coral’s  role of being the backbone of aquatic ecosystems is dependent on the symbiotic relationship between the coral and algae. All corals host dinoflagellates, single algae with a flagella that allows the algae to move. The relationship formed between the dinoflagellates and algae allow for the survival of coral in nutrient-sparse areas. The coral will obtain up a large portion of its caloric energy from photosynthetic products made by algae. The algae, on the other hand, will receive micro-nutrients like nitrogen from the corals, as well as an ideal environment for photosynthesis. If this relationship fails, the coral will perish, destabilizing its ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to aquatic ecosystems, many human industries also depend on the sustainability of coral reefs. For example, Dr. Baghdasarian also claims that the tourism brought by coral reefs bring several benefits to a nation’s economy. The reef hosts over 25 million aquatic species, providing food for one billion people. The reefs also act as a carbon sink, mitigating many impacts of rising carbon dioxide levels in the atmosphere. Clearly, many aspects of human life depend on services provided by coral reefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, climate change is posing a threat to the well-being of coral reefs. Dr. Baghdasarian mentioned that over 90 percent of climate change happens in the oceans, directly impacting the health of coral reefs. This leads to the phenomenon of coral “bleaching,” where coral reefs will turn white while algae living inside the corals die. In fact, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://oceanservice.noaa.gov/ocean/corals/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Ocean Service&lt;/a&gt; explains that small changes in ocean temperature, such as a 2 degree Celsius increase, can ultimately lead the corals to expel the algae living in them and turn white. As Dr. Baghdasarian’s research shows, while the bleaching of a coral does not mean that the coral is dead—some can even recover in 4 weeks in ideal conditions—numerous questions still revolve around the process of coral bleaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Baghdasarian hopes to answer the question of what will happen to the coral reefs in the future. He and his team began this research by comparing records of coral reefs 50-100 years ago to the coral reefs today. Their observations matched with the general consensus that rising water temperatures led to this catastrophe; as water temperature increased, more algae perished, eventually leading to greater amounts of coral bleaching. Additionally, the increase in water temperature has also seemed to erode tissue of the coral itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One surprising discovery was that in many locations with similar water temperature and pH levels, some corals would be bleached, while others would be completely fine. To find out the reasoning behind this phenomenon, Dr. Baghdasarian compared the different types of symbiotic algae with the hypothesis that some algae may have heat-resistant genes. However, after testing this theory out through his experiments, he concluded that the type of algae was not the factor of coral bleaching as his experimental data showed no correlation between the type of algae present in the coral and the degree of bleaching that the coral experienced. Therefore, Dr. Baghdasarian concluded that traits in the coral reefs themselves determine how severely they bleach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the future, Dr. Baghdasarian will conduct experiments to determine what specific characteristics in corals allow them to thrive in harsh conditions. He believes that in order to protect the coral species, humans must engineer a new species of supercoral that can thrive under more extreme heat conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His final message was that people should never lose hope. No matter how genetically fit human-made coral may be, all work will be done in vain if climate change, the root cause of mass coral bleaching, worsens. Humanity and natural ecosystems are interconnected; while one may not have experienced coral reefs much outside of seeing them in beautiful travel advertisements, the luxuries and benefits one takes from these beautiful organisms depends on their sustainability in the ocean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalgeographic.com/science/article/scientists-work-to-save-coral-reefs-climate-change-marine-parks&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(National Geographic)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Daniel Wang&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Daniel Wang is an incoming junior at Westlake High School. He is interested in many aspects of STEM, especially math.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Daniel Wang</name></author><summary type="html">The Future of Coral Reefs Daniel Wang. 07/17/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/july/coralCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/july/coralCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How Spotify knows exactly what you want to listen to</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/09/how-spotify-knows-exactly-what-you-want-to-listen-to.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Spotify knows exactly what you want to listen to" /><published>2021-07-09T17:00:03-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-09T17:00:03-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/07/09/how-spotify-knows-exactly-what-you-want-to-listen-to</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/09/how-spotify-knows-exactly-what-you-want-to-listen-to.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;How Spotify knows exactly what you want to listen to&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rachel Huang. 07/10/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/july/spotifyCover.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Algorithm-based streaming platform Spotify curates personalized playlists for users based on their favorite music &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spotify.com/us/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Spotify)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spotify. As the biggest music streaming platform in the world, Spotify has two main advantages over its competitors: its large and diverse reserves of music consisting of over 70 million songs and its ability to figure out exactly what you want to listen to. Utilizing a search engine that combines multiple machine learning and data analysis models, Spotify collects data from your playlists and then finds similar songs to recommend to you. The personalization of Spotify can be broken down into two main parts: its data infrastructure and personalization algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Data Infrastructure&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Open-source Apache software platforms Kafka, Storm, Crunch, and Cassandra make up the foundation of Spotify. These software systems seamlessly work together to collect and analyze data in real-time and then store it in user profiles as personalized suggestions according to the user’s preference. To make up Spotify’s personalization tech stack (in computing, a stack is a data structure used for storage), a sequence composed of these software systems is run: Kafka collects data, Storm and Hadoop Distributed File System (HDFS) process the data in real-time, Crunch further processes the data, and everything is stored in Cassandra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/july/spotifyOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;A diagram of data flow in Spotify &lt;a href=&quot;https://engineering.atspotify.com/2015/01/09/personalization-at-spotify-using-cassandra/#:~:text=We%20help%20our%20users%20discover,and%20distastes%20in%20different%20contexts.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Spotify)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cassandra database, Spotify’s storage unit, consists of over 100 Cassandra clusters, each containing a nested storage system within itself. The sequential layering of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://data-flair.training/blogs/cassandra-cluster/#:~:text=The%20cluster%20is%20a%20collection,storage%20unit%20in%20a%20database.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;shells&lt;/a&gt; can be represented as follows: cluster → nodes → keyspace → column families→ rows → column. The nodes are made up of computers that share data with each other, and each subsequent shell is a more specific classification of the data in the shell before it. User profile attributes and metadata about playlists and artists are stored in Cassandra clusters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;How the Personalization Algorithm Works&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;A popular feature of Spotify is the Discover Weekly playlist, a mixtape of 30 new songs that is updated every Monday. This playlist is the best example of Spotify’s personalization algorithm as its songs are directly determined by Spotify’s discovery engine, a mesh of the three data analysis models Collaborative Filtering, Natural Language Processing (NLP), and Audio Analysis. The Collaborative Filtering models rely on data that is stored in immense matrices containing millions of rows and columns, each row representing a user and each column representing a song. After running a matrix factorization formula (with Python libraries) on the user-song matrix, two vectors are produced. The first vector represents a user’s taste in music, and the second vector represents a song’s characteristics. These two vectors are unique to each user, and Spotify recommends songs by comparing your vector to other users’ vectors to find new songs that are similar to the music you are already listening to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/july/spotifyTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;From left to right: a section of the user--song matrix, a user vector, a song factor &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/s/story/spotifys-discover-weekly-how-machine-learning-finds-your-new-music-19a41ab76efe&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Medium)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
While the Collaborative Filtering models analyze data that is solely from Spotify, the NLP models analyze text on the internet about the songs in Spotify’s database, whether it be news articles about popular artists or tweets about new music. The NLP models use &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.google.com/natural-language/docs/analyzing-sentiment&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;sentiment analysis APIs&lt;/a&gt; to create vectors from this collected text that can then be compared to determine if two pieces of music are culturally similar to one another. Finally, audio models analyze the raw audio tracks themselves, an “equalizing” measure built into Spotify’s recommendation models that provide new artists with the same chances of being placed into a user’s Discover Weekly playlist compared to popular artists since audio analysis doesn’t discriminate against song popularity. The audio models use convolutional neural networks to analyze the soundtracks of songs by inputting data as time-frequency representations of audio frames. The frames are then concatenated to form a spectrogram and passed through the convolutional layers of the model, ultimately computing the representative statistics of the song, like the time signature, key, and tempo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/july/spotifyThree.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;A diagram of the audio model; rectangles represent the convolutional layers &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/s/story/spotifys-discover-weekly-how-machine-learning-finds-your-new-music-19a41ab76efe&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Medium)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where the Discover Weekly Playlist is a representative slice of Spotify’s personalization ability, Spotify’s Home Screen is the whole “personalized experience” pie. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://engineering.atspotify.com/2020/01/16/for-your-ears-only-personalizing-spotify-home-with-machine-learning/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Home Screen&lt;/a&gt; is organized like a bookcase with each shelf (or each horizontal section) displaying your favorite books (the square images that represent playlists, podcasts, artists, albums, etc., more formally known as cards). Each user’s bookcase is different as it is based on their most recent activity, favorite playlists, new releases, and custom mixtapes such as the Discover Weekly Playlist. The cards in each shelf are constantly updated with the help of machine learning. In this case, machine learning can be divided into two sections, exploitation and exploration. Exploitation displays the cards based on your previous activity, whether it be the playlist you last listened to or the artist you started following recently. On the other hand, the exploration aspect is based on initiating user engagement by displaying suggested content, seeing how users respond, and then modifying the suggested content according to user interaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As younger generations can attest, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://magazine.weverse.io/article/view?lang=en&amp;amp;colca=6&amp;amp;num=133&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;music industry&lt;/a&gt; is now centered on  digitally streaming music. For example, the International Federation of the Phonographic Industry’s reports show that music streaming made up 62% of the 2020 global music industry, raking in a grand total of $13.4 billion for artists and labels worldwide. &lt;a href=&quot;https://newsroom.spotify.com/company-info/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Spotify&lt;/a&gt; is at the forefront of this streaming movement with a user community of 356 million people that continues to grow every day. Spotify is necessary for singers to flourish, because their music has the possibility of being recommended to anybody and everybody, thanks to Spotify’s song analysis algorithms. 30% of plays on Spotify are credited to personalized recommendations, which serves as evidence of how Spotify is truly at the intersection of the roads of personalization and technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Spotify continuing to push the boundaries of what music streaming can be, the only limit to the music industry is our imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pinterest.com/pin/497366352578717874/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Pinterest)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Rachel Huang&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Rachel Huang</name></author><summary type="html">How Spotify knows exactly what you want to listen to Rachel Huang. 07/10/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/july/spotifyCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/july/spotifyCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Will the Earth ever run out of resources?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/09/will-the-earth-ever-run-out-of-resources.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Will the Earth ever run out of resources?" /><published>2021-07-09T17:00:03-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-09T17:00:03-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/07/09/will-the-earth-ever-run-out-of-resources</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/09/will-the-earth-ever-run-out-of-resources.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Will the Earth ever run out of resources?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sydney Hollingsworth. 07/10/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/july/resourcesOne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Coal mines in Columbia &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.globalcitizen.org/en/content/6-natural-resources-exploited-on-earth/?template=next&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Scott Wallace/World Bank)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have probably heard doomsday warnings such as “climate change will be irreversible by 2030” or “fossil fuels will run out by 2060” to the point that the end of humanity seems inevitable and quickly approaching. But is it true? There is a common theme for these predictions - depletion of natural resources, that humanity’s overconsumption will be its downfall - but what’s actually going on? How can an entire planet run out of resources so quickly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that there is only a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rd.com/list/what-would-happen-if-worlds-natural-resources-ran-out/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;finite amount&lt;/a&gt; of soil, fossil fuels, water, heavy metals, and minerals on Earth, so we must run out eventually, right? And it is true that as a species, we are using these finite resources very quickly; between 1950 and 2000, humans have consumed more natural resources than over the course of all of previous human history, and scientists have been warning against overconsumption since the 1970s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists’ predictions for what the future will bring have consistently changed, despite having known about overconsumption for years. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2002/jul/07/research.waste&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2002 report from the World Wildlife Fund&lt;/a&gt; claimed we would have to colonize at least 2 Earth-sized planets by 2050 to make up for the rate at which we use up natural resources. Now, in 2021, this prediction is less popular because we know that it is neither realistically possible nor necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the numbers seem to be against us, we’re still alive, and the fuel, soil, and minerals that we use everyday never seem to run out. The Club of Rome’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://wattsupwiththat.com/2019/05/15/why-resources-arent-natural-and-will-never-run-out/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Limits to Growth&lt;/a&gt; manifesto, written in 1972, predicted that we would have already run out of heavy metals such as gold, copper, mercury, silver, and zinc by now, but we haven’t. In fact, they’re quite common and used on a daily basis. So what does this mean? Were the scientists wrong? Not quite…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To “run out” of something really means there will be none left for us to use, not necessarily none left in the entire world. But why does that matter? Well, Earth is much bigger than you might think, and there are plenty of natural resources on it we could use, but reaching them is another story. There are smaller, less dense pockets of ores and minerals deep beneath the Earth’s surface, but reaching them would be too expensive and only considered when we have already depleted all the other, more easily accessible deposits and have no easier options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To say we will run out of resources fails to account for new technology. Resource availability is not determined by the finite amount of the resource, but by our ability to obtain it. Historically, technology needs to advance to extract a greater amount of resources, and we don’t have any reason to assume this won’t keep happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we be sure that technology will advance at an effective rate? Well, in many ways, it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.discovermagazine.com/planet-earth/the-world-is-running-out-of-elements-and-researchers-are-looking-in-unlikely&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;already is&lt;/a&gt;. Ore mines have expanded to the arctic in recent years and plans for deep sea mining operations and asteroid mining are underway for the more distant future. Heavy metals can be recycled from electronic waste, and elements such as nitrogen are extracted from the atmosphere to produce fertilizer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So will we ever really run out of resources? In short: no, or at least not anytime soon. The earth is far from actually “running out” of the resources we depend on. As time passes they will just become more and more expensive as their extraction becomes less convenient, eventually being replaced by cheaper, reusable options when the cost becomes too ridiculous for continued use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this outlook does not take into consideration the full picture of what is going on in the world. It is important to point out that for the general public to make the switch to renewable resources, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://welcome.arcadia.com/energy-101/energy-sources/will-we-ever-actually-run-out-of-fossil-fuels&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;cost of non-renewable resources&lt;/a&gt; must rise enough to outweigh the cost of renewable ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see this happening today: renewable energy sources such as solar or wind already exist, but they are not used nearly as much as fossil fuels, because the cost of extracting fossil fuels is cheap compared to green energy. As fossil fuels become more difficult and costly to obtain, oil prices will rise and consumers will turn to renewable energy, making it widespread and more affordable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But from the perspective of those living in poverty, their world will run out of resources long before this point. While 1st world countries can still afford the rising oil prices and do not yet feel the need to transition to green energy, 3rd world countries will be unable to afford either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, our current rate of consumption may not cause the Earth to deplete its resources anytime soon, but it does have drastic consequences on the environment. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7341033/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Global warming is a much larger issue&lt;/a&gt; than depletion of natural resources, and if we don’t do something, it will likely bring &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencealert.com/un-warns-of-biological-annihilation-up-to-a-million-animal-could-soon-be-extinct&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;our downfall&lt;/a&gt; long before we run out of natural resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal is not to downplay the costs of human exploitation of the environment, but to create a more accurate, less self-centered view of what is happening. We are certainly not destroying the Earth; our home planet has been through much worse and will carry on long after we’re gone, although how it appears on the surface may be quite different. Whether or not we will be included in its future depends on what we do next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.foeeurope.org/sites/default/files/publications/foee_overconsumption_0909.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Friends of the Earth Europe)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Sydney Hollingsworth&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sydney Hollingsworth</name></author><summary type="html">Will the Earth ever run out of resources? Sydney Hollingsworth. 07/10/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/july/resourcesCover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/july/resourcesCover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Antibiotic resistance and the human microbiome</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/09/antibiotic-resistance-and-the-human-microbiome.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Antibiotic resistance and the human microbiome" /><published>2021-07-09T17:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-09T17:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/07/09/antibiotic-resistance-and-the-human-microbiome</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/09/antibiotic-resistance-and-the-human-microbiome.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Bias in Facial Recognition Technology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tania Firouzbady. 07/10/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/july/antibioticOne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Image of bacteria at molecular level. &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.usc.edu/135660/how-bacteria-adapt-to-hostile-environments/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(USCNews)&lt;/a&gt;  &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Antibiotic resistance has become a pivotal topic for biomedical research in recent years. Its ability to hinder advancements in drug development makes it one of the biggest threats to public health. Each year, approximately 2.8 million people in the United States develop an infection due to antibiotic resistance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In simple terms, antibiotics are chemicals that inhibit the growth of microorganisms such as bacteria and fungi. They accomplish this by either directly killing the microorganism or by stopping its reproduction long enough for the host’s immune system to kick in. To better understand the various components of the immune system, it’s important to first discuss the human microbiome.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The human microbiome refers to the sum of all the microorganisms, or microbes, living in the human body. These microbes include eukaryotes, bacteria, archaea, and viruses. Research indicates that there are about ten times as many microbial cells as there are human cells. While it may seem surprising that microbes are such an important part of the body–after all, antibiotics are meant to target them–it is important to note that not all microbes are the same; some are harmful while others are beneficial.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The microbiome is closely linked to the immune system. According to the journal &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nature.com/articles/s41422-020-0332-7&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Cell Research&lt;/a&gt;, “The microbiome plays critical roles in the training and development of major components of the host’s innate and adaptive immune system, while the immune system orchestrates the maintenance of key features of host-microbe symbiosis.” In other words,  the microbiome and immune system have a mutually beneficial relationship because they rely on each other to operate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The immune system is responsible for getting rid of pathogens, or disease-causing microbes. White blood cells are one of the most important parts of the immune system. Certain types of white blood cells, namely B and T lymphocytes, are memory cells, meaning they remember a pathogen after its first invasion and produce antibodies, proteins that protect against pathogens, much more quickly in subsequent infections. These cells are part of the acquired immune system, which changes throughout an organism’s life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Different from the adaptive immune system,  the acquired immune system is inherited at birth and remains unchanged over time. During a pathogenic infection, the innate immune system sends phagocytes, a type of cell that can engulf bacteria and particles, to attack the invading cells. Through these mechanisms, both the innate and acquired immune systems work together to ward off pathogens.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antibiotics often work in conjunction with the immune system to prevent the spread of pathogens. One well-known antibiotic is penicillin, which is used to treat staphylococci and streptococci bacterial infections. The former is a skin infection that typically results from an open wound or surgery, while the latter is a mouth/throat infection. Penicillin works by damaging bacterial cell walls.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A vital aspect of such antibiotic development is ensuring that they don’t harm people. Since humans lack cell walls, they are unaffected by penicillin treatment. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.news-medical.net/health/Penicillin-Mechanism.aspx&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;News Medical&lt;/a&gt;, “Penicillin kills bacteria through binding of the beta-lactam ring to DD-transpeptidase, inhibiting its cross-linking activity and preventing new cell wall formation.” To put it simply, by binding to an enzyme (DD-transpeptidase), penicillin forms a highly stable intermediate that prevents the enzyme from functioning, which ultimately inhibits cell wall formation.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Antibiotic resistance is caused by genetic mutations in bacteria, which are more prone to mutations due to their rapid rate of reproduction. When bacteria reproduce in the vicinity of antibiotics, already present mutations that allow them to be resistant are passed onto future generations, eventually leading to the evolution of a resistant strain. Hence, the antibiotic becomes ineffective, and a stronger one is needed. Over time, as this cycle continues and  antibiotics become stronger, their production will become impractical. Even more worrisome is the fact that “bacterial strains can become resistant to more than one antibiotic, leading to the creation of ‘superbugs’ that are extremely difficult to treat.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/july/antibioticTwo.jpg&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Diagram of how bacteria develop antibiotic resistance.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.infextioustherapeutic.com/programs&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Infextious Therapeutic)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bacteria achieve resistance to antibiotics through various mechanisms. Penicillin resistance, for example, was the direct result of bacterial production of beta-lactamase, an enzyme that harms the beta-lactam ring. Without it, penicillin is no longer capable of damaging bacterial cells.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As time goes on, antibiotic resistance and the creation of superbugs has become more widespread. Fortunately, awareness of the issue has also increased and scientists are developing new methods to combat antibiotic resistance. One such method is focusing attention on natural antibiotics rather than artificial ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists from the Institute for Stem Cell Science and Regenerative Medicine have been doing just this. As outlined by &lt;a href=&quot;https://phys.org/news/2019-12-scientists-method-combat-antibiotic-resistant-bacteria.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;phys.org&lt;/a&gt;, “the team probed the cellular mechanisms that regulate the release of antimicrobial peptides (AMPs), which are natural antibiotics produced by skin cells to fight off bacteria.” What makes AMPs unique is that they attack bacteria in ways that make resistance to them very difficult. By understanding the mechanisms used by AMPs, researchers may be able to develop antibiotics that replicate them. Moreover, the research has already led to a groundbreaking discovery: skin cells utilize a signaling pathway that regulates how AMPs are released, meaning that by altering these pathways, scientists can allow the AMPs to be released without being exposed to the bacteria at all. This could potentially help groups of people that are in greater danger of infection, including those with a weak immune system.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://theconversation.com/antibiotic-resistance-new-discovery-could-change-the-future-of-treatment-131262&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(The Conversation)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Tania Firouzbady&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Tania Firouzbady</name></author><summary type="html">Bias in Facial Recognition Technology Tania Firouzbady. 07/10/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/july/antibioticCover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/july/antibioticCover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Bias in Facial Recognition Technology</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/09/Bias-in-facial-recognition-technology.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Bias in Facial Recognition Technology" /><published>2021-07-09T17:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-09T17:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/07/09/Bias-in-facial-recognition-technology</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/09/Bias-in-facial-recognition-technology.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Bias in Facial Recognition Technology&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Neha Bhardwaj. 07/10/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/july/biasOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Facial recognition technology works by recognizing and matching up key points on a person’s face, as shown in the picture. However, people of color in particular face much higher error rates with this software. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aclu.org/news/privacy-technology/how-is-face-recognition-surveillance-technology-racist/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(ACLU)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
For years, bias in policing and law enforcement has been a fiercely debated issue. Last year, the death of George Floyd provoked immense outcry, resulting in resurgences of the Black Lives Matter movement and calls for radical reformation of the criminal justice system. However, while there has been extensive discussion of the implicit biases and discriminatory actions of human police officers, few recognize the other segment of law enforcement in desperate need of reform: facial recognition technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of us interact with facial recognition on a daily basis in relatively benign ways, such as unlocking our phones or tagging our friends in a post on social media. However, on a broader scale, this software is used in everything from &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.facefirst.com/blog/amazing-uses-for-face-recognition-facial-recognition-use-cases/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;recognizing known criminals to diagnosing certain diseases.&lt;/a&gt; As the use of AI technology has expanded, so too have concerns about the potential biases in the software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://sitn.hms.harvard.edu/flash/2020/racial-discrimination-in-face-recognition-technology/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Harvard University’s Science in the News&lt;/a&gt;, while facial recognition boasts an impressive accuracy rate for certain groups, the technology is plagued by a far higher rate of errors among young, Black, and female subjects. In 2018, the &lt;a href=&quot;http://proceedings.mlr.press/v81/buolamwini18a/buolamwini18a.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“Gender Shades” project&lt;/a&gt; offered strong experimental proof of this bias. The algorithms tested in the experiment showed up to 34% higher error rates for darker-skinned female subjects than for lighter-skinned males, putting a global spotlight on the implications of using facial recognition technology. A year later, a federal study further showed egregious disparities on the basis of race, gender, and age. For instance, “Asian and African American people were up to 100 times more likely to be misidentified than white men,” according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.washingtonpost.com/technology/2019/12/19/federal-study-confirms-racial-bias-many-facial-recognition-systems-casts-doubt-their-expanding-use/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the Washington Post&lt;/a&gt;. Other minority groups, women, the elderly, and children were all subject to drastically higher rates of inaccuracy than middle-aged Caucasian men.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The implications of these biases are staggering. As pointed out by Jay Stanley of the American Civil Liberties Union, “One false match can lead to missed flights, lengthy interrogations, tense police encounters, false arrests, or worse.” In the realm of law enforcement in particular, not only is the technology itself biased, but there are several compounding factors that further disadvantage Black and Brown people. Many jurisdictions in the U.S. use mugshot databases to train facial recognition algorithms, subjecting the technology to prejudice of years past. As &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.aclu.org/news/privacy-technology/how-is-face-recognition-surveillance-technology-racist/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the American Civil Liberties Union&lt;/a&gt; explains, “Since Black people are more likely to be arrested than white people for minor crimes… their faces and personal data are more likely to be in mugshot databases. Therefore, the use of face recognition technology tied into mugshot databases exacerbates racism in the criminal legal system that already disproportionately polices and criminalizes Black people.” Moreover, there is a higher proportion of surveillance cameras installed in predominantly Black and Brown neighborhoods, further influencing the accuracy of facial recognition algorithms that process surveillance footage. Ultimately, these realities boil down to an undeniable truth: facial recognition is contributing to inequality in everything from suspect identification to alibi corroboration.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This naturally begs the question: how can the world of facial recognition be improved? The primary solution is &lt;a href=&quot;https://sitn.hms.harvard.edu/flash/2020/racial-discrimination-in-face-recognition-technology/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;improving training datasets&lt;/a&gt;. When facial recognition algorithms are created, they are “trained” on large databases of various people’s faces. However, these datasets are often lacking in diversity. The underrepresentation of Black, Brown, female, and young subjects in these datasets makes it harder for the algorithms to differentiate between darker-skinned female subjects. As a result, many are calling for algorithms to be trained on more representative and comprehensive datasets. Other solutions include establishing standards of image quality for people of all skin colors, regular auditing, and new legislation to regulate how mass surveillance is conducted and how law enforcement officers use the technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Facial recognition software is undeniably a powerful tool with great potential. The inherent bias in the technology is certainly not a reason to scrap it altogether. Rather, the facial recognition landscape must be transformed into a tool for equality and justice.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://spectrum.ieee.org/tech-talk/computing/software/do-you-have-the-right-complexion-for-facial-recognition&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(IEEE Spectrum)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Neha Bhardwaj&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Neha Bhardwaj</name></author><summary type="html">Bias in Facial Recognition Technology Neha Bhardwaj. 07/10/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/july/biasCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/july/biasCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How technology has helped preserve music during the pandemic</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/02/how-technology-has-helped-preserve-music.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How technology has helped preserve music during the pandemic" /><published>2021-07-02T17:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-02T17:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/07/02/how-technology-has-helped-preserve-music</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/02/how-technology-has-helped-preserve-music.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;How technology has helped preserve music during the pandemic&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catherine Todd. 07/03/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/july/musicOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
A Jamulus server as it appears to the user with the options to control the volume of each participant on their personal mix as well as putting different participants on mute and solo.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://maxton.xyz/blog/online-jamming-jamulus-reaper&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Maxton)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The global pandemic has closed schools and other locations across the country, forcing the music industry, along with others, to use technology to preserve their way of life. For one group in particular, musicians, this transition has been especially difficult. While business meetings can carry on in a more or less normal format through Zoom and other communication technologies, musicians require being able to hear one another in real-time, as they use their ears to fit in with the musical ensemble. If it seems hard to not interrupt people when simply talking on Zoom, imagine trying to achieve precisely timed entrances that are hard to coordinate even without the added complications of slow internet. This issue has made many people ask the question, “How can we have the technology to send humans into space and communicate with them but not the technology to produce one of man’s most basic forms of expression, music?”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, it turns out we do have that ability; we simply need to look a little deeper. One of these technologies actually allows musicians to play virtually with almost no delay. Although other iterations exist, one of the main areas this function exists is in Jamulus, an application that runs on a computer and allows musicians to hear each other by compiling the sounds into a server. While it is helpful to set up a private server that can host a specific group, especially if a group meets regularly, it is not necessary. Many servers are public, allowing anyone from around the world to join them and are therefore a great meeting place for a group, provided that you click the solo option to ensure that no one breaks up a rehearsal. Another application of Jamulus occurs when a group has rehearsed enough that they can put on a concert live online from their own houses. This also requires the use of Zoom (to display video), open broadcast software, YouTube live and someone to manage all of this. Of course, there are limitations to this, which means that most people using Jamulus will need to use an ethernet cable to minimize the overall delay and ping time so that this automation is actually useful. There is also the possibility of a technological failure, such as a server crash or downed internet, but overall the benefits of this server certainly outweigh the negative aspects, especially while people are not comfortable or safely able to congregate and play.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The other option is to not play live at all, but rather record each part individually and place them all together to form a piece. This requires a click track, which the musician can line themselves up with, as well as background music and a clear start time in each video so that it is clear when the piece starts. Unfortunately, it is not this simple because as any musician will tell you when playing in a group, it isn’t just about one person playing correctly, but it’s about the musician fitting into the correct sound of a group. As such, audio engineering will say that lining up the audio portions of each person will make the Los Angeles Philharmonic sound like a sixth-grade orchestra. However, by using technologies such as GarageBand, Audacity or other audio editors, audio engineers can do anything from splitting tapes and shifting the time between each note to changing the pitch of that note altogether. The result is a soundtrack that reflects or even enhances the abilities of the live ensemble. This choice was often the preferred method of large ensembles or school groups, as technologies such as Jamulus lag with too many people online. Additionally, schools may not be able to provide everyone with the appropriate amount of technology to run Jamulus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even with these technologies, it is hard to replicate the sound of a live performance through an old built-in computer or phone microphone. These microphones were made to pick up vocal sounds and often distort the sounds of instruments, especially loud brass sounds. This created a whole new market for external microphones which were once rare. There are two main types of microphones: dynamic, and condenser, each with its pros and cons. Dynamic microphones are more capable of withstanding loud sounds, while condenser microphones are better at picking up the intricacies of soft sounds but cannot deal with loud sounds well. These microphones have definitely become more popular over the past year, but many musicians, especially inexperienced ones, have decided that their computer or phone microphone better suit their needs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, the exact sound of a live performance can’t be replicated online, which is why concerts are still a popular phenomenon even though any song can be accessed for free on online platforms such as YouTube. Still, with the addition of softwares such as Jamulus, audio editing softwares, and microphones, musical performances have been able to continue throughout the pandemic.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.shutterstock.com/video/clip-33736174-sound-waves-audio-equalizer&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Visionative)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Catherine Todd&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Catherine Todd</name></author><summary type="html">How technology has helped preserve music during the pandemic Catherine Todd. 07/03/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/july/musicCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/july/musicCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Addressing ransomware attacks</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/25/addressing-ransomeware-attacks.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Addressing ransomware attacks" /><published>2021-06-25T17:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2021-06-25T17:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/06/25/addressing-ransomeware-attacks</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/25/addressing-ransomeware-attacks.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Addressing ransomware attacks&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simone Rothaupt. 06/26/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/june/ransomwareOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;In early May 2021, Colonial Pipeline Co. experienced a ransomware attack that caused a gas shortage throughout the East Coast.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2021-05-10/colonial-pipeline-reopens-section-of-pipeline-on-limited-basis&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Luke Sharrett / Bloomberg)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
On May 7. 2021, Joseph Blount, the CEO of Colonial Pipeline Co., authorized a payment of $4.4 million dollars to DarkSide, a cyber hacking group from Eastern Europe. Earlier that day, a worker had noticed a ransomware warning stating that DarkSide had shut down the company’s fuel lines and was now demanding payment to reopen them. While Colonial Pipeline Co. worked to resume operations, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/business-57050690&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;BBC&lt;/a&gt; reported that the 2.5 million-barrel-a-day pipeline, which supplied 45% of the East Coast’s diesel, petrol and jet fuel, was shut down for nearly a week.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though often unseen by the public, a variety of private and public enterprises have been attacked by ‘cybergangs’ that extort large sums from their victims in exchange for reopening the company’s digital infrastructure. According to leading cybercrime research group &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.herjavecgroup.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/12/CV-HG-2019-Official-Annual-Cybercrime-Report.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Cybersecurity Ventures&lt;/a&gt;, an attack occurs nearly every 11 seconds. Former Deputy Attorney General &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.justice.gov/opa/speech/deputy-attorney-general-rod-j-rosenstein-delivers-remarks-cambridge-cyber-summit&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Rod J. Rosenstein&lt;/a&gt; further reports that global ransom payments are approaching “$1 billion annually.” Some more prominent ransomware victims include &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.forbes.com/sites/leemathews/2021/05/25/bose-hit-by-ransomware-refuses-to-pay-ransom/?sh=66f5efea139a&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Bose&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sandiegouniontribune.com/news/health/story/2021-05-24/scripps-enters-fourth-week-of-ransomware-pain&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Scripps Mercy Hospital of San Diego&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One common trait shared among these hacking groups is that they often base themselves on former or current Communist countries. A recent exposé by &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newyorker.com/magazine/2021/04/26/the-incredible-rise-of-north-koreas-hacking-army&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The New Yorker&lt;/a&gt; revealed that the global attacks wrought by the Reconnaissance General Bureau, a cyberhacking team, were supported by the North Korean government. One prominent attack by the RGB includes the failed global ransomware scheme, Wannacry 2.0, in 2017.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While the first recorded ransomware attacks were quite simple in nature, the continuous evolution of computer technology has enabled increasingly complex attacks. For instance, CNN writer &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnn.com/2021/05/16/tech/ransomware-joseph-popp/index.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Samantha Kelly&lt;/a&gt; reports the first major ransomware attack involved sending floppy disks to victims. Once inserted in the computer, an error message would freeze the device and request victims to send “$189 in an envelope to a PO Box in Panama.” Over time, however, ransomware attacks became more complex and thus, more difficult to prevent. For instance, the aforementioned RGB once attempted to attack Redbanc, a network that connects all ATMs in Chile, by faking a job offer to an employee.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://security.berkeley.edu/faq/ransomware/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;UC Berkeley&lt;/a&gt; reports that the typical method that ransomware enters a computer is through links in phishing emails and drive-by downloading. Phishing emails are messages designed to trick victims into releasing private information. Typically, these emails imitate those sent by official institutions, such as banks and government organizations. Phishing emails are often sent by a botnet, which is a network of hijacked zombie computers controlled by cybercriminals. Drive-by downloading occurs when a victim visits an infected website and unknowingly downloads malware. As explained by &lt;a href=&quot;https://lifehacker.com/a-beginners-guide-to-encryption-what-it-is-and-how-to-1508196946&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Whitson Gordon&lt;/a&gt;, the malware then encrypts files, essentially encoding the information stored on a device that cannot be decoded without a key. If the victim pays the ransom (typically demanded in the form of bitcoin), the key is provided to the victim to regain access to their computer’s data. In the previously mentioned situation with the RGB and Redbanc, the ransomware initially entered the ATM network by asking the target to “download and run a program that generated a PDF of a résumé.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As ransomware attacks become more and more common, one growing concern is about their potential societal impacts. While attacks such as the one on Bose may only affect the company, others may have nationwide and global repercussions. For example, according to the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.wsj.com/articles/u-s-gas-prices-hit-3-a-gallon-as-shortage-sets-in-amid-colonial-pipeline-shutdown-11620832180&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Wall Street Journal&lt;/a&gt;, the Colonial Pipeline attack caused gasoline prices to jump to a six-year high, with the national gas price average increasing to over $3 per gallon. Without a doubt, the victims of ransomware attacks represent not only the targeted company but the entire world.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Following the recent Colonial Pipeline attack, the US government has issued various responses to improve national cybersecurity. Specifically, on May 12, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.whitehouse.gov/briefing-room/statements-releases/2021/05/11/fact-sheet-the-biden-harris-administration-has-launched-an-all-of-government-effort-to-address-colonial-pipeline-incident/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;President Biden&lt;/a&gt; signed an executive order which seeks to “modernize and implement stronger cybersecurity standards in the Federal government” and “establish a Cybersecurity Safety Review Board.” Moreover, the Department of Homeland Security aims to require pipeline companies to report ransomware attacks to federal authorities. New cybersecurity legislation, such as the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.meritalk.com/articles/senate-bill-pushes-for-federal-cybersecurity-employee-rotation-system/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Federal Rotational Cyber Workforce Program Act&lt;/a&gt;, is also expected to be enacted in the near future. The Federal Rotational Cyber Workforce Program in particular aims to improve government cybersecurity by allowing cyber-related employees to work across multiple agencies. By doing so, central, integrated cybersecurity would be created that can address attacks rapidly.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though these efforts attempt to stem the tide of ransomware attacks, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.chicagotribune.com/business/ct-biz-cb-ransomware-cyberattacks-computer-security-20210429-yewql3wcszas5g2xc7uf4gdbm4-story.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Philip Reiner&lt;/a&gt;, the CEO of the nonprofit Institute for Security and Technology, explains there is no simple solution to ransomware. Even so, the Department of Justice’s task force for ransomware believes that stricter regulation of cryptocurrency and allowing private companies to block online criminal activity, including botnets, can reduce these attacks. Through these government initiatives, ransomware attacks can hopefully be mitigated.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Getty Images / Andrey Popov)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Simone Rothaupt&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Simone Rothaupt</name></author><summary type="html">Addressing ransomware attacks Simone Rothaupt. 06/26/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/june/ransomwareCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/june/ransomwareCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Can carbon recapture technology be a realistic solution to the climate crisis?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/12/can-carbon-recapture-technology-be-a-realistic-solution-to-the-climate-crisis.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Can carbon recapture technology be a realistic solution to the climate crisis?" /><published>2021-06-12T17:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2021-06-12T17:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/06/12/can-carbon-recapture-technology-be-a-realistic-solution-to-the-climate-crisis</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/12/can-carbon-recapture-technology-be-a-realistic-solution-to-the-climate-crisis.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Can carbon recapture technology be a realistic solution to the climate crisis?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catherine Todd. 06/13/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You might not think about it often, but the original carbon capturers were trees and plants. For millennia, the world was kept in balance by the emittance of carbon dioxide by humans and the absorption of it by plants. Only during the Industrial Revolution did we stray from this model. Burning coal, natural gas and petroleum put unprecedented levels of toxins and greenhouse gases, like carbon dioxide, into the air. For a long time, people did not understand the huge impact emissions would have on the world. Even after they did, it was ignored for decades and some still ignore it. Even if we reach net-zero Earth, there will still a long period of time before plants can absorb all of this carbon dioxide.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here comes the idea for carbon recapture technology. If we are able to “grab” the carbon dioxide from the air and redeposit it into the ground where it was stored for years in the form of fossil fuels, then we will be able to save the Earth from the climate crisis. Unfortunately, it is not that simple. The technology has been around since the 1970s, but it has not really taken off. These days we hear about solar, hydro, wind and other forms of clean energy, but carbon recapture is often not in the conversation. However, to be fair, Elon Musk recently tweeted about giving 100 million dollars to carbon recapture technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Still, the financial problem of carbon recapture technology persists. The financial incentive for a company to fund an expensive process to remove carbon dioxide from the atmosphere and place it back into the ground does not exist. Why fund a company that removes carbon from the air in an expensive way rather than one that releases it with no immediate consequence? Maybe with more regulation and costs associated with releasing carbon dioxide, the financial incentive to support carbon recapture technology will grow.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the meantime though, carbon recapture technology continues to get better. For example, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2021/01/31/carbon-capture-technology.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Berend Smit on CNBC&lt;/a&gt; says he is trying a new technology that involves carbon dioxide flowing through a sponge with chemicals that latch onto the carbon dioxide in the air and when it is heated Carbon Dioxide can be separated from the sponge and sent to storage underground. With this technology, carbon recapture will be able to be more freestanding and mobile, so it will require less machinery. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cnbc.com/2021/01/31/carbon-capture-technology.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;According to Paitoon Tontiwachwuthikul&lt;/a&gt;, this new innovation could cost up to 70%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/june/carbonOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This infographic displays how many carbon recapture technologies aim to make a profit. They capture CO2 but then synthesize it into more fuel. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/news/science-environment-47638586&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Carbon Engineering)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Another factor to consider is how necessary recapture technology really is. Many people argue that trees are the only recapture technology we need and that we should plant more trees anyway. However, trees require a lot of resources, including water, which is in short supply in many places in the world. They also take time to grow, as well as a lot of land. Additionally, trees are already being cut down at a large rate in places such as the Amazon rainforest. There is no way to replenish trees at the rate they are killed and also plant enough to make a meaningful difference concerning the amount of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When speaking about these solutions, it is always imperative to mention that reducing fossil fuel consumption is still necessary to reduce greenhouse gas levels. Carbon recapture technology cannot be another ‘save the turtles by not using a plastic straw’ movement. Companies should not feel that they have no obligation to use green energy even if they employ carbon recapture tactics. It is too easy for someone to say that we can continue to use fossil fuels at our current levels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Again, we have been polluting the Earth for some time now, and in order to make a positive impact on the environment, we need negative emissions, not zero emissions. Carbon recapture technology is certainly part of that, but definitely not all. This negative emission world would require the usage of solar energy, hydroelectricity, wind power and many more types of renewable energy. Maybe if this climate threat was taken more seriously earlier on, a more mild solution, such as removing carbon dioxide from the atmosphere, could be possible. Alas, we currently have 415 ppm of carbon dioxide in the atmosphere, versus the 280 ppm before the Industrial Revolution. We must recognize that no one thing can fix the problem that we have. Even though carbon recapture technology is great, it must be accompanied by appropriate policy, social change and renewable energy solutions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (IEEE Spectrum)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Catherine Todd&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Catherine Todd</name></author><summary type="html">Can carbon recapture technology be a realistic solution to the climate crisis? Catherine Todd. 06/13/2021 You might not think about it often, but the original carbon capturers were trees and plants. For millennia, the world was kept in balance by the emittance of carbon dioxide by humans and the absorption of it by plants. Only during the Industrial Revolution did we stray from this model. Burning coal, natural gas and petroleum put unprecedented levels of toxins and greenhouse gases, like carbon dioxide, into the air. For a long time, people did not understand the huge impact emissions would have on the world. Even after they did, it was ignored for decades and some still ignore it. Even if we reach net-zero Earth, there will still a long period of time before plants can absorb all of this carbon dioxide.</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/june/carbonCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/june/carbonCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The neurochemistry behind school failure or how to stop procrastinating 101</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/12/the-neurochemistry-behind-school-failure-or-how-to-stop-procrastinating.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The neurochemistry behind school failure or how to stop procrastinating 101" /><published>2021-06-12T17:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2021-06-12T17:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/06/12/the-neurochemistry-behind-school-failure-or-how-to-stop-procrastinating</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/06/12/the-neurochemistry-behind-school-failure-or-how-to-stop-procrastinating.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The neurochemistry behind school failure or how to stop procrastinating 101&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vova Prylepa. 06/13/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/june/neurochemOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
This image taken explains how our brain interprets long-term tasks and the cognitive process that initiates procrastination. &lt;a href=&quot;https://thenextweb.com/news/brain-freeze-science-procrastination-smart-brains&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(The Next Web)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
First comes your homework, then your project, then the test and even the final exam— nothing and no one can escape the all-powerful, all-engulfing black hole of procrastination. Many people whose school performance is affected by procrastination tend to believe that they procrastinate for a variety of reasons: they believe they’re not good enough to complete or understand a specific task, they’re too lazy, or they think there’s a subconscious mechanism that maximizes their productivity under pressure. However, all of these statements are but a mere illusion— you are capable enough to finish that history project on time or to ace that biology test. Sometimes, the fact that you procrastinate isn’t even your fault, but one of the very deceptive neurotransmitters that control your impulsive decision-making: dopamine. By understanding the neurochemistry that reigns over the parts of the brain that makes us make these bad decisions, the ones that bring bitter, long-term consequences but so, so sweet short-term rewards, we can better understand procrastination, to eventually battle it and win.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As a start, we will divide our brain into many parts, but we’ll concentrate on the ones that are the most relevant to the neurochemistry of procrastination: the &lt;a href=&quot;https://nesslabs.com/neuroscience-of-procrastination&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;prefrontal system and the limbic system&lt;/a&gt;. The prefrontal system is the little brother of the limbic system. It is far weaker when it comes to its influence on our decision-making skills when being compared to the limbic system. The prefrontal system is responsible for the various ways in which we express our identity and our personality, for the planning of multiplex behaviors, reason and logic, while the limbic system is responsible for automatic, impulsive decisions in situations that are considered life-threatening or dangerous.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/age-of-awareness/from-procrastination-to-motivation-manipulating-dopamine-9c1a345b9bda&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Dopamine’s&lt;/a&gt; role is (and has always been) to make us repeat certain behavior patterns that are likely to guarantee our survival or reproduction, dating back to the times where we ran after animals with sharp sticks. When we did a certain thing that resulted in us getting a better chance at survival or reproduction, a certain dose of dopamine would be delivered to our brain which would make us feel rewarded, relaxed and pleasured. For instance, when we eat, our brain rewards us with dopamine as consuming food is equivalent to survival. Therefore, since our brain is addicted to dopamine, it will automatically— almost unnoticeably—  make us do the thing that will give us the higher dosage of dopamine, based on the predicted or experienced plausibility of an activity delivering dopamine to the brain, and thus to make us survive and reproduce.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now, when it comes to our complex human society, this dopamine dosage technique also applies to the satisfaction of other social needs (money, status, public perception, etc) and other human needs (i.e. entertainment) rather than our primal needs. In order to make us procrastinate, our brains make the decision (mostly using our limbic system) to choose an activity that would maximize the dopamine, or the immediate reward, as opposed to the activity that has better long-term consequences, as the quantity of dopamine that’s received by the brain from the said activity is uncertain. More precisely, the limbic system contains the amygdala, which is a part of our brain that produces a powerful &lt;a href=&quot;https://thenextweb.com/news/brain-freeze-science-procrastination-smart-brains&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;emotional response&lt;/a&gt;: a fight (resistance) or flight (ignorance) reaction to a difficult/long-term task. That effect is created by the production of norepinephrine (causing fear and anxiety) and even adrenaline, similarly to a reaction produced to a life-threatening situation except that now, the only thing threatened is your comfort zone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The amygdala plays a more important part in our rationale, as it takes 1/32 of a second to send its chemical signal, as opposed to the three seconds take by the prefrontal system to generate a well-evaluated, rational thought. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://thenextweb.com/news/brain-freeze-science-procrastination-smart-brains&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;amygdala is simply faster&lt;/a&gt;, so we listen to it more when making a decision. Essentially, this reaction with norepinephrine is simply a way for our brain to avoid a task low in immediate dopamine to take part in an activity that guarantees a dopamine release in the shortest delays. This explains the fact that you are more drawn to play Angry Birds than to do your chemistry homework— although your prefrontal system knows that in the long run, the chemistry homework will benefit you more and might bring you dopamine (pleasure) if you do it right, the limbic system, the more dominant one, will make you strive for the more immediate and certain reward, the one that requires less effort and time to get that desired dopamine dosage. That dreaded homework, on the other hand, will get postponed to a later date, and then an even later one until it sinks into oblivion.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To combat this, we need to rewire our brains into thinking of long-term tasks as the ones that bring the most dopamine (pleasure), and not the most norepinephrine/adrenaline (fight-flight response) for the victory in the fight against procrastination. Here are a few mental techniques that would allow you to do that:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;1: &lt;a href=&quot;http://blog.neurogistics.com/index.php/dopamine/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Create an environment that’s conducive to focus and work&lt;/a&gt;. By eliminating all kinds of distractions around you, such as putting your phone away, cleaning your work desk from useless items and closing all kinds of unimportant tabs on your computer, you take away all kinds of short-term sources of dopamine, leaving only long-term sources of dopamine (like working on a project or studying for a test) to your brain. This way, by leaving it no choice, your brain is obliged to choose the only potential source of dopamine available, even though the amygdala is telling it that the levels of dopamine brought by this activity are uncertain.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;2: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inc.com/kevin-daum/this-is-why-you-procrastinate-heres-what-to-do-about-it.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Set small goals and divide a big assignment into a series of smaller ones and set up a reward structure&lt;/a&gt;. The brain cannot tolerate any activities that don’t bring dopamine any soon, the amygdala making our focus shift to more rewarding activities. However, if we divide a task into smaller parts, which we do during set periods of time and get rewarded after that certain period of time, the amygdala considers each small part of that big task as a short-term source of dopamine. Thus our limbic and prefrontal cortex work in conjunction to guarantee the completion of the said long-term task, bit by bit. One method to use is the Pomodoro method, where one has to work for 25 minutes and take a short break after each work period, rewarding him or herself with a snack, a walk or simply a series of stretching exercises.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;3: Don’t be afraid to start and ask questions. People often procrastinate because they are too intimidated by a specific task or are too afraid to ask their teachers, supervisor, colleagues or friends about something they don’t understand, so they just never start. Just blindly starting a task without overthinking it would allow you to procrastinate far less. In fact, if you don’t know how to approach a specific activity, you can use &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.inc.com/jeff-haden/neuroscience-says-your-brain-is-wired-to-procrastinate-4-simple-ways-to-stop-putting-off-important-things-willpower-not-required.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;the five minutes rule:&lt;/a&gt; you’ll have to invest yourself into something for only five minutes, but you’ll have to do it thoroughly. It would allow your cognitive muscles to warm up and after five minutes, you’ll lose your fear of the task and keep doing it almost automatically.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end, don’t forget that when you procrastinate, you exchange potential big future rewards for smaller, futile pleasures. Some things just can’t be done tomorrow, and the best time to start them is today and now. Don’t be your dopamine’s slave— you can seek help for procrastination issues and no one will judge you for it. It is by disciplining your brain that you will be able to reach anything you want in life.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: (Tiny Buddha)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Vova Prylepa&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Vova Prylepa</name></author><summary type="html">The neurochemistry behind school failure or how to stop procrastinating 101 Vova Prylepa. 06/13/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/june/neurochemCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/june/neurochemCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">“Mixing and matching” COVID-19 vaccines</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/28/mixing-and-matching-covid-19-vaccines.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="“Mixing and matching” COVID-19 vaccines" /><published>2021-05-28T17:00:03-07:00</published><updated>2021-05-28T17:00:03-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/05/28/mixing-and-matching-covid-19-vaccines</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/05/28/mixing-and-matching-covid-19-vaccines.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;&quot;Mixing and matching&quot; COVID-19 vaccines&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rachel Huang. 05/29/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/may/vaccineOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
“Mixing” vaccines may boost our immunity against COVID-19. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.clinicaltrialsarena.com/analysis/covid-19-vaccine-mixing-the-good-the-bad-and-the-uncertain/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Clinical Trials Arena)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
The COVID-19 pandemic has lasted for over a year now, and many different brands of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/vaccines/different-vaccines.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;vaccines&lt;/a&gt; have been created in response to the coronavirus, such as the Pfizer-BioNTech, Moderna, Oxford-AstraZeneca and Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson vaccines. Even though not federally approved yet, the idea of mixing and matching these vaccines is gaining popularity as there is significant evidence that doing so strengthens the immune system. This “mix and match” method of administering vaccines can also be referred to as heterologous vaccination, which means that an individual receives one type of vaccine for their first shot and then another type for their second shot.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To better understand how this mixing approach utilizes different “types” of shots to strengthen the immune system, a brief overview of the human immune system is necessary. The human immune system has two main lines of defense: antibodies and T cells. Antibodies are proteins made by the immune system that bind to virus particles and “deactivate” them before they can infect any cells. T cells get rid of cells that have already been infected.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most vaccines currently focus on the antibody line of the immune system and something on the coronavirus’ surface called a spike protein. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.technologyreview.com/2021/05/06/1024640/why-mixing-vaccines-could-help-boost-immunity/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;spike protein&lt;/a&gt; is what defines the coronavirus, so if your body is able to recognize the spike protein, it is able to recognize the coronavirus. The Pfizer and Moderna vaccines deliver &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/vaccines/different-vaccines/mrna.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;mRNA&lt;/a&gt;, a set of instructions for the cell, to the ribosomes, where the cells can then recreate the spike protein. After the spike protein is completed, the body is able to recognize that the spike protein is a foreign object and starts building up a memory-like response to it with antibodies. On the other hand, Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson and Oxford-AstraZeneca notify the cell about the coronavirus’ spike protein by delivering another virus (an adenovirus) that has the spike protein “hidden” on it. The problem with using this Trojan horse-like contraption is that the immune system builds up immunity to the delivery molecule, in this case the adenovirus, which means that subsequent vaccinations will be less effective. Regardless of how they transfer the spike protein to our immune systems and the relative efficacy of their methods, the Pfizer, Moderna, Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson and Astra-Zeneca vaccines all protect our immune systems from their coronavirus by focusing on getting our cells to recognize the coronavirus’ spike protein.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/may/vaccineTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
The coronavirus’ spike protein is located on the exterior of the cell like a nametag that lets other cells recognize it. The instructions for the spike protein are found in the RNA in the coronavirus’ nucleus.
&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sfchronicle.com/projects/2021/coronavirus-vaccines-explainer/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(SF Chronicle)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The problem with focusing on the spike protein is that viruses are constantly changing through mutation, and there are at least five &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/variants/variant.html?CDC_AA_refVal=https%3A%2F%2Fwww.cdc.gov%2Fcoronavirus%2F2019-ncov%2Ftransmission%2Fvariant.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;variants&lt;/a&gt; of the coronavirus in the United States right now with modified spike proteins that may be unrecognizable to current vaccines. Here, the “mix and match” approach to administering vaccines comes into play, where Professor Shan Lu, the pioneer of this strategy, says that the mechanism of combining shots is where the first shot a person receives addresses the spike protein via antibodies, while the second shot rallies your T cells. Current plans to get the T cells’ “attention” center around adding another protein to the coronavirus, or using one that is already present like a nucleoprotein to boost T cell response. This additional protein will act as a name tag that T cells will be better able to recognize and respond to, increasing the number of T cells and antibodies in the cell due to the increased number of targets on the coronavirus. Together, T cells and antibodies will double the efficacy of our immune systems.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The United States, China, the United Kingdom, Spain and Russia have already begun human trials testing this mix and match method where participants receive the first dose of say, Pfizer, and then the second shot of Moderna. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.npr.org/sections/health-shots/2021/05/05/993882203/giving-2-doses-of-different-covid-19-vaccine-could-boost-immune-response&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Gritstone&lt;/a&gt;, a company in California, has made it its mission to design two different vaccines that are made to be given together, instead of using two different brands of vaccines. Gritstone’s CEO, &lt;a href=&quot;https://abc13.com/covid-vaccine-pfizer-moderna-astrazeneca/10591350/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Andrew Allen&lt;/a&gt;, says that their approach may be able to “give recipients the best of both worlds [antibodies and T cells]!” and Phase 1 human clinical trials have also recently begun.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This mix and match method of administering vaccines is especially appealing from a scientific standpoint, especially for lower income countries that have less accessibility to vaccines. With heterologous vaccination, these countries will be able to continue administering vaccines even if one vaccine’s supply runs low or health concerns about a brand of vaccine arise. For people who worry about the safety of combining shots, “there is no danger in mixing vaccines,” Professor of Immunology at London School of Hygiene and Tropical medicine Helen Fletcher said. In fact, it may be more beneficial for patients with other diseases like MS and cancer whose antibody aspect of their immune systems have been weakened by their treatments. With bountiful scientific evidence proving that “mixing and matching” vaccines is beneficial for our immune systems, we can only hope that global and national authorities will quickly approve this strategy in order to strengthen us in our united fight against COVID-19.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nbcnews.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(NBC)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Rachel Huang&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Rachel Huang</name></author><summary type="html">&quot;Mixing and matching&quot; COVID-19 vaccines Rachel Huang. 05/29/2021 “Mixing” vaccines may boost our immunity against COVID-19. (Clinical Trials Arena)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/may/vaccineCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/may/vaccineCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>