<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="http://localhost:4000/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="http://localhost:4000/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-04-02T13:23:09-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/feed.xml</id><title type="html">InterSTEM</title><entry><title type="html">What is bubble tea and how is it made?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/10/01/what-is-bubble-tea-and-how-is-it-made.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="What is bubble tea and how is it made?" /><published>2021-10-01T17:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2021-10-01T17:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/10/01/what-is-bubble-tea-and-how-is-it-made</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/10/01/what-is-bubble-tea-and-how-is-it-made.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;What is bubble tea and how is it made?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catherine Todd. 08/28/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/october/bobaOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
Bubble tea: a delightful mix of refreshing tea and chewy boba &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.foodunfolded.com/article/what-is-bubble-tea-insider-secrets-on-bubble-tea&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1633235420216000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw2ez-2TUdcD4bil2N-iL7-b&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(FoodUnfolded)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Bubble tea has quickly become a global phenomenon since its invention in Taichung, Taiwan in the 1980s. A refreshing mix of cool tea and sweet spheres of chewy boba, bubble tea comes in many flavors and forms. Drinks range from the traditional milk tea topped with boba to extravagant fruit-flavored teas or smoothies filled with chunks of pudding, jellies, and popping bubbles.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are many different flavors of tea, but all tea leaves come from the &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.google.com/url?q=https://www.sciencelearn.org.nz/resources/1661-the-science-of-tea&amp;amp;sa=D&amp;amp;source=editors&amp;amp;ust=1633235444527000&amp;amp;usg=AOvVaw1iDVQk5AMHQ5Ua1So0NHMP&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Camellia sinensis&lt;/a&gt; plant. Classic bubble tea uses &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.teatulia.com/tea-varieties/what-is-black-tea.htm&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;black tea&lt;/a&gt;, which has a malty taste that is created by rolling and bruising Camellia sinensis assamica leaves. This maximizes the amount of oxidation, a chemical process where oxygen reacts with the natural flavoring compounds in the leaves that the leaves go through. On the other hand, milder teas such as green tea are created by heating and drying Camellia sinensis assamica leaves as soon as they are harvested to prevent oxidation and preserve their fresh taste. Hence, tea-making follows this general concept: smaller leaves and less oxidation result in lighter-flavored teas, while larger leaves and more oxidation create stronger-flavored teas.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.scientificamerican.com/article/make-boba-for-bubble-tea/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Boba&lt;/a&gt; is the special ingredient that distinguishes bubble tea from others. The chewy morsels are made from a combination of tapioca flour, water, and brown sugar. The tapioca flour consists solely of starch, and when mixed with hot water, it swells and breaks apart, forming a water-retaining network that forms the solid gel-like texture of boba. This process is called starch gelatinization. Modern chefs have created a new type of boba with molecular gastronomy, called &lt;a href=&quot;https://fanaledrinks.com/blogs/blog/18322291-how-is-popping-boba-made&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;popping boba&lt;/a&gt;. This topping is exactly what it sounds like: chewy spheres that pop in your mouth, releasing a small burst of fruit juice. To create this popping effect, a small quantity of powdered sodium alginate is mixed with the fruit juice and then dripped into a bowl that contains a solution of calcium chloride. This forms small bubbles in the liquid that have a layer of thin skin composed primarily of seaweed extract. However, boba and its siblings are not the only &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.kungfutea.com/our-toppings&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;toppings&lt;/a&gt; available today - chunks of pudding, jelly, red beans, and cream caps are available as well&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To tie it all together, flavoring is needed. The first bubble tea used &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.healthline.com/nutrition/brown-sugar-vs-white-sugar&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;brown sugar&lt;/a&gt;, but now white sugar is also used. All sugar comes from the sugarcane plant: Saccharum officinarum. Sugarcane juice is extracted from the stalk of the plant, then purified and heated, forming a brown, concentrated syrup called molasses. Next, the molasses is centrifuged to produce brown sugar crystals, which are then ready for packaging. If white sugar is desired, the brown sugar is further processed to remove all remnants of molasses. Because brown sugar contains more molasses, it is denser, less sweet, and more expensive than white sugar. While homemade bubble teas usually use brown sugar to pertain to tradition, most bubble teas sold in stores use white sugar. As such, though a properly created cup of bubble tea may seem flawless and simple, there is actually a lot of work that goes into making it, i.e. processing the tea, making the boba, and flavoring and customizing it all to each person’s desires.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What began as a Taiwanese street vendor product has now blossomed into one of the most well-known drinks in the world. It has even become a popular staple in America with the help of chain stores such as Kung Fu Tea and Kokee Tea. These modern stores continue to innovate, creating new flavors of tea and types of toppings, all while sticking to the essence of Taiwanese culture that made it all possible. Sample a region’s bubble tea, and you will be able to glimpse the culture of the people living there. One sip of the traditional milk bubble tea will transport you to a Taiwanese night market, teeming with bubble tea vendors and hundreds of other food stands waiting for you to explore them. One sip of a milk cap deluxe bubble tea featuring brown sugar syrup streaks and thick, frothy cream, will drop you into one of Taiwan’s deluxe malls, bustling with energy and class. Whether you favor heartwarming, homemade bubble teas or lavish remixes, you will find yourself taking sip after sip of the wonderful drink called bubble tea.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thespruceeats.com/different-flavors-of-bubble-tea-766444&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(The Spruce Eats)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Rachel Huang&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Rachel Huang</name></author><summary type="html">What is bubble tea and how is it made? Catherine Todd. 08/28/2021 Bubble tea: a delightful mix of refreshing tea and chewy boba (FoodUnfolded)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/october/bobaCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/october/bobaCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Efficient Studying</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/10/01/efficient-studying.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Efficient Studying" /><published>2021-10-01T17:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2021-10-01T17:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/10/01/efficient-studying</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/10/01/efficient-studying.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Efficient Studying&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peter Bui. 10/26/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/october/studyingOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
&lt;a href=&quot;https://chilledcow.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(ChilledCow)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Studying for hours for little results, cramming at the last minute the night before a test, or forgetting everything you just studied. These methods are deemed inefficient for obvious reasons, but what exactly is efficient studying? What form of studying helps recall the most information in a timely manner?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;First of all, notes. Notes are an effective studying method because they help us learn both in school and out of school. Taking notes in class “&lt;a href=&quot;https://www.umassd.edu/dss/resources/students/classroom-strategies/why-take-notes/#:~:text=Note%20taking%20forces%20you%20to,and%20remember%20the%20information%20later.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;forces you to pay attention and helps you focus in class&lt;/a&gt;”. It’s more efficient than solely listening to the teacher, regardless how much you focus. Notes constantly keep you active and learning. There are many different types of notes, each appealing to different people. The first is summarizing (typically in a notebook or on scratch paper). With this method, an individual would write down the key points they hear in a lecture and use it for studying purposes later on. This is efficient because it keeps the person engaged in the class, but excludes minor, “less important” details, which may or may not contribute to the subject overall. Another method can be flashcards. Flashcards are typically helpful for learning definitions, so their use is more restricted/limited  than typical paper notes. They are still efficient, however, because one can study the material and quiz themselves  with ease. Last but not least, Cornell notes. Cornell Notes are infamous for being assigned  by teachers, and they &lt;a href=&quot;&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;serve their purpose incredibly well&lt;/a&gt;. This format is structured so that an individual   takes notes by using bullet points to highlight important information, as well as summarization at the end of the notes. Some honorable mentions, though more uncommon, can be The Outline Method, the Mind Mapping Method, and &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.lifehack.org/856826/note-taking&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;more&lt;/a&gt;. Notes are meant for studying in a productive manner, so it’s important that the user feels comfortable and the method is helpful for them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A study habit can be focusing on a specific topic. This study method is based on &lt;a href=&quot;https://gradepowerlearning.com/effects-of-multitasking-on-learning/#:~:text=Multitasking%20while%20doing%20homework%20(or,social%20media%20while%20doing%20homework.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;research&lt;/a&gt; and proves that putting all your focus into one subject or assignment can result in more effective studying. When multitasking (checking phones, studying multiple subjects at once, watching a show, etc.), the productivity of the student &lt;a href=&quot;https://gradepowerlearning.com/effects-of-multitasking-on-learning/#:~:text=Multitasking%20while%20doing%20homework%20(or,social%20media%20while%20doing%20homework.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;decreases to no more than 40%&lt;/a&gt; than without it. A way to avoid distractions and increase productivity is to remove anything that can serve as a distraction. A phone call from an unknown number, a spam Email, anything that can suddenly shift the attention from what is being done, should be removed or silenced. Another source/study proves that music is good for studying because it improves the mood, keeps the person alert, and increases &lt;a href=&quot;https://study.com/academy/popular/is-it-good-to-listen-to-music-while-studying.html#:~:text=Music%20that%20is%20soothing%20and,stress%20or%20anxiety%20while%20studying.&amp;amp;text=During%20long%20study%20sessions%2C%20music,which%20indirectly%20boosts%20memory%20formation.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;endurance&lt;/a&gt;. However, another study shows that listening to music can serve as a &lt;a href=&quot;https://themusicuniverse.com/disadvantages-listening-music-while-studying/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;distraction&lt;/a&gt; by making it more difficult to remember notes and diminishing the brain’s cognitive abilities. The changing words and tunes, as well as the changing songs and volumes can throw a person off their stream of study. A solution to this can be to listen to a type of music that maintains a consistent atmosphere  and has little to no words. Lo-Fi (Low Fidelity) Music, a combination of jazz and other instrumentals, is proven to aid study. It also increases the amount of dopamine and serotonin and improves focus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Last but not least, studying in groups can be an effective strategy. &lt;a href=&quot;https://source.wustl.edu/2006/07/discovering-why-study-groups-are-more-effective/#:~:text=Studying%20in%20groups%20helps%20students,has%20consistently%20demonstrated%20that%20fact.&amp;amp;text=%E2%80%9CA%20large%20number%20of%20college,their%20professor%2C%E2%80%9D%20says%20R.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Research&lt;/a&gt; shows that studying in groups usually results in  efficient study sessions. When students working together have a question, they can ask a peer in the study group and have access to help and tutoring, if needed. They can get an explanation for a question they have, or for something they don’t understand. It also pushes the students to be more committed and not fall behind the rest of the group.  Discussing topics and communicating amongst each other results in productivity. Notes can be compared and different perspectives can be displayed. Skeptical feelings towards a subject can be changed, and naivety on a subject can turn to full understanding. Test anxiety and stress is reduced, and is a fun learning experience.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Remember, it’s always important to study smarter, not harder. Whatever method works best and is reflected in performance should be a to-do. If cramming helps, that works too. At most times, it’s important to do what’s comfortable to you and helps you do things better, especially studying.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://unsplash.com/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Unsplash)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Peter Bui&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Peter Bui</name></author><summary type="html">Efficient Studying Peter Bui. 10/26/2021 (ChilledCow)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/october/studyingCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/october/studyingCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The environmental impacts of fast fashion</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/10/01/the-environmental-impacts-of-fast-fasion.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The environmental impacts of fast fashion" /><published>2021-10-01T17:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2021-10-01T17:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/10/01/the-environmental-impacts-of-fast-fasion</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/10/01/the-environmental-impacts-of-fast-fasion.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The environmental impacts of fast fashion&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Denzel Galang. 10/26/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/october/fashionOne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
The mass production of fast fashion, as shown here, can negatively affect the environment with its extreme use of nature’s resources. &lt;a href=&quot;https://thinksustainabilityblog.com/2020/04/14/the-unsustainable-growth-of-fast-fashion/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Think Sustainability)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our planet is already carrying a heavy burden ever since we started industrializing. Power plants burn fossil fuels, which have greatly contributed to the increase in greenhouse gas emissions along with mass deforestation to clear the way for buildings. Another great example would be the clothing industry, which has also played a role in destructing the environment by producing fast fashion clothing. Fast fashion is a practice used by some clothing retailers in an attempt to capitalize off the latest trends in fashion. They make a profit by mass-producing trendy outfits for a low price, but these clothes are made of low-quality materials such as polyester.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They are deliberately designed to be made of cheap fabrics so that they would wear out easily, making consumers return later on to buy more fast fashion clothes. The clothing’s ability to deteriorate quickly means consumers are throwing them out frequently, resulting in a massive increase in waste production. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://thinksustainabilityblog.com/2020/04/14/the-unsustainable-growth-of-fast-fashion/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Think Sustainably&lt;/a&gt;, more than 100 billion garments are produced every year, and around $450 billion worth of textiles are thrown away. This is why fast fashion is such a harmful business to the environment. The excessive amount of resources that are put into producing fast fashion ultimately end up being thrown away, as fashion trends inevitably come and go. This is a quick and convenient way for large companies to make tons of money while simultaneously disregarding any concerns for what they have done to the environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Shortcuts in the clothing industry not only create ludicrous amounts of waste but also lead to widespread water pollution due to cheap, toxic, textile dyes used to produce fast fashion clothing. Textile dyeing is the second largest cause of water pollution, with the fashion industry being responsible for approximately 20 percent of industrial water pollution worldwide, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.businessinsider.com/fast-fashion-environmental-impact-pollution-emissions-waste-water-2019-10#all-in-all-the-fashion-industry-is-responsible-for-20-of-all-industrial-water-pollution-worldwide-21&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Business Insider&lt;/a&gt;. This is another problem that could have been easily resolved if clothing retailers were not so greedy and instead spent a little more to make sure that their products were safe for both the consumers and the environment. Unfortunately, profit remains a top priority in these companies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fast fashion industries also dump these toxic textile dyes, along with microfibers, into waterways where they make their way into the wild, potentially harming entire ecosystems. Additionally, fashion that involves animal fur puts the well-being of these animals on the line. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theage.com.au/national/victoria/real-fur-from-tortured-dogs-being-sold-as-fake-in-melbourne-s-markets-20191121-p53cw2.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The Age&lt;/a&gt;, markets were caught selling beanies that claimed to be made from rabbits. However, when the beanies were sent for testing, it was discovered that the fur was from raccoons. As if the results were not shocking enough, undercover investigations were conducted that revealed that these raccoons were caged and treated poorly. The raccoons were killed through torturous methods, including skinning them alive, electrocuting them, or repeatedly striking them with a club until death. These practices are unacceptable (they amount to animal abuse) and are being perpetrated by the fast fashion industry. Inhumane treatment and killing of animals to gain some type of profit are downright disgusting. It is very saddening because many consumers do not know that some clothes that they purchase from fast fashion brands could be fur from abused animals. So, some of these brands are essentially scamming people by telling their consumers that they are selling products that have fur from one type of animal, when in reality it is from a completely different one, for the same reason as before: because it is cheaper and requires less effort to raise raccoons instead of rabbits, thus it is another example of a shortcut.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The fast fashion industry further tries to hide its wrongdoings to the environment by claiming to go green. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://goodonyou.eco/what-is-fast-fashion/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;good on you&lt;/a&gt;, some stores place bins where their customers can drop off unwanted items. Unfortunately, according to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newsweek.com/2016/09/09/old-clothes-fashion-waste-crisis-494824.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Newsweek&lt;/a&gt;, only 0.1 percent of all clothing collected by charities and take-back programs is recycled into new textile fiber. This shows how brands that produce fast fashion clothing make it seem like they want to do good when, in actuality, they do not care at all. These brands would have had more success converting donated clothes back into recycled textile fiber if they put more effort into it. Unfortunately, recycling clothes to help the environment is not a top priority, but money is.
All in all, fast fashion has played a detrimental role when it comes to the environment, so it is best to avoid clothes that come from fast fashion brands. Clothes made from polyester are good indicators of fast fashion, as polyester is a relatively cheap material. While it may be hard to refrain from buying from fast fashion brands, it is important to note that these companies are destroying the environment. We only have one planet to live on, so it is vital that we take care of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ecowatch.com/fast-fashion-riverblue-2318389169.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(RiverBlue)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Denzel Galang&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Denzel Galang</name></author><summary type="html">The environmental impacts of fast fashion Denzel Galang. 10/26/2021 The mass production of fast fashion, as shown here, can negatively affect the environment with its extreme use of nature’s resources. (Think Sustainability)</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/october/fashionCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/october/fashionCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How has the pandemic influenced sleep?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/09/03/how-has-the-pandemic-influenced-sleep.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How has the pandemic influenced sleep?" /><published>2021-09-03T17:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2021-09-03T17:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/09/03/how-has-the-pandemic-influenced-sleep</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/09/03/how-has-the-pandemic-influenced-sleep.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;How has the pandemic influenced sleep?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Audrey Lee. 09/04/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/september/sleepOne.png&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;An exhausted woman struggles to fall asleep despite the late hour. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.utoimage.com/?m=goods.photo_view&amp;amp;pm=goods.search&amp;amp;catg=CILL&amp;amp;sf=local&amp;amp;mk=%EB%B6%88%EB%A9%B4%EC%A6%9D&amp;amp;page=1&amp;amp;idx=20924827&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Utoimage)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Over a year ago, the world found itself facing a pandemic that forced several countries into lockdown and chaos. Many might believe that staying at home would have helped people to finally solve the all-too-familiar problem of sleep deprivation. So has it helped the world to catch up on lost sleep? Or did the pandemic make everything worse?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Revenge bedtime procrastination&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Back in 2014, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fpsyg.2014.00611/full&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;a study from the Netherlands&lt;/a&gt; revealed how procrastination can be found in sleeping and was not limited to the academic sector. Coining it bedtime procrastination (later renamed &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.bbc.com/worklife/article/20201123-the-psychology-behind-revenge-bedtime-procrastination&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;revenge bedtime procrastination&lt;/a&gt; in 2018), the collaborators of the study defined it as the tendency to push back on sleep for no reasonable explanation. Procrastination is an &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalgeographic.com/science/article/are-you-procrastinating-more-blame-the-pandemic&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;emotional coping strategy&lt;/a&gt; that is used when faced with high levels of stress. Thus, the heightened levels of stress brought by the pandemic have made it more difficult for people to resist the urge of staying up at night. Despite being aware of its consequences, the desire for a temporary escape from the never-ending demands during the daytime makes people fall into an unhealthy cycle that evidently takes a toll on &lt;a href=&quot;https://news.gallup.com/poll/327311/americans-mental-health-ratings-sink-new-low.aspx&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;mental health&lt;/a&gt;. Adults worldwide have expressed dissatisfaction with how long they sleep and more than half of the Americans surveyed by the &lt;a href=&quot;https://j2vjt3dnbra3ps7ll1clb4q2-wpengine.netdna-ssl.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/04/sleep-prioritization-survey-2021-covid-somnia.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;American Academy of Sleep Medicine (AASM)&lt;/a&gt; have reported new sleep problems post-pandemic. But the problem is yet to be solved.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Coronasomnia&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;On top of throwing the world into a &lt;a href=&quot;https://pubmed.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/34006330/#:~:text=Most%20patients%20with%20COVID%2D19,septic%20shock%2C%20and%20cardiovascular%20manifestations.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;health crisis&lt;/a&gt;, insomnia became an even larger problem. It was already the &lt;a href=&quot;https://openstax.org/books/psychology-2e/pages/4-4-sleep-problems-and-disorders&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;most common sleeping disorder&lt;/a&gt; before the pandemic but has increased so much so that a new term called “Coronasomnia” is being used. Coronasomnia, a portmanteau (i.e., blend) of the words “coronavirus” and “insomnia”, has been used to describe the recently surging cases of insomnia as a result of the pandemic. In short, those with insomnia struggle to fall asleep and stay asleep even if they manage to. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.verywellmind.com/what-is-revenge-bedtime-procrastination-5189591&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Stress, anxiety, and depression&lt;/a&gt; are all common side effects of sleep deprivation, and in turn, can lead to both insomnia and revenge bedtime procrastination. But if staying at home means easy access to beds, why has this reduced levels of sleep as opposed to increasing them?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Boundaries between work, school and home&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Forcing adults and students to stay home has &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.medicalnewstoday.com/articles/revenge-bedtime-procrastination-a-plight-of-our-times#What-is-it,-and-why-does-it-happen?&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“blurred the line”&lt;/a&gt; between academic or work life and personal life. Though it may seem unimportant at first glance, keeping a distinct separation between the two is an important factor toward reducing work or school-related stress and maintaining mental health. When they become so closely intertwined to the point that it is hard to tell where one starts and the other ends, it makes it increasingly difficult to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.charityjob.co.uk/careeradvice/keep-work-and-home-life-separate/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;“switch off”&lt;/a&gt; from one and focus on the other, which can thus influence productivity. It also leads to an increased risk of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.healthassured.org/blog/risk-burnout-everyone-needs-break-work/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;burning out&lt;/a&gt; if overworked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Escalated technology use&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Aside from meetings and classes being replaced with virtual alternatives, people have become increasingly reliant on technology to communicate with friends or take a break from the turmoil. Since many areas have been on lockdown for over a year and counting, the restrictions make it difficult for people to meet up in person. And although people have already been reliant on devices before the virus, people cannot help but use more of them now since there aren’t many options open.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Social media and streaming services are more accessible than ever before and everything is only a click away. So when exhausted and stressed individuals have had a long day, it is far more likely for them to whip out their phone or turn on their TV than take a jog outside. Students who used to meet their friends outside have now turned to social media or other chatting platforms to make up for the loss of social interaction. And having a smartphone readily available just before bed makes people even more susceptible to revenge bedtime procrastination and coronasomnia. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://openstax.org/books/psychology-2e/pages/4-1-what-is-consciousness&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;OpenStax&lt;/a&gt;, melatonin, a hormone that helps to regulate sleep, is “stimulated by darkness and inhibited by light”. So staying up late at night staring at a bright computer screen will signal the brain to stop producing melatonin and is counterproductive toward a better night’s sleep. The pandemic seems to be far from drawing to a close, so how can people improve their sleeping habits?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Adjustments to improve sleep&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Due to the sudden changes in lifestyle, it is only natural that individuals’ circadian rhythms have been thrown out of balance. One way to slowly return to a normalized sleep schedule is to keep screens off in the bedroom. As mentioned above, stopping the production of melatonin will only keep the brain more alert. Instead, read a book or engage in an alternative activity that does not require a device. Avoid taking naps longer than 20 to 30 minutes to allow adenosine (a chemical that promotes sleep at night) to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.psychologytoday.com/us/blog/the-couch/202101/7-ways-get-sleep-stay-asleep-and-get-back-sleep&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;build up&lt;/a&gt; throughout the day. And although it may be tempting to do everything in bed, marking it as the “sleeping place” can help the &lt;a href=&quot;https://health.ucdavis.edu/health-news/newsroom/covid-19-is-wrecking-our-sleep-with-coronasomnia--tips-to-fight-back-/2020/09&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;brain associate it with only sleep&lt;/a&gt; and not productivity. In addition to maintaining a regular daily sleeping and working schedule, &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.healthline.com/health-news/coronasomnia-how-the-pandemic-may-be-affecting-your-sleep#How-to-get-the-rest-you-need&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;setting aside&lt;/a&gt; an hour or two specifically for relaxation can help to prevent revenge bedtime procrastination and thus improve sleep cycles. And finally, keep in mind that an individual suspecting they may be suffering from insomnia or any other health issue should always consult or reach out to a medical professional instead of self-diagnosing. Even if it turns out to be nothing, it is always better to be safe instead of risking further consequences in the future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.everydayhealth.com/sleep/how-put-racing-mind-bed-sleep-now/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Everyday Health)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Audrey Lee&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Audrey Lee</name></author><summary type="html">How has the pandemic influenced sleep? Audrey Lee. 09/04/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/september/sleepCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/september/sleepCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Sources of Renewable Energy</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/08/27/sources-of-renewable-energy.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Sources of Renewable Energy" /><published>2021-08-27T17:00:02-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-27T17:00:02-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/08/27/sources-of-renewable-energy</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/08/27/sources-of-renewable-energy.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Sources of Renewable Energy&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Catherine Todd. 08/28/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Currently, there are unprecedented levels of greenhouse gasses in the air and global temperatures continue to rise. Still, humans heavily rely on the use of fossil fuels to create the electricity that most of the world runs on. Up until recently, fossil fuels have been more convenient and cost effective. However, with the many advances in science, renewable alternatives to fossil fuels have become much more realistic and useful. Here are some of the leading renewable energy alternatives.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Solar power is a common energy alternative. By utilizing photovoltaic cells made of silicon, it absorbs energy from sunlight. The energy knocks electrons away from atoms and flows through conductors to form an electrical circuit that creates direct current electricity. There is an abundance of solar energy in theory since there are enough photons hitting the earth within an hour to generate power for about a year. Despite being the fastest-growing source of energy, however, solar energy provides just 0.5% of the energy on earth. When placing solar panels, though, it is important to set them up in certain locations. Certain cities that are generally foggy such as San Francisco are not ideal for solar panels.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For these locations, wind turbines might be a better option. Wind turbines work by using blades like a propeller, which are turned by the wind and therefore turn a generator that creates electricity. Usually, wind turbines use either a two or three bladed propeller. There are about 57,000 wind turbines in the United States and if placed in the ideal location, each of these turbines could power a single home. That is, assuming that they are all small turbines. Very large wind turbines with blades about 162 meters long can generate up to 58 times the energy of small wind turbines. Furthermore, wind turbines have to be placed in mountainous regions or regions with similar wind levels in order for them to generate a reasonable amount of power. Some of the largest barriers to increasing the amount of wind turbines is their large size and unappealing appearance.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nuclear energy also generates electricity. Though not exactly a renewable energy source, nuclear energy has zero emissions, so it is a positive form of energy for the sake of mitigating climate change. Within a nuclear power plant, uranium is split up into smaller atoms by using a process known as fission. This creates a heat source which is used to heat water and create steam. The steam is then converted into energy by using a turbine generator. This explains why nuclear energy generation does not produce fossil fuel emissions: none are burned. Nuclear energy is not renewable though because uranium is not a resource that renews itself like wind or sunlight. Nuclear energy is currently powering about 20% of the United States’ electricity. However, people are skeptical of expanding nuclear power because if a reactor were to melt down, all living organisms around the reactor could suffer radiation poisoning.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly, geothermal energy also utilizes steam to create energy. The steam for geothermal energy, however, comes from the ground, where hot pools of water lie a few miles beneath earth’s surface. This steam is then used to turn a turbine and generate electricity. To do this, three types of geothermal power plants are used: dry steam, flash steam, and binary steam. Dry steam uses steam found underground, like those near geysers for power generation. Flash steam uses water from underground reservoirs that have a temperature above 360 degrees Fahrenheit. The water decreases in pressure as it goes up into wells and steam is created. Finally, binary steam generation works on water as low as 225 degrees Fahrenheit and uses water to boil a low boiling point fluid, which is vaporized and used to create energy. The United States primarily produces geothermal energy from dry steam plants located in Northern California geysers because the other geysers are located in Yellowstone National Park. Iceland is also a large consumer of geothermal energy and creates about 25% of its electricity from geothermal plants and around 85% of heating and cooling.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/august/renewableOne.png&quot; width=&quot;50%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Geothermal activity in Iceland showing fumaroles and mud pools &lt;a href=&quot;https://stock.adobe.com/ca/images/steaming-cone-in-hverir-geothermal-area-with-boiling-mudpools-and-steaming-fumaroles-in-iceland/292868253?prev_url=detail&amp;amp;asset_id=292868253&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Adobe Stock)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Finally, tidal energy is another form of renewable energy that is still in early development. Energy can be produced by utilizing the flow of the ocean between high and low tides. The three ways that it  is harnessed are in tidal streams, barrages, and tidal lagoons. Tidal stream generation involves placing the turbine in shallow, fast moving water that is created by the tide. Barrages are similar to dams that are used for hydropower and can be placed across water sources like bays and harnesses. Finally, a tidal lagoon source would work like a barrage on a natural coastline and would operate during the filling and emptying of the lagoon. Tidal energy is more powerful than wind energy because water is denser than air, and contrary to solar and wind, tides are reliably predictable. However, similar to hydropower, tidal energy disrupts the ocean and its ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In conclusion, there are many alternatives to fossil fuels that can be found in the above list as well as some not listed. Although all the above methods have their pros and cons, together they can create a strong energy source for our future.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nrdc.org/stories/renewable-energy-clean-facts&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(NRDC)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Catherine Todd&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Catherine Todd</name></author><summary type="html">Sources of Renewable Energy Catherine Todd. 08/28/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/august/renewableCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/august/renewableCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Parthenogenesis: The miracle behind ‘Virgin Birth’</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/08/27/parthenogenesis-the-miracle-behind-virgin-birth.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Parthenogenesis: The miracle behind ‘Virgin Birth’" /><published>2021-08-27T17:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-27T17:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/08/27/parthenogenesis-the-miracle-behind-virgin-birth</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/08/27/parthenogenesis-the-miracle-behind-virgin-birth.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Parthenogenesis: The miracle behind 'Virgin Birth'&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Vova Prylepa. 08/28/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/august/parthenogenesisOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;This image represents the steps of asexual reproduction (also called parthenogenesis) in planarian, hydra, and starfish species. &lt;a href=&quot;https://bastiani.biology.utah.edu/courses/3230/db%20lecture/Lectures/a8Pattern.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Developmental Biology 3230)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Biologically speaking, all animals have the blessing of procreation, the ability to bring a completely new individual into this world as a product of sexual intercourse between two partners of the opposite gender. However, some creatures can bypass the requirement of mating to create new life. Their bodies allow them to replicate themselves in such a way that the offspring contains the same biological information as the parent.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In some cases, the naturally occurring genetic modification will even produce fertile offspring. Nevertheless, some of the more highly intriguing processes hide behind a curtain of mystery from the public eye or have sunk into oblivion with the rest of the information learned in years of schooling. To shine some light onto some more precise concepts of parthenogenesis (also called incomplete asexual reproduction as sex cells are still involved), we will describe the four steps of the procedure, as well as some examples of the utility and marvels of this miraculous birthing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Parthenogenesis consists of &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.thoughtco.com/parthenogenesis-373474&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2 main distinct phases&lt;/a&gt;: apomixis and automixis. Apomixis is the process of mitotic production of egg cells. In apomictic parthenogenesis, the oocyte, or female sexual cell, creates a copy of itself by mitosis, forming a pair of diploid cells. These diploid cells have all of the chromosomes needed for embryonary development. The derived offspring are exact copies of the parent cell. Some organisms that breed in this manner are aphids and flowering plants.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In automixis, egg cells are produced by meiosis. Usually, in egg cell development, the resulting daughter cells are split unevenly during meiosis. Asymmetrical cytokinesis eventually results in one large egg cell (oocyte) and several smaller cells called polar bodies. The polar bodies degrade without fertilization. The oocyte is haploid (has only a single set of unpaired chromosomes) and becomes diploid (has two pairs of completed chromosomes) after it is fertilized by male sperm. Because automictic parthenogenesis does not require male involvement, the oocyte becomes diploid by combining with one of the polar bodies or by duplicating its chromosomes. Since the following offspring is a product of meiosis, the occurring genetic recombination makes these individuals false clones of the parent cell.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://education.seattlepi.com/benefits-parthenogenesis-4022.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Benefits of parthenogenesis&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Animal populations where individuals are scarce or isolated amongst themselves, benefit from parthenogenesis, as it removes the requirement of having a partner (for more than one organism to be present) for reproduction to be possible. If males are not accessible for sexual reproduction, parthenogenesis still grants the female a chance at procreation. More importantly, the females do not have to spend energy searching for a mate.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In most organisms, parthenogenesis produces only female offspring, which has a definite advantage over other forms of reproduction. Female offspring are able to contribute directly to the population of a species, being able to bear and produce the next generation. As a result, the rate of population growth is increased for organisms that use parthenogenesis than among related species that reproduce through a method that creates both male and female offspring. In other words, parthenogenesis offers a noticeable advantage when the objective of reproduction is to maximize the number of offspring with the shortest delays possible.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since organisms created via parthenogenesis have a genetic code that belongs to only one individual instead of two, they are genetically stable.It means that all the cells that make up an organism contain identical genetic information which does not vary throughout their entire life. If a specific organism is particularly well suited to its niche and environment, and if that environment has sturdy living conditions, parthenogenesis can stabilize the species in the aforementioned environment even more. Nonoptimal genes may not be introduced into the genetic makeup of the species, and individual organisms can continue to thrive in an environment.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;https://education.seattlepi.com/benefits-parthenogenesis-4022.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Parthenogenesis Disadvantages&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Though parthenogenetic reproduction can be advantageous, it is not as frequently encountered in animals as sexual reproduction, indicating its very specific advantages. Parthenogenesis can be disadvantageous because it limits the genetic diversity that comes from the recombination of genetic material. Recombination strengthens a species in the long term and allows for the selection of important traits.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Interestingly enough, parthenogenesis can also occur in humans. However, it cannot produce viable embryos, as unfertilized eggs lack necessary genetic information that is normally provided by sperm. Spontaneous androgenetic and parthenogenetic occurrences happen amongst humans, but instead of creating viable embryos, they form human-like benign tumors or primitive non-viable fetuses with imperfect body parts. Nonetheless, there was one reported &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.newscientist.com/article/mg14819982-300-the-boy-whose-blood-has-no-father/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;case&lt;/a&gt; of partial-parthenogenesis; a young boy with all his cells (such as blood cells) left without his father’s DNA. He was perfectly healthy, excluding his asymmetrical facial features and learning difficulties. Tracing back to this boy’s biological origins, scientists can infer that an unfertilized egg began the process of self-division, but proceeded to have some of its cells fertilized by sperm in early development. In other words, the boy is a parthenogenetic chimera, because he has two cell lineages in his organism. There have been no scientifically confirmed reports of a clinically healthy nonchimeric human produced from a single, parthenogenetic-activated oocyte.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With the analysis of specific scenarios and historical evolution, parthenogenesis can be perceived as an animal way of reproduction, but one that excludes most mammals, including humans. In regards to the latter, no viable human embryos have ever been produced, so the miracle of virgin birth remains, in fact, a scientifically refuted phenomenon.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parthenogenesis#Humans&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Wikipedia)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Vova Prylepa&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Vova Prylepa</name></author><summary type="html">Parthenogenesis: The miracle behind 'Virgin Birth' Vova Prylepa. 08/28/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/august/parthenogenesisCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/august/parthenogenesisCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Garbage ‘patches’: A buoyant Dumpster-fire</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/08/01/garbage-patches.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Garbage ‘patches’: A buoyant Dumpster-fire" /><published>2021-08-01T17:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2021-08-01T17:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/08/01/garbage-patches</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/08/01/garbage-patches.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Garbage ‘patches’: A buoyant Dumpster-fire&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Amber Abbas. 07/03/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/august/garbageOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
A turtle entangled in a ghost net. &lt;a href=&quot;https://theoceancleanup.com/great-pacific-garbage-patch/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(The Ocean cleanup)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Right now, as you read this, a 1.6 million-square-kilometer expanse of trash is sailing in the Pacific Ocean, off the coast of Hawai’i. The word ‘patch’ is a misnomer; that immense stretch of filth sailing amongst the thunderous waves of the Pacific Ocean isn’t a ‘patch’ in any sense of the word. It’s a collection of 1.8 trillion pieces of plastic – 250 for every human being alive, weighing about 80,000 tonnes. That’s about as heavy as 250 jumbo jets and spread over an area three times the size of France. This garbage, orbiting around 32°N and 145°W, is the world’s largest collection of ocean debris. Let’s dive deeper and learn more about the GPGP.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These metric tonnes of garbage weren’t in the ocean since time immemorial. We humans are solely responsible for this nasty turn of events. Plastic items thrown in the ocean catch the flow of water currents, sail across thousands of kilometers, and end up in the patch. The area in the center of a gyre tends to be very calm and stable. Additionally, the circular motion of the gyre draws debris into this center, where it gets trapped for what seems like an eternity.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Distribution of the debris&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/august/garbageTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;
A modelled mass concentration of the garbage in the patch. &lt;a href=&quot;https://theoceancleanup.com/great-pacific-garbage-patch/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(The Ocean cleanup)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The garbage within the patch is densely distributed but does not form a solid mass. There is no island of trash. Instead, it ranges from light, floatable plastics at the periphery to debris so big it touches the ocean floor. The center of the patch has more than 100kg/m2 of debris while there’s only 10kg/m2 on the boundary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Plastic, which makes the entirety of the debris, does not decompose. Over the years, larger pieces just break into smaller fragments called microplastics. This deterioration into microplastics is usually the result of sun exposure, waves, marine life, and temperature changes. Microplastics have been discovered floating within the water surface layers, in the water column, and as far down as the ocean floor. These microplastics account for 94% of the floating pieces and simply do not go away. They are a hazard to aquatic animals, both small and large. They’re also very difficult to pull out of the ocean, being almost invisible from vessels due to their minuscule size ranging from 0.05 to 0.5 centimeters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Dangers arising from the trash/patch&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Apart from reflecting the effect that humankind has had on the Earth, the debris is a serious threat to aquatic life. Fishing nets, which make up about 45% of all the garbage, floating in the debris lead to ‘ghost fishing’, meaning aquatic animals constantly becoming tangled in the nets without anyone at the helm. An estimated 100,000 marine animals are strangled, suffocated, or injured by plastics every year. The sheer amount of trash may even destabilize the fragile ocean ecosystem, impacting seafood and people who eat it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;So, what can we do about the GPGP?&lt;/b&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
At the moment, scientists believe that there is no practical way to clean the patch. Charles Moore, the man who discovered the patch, said that cleaning up the patch could “bankrupt entire nations”. &lt;a href=&quot;https://marinedebris.noaa.gov/info/patch.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;The National Ocean and Atmospheric Administration’s (NOAA) Marine Debris Program&lt;/a&gt; has estimated that it would take 67 ships a year to clean up less than one percent of the North Pacific Ocean. The area of the North Pacific is 77,010,000 km2. Needless to say, the current population will be long gone before the patch has been cleaned.  It  is a collection of garbage brought in by rivers from multiple countries into the ocean, a mishmash of waste ranging from plastic crates manufactured in the ‘70s to hard hats made in 2010, a multitude of filth, and a timeless reminder that humans do not deserve good things.&lt;br /&gt;
The trash already in the ocean is here to stay for the foreseeable future. We cannot do anything to dispose of  it. What we can do though, is never, ever, dump trash in the ocean. The Earth’s waters cannot and should not handle people’s waste.  It is high time for us to stop treating the Earth as our dumping ground, taking the ravines and plains for granted, for us to stop being nasty.For, as the present situation has demonstrated, when worse comes to worst, even the most powerful find it difficult to catch a breath.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://theoceancleanup.com/great-pacific-garbage-patch/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(The Ocean cleanup)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Amber Abbas&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Amber Abbas</name></author><summary type="html">Garbage ‘patches’: A buoyant Dumpster-fire Amber Abbas. 07/03/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/august/garbageOne.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/august/garbageOne.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">The Future of Coral Reefs</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/16/coral-reefs.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="The Future of Coral Reefs" /><published>2021-07-16T17:00:01-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-16T17:00:01-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/07/16/coral-reefs</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/16/coral-reefs.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;The Future of Coral Reefs&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Daniel Wang. 07/17/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/july/coralOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Coral bleaching is the phenomenon in which coral reefs turn white while algae living inside the coral perish. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nbcnews.com/science/environment/great-barrier-reef-hit-third-major-bleaching-event-five-years-n1166676&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(NBC News)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each year, billions of tourists are drawn to the beauty of tropical shores and flock to places such as the Caribbean for vacation. In this age of information, a simple internet search of coral reefs will result in mesmerizing images of sparkling water filled with patches of multiple shades of green. While most may only associate the words “coral reef” with these images, coral reefs aren’t just natural sights, but they are more importantly, ecosystems that humans depend on. At the InterSTEM Speaker Series presentation, Dr. Garen Baghdasarian, a professor of marine biology at Santa Monica College, explained humanity’s dependence on coral reefs as well as the threats to their survival.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In his presentation, Dr. Baghdasarian first established that coral reefs are indeed organisms. According to &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.livescience.com/40276-coral-reefs.html&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;LiveScience&lt;/a&gt;, coral reefs are structures formed from the skeletons of hermatypic coral, a marine invertebrate. Corals have exoskeletons that provide natural protection from underwater threats. In addition, Dr. Baghdasarian mentioned that coral reefs are the building blocks of clear, shallow water ecosystems as they are an energy source that many aquatic organisms depend on for survival. The coral’s  role of being the backbone of aquatic ecosystems is dependent on the symbiotic relationship between the coral and algae. All corals host dinoflagellates, single algae with a flagella that allows the algae to move. The relationship formed between the dinoflagellates and algae allow for the survival of coral in nutrient-sparse areas. The coral will obtain up a large portion of its caloric energy from photosynthetic products made by algae. The algae, on the other hand, will receive micro-nutrients like nitrogen from the corals, as well as an ideal environment for photosynthesis. If this relationship fails, the coral will perish, destabilizing its ecosystem.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In addition to aquatic ecosystems, many human industries also depend on the sustainability of coral reefs. For example, Dr. Baghdasarian also claims that the tourism brought by coral reefs bring several benefits to a nation’s economy. The reef hosts over 25 million aquatic species, providing food for one billion people. The reefs also act as a carbon sink, mitigating many impacts of rising carbon dioxide levels in the atmosphere. Clearly, many aspects of human life depend on services provided by coral reefs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Unfortunately, climate change is posing a threat to the well-being of coral reefs. Dr. Baghdasarian mentioned that over 90 percent of climate change happens in the oceans, directly impacting the health of coral reefs. This leads to the phenomenon of coral “bleaching,” where coral reefs will turn white while algae living inside the corals die. In fact, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://oceanservice.noaa.gov/ocean/corals/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;National Ocean Service&lt;/a&gt; explains that small changes in ocean temperature, such as a 2 degree Celsius increase, can ultimately lead the corals to expel the algae living in them and turn white. As Dr. Baghdasarian’s research shows, while the bleaching of a coral does not mean that the coral is dead—some can even recover in 4 weeks in ideal conditions—numerous questions still revolve around the process of coral bleaching.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dr. Baghdasarian hopes to answer the question of what will happen to the coral reefs in the future. He and his team began this research by comparing records of coral reefs 50-100 years ago to the coral reefs today. Their observations matched with the general consensus that rising water temperatures led to this catastrophe; as water temperature increased, more algae perished, eventually leading to greater amounts of coral bleaching. Additionally, the increase in water temperature has also seemed to erode tissue of the coral itself.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One surprising discovery was that in many locations with similar water temperature and pH levels, some corals would be bleached, while others would be completely fine. To find out the reasoning behind this phenomenon, Dr. Baghdasarian compared the different types of symbiotic algae with the hypothesis that some algae may have heat-resistant genes. However, after testing this theory out through his experiments, he concluded that the type of algae was not the factor of coral bleaching as his experimental data showed no correlation between the type of algae present in the coral and the degree of bleaching that the coral experienced. Therefore, Dr. Baghdasarian concluded that traits in the coral reefs themselves determine how severely they bleach.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the future, Dr. Baghdasarian will conduct experiments to determine what specific characteristics in corals allow them to thrive in harsh conditions. He believes that in order to protect the coral species, humans must engineer a new species of supercoral that can thrive under more extreme heat conditions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;His final message was that people should never lose hope. No matter how genetically fit human-made coral may be, all work will be done in vain if climate change, the root cause of mass coral bleaching, worsens. Humanity and natural ecosystems are interconnected; while one may not have experienced coral reefs much outside of seeing them in beautiful travel advertisements, the luxuries and benefits one takes from these beautiful organisms depends on their sustainability in the ocean.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.nationalgeographic.com/science/article/scientists-work-to-save-coral-reefs-climate-change-marine-parks&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(National Geographic)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Daniel Wang&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Daniel Wang is an incoming junior at Westlake High School. He is interested in many aspects of STEM, especially math.
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Daniel Wang</name></author><summary type="html">The Future of Coral Reefs Daniel Wang. 07/17/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/july/coralCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/july/coralCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">How Spotify knows exactly what you want to listen to</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/09/how-spotify-knows-exactly-what-you-want-to-listen-to.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="How Spotify knows exactly what you want to listen to" /><published>2021-07-09T17:00:03-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-09T17:00:03-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/07/09/how-spotify-knows-exactly-what-you-want-to-listen-to</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/09/how-spotify-knows-exactly-what-you-want-to-listen-to.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;How Spotify knows exactly what you want to listen to&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Rachel Huang. 07/10/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/july/spotifyCover.png&quot; width=&quot;60%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Algorithm-based streaming platform Spotify curates personalized playlists for users based on their favorite music &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.spotify.com/us/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Spotify)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Spotify. As the biggest music streaming platform in the world, Spotify has two main advantages over its competitors: its large and diverse reserves of music consisting of over 70 million songs and its ability to figure out exactly what you want to listen to. Utilizing a search engine that combines multiple machine learning and data analysis models, Spotify collects data from your playlists and then finds similar songs to recommend to you. The personalization of Spotify can be broken down into two main parts: its data infrastructure and personalization algorithm.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Data Infrastructure&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;Open-source Apache software platforms Kafka, Storm, Crunch, and Cassandra make up the foundation of Spotify. These software systems seamlessly work together to collect and analyze data in real-time and then store it in user profiles as personalized suggestions according to the user’s preference. To make up Spotify’s personalization tech stack (in computing, a stack is a data structure used for storage), a sequence composed of these software systems is run: Kafka collects data, Storm and Hadoop Distributed File System (HDFS) process the data in real-time, Crunch further processes the data, and everything is stored in Cassandra.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/july/spotifyOne.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;A diagram of data flow in Spotify &lt;a href=&quot;https://engineering.atspotify.com/2015/01/09/personalization-at-spotify-using-cassandra/#:~:text=We%20help%20our%20users%20discover,and%20distastes%20in%20different%20contexts.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Spotify)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The Cassandra database, Spotify’s storage unit, consists of over 100 Cassandra clusters, each containing a nested storage system within itself. The sequential layering of the &lt;a href=&quot;https://data-flair.training/blogs/cassandra-cluster/#:~:text=The%20cluster%20is%20a%20collection,storage%20unit%20in%20a%20database.&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;shells&lt;/a&gt; can be represented as follows: cluster → nodes → keyspace → column families→ rows → column. The nodes are made up of computers that share data with each other, and each subsequent shell is a more specific classification of the data in the shell before it. User profile attributes and metadata about playlists and artists are stored in Cassandra clusters.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;How the Personalization Algorithm Works&lt;/b&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;A popular feature of Spotify is the Discover Weekly playlist, a mixtape of 30 new songs that is updated every Monday. This playlist is the best example of Spotify’s personalization algorithm as its songs are directly determined by Spotify’s discovery engine, a mesh of the three data analysis models Collaborative Filtering, Natural Language Processing (NLP), and Audio Analysis. The Collaborative Filtering models rely on data that is stored in immense matrices containing millions of rows and columns, each row representing a user and each column representing a song. After running a matrix factorization formula (with Python libraries) on the user-song matrix, two vectors are produced. The first vector represents a user’s taste in music, and the second vector represents a song’s characteristics. These two vectors are unique to each user, and Spotify recommends songs by comparing your vector to other users’ vectors to find new songs that are similar to the music you are already listening to.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/july/spotifyTwo.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;From left to right: a section of the user--song matrix, a user vector, a song factor &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/s/story/spotifys-discover-weekly-how-machine-learning-finds-your-new-music-19a41ab76efe&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Medium)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
While the Collaborative Filtering models analyze data that is solely from Spotify, the NLP models analyze text on the internet about the songs in Spotify’s database, whether it be news articles about popular artists or tweets about new music. The NLP models use &lt;a href=&quot;https://cloud.google.com/natural-language/docs/analyzing-sentiment&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;sentiment analysis APIs&lt;/a&gt; to create vectors from this collected text that can then be compared to determine if two pieces of music are culturally similar to one another. Finally, audio models analyze the raw audio tracks themselves, an “equalizing” measure built into Spotify’s recommendation models that provide new artists with the same chances of being placed into a user’s Discover Weekly playlist compared to popular artists since audio analysis doesn’t discriminate against song popularity. The audio models use convolutional neural networks to analyze the soundtracks of songs by inputting data as time-frequency representations of audio frames. The frames are then concatenated to form a spectrogram and passed through the convolutional layers of the model, ultimately computing the representative statistics of the song, like the time signature, key, and tempo.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/july/spotifyThree.png&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;A diagram of the audio model; rectangles represent the convolutional layers &lt;a href=&quot;https://medium.com/s/story/spotifys-discover-weekly-how-machine-learning-finds-your-new-music-19a41ab76efe&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Medium)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Where the Discover Weekly Playlist is a representative slice of Spotify’s personalization ability, Spotify’s Home Screen is the whole “personalized experience” pie. The &lt;a href=&quot;https://engineering.atspotify.com/2020/01/16/for-your-ears-only-personalizing-spotify-home-with-machine-learning/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Home Screen&lt;/a&gt; is organized like a bookcase with each shelf (or each horizontal section) displaying your favorite books (the square images that represent playlists, podcasts, artists, albums, etc., more formally known as cards). Each user’s bookcase is different as it is based on their most recent activity, favorite playlists, new releases, and custom mixtapes such as the Discover Weekly Playlist. The cards in each shelf are constantly updated with the help of machine learning. In this case, machine learning can be divided into two sections, exploitation and exploration. Exploitation displays the cards based on your previous activity, whether it be the playlist you last listened to or the artist you started following recently. On the other hand, the exploration aspect is based on initiating user engagement by displaying suggested content, seeing how users respond, and then modifying the suggested content according to user interaction.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As younger generations can attest, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://magazine.weverse.io/article/view?lang=en&amp;amp;colca=6&amp;amp;num=133&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;music industry&lt;/a&gt; is now centered on  digitally streaming music. For example, the International Federation of the Phonographic Industry’s reports show that music streaming made up 62% of the 2020 global music industry, raking in a grand total of $13.4 billion for artists and labels worldwide. &lt;a href=&quot;https://newsroom.spotify.com/company-info/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Spotify&lt;/a&gt; is at the forefront of this streaming movement with a user community of 356 million people that continues to grow every day. Spotify is necessary for singers to flourish, because their music has the possibility of being recommended to anybody and everybody, thanks to Spotify’s song analysis algorithms. 30% of plays on Spotify are credited to personalized recommendations, which serves as evidence of how Spotify is truly at the intersection of the roads of personalization and technology.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With Spotify continuing to push the boundaries of what music streaming can be, the only limit to the music industry is our imagination.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.pinterest.com/pin/497366352578717874/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Pinterest)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Rachel Huang&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Rachel Huang</name></author><summary type="html">How Spotify knows exactly what you want to listen to Rachel Huang. 07/10/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/july/spotifyCover.png" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/july/spotifyCover.png" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry><entry><title type="html">Will the Earth ever run out of resources?</title><link href="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/09/will-the-earth-ever-run-out-of-resources.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Will the Earth ever run out of resources?" /><published>2021-07-09T17:00:03-07:00</published><updated>2021-07-09T17:00:03-07:00</updated><id>http://localhost:4000/2021/07/09/will-the-earth-ever-run-out-of-resources</id><content type="html" xml:base="http://localhost:4000/2021/07/09/will-the-earth-ever-run-out-of-resources.html">&lt;h2 style=&quot;font-family: Ergonomique Bold&quot;&gt;Will the Earth ever run out of resources?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sydney Hollingsworth. 07/10/2021&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/blogs/2021/july/resourcesOne.jpg&quot; width=&quot;70%&quot; style=&quot;display: block; margin: 0 auto&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;center&gt;&lt;i&gt;Coal mines in Columbia &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.globalcitizen.org/en/content/6-natural-resources-exploited-on-earth/?template=next&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Scott Wallace/World Bank)&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You have probably heard doomsday warnings such as “climate change will be irreversible by 2030” or “fossil fuels will run out by 2060” to the point that the end of humanity seems inevitable and quickly approaching. But is it true? There is a common theme for these predictions - depletion of natural resources, that humanity’s overconsumption will be its downfall - but what’s actually going on? How can an entire planet run out of resources so quickly?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We know that there is only a &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.rd.com/list/what-would-happen-if-worlds-natural-resources-ran-out/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;finite amount&lt;/a&gt; of soil, fossil fuels, water, heavy metals, and minerals on Earth, so we must run out eventually, right? And it is true that as a species, we are using these finite resources very quickly; between 1950 and 2000, humans have consumed more natural resources than over the course of all of previous human history, and scientists have been warning against overconsumption since the 1970s.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Scientists’ predictions for what the future will bring have consistently changed, despite having known about overconsumption for years. A &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.theguardian.com/uk/2002/jul/07/research.waste&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;2002 report from the World Wildlife Fund&lt;/a&gt; claimed we would have to colonize at least 2 Earth-sized planets by 2050 to make up for the rate at which we use up natural resources. Now, in 2021, this prediction is less popular because we know that it is neither realistically possible nor necessary.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although the numbers seem to be against us, we’re still alive, and the fuel, soil, and minerals that we use everyday never seem to run out. The Club of Rome’s &lt;a href=&quot;https://wattsupwiththat.com/2019/05/15/why-resources-arent-natural-and-will-never-run-out/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Limits to Growth&lt;/a&gt; manifesto, written in 1972, predicted that we would have already run out of heavy metals such as gold, copper, mercury, silver, and zinc by now, but we haven’t. In fact, they’re quite common and used on a daily basis. So what does this mean? Were the scientists wrong? Not quite…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To “run out” of something really means there will be none left for us to use, not necessarily none left in the entire world. But why does that matter? Well, Earth is much bigger than you might think, and there are plenty of natural resources on it we could use, but reaching them is another story. There are smaller, less dense pockets of ores and minerals deep beneath the Earth’s surface, but reaching them would be too expensive and only considered when we have already depleted all the other, more easily accessible deposits and have no easier options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To say we will run out of resources fails to account for new technology. Resource availability is not determined by the finite amount of the resource, but by our ability to obtain it. Historically, technology needs to advance to extract a greater amount of resources, and we don’t have any reason to assume this won’t keep happening.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;How can we be sure that technology will advance at an effective rate? Well, in many ways, it &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.discovermagazine.com/planet-earth/the-world-is-running-out-of-elements-and-researchers-are-looking-in-unlikely&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;already is&lt;/a&gt;. Ore mines have expanded to the arctic in recent years and plans for deep sea mining operations and asteroid mining are underway for the more distant future. Heavy metals can be recycled from electronic waste, and elements such as nitrogen are extracted from the atmosphere to produce fertilizer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So will we ever really run out of resources? In short: no, or at least not anytime soon. The earth is far from actually “running out” of the resources we depend on. As time passes they will just become more and more expensive as their extraction becomes less convenient, eventually being replaced by cheaper, reusable options when the cost becomes too ridiculous for continued use.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;However, this outlook does not take into consideration the full picture of what is going on in the world. It is important to point out that for the general public to make the switch to renewable resources, the &lt;a href=&quot;https://welcome.arcadia.com/energy-101/energy-sources/will-we-ever-actually-run-out-of-fossil-fuels&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;cost of non-renewable resources&lt;/a&gt; must rise enough to outweigh the cost of renewable ones.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;We can see this happening today: renewable energy sources such as solar or wind already exist, but they are not used nearly as much as fossil fuels, because the cost of extracting fossil fuels is cheap compared to green energy. As fossil fuels become more difficult and costly to obtain, oil prices will rise and consumers will turn to renewable energy, making it widespread and more affordable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But from the perspective of those living in poverty, their world will run out of resources long before this point. While 1st world countries can still afford the rising oil prices and do not yet feel the need to transition to green energy, 3rd world countries will be unable to afford either.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, our current rate of consumption may not cause the Earth to deplete its resources anytime soon, but it does have drastic consequences on the environment. &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC7341033/&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;Global warming is a much larger issue&lt;/a&gt; than depletion of natural resources, and if we don’t do something, it will likely bring &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.sciencealert.com/un-warns-of-biological-annihilation-up-to-a-million-animal-could-soon-be-extinct&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;our downfall&lt;/a&gt; long before we run out of natural resources.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My goal is not to downplay the costs of human exploitation of the environment, but to create a more accurate, less self-centered view of what is happening. We are certainly not destroying the Earth; our home planet has been through much worse and will carry on long after we’re gone, although how it appears on the surface may be quite different. Whether or not we will be included in its future depends on what we do next.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Cover Photo: &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.foeeurope.org/sites/default/files/publications/foee_overconsumption_0909.pdf&quot; target=&quot;_blank&quot;&gt;(Friends of the Earth Europe)&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;/images/writingTeam/noProfile.jpg&quot; width=&quot;170&quot; style=&quot;float: left; margin-right: 30px; margin-bottom: 20px;&quot; /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style=&quot;margin-bottom: 5%;&quot;&gt;
&lt;span style=&quot;font-size: 30px; font-weight: 900;&quot;&gt;Sydney Hollingsworth&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</content><author><name>Sydney Hollingsworth</name></author><summary type="html">Will the Earth ever run out of resources? Sydney Hollingsworth. 07/10/2021</summary><media:thumbnail xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/july/resourcesCover.jpg" /><media:content medium="image" url="http://localhost:4000/2021/july/resourcesCover.jpg" xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" /></entry></feed>